<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>GDP Status Report</title>
<date>December 6, 2003</date>
<version>1.0</version>
<author><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></author>
<abstract>Status report of the GDP project</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo Documentation Project. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> or to 
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">me</mail> personally.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project, from now on abbreviated to GDP, has its own
project page (just like almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp</uri>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content</title>
<body>

<p>
This status mail will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives and/or
projects related to the GDP:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap2">PDF Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap3">Translator script</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap4">Gentoo Handbook Development</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap5">Translation-specific requests</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>PDF documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<note>
This point isn't valid anymore -- apparently, FOP requires xfree-libs for some
features we don't need, so we can probably use it without installing xfree-libs.
</note>

<p>
Sadly enough, the previously discussed option (FOP) is a no-go. It requires a
working XFree installation, which is not allowed on our webservers. Blackace is
checking out if PassiveTex is a better solution, but he is having problems
getting pdfxmltex to work (as did I).
</p>

<p>
Don't expect Gentoo to provide PDFs really soon now. Creating them off-line is
no problem (lots of existing solutions) so perhaps some developer might publish
PDF versions of documents on his webspace at dev.gentoo.org (I'm checking out if
I will do that or not). However, this will *not* be an official location.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Translator script</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Xavier Neys has been improving his ruby-script that allows lead translators to
quickly grasp the situation of the translation efforts. More information is
available at 
<uri>http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.documentation/748</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Handbook development</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The development of the Gentoo Handbook is continuïng (duh). The second part of
the Handbook is progressing, with 5 out of 7 chapters finished. This includes
chapters on:
</p>

<ul>
<li>USE flags</li>
<li>Portage</li>
<li>Init scripts</li>
</ul>

<p>
The draft version of these chapters can be found online at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/draft/handbook.xml?part=2</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Translation-specific requests</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
I have asked all translation teams to give some input on how the translation
process can be improved, what issues they have and how the documentation team
can help more. This resulted in a couple of requests, amongst which are
language-specific mailinglists and a GWN request for more volunteers.
</p>

<p>
The mailinglists for the Polish, German and Indonesian language have been
created to improve the translation efforts, and the GWN has asked for extra
volunteers for some languages. Some translation teams have already noticed more
volunteer requests.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
