<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>GDP Status Report</title>
<date>November 13, 2003</date>
<version>1.0</version>
<author><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></author>
<abstract>Status report of the GDP project</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo Documentation Project. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> or to 
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">me</mail> personally.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project, from now on abbreviated to GDP, has its own
project page (just like almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp</uri>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content</title>
<body>

<p>
This status mail will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives and/or
projects related to the GDP:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap2">Gentoo Handbook</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap3">PDF Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap4">Non-gdp Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap5">Packaged documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap6">New supported languages</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Handbook</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The first part of the <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/index.xml">Gentoo 
Handbook</uri> (<uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml?part=1">Installing 
Gentoo</uri>) is finished and should be production ready. It is available <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">online</uri> and
contains the installation instructions for almost all supported architectures
(x86, ppc, sparc, hppa, alpha). I hope to extend it with the other architectures
that are lurking (amd64, ia64, mips) when I receive more information about 
those.
</p>

<p>
I will start with designing the second part pretty soon now. This part should
contain the Gentoo-specific items for administering your system (Portage,
initscripts, conf.d/env.d)
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>PDF Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Using FOP gives us the best results and can be perfectly integrated with our
current GuideXML format (as it uses an XML format itself, XML-FO). The
resulting transformation of our x86 installation guide can be found at <uri
link="http://emu.gentoo.org/~swift/gentoo-x86-install.pdf">my dev-page</uri>.
</p>

<p>
I am now working on a script to have the transformation (GuideXML -> PDF) done
on the server-level so that everything can be automated.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Non-GDP Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
We have started with the cluster project documentation and are integrating it
in our documentation tree. Other documentation (and projects) should follow
soon.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Packaged Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
After a <uri
link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.documentation/619">discussion</uri>
we came to the agreement that it is not beneficial to provide a package for our 
documentation. If a user wants the Gentoo documentation somewhere on his disk, 
(s)he should use wget, like this:
</p>

<pre caption="Downloading documentation">
$ wget  --recursive --level=1 1 --no-parent --page-requisites --convert-link \
      --no-host-directories --html-extension \
      http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/index.xml
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New Supported Languages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Danish language is now an officially supported language, and the Greek
language volunteers have stepped up and are "in training".
</p>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
