<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>GDP Status Report</title>
<date>December 17, 2003</date>
<version>1.0</version>
<author><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></author>
<abstract>Status report of the GDP project</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo Documentation Project. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> or to 
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">me</mail> personally.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project, from now on abbreviated to GDP, has its own
project page (just like almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp</uri>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content</title>
<body>

<p>
This status mail will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives and/or
projects related to the GDP:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap2">PDF Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap3">Gentoo Handbook Development</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap4">Translation-Specific Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap5">Todo List</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap6">New / Removed Documents</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>PDF Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As mentioned as an errata previously, <c>fop-bin</c> only requires the
<c>xfree-libs</c> in case SVG graphics are used. As we don't use SVG (we use MVG
*mwhahaha* - just kidding :) we should be able to remove this dependency. Due
to other projects / development, this hasn't been investigated thoroughly yet,
but it is still on our TODO list.
</p>

<p>
While we are at it, we are in search of people that know XSL:FO and are able to
create a professional design to use for both the Gentoo Guides as the Gentoo
Handbook.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Handbook Development</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The second part of the Gentoo Handbook is finished and ready for massive
testing. You can find this "beta"-version <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/draft/handbook.xml?part=2">online</uri>. This part will
learn the users how to work with Gentoo: USE-flags, Portage, Init scripts and
Environment variables. This version should be official before the next Gentoo
release and replaces the following guides:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="/doc/en/portage-user.xml">Portage User Guide</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="/doc/en/use-howto.xml">USE Howto</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="/doc/en/rc-scripts.xml">Gentoo Linux Init System</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="/doc/en/env.d-howto.xml">Environment Variables Howto</uri></li>
</ul>

<p>
It must be made clear that the Gentoo Handbook will not replace all guides -
only those that can really benefit from being integrated will be integrated
(duh).
</p>

<p>
The next parts in the Gentoo Handbook will be an extended <e>Desktop
Configuration</e> part (which is a rewrite of the <uri
link="/doc/en/desktop.xml">Desktop Configuration Guide</uri>) and a
<e>Developing Gentoo</e> part (which will contain information on ebuild
development, e-class usage, etc.).
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Translation-Specific Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
During the past few months, the integration of more and more languages in the
documentation team was a bit hectic: no clear acceptance rules, no clear
definition on the status, no clear priority list regarding translations. This
is now solved with the release of the <uri
link="/proj/en/gdp/translators-howto.xml">Translators Howto</uri>.
</p>

<p>
A <uri link="/proj/en/gdp/tipsntricks.xml">Tips &amp; Tricks</uri> document is
also available that contains information for all documentation editors (both
developers and contributors).
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Todo List</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="/proj/en/gdp">Gentoo Documentation Project</uri> website now has
a TODO-list which lists -- guess -- our TODO list. This substitutes the "tasks"
we had previously which made the project page less readable. The todo list
currently holds the following subjects:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Gentoo Release 2004 Requirements</li>
  <li>Printable Documentation</li>
  <li>Moving User-Specific Documentation</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New / Removed Documents</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    Installation instructions for the MIPS architecture have been added to the
    <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    A <uri link="/doc/en/mips-requirements.xml">MIPS Requirements Document</uri>
    has been added to the documentation since no real good source is available
    on the development of MIPS support for Linux
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-release-policy.xml">Gentoo Release
    Policy</uri> which was previously available in the documentation repository
    is now unlinked as it is fairly outdated (due to the new 
    <uri link="/proj/en/releng">release engineering process</uri>)
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
