<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>GDP Status Report</title>
<author><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></author>
<abstract>Status report of the GDP project</abstract>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2005-01-02</date>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo Documentation Project. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> or to 
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">me</mail> personally.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project, from now on abbreviated to GDP, has its own
project page (just like almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp</uri>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content</title>
<body>

<p>
This status mail will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives and/or
projects related to the GDP:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap2">New / Updated Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap3">Uncertainties about stage files</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap4">Separating Handbook into Release and Current</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap5">Automatically Generating Documentation Index</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New / Updated Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<!-- Verify by grepping version and checking if it's 3.XXX -->

<p>
Most translation teams have completed their translation of the <uri
link="/doc/ja/handbook/handbook-x86.xml">Gentoo/x86 2004.3</uri> handbook. A job
well done! This makes that the following languages have an up to date handbook:
Danish, German, English, Spanish, Finnish, French, Italian, Japanese, Polish, 
Brazilian Portuguese, Romanian and Traditional Chinese. Others are working on 
the necessary updates. We can't say enough "Thank you" to the hard-working 
translation teams.
</p>

<p>
Note especially the availability of the Romanian and Polish translations, which
are new languages for our growing translation community. A big thanks to both
for joining the Gentoo Documentation Project and dedicating their free time to
the continuous translation of the ever-changing documentation repository.
</p>

<p>
We have received a new documented titled <uri
link="/doc/en/keychain-guide.xml">Gentoo Keychain Guide</uri> by <mail
link="airuike@gmail.com">Eric Brown</mail>, covering SSH public key
authentication and the use of keychain.
</p>

<p>
Another new document is the <uri link="/doc/en/cron-guide.xml">Cron Guide</uri>,
written by Eric Brown, which describes how to setup and use cron, a daemon that
runs scheduled tasks.
</p>

<p>
Other documents that are updated are the <uri
link="/doc/en/distcc.xml">Distcc Guide</uri>, <uri
link="/doc/en/guide-to-mutt.xml">Quickstart Guide to Mutt E-mail</uri>, <uri
link="/doc/en/altinstall.xml">Alternative Installation Guide</uri>, <uri
link="/doc/en/faq.xml">Gentoo FAQ</uri>, <uri
link="/doc/en/virt-mail-howto.xml">Virtual Mail Hosting HOWTO</uri>, <uri
link="/doc/en/migration-to-2.6.xml">Migration To Linux 2.6 Guide</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Of course, we shouldn't forget all the updates to the other guides, such as
spelling and grammar fixes and bugfixes that were reported to <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Bugzilla</uri>.
</p>

<p>
An overview of all fixed bugreports since the last status update can be found on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?query_format=advanced&amp;short_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;short_desc=&amp;long_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;long_desc=&amp;bug_file_loc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;bug_file_loc=&amp;status_whiteboard_type=allwordssubstr&amp;status_whiteboard=&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;keywords=&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;emailcc1=1&amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;email1=docs-team%40gentoo.org&amp;emailassigned_to2=1&amp;emailreporter2=1&amp;emailcc2=1&amp;emailtype2=substring&amp;email2=&amp;bugidtype=include&amp;bug_id=&amp;changedin=&amp;chfield=resolution&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-21&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldvalue=FIXED&amp;cmdtype=doit&amp;field0-0-0=noop&amp;type0-0-0=noop&amp;value0-0-0=">Gentoo's bugtracking system</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Uncertainties about stage files</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
A nice <uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.documentation/1676">thread</uri>
on the gentoo-doc mailinglist discussed possible issues with the use of stage1.
The Gentoo Documentation Team leaves it up to the Release Engineering team to
decide what to do.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Separating Handbook into Release and Current</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
With the Release Engineering Team deciding to lower the release cycle to a
biannual release (from a quarterly release), the installation instructions will
undoubtedly have difficulties containing both the newest instructions for those
performing a live, Internet-based installation, and the instructions for a
networkless installation.
</p>

<p>
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail> has proposed to split the
Handbook's installation instructions in two: one handbook will be dedicated to
the ongoing installation instructions, based on the latest stable trees. The
other handbook will contain the networkless installation instructions for a
particular release (such as 2004.3, 2005.0).
</p>

<p>
Of course, this change only applies to the installation instructions. All
subsequent parts remain the same since, after executing <c>emerge --update
world</c> on their system, users who have performed a networkless installation
are then running an up-to-date system as well as any other Gentoo user.
</p>

<p>
At this moment, preliminary drafts for the handbooks are available for all
architectures. The move of the documentation is scheduled for January 4th, 2005.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Automatically Generating Documentation Index</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail> has introduced a <uri
link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/metadoc-guide.xml">metadoc.xml</uri> file which enables
the GDP to automatically generate the documentation index. By introducing this
file, we are now also able to:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    hide documentation from the index easily when a showstopper bug (security or
    extremely outdated) has occurred
  </li>
  <li>
    easily view the bugreports that affect documentation which aren't solved
    immediately. This enables contributors to easily see where they can
    contribute.
  </li>
  <li>
    categorise documentation for easy access to the entire repository
  </li>
  <li>
    list the translation team members 
  </li>
  <li>
    ...
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
The <uri link="/doc/en/index.xml">automatically generated index</uri> is
accompanied by a <uri link="/doc/en/list.xml">documentation listing</uri> and an
<uri link="/doc/en/overview.xml">overview</uri> page.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
