<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>GDP Status Report</title>
<date>November 24, 2003</date>
<version>1.0</version>
<author><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></author>
<abstract>Status report of the GDP project</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo Documentation Project. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> or to 
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">me</mail> personally.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project, from now on abbreviated to GDP, has its own
project page (just like almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp</uri>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content</title>
<body>

<p>
This status mail will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives and/or
projects related to the GDP:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap2">Supported Languages</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap3">PDF Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap4">GuideXML Update</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap5">Gentoo Handbook</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap6">WYSIWYG Editor</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap7">Stylesheets</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Supported Languages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Danish translations are fully integrated in the documentation project. Their
documentation can be found at <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/da/index.xml">the Danish documentation index 
page</uri>. We welcome <mail link="broeman@gentoo.org">broeman</mail> and 
<mail link="aaby@gentoo.org">Aaby</mail> to our team :)
</p>

<p>
Dertobi123 will also joined our team as new lead translator for the German
language. He will take over Pylon's position. We ofcourse also welcome
dertobi123 aboard :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>PDF Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As is mentioned in previous status mails, we will create PDFs using FOP.
However, development of the script is on a hiatus until the new infrastructure
design is ready to be deployed (namely having webnodes sync from a master
webnode instead of from the gentoo cvs server).
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>GuideXML Update</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The GuideXML format, used to develop the documentation, has been extended with
the possibility to identify chapters or sections so that internal references are
dealt with more easily. More information on this can be found at <uri
link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.documentation/688">the online
gentoo-doc archive</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Handbook</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The part on "Installing Gentoo" is now the official source for installation
instructions. The "older" installation guides are still maintained though up
until the new Gentoo Linux comes out.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>WYSIWYG Editor</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
<mail link="ian@gentoo.org">ian</mail> is working on a (GPL'd) tool that allows 
editors to create documents through a webbased WYSIWYG editor. Currently it 
works but lacks some necessary features, such as 100% GuideXML compliance, and 
the use of the Coding Style. However, the project looks very promising. 
Certainly one to keep an eye on :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Stylesheets</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The guide-print.xsl style has been updated so that the printable versions of our
documentation is really printable. Before, a margin was left unprinted,
rendering the "printer friendly" feature useless.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
