<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>GDP Status Report</title>
<date>January 2, 2003</date>
<version>1.0</version>
<author><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></author>
<abstract>Status report of the GDP project</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo Documentation Project. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> or to 
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">me</mail> personally.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project, from now on abbreviated to GDP, has its own
project page (just like almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp</uri>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content</title>
<body>

<p>
This status mail will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives and/or
projects related to the GDP:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap2">Gentoo Handbook Development</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap3">New Gentoo Release</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap4">New Developers</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap5">New Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap6">Upcoming Updates</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Handbook Development</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The second part of the Gentoo Handbook is now online and production-ready. This
part is currently available side-by-side with the guides it replaces. This
situation will continue until the first bugs of the second part are removed. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New Gentoo Release</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
With the upcoming new Gentoo release, most efforts in the documentation team are
brought to the auditing of the current documentation and getting all bugreports
on the installation instructions fixed. We are working closely with the release
engineering team to have the instructions in tip-top shape for inclusion on the
upcoming LiveCDs.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New Developers</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Although not that new to the Gentoo Documentation Project, the following
developers have been introduced since the last status update:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <mail link="broeman@gentoo.org">Jesper Brodersen</mail> as Lead Translator
    for the Danish language
  </li>
  <li>
    <mail link="aaby@gentoo.org">Arne Mejlholm</mail> as Follow-Up Translator
    for the Danish language
  </li>
  <li>
    <mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail> as Lead
    Translator of the German language and Editor of the English documents
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Two new documents have emerged from the older OpenMOSIX howto:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/openmosix-howto.xml">OpenMOSIX Howto</uri> which covers
    OpenMOSIX :p
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/diskless-howto.xml">Diskless Howto</uri> which covers
    creating diskless nodes with Gentoo
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Upcoming Updates</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Also known as TODO :) There is a small TODO section on our website. I will
improve that part so it contains more information and try sum up what actions
need to be done.
</p>

<p>
In short, these are the upcoming changes:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The Desktop Configuration Guide will be rewritten and possibly integrated in
    the Handbook
  </li>
  <li>
    Development-related documentation will be rewritten and integrated in the
    Handbook
  </li>
  <li>
    Off-project documentation (documentation that is available through
    gentoo.org but not linked on our documentation resource page) that is of
    interest for users will be integrated in the current documentation resource
    page after carefull reviewing
  </li>
  <li>
    We are still hoping to get PDF versions online for the documentation. If it
    plays out to be very difficult, we will improve the "printable"
    documentation (for instance a one-page, fits-all for the handbook) and/or
    include information on how to generate PDFs from XSL-FO (after providing
    such formatted documents of course).
  </li>
  <li>
    More supported languages :)
  </li>
  <li>
    A uDev guide and, if udev is flexible enough, change the installation
    instructions (after carefull consideration with releng and the architecture
    developers of course) to provide the user with the choice of devfs vs udev. 
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
