<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>GDP Status Report</title>
<author>
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Status report of the GDP project
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2005-12-16</date>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo Documentation Project. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> or to 
<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">me</mail> personally.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project, from now on abbreviated to GDP, has its own
project page (just like almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp</uri>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content</title>
<body>

<p>
This status mail will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives and/or
projects related to the GDP:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap2">New/Updated Documentation</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap3">Moving Stage1/Stage2 To Gentoo FAQ</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap4">Removed Documentation</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New/Updated Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Users who are seeking a distributed file system can look at our updated <uri
link="/doc/en/openafs.xml">OpenAFS Guide</uri> for installation and
configuration instructions of the powerful Open Andrew File System which got
updated to the current release, and extended quite a bit with additional
documented functions.
</p>

<p>
Also, our <uri link="/doc/en/kde-split-ebuilds.xml">KDE Split Ebuilds</uri>
document has been updated with some information about the possible new build
scheme that KDE 4 will use, and confcache (an improvement for repeated
autoconf-generated configure script executions). The FAQ on how to unmerge older
KDE versions has been moved out...
</p>

<p>
Talking about KDE, our <uri link="/doc/en/kde-config.xml">KDE Configuration
Guide</uri> has been updated to reflect the stabilisation of KDE 3.4 in the
Portage tree and, with that, the introduction of new KDE packages. The update
also improves the <c>hal</c> and <c>dbus</c> descriptions. And that's not all,
the guide now contains information about maintaining several KDE versions
simultaneously and includes the instructions about deinstalling KDE which were
previously in the <uri link="/doc/en/kde-split-ebuilds.xml">KDE Split
Ebuilds</uri> guide.
</p>

<p>
Readers interested in virtualisation should really take a look at the updated
<uri link="/doc/en/uml.xml">User-Mode Linux Guide</uri> which gives some
additional help with virtual networks within the run-linux-in-linux context.
</p>

<p>
Upcoming support for the FreeBSD platform is on its way. This is clearly
reflected upon the <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-freebsd.xml">short guide to 
Gentoo/FreeBSD</uri> which is getting larger and larger; the last updates
include more verbose installation instructions and kernel configuration
instructions, amongst various smaller updates which keep the documentation up to
par with the codebase.
</p>

<p>
We now have a <uri link="/doc/en/gcc-upgrading.xml">Gentoo GCC Upgrading
Guide</uri> which replaces the old guide which was stored in the <uri
link="/proj/en/base/x86">x86/Base Project</uri> space. We never said upgrading 
GCC is painless, but with guides like these it is just a matter of reading, 
learning and executing.
</p>

<p>
Other documents that have been updated are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/home-router-howto.xml">Gentoo Home Router HOWTO</uri>
    now tells the reader what kernel configuration is required for ADSL/PPPoE
    and includes a new section on connecting to one or more networks.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/printing-howto.xml">Gentoo Printing HOWTO</uri> gives
    more accurate information for PNM2PPA and HPLIP users.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/faq.xml">Gentoo FAQ</uri> informs its readers about
    the use of a statical <path>/dev</path> structure.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/java.xml">Gentoo Java Guide</uri> has been updated to
    reflect the use of the <c>nsplugin</c> flag.
  </li>
  <li>
    Users of <c>mrxvt</c> and <c>xterm</c> can now find more accurate Unicode
    information about their tool in the <uri link="/doc/en/utf-8.xml">Gentoo
    UTF-8</uri> document.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/handbook">Gentoo Handbook</uri> has been updated with
    a few changes, like
    <ul>
      <li>broadcasting information for the interfaces</li>
      <li>improved kernel installation instructions</li>
      <li>timezone copying instead of symlinking</li>
      <li>
        fixed <path>grub.conf</path> examples with respect to the 
        <path>/boot</path> location
      </li>
      <li>2005.1-r1 release changes (which is mostly a change of media)</li>
      <li>improved <c>grub-install</c> information</li>
      <li>introducing <c>RSYNC_EXCLUDEFROM</c> for rsync exclusion</li>
      <li>new references to the catalyst documentation</li>
      <li>support for the <path>no-nptl</path> profile for 2.4 kernels</li>
      <li>deprecation of the <c>--udev</c> option for <c>genkernel</c></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/security">Gentoo Security Handbook</uri> has had a
    touch-up on Aide (a tool for intrusion detection) and some smaller fixes.
  </li>
  <li>
    OpenOffice 2.0.x doesn't build on 64-bit AMD64 systems either, says the <uri
    link="/doc/en/gentoo-amd64-faq.xml">Gentoo AMD64 FAQ</uri> now.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/virt-mail-howto.xml">Gentoo Virtual Mailhosting
    Guide</uri> has a fix where we forgot to put the <c>FLUSH PRIVILEGES</c> SQL
    command.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="/doc/en/grub-error-guide.xml">Grub Error Guide</uri> fixes a
    forgotten <c>chroot</c> command.
  </li>
</ul> 

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Moving Stage1/Stage2 To Gentoo FAQ</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Historically, the Gentoo Handbook contained all the installation methods that
were possible to obtain a Gentoo installed environment. At first, this included
the Knoppix and other alternative installation instructions. Those were moved to
the <uri link="/doc/en/altinstall.xml">Alternative Installation Guide</uri>
because they were interfering with the "regular" installation method that Gentoo
promoted.
</p>

<p>
Now, due to various bugs and, more importantly, because the instructions were
(and still are) flawed under some circumstances, the bootstrapping and
system-emerge steps (also known as the stage1 and stage2 installation
procedures) have been moved to the <uri link="/doc/en/faq.xml">Gentoo FAQ</uri>.
</p>

<p>
The idea is to keep the Gentoo Handbook for the <e>official</e> installation
instructions which are supported by the release engineering team and fully
documented and maintained by the documentation project, while the other
installation instructions are maintained by the documentation project but not
official.
</p>

<p>
Work is on the way to create a bootstrapping guide, detailing why bootstrapping
is needed, when and how to create installation media for an unsupported
platform, etc. People with knowledge about this subject and who are interested
in providing feedback can take a look at the current <uri
link="/doc/en/draft/bootstrapping-guide.xml">draft</uri> and mail <mail
link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail> with their much appreciated
feedback.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Removed Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The MacOS Guide has been removed; people are now referred to the <uri
link="/proj/en/gentoo-alt/macos/">Portage for Darwin/Mac OS X</uri> project.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
