<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-tipsntricks.xml,v 1.30 2010/12/06 12:07:01 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Documentation Development Tips &amp; Tricks</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="neysx"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
Some tips &amp; tricks that make the life for a Gentoo Documentation Developer
easier
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>6</version>
<date>2010-12-06</date>

<chapter>
<title>Checking out the web site files</title>
<section>
<title>Using anonymous CVS</title>
<body>

<p>
Contributors should use our <uri link="http://anoncvs.gentoo.org/">anonymous
CVS server</uri>. It contains the same files as the official CVS that Gentoo
developers use. The anonymous CVS repository is updated every hour.
</p>

<p>
Create a dedicated directory for the sole purpose of developing documentation,
then check out the web site files.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking out the web site files">
$ <i>cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@anoncvs.gentoo.org/var/cvsroot co gentoo/xml</i>
</pre>

<p>
To update your copy of the repository, run <c>cvs update -dP</c> in the
<path>gentoo/xml</path> directory.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Live repository for Gentoo developers</title>
<body>

<p>
If you haven't checked out the <c>gentoo</c> module yet, do it:
</p>

<pre caption="Checking out the gentoo module">
$ <i>export CVSROOT=</i><comment>&lt;your nick&gt;</comment><i>@cvs.gentoo.org:/var/cvsroot</i>
$ <i>cvs co gentoo/xml</i>
</pre>

<p>
To update our copy of the repository, run <c>cvs update -dP</c> in the
<path>gentoo/xml</path> directory.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Online CVS Repository</title>
<body>

<p>
You can request our <uri link="http://sources.gentoo.org/">Online CVS
Repository</uri> to provide the differences between individual versions. The
main English repository is <uri
link="http://sources.gentoo.org/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/">fully
available</uri>. The online CVS repository is updated every hour.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Setting up your local environment</title>
<section>
<title>Installing gorg</title>
<body>

<p>
Our GuideXML documentation is transformed into HTML by the
<uri link="gorg.xml">www-servers/gorg</uri> package. You need to install it.
</p>

<note>
You need at least <c>gorg-0.6.3</c>. You may need to keyword it for your
architecture.
</note>

<p>
Follow the <uri link="gorg.xml">directions</uri> to configure gorg. You need to
define the web root directory where you checked out our CVS repository
(<path>.../gentoo/xml/htdocs</path>). The other parameters are only useful if
you want to serve a local copy of <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org">www.gentoo.org</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Setting up your XML Environment</title>
<body>

<p>
Your system needs to know where to find the DTDs that our documentation uses.
Edit <path>/etc/xml/catalog</path> as root and add the following line:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/xml/catalog addendum">
&lt;rewriteURI uriStartString="/dtd/" rewritePrefix="<i>/usr/portage/metadata/dtd/</i>"/&gt;
</pre>

<note>
You can also rewrite to the path where the DTDs have been checked out of CVS.
</note>

<p>
If your <path>/etc/xml/catalog</path> is empty or does not contain any entry,
you need to <e>insert</e> the <c>&lt;rewriteURI&gt;</c> element <e>inside</e>
the <c>&lt;catalog&gt;</c> element:
</p>

<pre caption="Minimal /etc/xml/catalog">
&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE catalog PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Entity Resolution XML Catalog V1.0//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/entity/release/1.0/catalog.dtd"&gt;
&lt;catalog xmlns="urn:oasis:names:tc:entity:xmlns:xml:catalog"&gt;
  &lt;rewriteURI uriStartString="/dtd/" rewritePrefix="<i>/usr/portage/metadata/dtd/</i>"/&gt;
&lt;/catalog&gt;
</pre>

<p>
Besides, some files may specify the on-line DTD with an uri like
<path>http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd</path>. You can also rewrite those
references and avoid slow accesses to the net at validation time:
</p>

<pre caption="Extra /etc/xml/catalog addendum">
&lt;rewriteURI uriStartString="http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/" rewritePrefix="<i>/usr/portage/metadata/dtd/</i>"/&gt;
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Testing a Gentoo Guide</title>
<body>

<p>
To test a Gentoo Guide, first use <c>xmllint</c> (from <c>dev-libs/libxml2</c>)
to check if it uses valid XML:
</p>

<pre caption="Using xmllint to validate GuideXML">
$ <i>xmllint --valid --noout alsa-guide.xml</i>
</pre>

<p>
If <c>xmllint</c> returns without showing anything, then the file structure is
valid. Next you need to convert it to HTML:
</p>

<pre caption="Converting to HTML">
$ <i>gorg &lt; alsa-guide.xml > alsa-guide.html</i>
</pre>

<p>
If no errors are displayed, you should be able to point your browser to
<path>alsa-guide.html</path> to view the resulting document. If not, fix your
guide until it works.
</p>

<note>
In handbook chapters, links to other chapters will not be generated because
on-line versions access handbook chapters via the master file, and the
<c>chap</c> and <c>part</c> parameters.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Browsing your local copy of Gentoo's web site</title>
<body>

<p>
Since you checked out a copy of Gentoo's web site out of our CVS, you can also
use gorg to browse your local copy. Make sure you download the news index as
explained <uri link="gorg.xml">in the guide</uri> if you want to see the same
front page.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<section>
<title>How do I convert a file to UTF-8?</title>
<body>

<p>
There are quite a few tools that help you. A popular one is
<c>app-text/recode</c>. Another one is <c>iconv</c>, part of
<c>sys-libs/glibc</c>.
</p>

<p>
Recode's use is pretty straightforward. You tell it what character encoding is
currently used by the document and to what encoding you want to convert the
document.
</p>

<p>
For instance, to convert a document from ISO-8859-15 (also known as Latin-9) to
UTF-8, you can use:
</p>

<pre caption="Recoding a file">
<comment>(l9 = ISO-8859-15, u8 = UTF-8)</comment>
$ <i>recode l9..u8 file.xml</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Documentation Submission Tips</title>
<section>
<title>Check for correct &lt;guide&gt; tags</title>
<body>

<p>
Make sure that the &lt;guide link&gt; attribute points to the correct location
for the guide. This is generally <path>/doc/${LANG}/filename.xml</path>. If you
have a translated document, always specify the absolute path to the document
(e.g. <path>/doc/${LANG}/</path>). If you are writing a guide that uses the
<c>guide</c> or <c>book</c> DTD, you may use either
<path>/doc/${LANG}/filename.xml</path> or <path>filename.xml</path>. Generally,
the GDP recommends the former specification.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Check links</title>
<body>

<p>
You <e>must</e> verify that all hyperlinks in your document work. If it is a
translated document, make sure that any links to other translated documents
point to the existing files.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Check for tabs</title>
<body>

<p>
Tabs are absolutely forbidden in GuideXML documents except when required (e.g.
if the document instructs the user to use tabs). To check a document for tabs,
run <c>grep "CTRL+V&lt;TAB&gt;" file.xml</c>. Fix any lines that <c>grep</c>
prints out.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<body>

<p>
Once you have finished your document, submit it to the Documentation Team using
<uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Documentation">Bugzilla</uri>.
You don't have to mention information like platform, <c>emerge info</c>
output, arch, steps to reproduce, etc. If you have a translated document, be
sure to select the <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Doc%20Translations">Doc
Translations</uri> component for your bug. Also, include a helpful summary
for your translation using the preferred format: "[fr] New translation:
/doc/fr/gnupg-user.xml". Replace <b>[fr]</b> with the two-letter code for your
language.
</p>

<p>
By default, <mail>docs-team@gentoo.org</mail> is the assignee of your bug;
there's no need to change the assignee field.
</p>

<p>
Attach files and patches to the bug using the "plain text (text/plain)"
selection.  Do <e>not</e> select "XML source (application/xml)", even if you
are submitting a <path>.xml</path> file. Patches should have the "Patch" option
checked. Do not submit tarballs full of documents; attach each document and
patch individually.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Commonly or Dangerous Made Mistakes</title>
<section>
<title>Forgetting the all-arch-aspect of the Gentoo Handbook</title>
<body>

<p>
The files in <path>[gentoo]/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook</path> that do not end
with a "-&lt;arch&gt;.xml" suffix are read by <e>all</e> handbooks, which means
that whatever is listed inside must be cross-architectural.
</p>

<p>
If you need to make modifications regarding your own architecture and you're
afraid you need to place this in such a file, you might want to ask on
<c>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</c> first how to solve this. Sometimes there is a way
without making it more difficult for other architectural users.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Not bumping version/date or doing it the wrong way</title>
<body>

<p>
Conforming to the policy, you <e>must</e> bump a version/date when you make
certain changes (most actually). Although the version is less important (the GDP
lead will still kill you if you forget it) the date tells our users when the
document was last modified.
</p>

<p>
If you are making a <e>content</e> change to a document (such as instructions,
code examples, etc.), then you must increment the version. For
<e>non-content</e> changes (e.g. typo or GuideXML fixes), version bumping is
usually unnecessary.
</p>

<p>
When updating the handbook, only bump the date and version of the files you
changed. Don't bump the handbook-<e>ARCH</e>.xml unless you actually changed
its content.
</p>

<!-- Since 2007 or so we've been moving toward simple whole numbers;
No need for complicated decimals 
<p>
Another common mistake is to update the version number as if it were a decimal
number. It's not. <c>3.9</c> should become <c>3.10</c>, not <c>4.0</c>, nor
<c>3.91</c>.
</p>
-->

<p>
Another common mistake is to update the version number using decimals. You
shouldn't do this. The version is a simple whole number. Each update should
increment it by one. <c>9</c> should become <c>10</c>, not <c>9.1</c>. For old
documents not yet using the simpler whole number versioning, please increment
it to the nearest whole number the next time you make a commit to it. So
<c>4.67</c> should become <c>5</c>, <c>1.2</c> should become <c>2</c>, and so
on.
</p>

<impo>
The exception to this rule is <path>/doc/en/metadoc.xml</path>. Metadoc should
still use the existing point version scheme. So <c>1.119</c> becomes
<c>1.120</c>, not <c>2</c>.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
