<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-quiz.xml,v 1.6 2012/10/28 15:21:05 swift Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>

<title>Gentoo Linux Documentation Quiz</title>
<author title="Author">
    <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->

<abstract>
This document contains the Documentation Project Quiz, a collection of questions
pertaining to documentation development which need to be answered correctly
before a developer can be given CVS access to the Gentoo Documentation
Repository.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.2</version>
<date>2005-05-17</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Documentation Project Quiz</title>
<section>
<title>GuideXML Format</title>
<body>

<p>
What is the <c>&lt;version&gt;</c> element used for? 
</p>

<p>
What license does a Gentoo Document use when the <c>&lt;license&gt;</c>
element is set?
</p>

<p>
Where is the content of the <c>&lt;abstract&gt;</c> element placed on the
Gentoo website for a particular guide? And for the Gentoo Handbook?
</p>

<p>
Give the recommended format that you would use for "February 17th, 2005" inside
<c>&lt;date&gt;</c>. What is the benefit for this format?
</p>

<p>
What are the differences between an English document and a translated document
XML-wise (not taking into account <path>metadoc.xml</path>)?
</p>

<p>
Suppose you have a document on the differences between distributions. The
document has the following chapters and sections. How would you create a link 
to the section <e>Availability</e>?
</p>

<pre caption="Document layout">
Chapter: What is a Distribution?
Chapter: What are the Differences?
Section:    Optimization
Section:    Availability
Section:    Software Choices
Section:    Internationalisation
Section:    Software Maintenance
Section:    Branding
Section:    Installation
Section:    System Configuration
Chapter: What is Gentoo?
Chapter: Gentoo's Advantages
</pre>

<p>
What is wrong with the following code snippet of a Gentoo Handbook main file
which covers "Gentoo Security" in German? Why do you make the changes you made?
</p>

<pre caption="Excerpt of a handbook main page">
&lt;?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd"&gt;

&lt;book lang="de"&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Gentoo Sicherheit&lt;/title&gt;
</pre>

<p>
What is the result of using the <c>lang</c> attribute?
</p>

<p>
What is a valid GuideXML file and how do you check for validity?
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Coding Style</title>
<body>

<p>
Please download the following <uri link="fix-me.xml.txt?passthru=1">GuideXML
document</uri> that does not validate GuideXML correctly and also isn't written
using the Coding Style.  Reformat the code so it adheres to the Gentoo
Documentation Coding Style and GuideXML format.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Commit Policy</title>
<body>

<p>
A new document is submitted through bugzilla. You have successfully reviewed
the document but have not found any issues. What is the procedure for adding it
to CVS (give commands and the actions you perform)?
</p>

<p>
A patch for "KaBooZa Guide" has been submitted to bugzilla and you have decided
to take care of it even though you know nothing about KaBooZa. How do you
proceed?
</p>

<p>
Someone notices a grammar issue on one of Gentoo's pages and reports it on IRC.
What do you do if the page is one that you can correct (you have access and you
understand the language)? What if you can't correct it?
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
