<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gdp/doc/translators-howto.xml,v 1.16 2012/12/28 19:05:49 swift Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Translators Howto for Gentoo Documentation</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
A frequently asked question is how to become a translator and what actions
should be performed both to become one and to act as one. This document tries to
explain all this.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>3</version>
<date>2012-12-28</date>


<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>What does this document explain?</title>
<body>

<p>
Frequently, people are interested in joining the Gentoo translation teams and
contributing to the translation efforts. However, few of them know what a
translator does, needs to know and how translations are handled. This howto
should answer most questions, and if you still have some questions left,
contact <mail link="nightmorph"/> or one of the <uri
link="/proj/en/gdp/international.xml">translation team leads</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Situation</title>
<section>
<title>Structure</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="/proj/en/gdp/">Gentoo Documentation Project</uri> has a separate
<uri link="/proj/en/gdp/international.xml">Internationalisation Project</uri>
which involves all translation efforts. This subproject is lead by <mail
link="nightmorph"/> and embraces all translation teams.
</p>

<p>
Every translation team is lead by a <e>Lead Translator</e>. This person is
responsible for all the translations created by the translation team. You can
find the <e>Lead Translator</e> for your language on the <uri
link="/proj/en/gdp/international.xml">Internationalisation Project Page</uri>.
</p>

<p>
In case the <e>Lead Translator</e> is off (vacation, exams, network connectivity
issues, ...) the <e>Translator Follow-Up</e> takes over his job. Both the
<e>Lead Translator</e> and <e>Follow-Up Lead Translator</e> are Gentoo
Developers and should act like one.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="trans_situation">
<title>Lead Translator and Translator Follow-Up</title>
<body>

<p>
The <e>Lead Translator</e> acts as the translation lead, his successor is the
<e>Translator Follow-Up</e>. Both developers must be acquainted
with the following important documents:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/devrel/handbook/handbook.xml?part=2&amp;chap=1">Gentoo 
    Ebuild Policy</uri>:
    Although this document is most important for Ebuild-writers, the <e>Lead
    Translator</e> and <e>Translator Follow-Up</e> must understand this 
    document. As Gentoo Developers they are supposed to be able to answer the 
    common questions about Gentoo that are discussed in this document (such as 
    QA and masked packages).
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-policy.xml">Gentoo Documentation
    Policy</uri>: Every Gentoo Documentation Developer, including the <e>Lead
    Translator</e> and <e>Translator Follow-Up</e> must read and learn this
    policy by heart. It lists all guidelines regarding documentation
    development. Not adhering to this policy may lead to sanctions.
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">Gentoo Linux XML Guide</uri>: All Gentoo
    Documentation is written in GuideXML, an easy-to-learn and easy-to-write
    format that allows us to easily convert the documentation to any format
    using XSLT. This document explains how GuideXML is structured <e>and</e>
    discloses the Coding Style used in the Gentoo Documentation Project.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
The <e>Lead Translator</e> has CVS commit access to the documentation tree in
Gentoo's CVS repository. The <e>Lead Translator</e> and his <e>Follow-Up</e>
are allowed to add and update translations on the website. He is responsible
for the translations on the website and for their accuracy. Failing to
correctly review the translations (resulting in wrong instructions in our
translated guides that don't exist in the English versions) is a serious error.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Translation Teams</title>
<body>

<p>
Every translation team is free to organise their translation efforts as they see
fit. If a team requires a common mailinglist, they can contact <mail
link="nightmorph"/> and/or <mail link="infra@gentoo.org">Gentoo's Infrastructure
Project</mail> to setup a translation-specific mailinglist for their language
(gentoo-doc-${LANG}@gentoo.org). 
</p>

<p>
Unlike the <e>Lead Translator</e> and <e>Translator Follow-Up</e>, the members
of the translation team have no CVS access nor Gentoo Developer status. They do
not have to adhere to the restrictions of the Gentoo Developer as listed above.
It is up to the <e>Lead Translator</e> to provide the translation team members
with the necessary information. However, <uri
link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-tipsntricks.xml">tips and tricks</uri> are available
that can be of help for the translation efforts.
</p>

<p>
Translators will probably want to subscribe to our <mail
link="gentoo-doc-cvs@gentoo.org">CVS mailing list</mail>. Whenever a Gentoo
developer commits a new English version of a document, a message is mailed to
this list. The mail contains the list of committed files and a diff of modified
files. Check our <uri link="/main/en/lists.xml">mailing lists page</uri> to
learn how to subscribe to our lists.
</p>

<p>
Translation teams can opt to use the <uri
link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/metadoc-guide.xml">metadoc.xml</uri> file for their
language. This file also allows translation team members to be listed on the
website when the overview page functionality is used.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Requirements</title>
<section id="trans_req">
<title>Translation Accuracy</title>
<body>

<p>
Translations available on the Gentoo website must be as accurate as possible.
The installation instructions (<uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-x86.xml?part=1">Part I</uri> of the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/index.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>) are the most important
instructions and have absolute priority over all other documents. They may not
lag <e>more than three days</e> behind on the English document in case of
<b>important</b> updates (which will be announced on <mail
link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> by the <e>Operational
Manager</e> with "Important" in the subject. Less important updates are not
announced; in this case the documentation must be <e>accurate to two weeks</e>.
</p>

<p>
Operational documents (listed below) have the second highest priority. Their
translations may not lag <e>more than two weeks</e> behind on the English
document in case of <b>important</b> updates (which will be announced on <mail
link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail> by the <e>Operational
Manager</e> with "Important" in the subject. Less important updates are not
announced; in this case the documentation must be <e>accurate to three
weeks</e>.
</p>

<p>
Operational documents are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/altinstall.xml">Alternative Installation Guide</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-x86.xml?part=2">Part II</uri> of the
    <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/index.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/security/">Gentoo Security Handbook</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/alsa-guide.xml">ALSA Configuration Guide</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
All other documentation may not lag more than <e>two months</e> behind.
</p>

<p>
In case these requirements cannot be met, the translations must be
<e>unlinked</e> from the website until they are updated. In case a complete
language fails to have updated documentation (meaning that most documents are
unlinked from the main page) the <e>Operational Manager</e> is in charge of the
language.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation that does not require translations</title>
<body>

<p>
The following documents are not required to be translated. They are targeted at
Gentoo Developers who should understand the English language:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/devrel/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo Development Handbook</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-policy.xml">Gentoo Linux Documentation Policy</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    All project-specific documentation located in
    <path>[gentoo]/xml/htdocs/proj/</path>.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
However, teams that have enough resources and feel there is a demand amongst
their community for translations of project pages, are welcome to translate
<e>and maintain</e> them. Please do contact the project leads or members to
make sure the documentation is up-to-date and not about to be significantly
changed before undertaking such a translation.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contributing</title>
<section>
<title>Contacting the Lead Translator</title>
<body>

<p>
Contributors should contact the <e>Lead Translator</e> listed on the <uri
link="/proj/en/gdp/international.xml">Internationalisation Project Page</uri> 
to ask how they can help. The <e>Lead Translator</e> should then inform the 
potential translation member about how the translations for his language are 
managed.  
</p>

<p>
In case a contributor believes that the <e>Lead Translator</e> does not perform
well, he can always contact <mail link="nightmorph"/> to express his concerns.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!--
<section>
<title>Assigning Copyright to Gentoo</title>
<body>

<p>
All documentation, including translations, must be released under the <uri
link="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0">Creative Commons -
Attribution / Share Alike</uri> license. Second, to be able to protect the
documentation from infringement, Gentoo requires all contributors and developers
to assign their copyright to Gentoo. This Copyright Assignation clearly states
that the copyright is Gentoo's, but that Gentoo can not change the license on
the documentation (otherwise the Copyright Assignment is no longer valid).
</p>

</body>
</section>
-->
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Requesting Lead Translator / Translator Follow-Up status</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminary Requirements</title>
<body>

<p>
All requirements as defined in <uri link="#trans_situation">Lead Translator and
Translator Follow-Up</uri> must be met. In addition, the candidate (with
co-operation of his translation team if applicable) must submit a
considerable amount of translated documents to <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo's Bugtracking System</uri>. This ensures
that:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The language has a certain amount of documents ready for the community
  </li>
  <li>
    The translation team knows what efforts translations require
  </li>
  <li>
    The translation team knows how to handle GuideXML and the Coding Style
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
The documents that are required before a language can be considered for
inclusion on the <uri link="/">Gentoo Website</uri> are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/">Part I</uri> of the Gentoo Handbook (all
    architectures)
  </li>
  <li>
    At least one of the operational documents listed in <uri
    link="#trans_req">Translation Accuracy</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Asking for Developer Status</title>
<body>

<p>
If the preliminary requirements are met, the <e>Lead Translator</e> candidate
and <e>Translator Follow-Up</e> candidate should mail the following
information to <mail link="nightmorph"/>:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Full name</li>
  <li>Nickname, registered on irc.freenode.net</li>
  <li>E-mail address</li>
  <li>GPG Information (Key-ID)</li>
  <li>Language</li>
  <li>
    Requested Status (<e>Lead Translator</e> or <e>Translator Follow-Up</e>)
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Developer Status Progress</title>
<body>

<p>
If the preliminary requirements are met and all necessary information is
delivered, the candidate will be contacted by a member of the Infrastructure
team for his public <uri
link="/proj/en/infrastructure/cvs-sshkeys.xml#doc_chap1_sect1">SSH Key</uri>.
Keep the private key <b>private</b>!
</p>

<p>
When your account has been set up, a <e>mentor</e> will be assigned (mostly a
senior <e>Lead Translator</e>) to aid you in committing the documents and
managing the translations.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
