<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2004.3/hb-install-next.xml,v 1.5 2005/09/23 13:57:32 neysx Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>1.16</version>
<date>2005-03-25</date>

<section>
<title>Documentation</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Congratulations! You now have a working Gentoo system. But where to go from
here? What are your options now? What to explore first? Gentoo provides its
users with lots of possibilities, and therefore lots of documented (and less
documented) features.
</p>

<p>
You should definitely take a look at the next part of the Gentoo Handbook
entitled <uri link="?part=2">Working with Gentoo</uri> which explains
how to keep your software up to date, how to install more software, what USE 
flags are, how the Gentoo Init system works, etc.
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in optimizing your system for desktop-use, or you want to
learn how to configure your system to be a full working desktop system, consult
our extensive <uri link="/doc/en/index.xml?catid=desktop">Gentoo Desktop 
Documentation Resources</uri>.
</p>

<p>
We also have a large document on <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-security.xml">Gentoo
Security</uri> which is worth reading.
</p>

<p>
For a full listing of all our available documentation check out our <uri
link="/doc/en/index.xml">Documentation Resources</uri> page.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Online</title>
<body>

<p>
You are of course always welcome on our <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri> or on one of our many 
<uri link="/main/en/irc.xml">Gentoo IRC channels</uri>.
</p>

<p>
We also have several <uri 
link="/main/en/lists.xml">mailinglists</uri> open to all 
our users. Information on how to join is contained in that page.
</p>

<p>
We'll shut up now and let you enjoy your installation :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Changes since 2004.3</title>
<subsection>
<title>Changes?</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo is a fast-moving target. The following sections describe important
changes that affect a Gentoo installation. We only list those that have anything
in common with the installation, not with package changes that did not occur
during the installation.
</p>

<p>
The following changes need to happen right after having updated your system (and
before rebooting).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hotplug and Coldplug</title>
<body>

<p>
The functionality of <c>hotplug</c>, used by <c>genkernel</c> users, has been
split over two packages: <c>coldplug</c> and <c>hotplug</c>. Users of
<c>hotplug</c> need to install <c>coldplug</c> as well, remove <c>hotplug</c>
from the default runlevel, and replace it with <c>coldplug</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Coldplug/Hotplug changes">
# <i>emerge coldplug</i>
# <i>rc-update del hotplug default</i>
# <i>rc-update add coldplug default</i>
</pre>

<p>
For more information, please read the <uri 
link="/news/20041113-kernels.xml">Hotplug Change Announcement</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Removed Kernel Trees</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to keep our kernel packages manageable, we have removed some
of the older and unmaintained packages from the tree. All information about the
changes are available in the <uri
link="/news/20041113-kernels.xml">Kernel Change Announcement</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
