<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gentoo-alt/prefix/bootstrap-freebsd.xml,v 1.36 2012/04/11 16:50:58 darkside Exp $ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/gentoo-alt/prefix/bootstrap-freebsd.xml" lang="en">
  <title>Gentoo Prefix Bootstrap Process for FreeBSD</title>
  

  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="grobian@gentoo.org">Fabian Groffen</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="fauli@gentoo.org">Christian Faulhammer</mail>
  </author>

  <abstract>
    How to bootstrap Gentoo Prefix on your FreeBSD system
  </abstract>


  <!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
  <!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
  <license/>

  <version>2.49</version>
  <date>2012-04-11</date>

  <chapter>
    <title>Bootstrapping on FreeBSD</title>

    <section><!-- {{{ Introduction -->
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          An off-the-shelf FreeBSD system is bare.  Very bare.
          Whoever thought that bootstrapping on Solaris was hard,
          FreeBSD makes it even harder.  The lack of tools like bash
          and perl requires some pre-bootstrapping prior to the actual
          bootstrapping process.  Alternatively you can install a Bash
          through the ports system.  If you bootstrap on FreeBSD, make
          sure the development tools are installed, which include
          system headers and a compiler.  This bootstrap guide was
          tested on a FreeBSD 8.2 x86_64 system.  Other architectures
          should not differ too much.  Feel free to try it out on
          other configurations and post to the <c>gentoo-alt</c>
          mailing list for additional help.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section><!-- }}} -->

    <section><!-- {{{ Bootstrapping -->
      <title>Bootstrapping</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          As prerequisite, you need a GCC compiler, the GNU binutils
          linker and system headers, such that source code can be
          compiled into working executables.  Sufficient versions are
          installed by installing the developer tools.
        </p>
        <p>
          The first step is to choose a path to install into.  We refer
          to this path as "prefix path", stored in the variable
          <c>EPREFIX</c>.  A suggestion for your prefix path is
          <path>$HOME/gentoo</path>.
          Whatever you chose, make sure you set it in your environment:
        </p>
        <pre caption="Export EPREFIX variable">
$ <i>export EPREFIX="$HOME/gentoo"</i>
        </pre>
        <note>
          tcsh users can use <c>setenv EPREFIX "$HOME/gentoo"</c>
          instead.
        </note>
        <p>
          Next, add the following paths in your soon to be prefix to
          your <c>PATH</c> environment.
          <path>$EPREFIX/bin</path>,
          <path>$EPREFIX/usr/bin</path>,
          <path>$EPREFIX/tmp/bin</path> and
          <path>$EPREFIX/tmp/usr/bin</path>.
          Adding these paths makes sure that they will be available
          later on in the process.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Add prefix paths to your PATH">
$ <i>export PATH="$EPREFIX/usr/bin:$EPREFIX/bin:$EPREFIX/tmp/usr/bin:$EPREFIX/tmp/bin:$PATH"</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          Now the path is set, start with downloading the bootstrap
          script from
          <uri>http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/alt/browser/trunk/prefix-overlay/scripts/bootstrap-bash.sh?format=txt</uri>
          and
          <uri>http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/alt/browser/trunk/prefix-overlay/scripts/bootstrap-prefix.sh?format=txt</uri>.
          From the directory where the bootstrap scripts were stored execute
          the following commands:
        </p>
        <pre caption="Use the bootstrap script">
$ <i>chmod 755 bootstrap-bash.sh bootstrap-prefix.sh</i>
$ <i>mkdir $EPREFIX/tmp</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-bash.sh $EPREFIX/tmp</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX tree</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp make</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp wget</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp sed</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp python</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp coreutils8</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp findutils3</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp tar22</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp patch</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX/tmp gawk</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX portage</i>
        </pre>
        <note>
          Please note that <c>python</c>, <c>sed</c>, <c>wget</c>
          etc. are installed in <path>$EPREFIX/tmp</path>!
          <c>patch</c> and the like are not typing errors but build
          different versions that will compile out of the box on
          FreeBSD.
        </note>
        <p>
          The script will setup the <path>$EPREFIX</path>
          directory, download a portage tree snapshot, unpack it and
          download and install portage.  Afterwards it will try to setup
          some sane defaults.  We continue with a little hack necessary
          for a successful bootstrap.
        </p>
        <p>
          Let your shell take notice of all just installed programs.
        </p>
        <pre caption="rehash in sh">
$ <i>hash -r</i>
        </pre>
        <note>
          tcsh users can use the <c>rehash</c> command.
        </note>
        <p>
          We continue adding some necessary tools which will deal with
          many errors and warnings you might see during emerging.
        </p>
        <pre caption="emerge sed">
$ <i>emerge --oneshot sed</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          Next, we emerge the <c>bash</c> shell Portage heavily relies
          on.  The same holds for <c>wget</c>, the download manager.
          Since its dependencies cannot be compiled at this stage,
          we ignore those for the moment.
        </p>
        <pre caption="emerge bash and wget">
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps bash</i> (avoid deps that ship scripts with shebang /bin/sh)
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps xz-utils</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps "&lt;wget-1.13.4-r1"</i> (until we fix #393277)
        </pre>
        <note>
          It is safe to ignore the "1 config files in XXX need updating"
          message that appears till the end of the bootstrap process.
        </note>
        <p>
          Now, we will emerge a compiler which will use the GNU
          linker.  This is a requirement for many packages that follow
          in the bootstrap process, in particular Perl.  The packages
          to emerge include the <c>baselayout</c> package.  Some, if
          not many, scripts and tools within a Gentoo system assume
          the availability of the <c>baselayout</c> package for all
          communication using the Gentoo colour scheme.
        </p>
        <pre caption="emerge linker and compiler">
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps baselayout-prefix</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps m4</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps flex</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps bison</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps binutils-config</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps binutils</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps gcc-config</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps "=gcc-4.2*"</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          We continue getting more tools in our Prefix.  We no longer
          ignore dependencies all the time, so a lot of packages will be
          emerged at this stage.  Slowly our Prefix gets more robust as
          we progress here.
        </p>
        <pre caption="emerge several tools">
$ <i>emerge --oneshot perl</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot coreutils</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot findutils</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot tar</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot grep</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot patch</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot gawk</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot make</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps file</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot --nodeps eselect</i>
$ <i>emerge --oneshot pax-utils</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          Now we have a good bunch of programs that Portage needs, we
          can replace the bootstrapped Portage by a properly installed
          one, using Portage itself.  Also here a few dependencies are
          first emerged, such as the language Portage is written in:
          <c>python</c>.  We need to temporarily tell Portage that the
          bootstrapped Portage can be overwritten.
        </p>
        <pre caption="emerge portage">
$ <i>env FEATURES="-collision-protect" emerge --oneshot portage</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          Now we have emerged everything we bootstrapped before, we
          remove the temporary directory and its use as it is no longer
          necessary.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Remove tmp directory">
$ <i>rm -Rf $EPREFIX/tmp/*</i>
$ <i>hash -r</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          Before we do any further merges, we are going to update our
          tree.  Updating the tree is done using:
        </p>
        <pre caption="Updating the tree">
$ <i>emerge --sync</i>
        </pre>
        <note>
          If you're behind a firewall that blocks rsync traffic, you can
          try to run <c>${EPREFIX}/usr/sbin/emerge-webrsync</c> instead.
        </note>
        <p>
          Next, we let Portage emerge all packages that complete a
          system install that we eventually need to finalise this Prefix
          installation.
        </p>
        <pre caption="emerge system">
$ <i>USE=-git emerge -u system</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          Now is a good time to set the preferences for our soon to be
          Prefix.  This includes customisations such as general
          <c>USE</c>-flags, <c>CFLAGS</c> and <c>MAKEOPTS</c> in
          <path>$EPREFIX/etc/portage/make.conf</path>.  Be conservative with
          <c>CFLAGS</c>!  Note that the code below is an example, and is
          meant for inspiration only.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Customising the Prefix installation - example">
$ <i>echo 'USE="unicode nls"' >> $EPREFIX/etc/portage/make.conf</i>
$ <i>echo 'CFLAGS="-O2 -pipe"' >> $EPREFIX/etc/portage/make.conf</i>
$ <i>echo 'CXXFLAGS="${CFLAGS}"' >> $EPREFIX/etc/portage/make.conf</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          Since we have everything in place for a self-catered rebuild,
          we can start the final stage to install the Prefix system.
          This final stage recompiles everything in the system, but now
          all packages can be compiled with tools from the Prefix,
          instead of those from the host system.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Doing the final system installation">
$ <i>emerge -e system</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          After <c>system</c> has emerged successfully, your Prefix will
          be set up properly, and you can emerge the whichever tools you
          choose from the Prefix tree.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section><!-- }}} -->

    <section><!-- {{{ Using the Prefix -->
      <title>Using the Prefix</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          To use your bootstrapped prefix environment, you best start a
          shell from the prefix, such that your path and other
          environment variables are set correctly.  To facilitate in
          this, a small helper script can be created by the bootstrap
          script.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Creating a start-script">
$ <i>cd $EPREFIX/usr/portage/scripts</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh $EPREFIX startscript</i>
        </pre>
        <p>
          After running this, a script <c>startprefix</c> will be
          present in <c>$EPREFIX</c>.  You can freely move the script to
          e.g. your homedir for convenience.  Running the script will
          drop you into a prefix shell, where for example <c>emerge</c>
          is directly at your disposal.  Enjoy your prefix!
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>

  </chapter>

</guide>

<!-- vim: set expandtab ts=2 sw=2 foldmethod=marker foldenable spell spelllang=en_gb: -->
<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; -->
