<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gentoo-alt/prefix/bootstrap.xml,v 1.52 2012/10/28 15:21:06 swift Exp $ -->

<guide lang="en">
  <title>Gentoo Prefix Bootstrap Process</title>


  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="grobian@gentoo.org">Fabian Groffen</mail>
  </author>

  <abstract>
    How to bootstrap Gentoo Prefix on your system
  </abstract>


  <!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
  <!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
  <license/>

  <version>1.94</version>
  <date>2012-10-01</date>

  <chapter>
    <title>Bootstrapping in general</title>

    <section><!-- {{{ Global -->
      <title>Global</title>
      <body>

        <p>
          Bootstrapping is the process required to get Prefixed Portage
          installed on your system.  For several years since its
          existence, the Gentoo Prefix team has documented the exact
          process for bootstrapping a system, on a per platform basis.
          Those instructions often became outdated and differed in
          subtle ways between platforms.  Because maintenance of this
          became too high and errors became too much a barrier for new
          users to join, the Gentoo Prefix team has switched to an
          almost fully automated bootstrap process.  The old
          step-by-step, and package-by-package instructions are no
          longer supported, and all users are highly encouraged to use
          the automated bootstrap process.
        </p>

      </body>
    </section><!-- }}} -->

    <section><!-- {{{ bootstrap script -->
      <title>Bootstrap script</title>
      <body>

        <p>
          The <c>bootstrap-prefix.sh</c> script contains all the
          necessary bits to bootstrap a Gentoo Prefix system.  It uses
          a trial-and-error approach to avoid having to make assumptions
          about the system being bootstrapped at where possible.
        </p>

        <p>
          Simply running the <c>bootstrap-prefix.sh</c> script, launches
          the interactive installer.  This installer will ask for some
          information, and discuss some options based on the system
          being bootstrapped on.  Running this interactive installer is
          the easiest way to bootstrap a Gentoo Prefix system, since it
          caters for the entire process up to the point where the Prefix
          can be used.
        </p>

        <p>
          In case the interactive installer is not desired due to
          automation, or what reason else, the process of bootstrapping
          can be performed in roughly 4 stages.  These stages are
          performed by the interactive installer.  Running these stages
          manually is not recommended, and only meant for special cases,
          such as debugging problems, e.g. when the interactive
          installer fails to finish the bootstrap.
        </p>

      </body>
    </section><!-- }}} -->

    <section><!-- {{{ performing a bootstrap -->
      <title>Performing a Gentoo Prefix bootstrap using the interactive installer (recommended)</title>
      <body>

        <p>
          The <c>bootstrap-prefix.sh</c> requires a working version of
          the GNU Bourne Again SHell (<c>bash</c>).  If you don't have
          <c>bash</c> available on your system, you will have to
          bootstrap a <c>bash</c> binary first.  Systems that often lack
          <c>bash</c> are the *BSD systems such as FreeBSD.
          If you don't have <c>bash</c> installed, download the
          <c>bootstrap-bash.sh</c> script from
          <uri>http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/alt/browser/trunk/prefix-overlay/scripts/bootstrap-bash.sh?format=txt</uri>.
          You can use <c>wget</c>, <c>curl</c>, <c>fetch</c> or
          <c>ftp</c> if they are available.  Downloading the script with
          a web-browser, and/or copying via scp/ftp/NFS is also fine.
        </p>
        <pre caption="Bootstrap bash (ONLY if no bash exists on the system)">
$ <i>chmod 755 bootstrap-bash.sh</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-bash.sh /var/tmp/bash</i>
$ <i>export PATH="/var/tmp/bash/usr/bin:${PATH}"</i>
        </pre>
        <note>
          You ONLY have to bootstrap <c>bash</c> if you don't have
          <c>bash</c> yet on your system!  It is NOT necessary to run
          <c>bash</c> as your login shell.  <c>tcsh</c> users should use
          <c>setenv PATH "/var/tmp/bash/bin:${PATH}"</c> to update their
          path instead of the export.
        </note>

        <p>
          Download the Gentoo Prefix bootstrap script from
          <uri>http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/alt/browser/trunk/prefix-overlay/scripts/bootstrap-prefix.sh?format=txt</uri>.
          Like mentioned above, you can use various ways to obtain the
          script and get it to a place where you can execute it.  Once
          in position, preform the following commands:
        </p>
        <pre caption="Start the interactive bootstrap script">
$ <i>chmod 755 bootstrap-prefix.sh</i>
$ <i>./bootstrap-prefix.sh</i>
(follow the instructions)
        </pre>

        <p>
          That's all!  The script will guide you through the full
          process, and tells you how to start your freshly bootstrapped
          Gentoo Prefix system if it successfully runs up til the end.
          In normal cases, you don't need any more than just this.  You
          can stop reading here if this works fine for you.
        </p>

      </body>
    </section><!-- }}} -->

    <section><!-- {{{ performing a manual bootstrap -->
      <title>Performing a Gentoo Prefix manually</title>
      <body>

        <p>
          If you want or need to perform a Gentoo Prefix bootstrap
          manually, follow the <uri
            link="bootstrap-solaris.xml">instructions for bootstrapping
            on UNIX-like systems</uri>.
        </p>

      </body>
    </section><!-- }}} -->

  </chapter>
</guide>

<!-- vim: set expandtab ts=2 sw=2 foldmethod=marker foldenable: -->
