<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gentoo-alt/prefix/faq.xml,v 1.7 2012/10/28 15:21:06 swift Exp $: -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide lang="us">
<title>Frequently Asked questions about the Gentoo Prefix Project</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="darkside@gentoo.org">Jeremy Olexa</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
This guide covers questions frequently asked by users of Gentoo Prefix
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.3</version>
<date>2011-12-03</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Prefix Frequently Asked Questions</title>
  <section>
    <title>How can I contribute?</title>
    <body>
    <p>
    Due to the depth of the Gentoo Prefix project, we really like to have users
    become involved. It helps us immensely. Here are some possibilities:
  	</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
      Report bugs! Unreported bugs are very bad for the health of the
      project, please do report bugs
      </li>
      <li>
      Report working packages that you may have <uri
      link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gentoo-alt/prefix/ecopy.xml">imported</uri>
      </li>
      <li>
      Test packages - We cannot make sure that every package on every arch works
      by ourselves.
      </li>
      <li>
      Bootstrapping must always work, rebootstrapping often and reporting issues
      would benefit all and you might learn something as well.
      </li>
    </ul>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>I made a fix, what is the best way to report this?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  The absolute best way to report fixes is through <uri
  link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/">Gentoo's Bugzilla.</uri> Use the
  "Gentoo/Alt" Product with the "Prefix Support" component, or click <uri
  link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Gentoo%2FAlt">here</uri>.
  The second best way is to report them on the gentoo-alt <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml">mailing list</uri>, however, 
  items may get forgotten or overlooked on the mailing list. Finally, you may
  report items in irc, but be sure you are speaking to a Gentoo Prefix
  developer, otherwise it is likely to not be noticed.
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>XXX ebuild works for me, now what?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  Please report it! See above and also see <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gentoo-alt/prefix/ecopy.xml#doc_chap2">here</uri>
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>I want to run Gentoo Prefix within my company, am I allowed to do so?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  Of course, see above for support ;) Also, you must obey whichever license as
  applies.
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>
  
  <section>
  <title>How mature is Gentoo Prefix?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  Many of us use Gentoo Prefix everyday and it has been in existance since
  2004. Keep in mind that you are riding the tip of the portage code and the
  latest packages as they exist in the gentoo-x86 tree.

  Gentoo Prefix is believed to have a reasonable maturity. However, as always,
  our software comes without warranty.
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>What is the "gentoo-x86 tree" ?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  gentoo-x86 (sometimes simply referred to as gx86) is what Gentoo Linux
  calls their tree that contains all the
  ebuilds. See <uri link="http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo-x86/">
  here.</uri>
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>On which platforms does Gentoo Prefix run on?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  Many platforms, including but not limited to: RHEL, SLES, HP-UX, AIX, Solaris,
  Mac OS X, Interix (SFU on Windows).
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>What is the best way to contact a Gentoo Prefix developer?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  Please do not send us private mail. We prefer to receive list mail.
  See above for info on the gentoo-alt mailing list.
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>I want to import an ebuild, how do I go about that?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gentoo-alt/prefix/ecopy.xml">Documentation</uri>
  already exists.
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>I want to uninstall Gentoo Prefix from my system, how?</title>
  <body>
  <p>
  rm -rf "${EPREFIX}" 
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>What is the difference between gcc and gcc-apple?</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        Mac OS X users will have gcc-apple installed, which is Apple's
        branch of the GCC compiler.  Normal GCC compiles fine on Mac OS
        X as well.  The difference between the two are modifications
        made by Apple that are not in FSF GCC.  Many of these
        modifications are necessary for applications like Qt, MPlayer
        and GHC to compile.  For this reason, Mac OS X users need
        gcc-apple to be installed.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>A fix was committed, but I don't have it, how come?</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        Gentoo Prefix users no longer are using a SVN snapshot as their
        portage tree.  This means a commit made by a developer is not
        directly accessible to users.  Instead, users are using an rsync
        version of the portage tree that is amongst others enriched with
        metadata for improved performance.  This tree is generated twice
        an hour, at 01 and 31.  The generation usually takes about 5
        minutes, but may take up to 25 minutes when lots of changes have
        been committed.  From the moment the generation is done, the
        rsync slaves have to pick up the updated copy from the main
        generation server.  The slaves will sync with the main server in
        the last 5 minutes, thus from 25th till 30th minute.
      </p>
      <p>
        In short this means that you can only safely sync to get the fix
        60 minutes after the commit has taken place.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>My PATH does not include the Prefix directories after
      I ran ./startprefix</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        you probably override PATH in your <c>~/.profile</c>,
        <c>~/.bashrc</c>, <c>~/.cshrc</c> or <c>~/.tcshrc</c> (or what
        else is your shell initialisation file)
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
  <title>I don't understand something in this FAQ!</title>
  <body>
  <p>Please join #gentoo-prefix on irc.gentoo.org or utilize the gentoo-alt
  mailing list.
  </p>
  </body>
  </section>

</chapter>
</guide>

<!-- vim: set expandtab ts=2 sw=2 foldmethod=marker foldenable: -->
