<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.0/hb-install-hppa-kernel.xml,v 1.2 2006/02/27 00:37:17 fox2mike Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>6.0</version>
<date>2006-02-27</date>

<section>
<title>Timezone</title>
<body>

<p>
You first need to select your timezone so that your system knows where it is
located. Look for your timezone in <path>/usr/share/zoneinfo</path>, then copy
it to <path>/etc/localtime</path>. Please avoid the
<path>/usr/share/zoneinfo/Etc/GMT*</path> timezones as their names do not
indicate the expected zones. For instance, <path>GMT-8</path> is in fact GMT+8.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the timezone information">
# <i>ls /usr/share/zoneinfo</i>
<comment>(Suppose you want to use GMT)</comment>
# <i>cp /usr/share/zoneinfo/GMT /etc/localtime</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing the Sources</title>
<subsection>
<title>Choosing a Kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
The core around which all distributions are built is the Linux kernel. It is the
layer between the user programs and your system hardware. Gentoo provides its
users several possible kernel sources. A full listing with description is
available at the <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-kernel.xml">Gentoo Kernel
Guide</uri>. 
</p>

<p>
For HPPA we have <c>hppa-sources</c>. Default these sources are based on the
2.6 kernel sources. If you want to install a 2.4 kernel, you will need to
install Gentoo from a working Internet connection as we do not supply those
sources on our Installation CD. Continue by installing the kernel source.  The
<c>USE="-doc"</c> is necessary to avoid installing xorg-x11 or other
dependencies at this point. <c>USE="symlink"</c> is not necessary for a new
install, but ensures proper creation of the <path>/usr/src/linux</path>
symlink.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a kernel source">
# <i>USE="-doc symlink" emerge hppa-sources</i>
</pre>

<p>
When you take a look in <path>/usr/src</path> you should see a symlink called
<path>linux</path> pointing to your kernel source. In this case, the installed
kernel source points to <c>hppa-sources-2.6.15.1-pa4</c>. Your version may be
different, so keep this in mind. 
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the kernel source symlink">
# <i>ls -l /usr/src/linux</i>
lrwxrwxrwx    1 root     root           12 Oct 13 11:04 /usr/src/linux -&gt; linux-2.6.15.1-pa4
</pre>

<p>
Now it is time to configure and compile your kernel source. All architectures 
can use <c>genkernel</c> for this, which will build a generic kernel as used 
by the Installation CD. We explain the "manual" configuration first though, as
it is the best way to optimize your environment.
</p>

<p>
If you want to manually configure your kernel, continue now with <uri
link="#manual">Default: Manual Configuration</uri>. If you want to use 
<c>genkernel</c> you should read <uri link="#genkernel">Alternative: Using 
genkernel</uri> instead.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="manual">
<title>Default: Manual Configuration</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Manually configuring a kernel is often seen as the most difficult procedure a
Linux user ever has to perform. Nothing is less true -- after configuring a
couple of kernels you don't even remember that it was difficult ;)
</p>

<p>
However, one thing <e>is</e> true: you must know your system when you start
configuring a kernel manually. Most information can be gathered by emerging 
pciutils (<c>emerge pciutils</c>) which contains <c>lspci</c>. You will now 
be able to  use <c>lspci</c> within the chrooted environment. You may safely 
ignore any <e>pcilib</e> warnings (like pcilib: cannot open 
/sys/bus/pci/devices) that <c>lspci</c> throws out. Alternatively, you can run 
<c>lspci</c> from a <e>non-chrooted</e> environment. The results are the same. 
You can also run <c>lsmod</c> to see what kernel modules the Installation CD 
uses (it might provide you with a nice hint on what to enable).
</p>

<p>
Now go to your kernel source directory and execute <c>make menuconfig</c>. This
will fire up an ncurses-based configuration menu.
</p>

<pre caption="Invoking menuconfig">
# <i>cd /usr/src/linux</i>
# <i>make menuconfig</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will be greeted with several configuration sections. We'll first list some
options you must activate (otherwise Gentoo will not function, or not function
properly without additional tweaks).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Activating Required Options</title>
<body>

<p>
First of all, activate the use of development and experimental code/drivers.
You need this, otherwise some very important code/drivers won't show up:
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting experimental code/drivers, General setup">
Code maturity level options ---&gt;
  [*] Prompt for development and/or incomplete code/drivers
General setup --->
  [*] Support for hot-pluggable devices
</pre>

<p>
Now go to <c>File Systems</c> and select support for the filesystems you use.
<e>Don't</e> compile them as modules, otherwise your Gentoo system will not be
able to mount your partitions. Also select <c>Virtual memory</c> and <c>/proc
file system</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting necessary file systems">
File systems ---&gt;
  Pseudo Filesystems ---&gt;
    [*] /proc file system support
    [*] Virtual memory file system support (former shm fs)

<comment>(Select one or more of the following options as needed by your system)</comment>
  &lt;*&gt; Reiserfs support
  &lt;*&gt; Ext3 journalling file system support
  &lt;*&gt; JFS filesystem support
  &lt;*&gt; Second extended fs support
  &lt;*&gt; XFS filesystem support
</pre>

<p>
If you are using PPPoE to connect to the Internet or you are using a dial-up
modem, you will need the following options in the kernel:
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting PPPoE necessary drivers">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  Networking support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; PPP (point-to-point protocol) support
    &lt;*&gt;   PPP support for async serial ports
    &lt;*&gt;   PPP support for sync tty ports
</pre>

<p>
The two compression options won't harm but are not definitely needed, neither
does the <c>PPP over Ethernet</c> option, that might only be used by 
<c>rp-pppoe</c> when configured to do kernel mode PPPoE.
</p>

<p>
If you require it, don't forget to include support in the kernel for your
ethernet card.
</p>

<p>
If you have a HIL mouse or keyboard, do not forget to compile in support for
them.
</p>

<pre caption="Activating HIL support">
Input core support ---&gt;
  [*] Keyboard support
  [*] Mouse support
  [*] Event interface support
</pre>

<p>
If you have no mouse on your HIL port, only use the basic support:
</p>

<pre caption="Basic HIL support">
HIL support ---&gt;
  [*] HIL Keyboard (basic) support
</pre>

<p>
If you however want <e>full</e> HIL support, select the following options:
</p>

<pre caption="Full HIL support">
HIL support ---&gt;
  [*] HP System Device Controller i8042 Support
  [*] HIL MLC Support
  [*] HIL Keyboard (full) support
  [*] HIL Mouse &amp; Pointer support
</pre>

<p>
Also include display driver support:
</p>

<pre caption="Display Driver support">
Graphics support ---&gt;
  [*] Support for frame buffer devices
      [*] HP STI frame buffer device support
  Console display driver support ---&gt;
      [*] STI text console
</pre>

<p>
When you're done configuring your kernel, continue with <uri
link="#compiling">Compiling and Installing</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="compiling">
<title>Compiling and Installing</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel is configured, it is time to compile and install it. Exit 
the configuration and start the compilation process:
</p>

<pre caption="Compiling the kernel">
# <i>make &amp;&amp; make modules_install</i>
</pre>

<p>
When the kernel has finished compiling, copy the kernel image to
<path>/boot</path>. Use whatever name you feel is appropriate for your kernel
choice and remember it as you will need it later on when you configure your
bootloader. Remember to replace <path>&lt;kernel-version&gt;</path> with the
name and version of your kernel.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing the kernel">
# <i>cp vmlinux /boot/&lt;kernel-version&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#kernel_modules">Configuring Kernel
Modules</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="genkernel">
<title>Alternative: Using genkernel</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are reading this section, you have chosen to use our <c>genkernel</c>
script to configure your kernel for you.
</p>

<p>
Now that your kernel source tree is installed, it's now time to compile your 
kernel by using our <c>genkernel</c> script to automatically build a kernel for 
you. <c>genkernel</c> works by configuring a kernel nearly identically to the 
way our Installation CD kernel is configured. This means that when you use 
<c>genkernel</c> to build your kernel, your system will generally detect all 
your hardware at boot-time, just like our Installation CD does. Because genkernel 
doesn't require any manual kernel configuration, it is an ideal solution for 
those users who may not be comfortable compiling their own kernels.
</p>

<p>
Now, let's see how to use genkernel. First, emerge the genkernel ebuild:
</p>

<pre caption="Emerging genkernel">
# <i>emerge genkernel</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now, compile your kernel sources by running <c>genkernel all</c>.
Be aware though, as <c>genkernel</c> compiles a kernel that supports almost all 
hardware, this compilation will take quite a while to finish!
</p>

<p>
Note that, if your boot partition doesn't use ext2 or ext3 as filesystem you
need to manually configure your kernel using <c>genkernel --menuconfig all</c>
and add support for your filesystem <e>in</e> the kernel (i.e. <e>not</e> as a
module).
</p>

<pre caption="Running genkernel">
# <i>genkernel all</i>
<comment>(Output removed to increase readability)</comment>
* Kernel compiled successfully!
* Required Kernel Params:
*   : root=/dev/ram0 init=/linuxrc real_root=/dev/$ROOT
*     where $ROOT is the devicenode for your root partition as
*     you should have specified in /etc/fstab
*              
* You MUST tell your bootloader to use the generated initrd
*              
* Recommended Kernel Params:
*   : vga=0x317 splash=verbose
*              
* Do NOT report kernel bugs (configs included) as genkernel bugs.
* Make sure you have the latest genkernel before reporting bugs
*              
* For more info see /usr/share/genkernel/README
</pre>

<p>
Once <c>genkernel</c> completes, a kernel, full set of modules and 
<e>initial root disk</e> (initrd) will be created. We will use the kernel 
and initrd when configuring a boot loader later in this document. Write
down the names of the kernel and initrd as you will need it when writing
the bootloader configuration file. The initrd will be started immediately after 
booting to perform hardware autodetection (just like on the Installation CD) 
before your "real" system starts up.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking the created kernel image name and initrd">
# <i>ls /boot/kernel* /boot/initramfs*</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now, let's perform one more step to get our system to be more like the 
Installation CD -- let's emerge <c>coldplug</c>. While the initrd autodetects 
hardware that is needed to boot your system, <c>coldplug</c> autodetects 
everything else. To emerge and enable <c>coldplug</c>, type the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Emerging and enabling coldplug">
# <i>emerge coldplug</i>
# <i>rc-update add coldplug default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="kernel_modules">
<title>Configuring Kernel Modules</title>
<subsection>
<title>Configuring the Modules</title>
<body>

<p>
You should list the modules you want automatically loaded in 
<path>/etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6</path>.
You can add extra options to the modules too if you want.
</p>

<p>
To view all available modules, run the following <c>find</c> command. Don't
forget to substitute "&lt;kernel version&gt;" with the version of the kernel you
just compiled:
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing all available modules">
# <i>find /lib/modules/&lt;kernel version&gt;/ -type f -iname '*.o' -or -iname '*.ko'</i>
</pre>

<p>
For instance, to automatically load the <c>3c59x.o</c> module, edit the
<path>kernel-2.6</path> file and enter the module
name in it.
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6">
# <i>nano -w /etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6">
3c59x
</pre>

<p>
Continue the installation with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=8">Configuring 
your System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
