<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.0/hb-install-gli-dialog.xml,v 1.1 2006/02/27 00:37:17 fox2mike Exp $ -->

<!--  The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!--  See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<sections>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-02-27</date>

<section>
<title>Welcome</title>
<subsection>
<title>Before you begin</title>
<body>

<p>
After you boot the Gentoo Linux Installer LiveCD, it will attempt to load a
graphical desktop. If it is unable to do so, it will instead display a command
line prompt. To launch the installer, simply type:
</p>

<pre caption="Start the installer">
# <i>installer</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once the installer has finished loading, you will be greeted by the welcome
screen.  It provides a friendly introduction to the process of installing
Gentoo on your computer. Remember to read each option carefully.  There is
detailed help available for each step of installation at the top of the screen.
We recommend that you always read the help provided before making your choices.
Note that at any time during the installation process, you can save your
configuration progress in case you need to resume your installation at a later
time. Use the <c>Tab</c> key (on your keyboard) to move around the menus within
a screen and the <c>Enter</c> key to confirm an action.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Partitioning</title>
<subsection>
<title>Preparing the disks</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to install Gentoo on your machine, you will need to prepare your
disks. The <c>Partitioning</c> screen will show you a list of detected disks and
allow you to specify the filesystems you would like to have on your
partitions. Selecting <c>Clear partitions</c> will erase all previous partitions on
your disk, so be careful with this option! It is also possible to resize
certain partition types.
</p>

<p>
If you choose to go with the <c>Recommended layout</c>, the installer will
create three partitions: 100MB for <path>/boot</path>, a <path>/swap</path>
partition up to 512MB in size, and the rest of the available space on the disk
is used for <path>/</path>, the root partition. If you have more than 4GB of
unpartitioned space, using the "Recommended layout" will automatically configure
your partitions without destroying any data on any existing partitions. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Network Mounts</title>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Define network mounts</title>
<body>

<p>
This screen lets you set up and use any existing network mounts during and
after installation. Select <c>New</c> to begin configuration. At this time, only NFS
is supported.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Stage Selection</title>
<subsection>
<title>Dynamic stage generation</title>
<body>

<p>
Since you are performing an installation <e>without</e> an internet connection,
you <e>must</e> select <c>GRP</c> from the stage options present. Then, on the next
screen, select <c>Create from CD</c>. Everything you need to build your system will
then be generated from the files on the LiveCD.
</p>

<warn>
Do <e>not</e> select any options other than those specified above when you are
installing without an internet connection.
</warn>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Kernel Sources</title>
<subsection>
<title>Using the LiveCD kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
You must use the kernel present on the LiveCD for the GRP/networkless
install. This is merely a <c>gentoo-sources</c> kernel compiled by
<c>genkernel</c>, Gentoo's automated compilation utility, and will give you a
kernel that automatically detects and configures your hardware upon boot.
</p>

<p>
Select <c>LiveCD kernel</c> and continue to the next screen.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Bootloader</title>
<subsection>
<title>Making your choice</title>
<body>

<p>
This screen allows to you choose your bootloader. The installer will
automatically configure your choice.
</p>

<!-- do we need to cover all the stuff about lilo/grub and kernel parameter
lines and/or block devices here? -->
</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Timezone</title>
<subsection>
<title>Choose your timezone</title>
<body>

<p>
Study the list and select the region closest to your actual location.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Networking</title>
<subsection>
<title>Add network device</title>
<body>

<p>
On this screen, you will be able to configure the various network interface
devices detected on your computer. Read the available options carefully.
</p>

<p>
The next screen gives you a choice between DHCP and manual IP address
configuration. Once your network interface is properly configured, you will
need to create a hostname for your system. Optionally, you may specify a
domainname and any DNS server information needed.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Extra Packages</title>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: installing extra packages</title>
<body>

<p>
The LiveCD contains a number of available pre-built packages. If you wish to
install any of them, check the appropriate box.
</p>

<impo>
As you are installing Gentoo without an internet connection, you cannot add
any extra packages other than those shown in the installer.
</impo>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Users</title>
<subsection>
<title>Adding users and groups</title>
<body>

<p>
First set the root password for the system administrator (the <e>root</e>
user).
</p>

<p>
We <e>strongly</e> recommend that you create a regular user for daily work.
Working as root all the time is <e>dangerous</e> and should be avoided! Create
your users, set their passwords, and add them to the appropriate groups. You
can optionally change their home directories, select their login shell, and set
helpful comments.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Review</title>
<subsection>
<title>Finishing up</title>
<body>

<p>
Please take the time to double-check each step of the installation process,
ensuring that your system is properly configured. When you have finished
reviewing, you may save your progress and exit, or select <c>Install</c> to
begin automatically installing Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
The installer will alert you when it has finished. It will then return you to
the command prompt. All you need to do to reboot is type:
</p>

<pre caption="Rebooting">
# <i>shutdown -r now</i>
</pre>

<p>
Congratulations, your system is now fully equipped! Continue with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=5">Where to go from here?</uri> to learn more about
Gentoo.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>

<!--
Steps of the dialog:
(pre): type installer at the prompt to begin the dialog
1. Partitioning
(note: we absolutely must include partitioning info here; gli-dialog refers
users to the partitioning info in the gentoo handbook! note that the gtkfe
installer already has this partition info in its graphical help screens)

2. Network mounts
3. Stage Selection
4. kernel sources
5. bootloader
6. timezone
7. network interface selection/configuration (inc. dhcp/static-manual)
8. hostname/domainname/dns
9. Optional: install additional packages
10. set root password
11. add user, set passwords/groups
12. review
(post) finishes, drops to prompt: shutdown -r now
-->
