<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.0/hb-install-tools.xml,v 1.3 2006/03/14 19:30:36 neysx Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>6.0</version>
<date>2006-02-27</date>

<section>
<title>System Logger</title>
<body>

<p>
Some tools are missing from the <e>stage3</e> archive because several packages
provide the same functionality. It is now up to you to choose which ones you
want to install.
</p>

<p>
The first tool you need to decide on has to provide logging facilities for your
system. Unix and Linux have an excellent history of logging capabilities -- if
you want you can log everything that happens on your system in logfiles. This
happens through the <e>system logger</e>.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo offers several system loggers to choose from. There are <c>sysklogd</c>,
which is the traditional set of system logging daemons, <c>syslog-ng</c>, an 
advanced system logger, and <c>metalog</c> which is a highly-configurable 
system logger. Others might be available through Portage as well - our number of
available packages increases on a daily basis.
</p>

<p>
If you plan on using <c>sysklogd</c> or <c>syslog-ng</c> you might want to
install <c>logrotate</c> afterwards as those system loggers don't provide any 
rotation mechanism for the log files.
</p>

<!--
  Even though syslog-ng does not rotate the logs, it does conform to the syslog
  RFC (http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc3164.html) and is far more powerful than most  other system loggers. That and some architectures really prefer syslog-ng
  above others (metalog for instance doesn't work nicely with sparc all the
  time).
-->

<p>
To install the system logger of your choice, <c>emerge</c> it and have it added
to the default runlevel using <c>rc-update</c>. The following example installs
<c>syslog-ng</c>. Of course substitute with your system logger:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a system logger">
# <i>emerge syslog-ng</i>
# <i>rc-update add syslog-ng default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Optional: Cron Daemon</title>
<body>

<p>
Next is the cron daemon. Although it is optional and not required for your
system, it is wise to install one. But what is a cron daemon? A cron daemon 
executes scheduled commands. It is very handy if you need to execute some 
command regularly (for instance daily, weekly or monthly).
</p>

<p>
We only provide <c>vixie-cron</c> for networkless installations. If you want
another cron daemon you can wait and install it later on.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a cron daemon">
# <i>emerge vixie-cron</i>
# <i>rc-update add vixie-cron default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Optional: File Indexing</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to index your system's files so you are able to quickly
locate them using the <c>locate</c> tool, you need to install
<c>sys-apps/slocate</c>. 
</p>

<pre caption="Installing slocate">
# <i>emerge slocate</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>File System Tools</title>
<body>

<p>
Depending on what file systems you are using, you need to install the necessary
file system utilities (for checking the filesystem integrity, creating 
additional file systems etc.).
</p>

<p>
The following table lists the tools you need to install if you use a certain
file system. Not all filesystems are available for each and every architecture
though.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>File System</th>
  <th>Tool</th>
  <th>Install Command</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>XFS</ti>
  <ti>xfsprogs</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge xfsprogs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ReiserFS</ti>
  <ti>reiserfsprogs</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge reiserfsprogs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>JFS</ti>
  <ti>jfsutils</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge jfsutils</c></ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
If you are an EVMS user, you need to install <c>emvs</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing EVMS utilities">
# <i>USE="-gtk" emerge evms</i>
</pre>

<p>
The <c>USE="-gtk"</c> will prevent the installation of dependencies. If you
want to enable the <c>evms</c> graphical tools, you can recompile <c>evms</c>
later on.
</p>

<p>
If you don't require any additional networking-related tools (such as rp-pppoe
or a dhcp client) continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=10">Configuring the
Bootloader</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Networking Tools</title>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Installing a DHCP Client</title>
<body>

<p>
If you require Gentoo to automatically obtain an IP address for your network
interface(s), you need to install <c>dhcpcd</c> (or any other DHCP Client) 
on your system. If you don't do this now, you might not be able to connect 
to the internet after the installation!
</p>

<pre caption="Installing dhcpcd">
# <i>emerge dhcpcd</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Installing a PPPoE Client</title>
<body>

<p>
If you need <c>rp-pppoe</c> to connect to the net, you need to install it.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing rp-pppoe">
# <i>USE="-X" emerge rp-pppoe</i>
</pre>

<p>
The <c>USE="-X"</c> will prohibit xorg-x11 to be installed as a dependency
(<c>rp-pppoe</c> has graphical tools; if you want those enabled, you can
recompile <c>rp-pppoe</c> later on or have xorg-x11 installed now -- which takes a
long time to compile).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: RAID utilities for IBM hardware</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are using SCSI RAID on a POWER5-based system, you should consider
installing the <c>iprutils</c> which will allow you to work with the RAID disk
array, get status on the disks in the arrays, and update microcode among other
functions.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing iprutils">
# <i>emerge iprutils</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=10">Configuring the
Bootloader</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
