<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.0/hb-install-amd64-medium.xml,v 1.2 2006/02/27 00:37:17 fox2mike Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>6.0</version>
<date>2006-02-27</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>CPU</th>
  <ti>Any AMD64 CPU *</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Memory</th>
  <ti>64 MB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Diskspace</th>
  <ti>1.5 GB (excluding swap space)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Swap space</th>
  <ti>At least 256 MB</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
You should check the <uri link="http://amd64.gentoo.org">Gentoo
AMD64 Project Page</uri> before proceeding.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- Copy/paste from hb-install-x86-medium.xml (with s/x86/amd64/) -->
<!-- START -->
<section>
<title>The Gentoo Universal Installation CD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo Linux can be installed using a <e>stage3</e> tarball file.
Such a tarball is an archive that contains a minimal environment from
which you can succesfully install Gentoo Linux onto your system.
</p>

<p>
Installations using a stage1 or stage2 tarball file are not documented in the
Gentoo Handbook - please read the <uri link="/doc/en/faq.xml#stage12">Gentoo
FAQ</uri> on these matters.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo Universal Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
An Installation CD is a bootable medium which contains a self-sustained Gentoo 
environment. It allows you to boot Linux from the CD. During the boot process 
your hardware is detected and the appropriate drivers are loaded. The Gentoo 
Installation CDs are maintained by Gentoo developers.
</p>

<p>
There currently are two Installation CDs available:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The Universal Installation CD contains everything you need to install 
    Gentoo. It provides stage3 files for common architectures, source code 
    for the extra applications you need to choose from and, of course, the 
    installation instructions for your architecture.
  </li>
  <li>
    The Minimal Installation CD contains only a minimal environment that allows 
    you to boot up and configure your network so you can connect to the 
    Internet. It does not contain any additional files and cannot be used 
    during the current installation approach.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Gentoo also provides a Package CD. This is not an Installation CD but an
additional resource that you can exploit during the installation of your Gentoo
system. It contains prebuilt packages (also known as the GRP set) that allow
you to easily and quickly install additional applications (such as
OpenOffice.org, KDE, GNOME, ...) immediately after the Gentoo installation and
right before you update your Portage tree.
</p>

<p>
The use of the Package CD is covered later in this document. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- STOP -->
<section>
<title>Download, Burn and Boot the Gentoo Universal Installation CD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Downloading and Burning the Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
You can download the Universal Installation CD (and, if you want to, the 
Packages CD as well) from one of our <uri 
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri>. The Installation CD is located in 
the <path>releases/amd64/2006.0/installcd</path> directory;
the Package CD is located in the <path>releases/amd64/2006.0/packagecd</path>
directory.
</p>

<p>
Inside those directories you'll find ISO-files. Those are full CD images which
you can write on a CD-R.
</p>

<p>
After downloading the file, you can verify its integrity to see if it is 
corrupted or not:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    You can check its MD5 checksum and compare it with the MD5 checksum we 
    provide (for instance with the <c>md5sum</c> tool under Linux/Unix or 
    <uri link="http://www.etree.org/md5com.html">md5sum</uri> for Windows)
  </li>
  <li>
    You can verify the cryptographic signature that we provide. You need to
    obtain the public key we use (17072058) before you proceed though.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
To fetch our public key using the GnuPG application, run the following command:
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining the public key">
$ <i>gpg --keyserver subkeys.pgp.net --recv-keys 17072058</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now verify the signature:
</p>

<pre caption="Verify the cryptographic signature">
$ <i>gpg --verify &lt;signature file&gt; &lt;downloaded iso&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
To burn the downloaded ISO(s), you have to select raw-burning. How you
do this is highly program-dependent. We will discuss <c>cdrecord</c> and
<c>K3B</c> here; more information can be found in our <uri
link="/doc/en/faq.xml#isoburning">Gentoo FAQ</uri>.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    With cdrecord, you simply type <c>cdrecord dev=/dev/hdc &lt;downloaded iso
    file&gt;</c> (replace <path>/dev/hdc</path> with your CD-RW drive's device
    path).
  </li>
  <li>
    With K3B, select <c>Tools</c> &gt; <c>CD</c> &gt; <c>Burn Image</c>. Then
    you can locate your ISO file within the 'Image to Burn' area. Finally click
    <c>Start</c>.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Booting the Universal Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
Once you have burned your installation CDs, it is time to boot them.
Remove all CDs from the CD drives, reboot your system and enter the BIOS. 
This is usually done by hitting DEL, F1
or ESC, depending on your BIOS. Inside the BIOS, change the boot
order so that the CD-ROM is tried before the hard disk. This is often found
under "CMOS Setup". If you don't do this, your system will just reboot from the 
hard disk, ignoring the CD-ROM.
</p>

<p>
Now place the installation CD in the CD-ROM drive and reboot. You
should see a boot prompt. At this
screen, you can hit Enter to begin the boot process with the default
boot options, or boot the Installation CD with custom boot options by specifying
a kernel followed by boot options and then hitting Enter. 
</p>

<p>
Specifying a kernel? Yes, we provide several kernels on our Installation CD. The
default one is <c>gentoo</c>. Other kernels are for specific hardware needs and
the <c>-nofb</c> variants which disable framebuffer.
</p>

<p>
Below you'll find a short overview on the available kernels:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Kernel</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>gentoo</ti>
  <ti>Default kernel with support for K8 CPUs with NUMA</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
You can also provide kernel options. They represent optional settings
you can (de)activate at will. The following code listing explains all available
kernel options.
</p>

<pre caption="Available boot options">
- agpgart       loads agpgart (use if you have graphic problems,lockups)
- acpi=on       loads support for ACPI firmware
- ide=nodma     force disabling of DMA for malfunctioning IDE devices
- doscsi        scan for scsi devices (breaks some ethernet cards)
- dopcmcia      starts pcmcia service for PCMCIA cdroms
- nofirewire    disables firewire modules in initrd (for firewire cdroms,etc)
- nokeymap      disables keymap selection for non-us keyboard layouts
- docache       cache the entire runtime portion of cd in RAM, allows you
                to umount /mnt/cdrom to mount another cdrom.
- nodetect      causes hwsetup/kudzu and hotplug not to run
- nousb         disables usb module load from initrd, disables hotplug
- nodhcp        dhcp does not automatically start if nic detected
- nohotplug     disables loading hotplug service
- noapic        disable apic (try if having hardware problems nics,scsi,etc)
- noevms2       disable loading of EVMS2 modules
- nolvm2        disable loading of LVM2 modules
- hdx=stroke    allows you to partition the whole harddrive even when your BIOS
                can't handle large harddrives
- noload=module1[,module2[,...]]
                disable loading of specific kernel modules
</pre>

<p>
Now boot your CD, select a kernel (if you are not happy with the default
<c>gentoo</c> kernel) and boot options. As an example, we show you how
to boot the <c>gentoo</c> kernel, with <c>dopcmcia</c> as kernel
parameters:
</p>

<pre caption="Booting an Installation CD">
boot: <i>gentoo dopcmcia</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will then be greeted with a boot screen and progress bar. If you are
installing Gentoo on a system with a non-US keyboard, make sure you
immediately press Alt-F1 to switch to verbose mode and follow the prompt. If no
selection is made in 10 seconds, the default (US keyboard) will be accepted and
the boot process will continue. Once the boot process completes, you will be
automatically logged in to the "Live" Gentoo Linux as
"root", the super user. You should have a root ("#") prompt
on the current console and can also switch to other consoles by pressing Alt-F2,
Alt-F3 and Alt-F4. Get back to the one you started on by pressing Alt-F1.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#hardware">Extra Hardware 
Configuration</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="hardware">
<title>Extra Hardware Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
When the Installation CD boots, it tries to detect all your hardware devices and
loads the appropriate kernel modules to support your hardware. In the
vast majority of cases, it does a very good job. However, in some cases it may 
not auto-load the kernel modules you need. If the PCI auto-detection missed 
some of your system's hardware, you will have to load the appropriate kernel 
modules manually. 
</p>

<p>
In the next example we try to load the <c>8139too</c> module (support for 
certain kinds of network interfaces):
</p>

<pre caption="Loading kernel modules">
# <i>modprobe 8139too</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you need PCMCIA support, you should start the <c>pcmcia</c> init script:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the PCMCIA init script">
# <i>/etc/init.d/pcmcia start</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Tweaking Hard Disk Performance</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are an advanced user, you might want to tweak the IDE hard disk
performance using <c>hdparm</c>. With the <c>-tT</c> options you can
test the performance of your disk (execute it several times to get a
more precise impression):
</p>

<pre caption="Testing disk performance">
# <i>hdparm -tT /dev/hda</i>
</pre>

<p>
To tweak, you can use any of the following examples (or experiment
yourself) which use <path>/dev/hda</path> as disk (substitute with your
disk):
</p>

<pre caption="Tweaking hard disk performance">
<comment>Activate DMA:</comment>                                       # <i>hdparm -d 1 /dev/hda</i>
<comment>Activate DMA + Safe Performance-enhancing Options:</comment>  # <i>hdparm -d 1 -A 1 -m 16 -u 1 -a 64 /dev/hda</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="useraccounts">
<title>Optional: User Accounts</title>
<body>

<p>
If you plan on giving other people access to your installation
environment or you want to chat using <c>irssi</c> without root privileges (for
security reasons), you need to create the necessary user accounts and change 
the root password.
</p>

<p>
To change the root password, use the <c>passwd</c> utility:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the root password">
# <i>passwd</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter your new password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter your password)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
To create a user account, we first enter their credentials, followed by
its password. We use <c>useradd</c> and <c>passwd</c> for these tasks.
In the next example, we create a user called &quot;john&quot;.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a user account">
# <i>useradd -m -G users john</i>
# <i>passwd john</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter john's password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter john's password)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
You can change your user id from root to the newly created user by using
<c>su</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing user id">
# <i>su - john</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Viewing Documentation while Installing</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to view the Gentoo Handbook (either from-CD or online) during the
installation, make sure you have created a user account (see <uri
link="#useraccounts">Optional: User Accounts</uri>). Then press <c>Alt-F2</c> to
go to a new terminal and log in.
</p>

<p>
If you want to view the documentation on the CD you can immediately run
<c>links</c> to read it:
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the on-CD documentation">
# <i>links /mnt/cdrom/docs/handbook/html/index.html</i>
</pre>

<p>
However, it is preferred that you use the online Gentoo Handbook as it will be
more recent than the one provided on the CD. You can view it using <c>links</c>
as well, but only after having completed the <e>Configuring your Network</e>
chapter (otherwise you won't be able to go on the Internet to view the
document):
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the Online Documentation">
# <i>links http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can go back to your original terminal by pressing <c>Alt-F1</c>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Starting the SSH Daemon</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to allow other users to access your computer during the
Gentoo installation (perhaps because those users are going to help you
install Gentoo, or even do it for you), you need to create a user
account for them and perhaps even provide them with your root password 
(<e>only</e> do that <e>if</e> you <b>fully trust</b> that user).
</p>

<p>
To fire up the SSH daemon, execute the following command:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the SSH daemon">
# <i>/etc/init.d/sshd start</i>
</pre>

<p>
To be able to use sshd, you first need to set up your networking. Continue with
the chapter on <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">Configuring your Network</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
