<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.0/hb-install-ppc-kernel.xml,v 1.2 2006/02/27 00:37:17 fox2mike Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>6.0</version>
<date>2006-02-27</date>

<section>
<title>Timezone</title>
<body>

<p>
You first need to select your timezone so that your system knows where it is
located. Look for your timezone in <path>/usr/share/zoneinfo</path>, then copy
it to <path>/etc/localtime</path>. Please avoid the
<path>/usr/share/zoneinfo/Etc/GMT*</path> timezones as their names do not
indicate the expected zones. For instance, <path>GMT-8</path> is in fact GMT+8.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the timezone information">
# <i>ls /usr/share/zoneinfo</i>
<comment>(Suppose you want to use GMT)</comment>
# <i>cp /usr/share/zoneinfo/GMT /etc/localtime</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing the Sources</title>
<subsection>
<title>Choosing a Kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
The core around which all distributions are built is the Linux kernel. It is the
layer between the user programs and your system hardware. Gentoo provides its
users several possible kernel sources. A full listing with description is
available at the <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-kernel.xml">Gentoo Kernel
Guide</uri>. 
</p>

<p>
We suggest using either <c>vanilla-sources</c> or <c>gentoo-sources</c> on PPC,
which are both 2.6 kernels. The latter is available when you perform a
networkless installation. So let's continue with <c>emerge</c>'ing the kernel
sources.  The <c>USE="-doc"</c> is necessary to avoid installing xorg-x11 or
other dependencies at this point. <c>USE="symlink"</c> is not necessary for a
new install, but ensures proper creation of the <path>/usr/src/linux</path>
symlink.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a kernel source">
# <i>USE="-doc symlink" emerge gentoo-sources</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you take a look in <path>/usr/src</path> you should see a symlink named
<path>linux</path> pointing to your current kernel source. In this case, the
installed kernel source points to <c>gentoo-sources-2.6.15</c>. Your version
may be different, so keep this in mind.
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the kernel source symlink">
# <i>ls -l /usr/src/linux</i>
lrwxrwxrwx    1 root     root           22  Mar 18 16:23 /usr/src/linux -&gt; linux-2.6.15
</pre>

<p>
Now it is time to configure and compile your kernel source. You 
can use <c>genkernel</c> for this, which will build a generic kernel as used 
by the Installation CD. We explain the "manual" configuration first though, as
it is the best way to optimize your environment.
</p>

<p>
If you want to manually configure your kernel, continue now with <uri
link="#manual">Default: Manual Configuration</uri>. If you want to use 
<c>genkernel</c> you should read <uri link="#genkernel">Alternative: Using 
genkernel</uri> instead.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="manual">
<title>Default: Manual Configuration</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Manually configuring a kernel is often seen as the most difficult procedure a
Linux user ever has to perform. Nothing is less true -- after configuring a
couple of kernels you don't even remember that it was difficult ;)
</p>

<p>
However, one thing <e>is</e> true: you must know your system when you start
configuring a kernel manually. Most information can be gathered by emerging 
pciutils (<c>emerge pciutils</c>) which contains <c>lspci</c>. You will now 
be able to  use <c>lspci</c> within the chrooted environment. You may safely 
ignore any <e>pcilib</e> warnings (like pcilib: cannot open 
/sys/bus/pci/devices) that <c>lspci</c> throws out. Alternatively, you can run 
<c>lspci</c> from a <e>non-chrooted</e> environment. The results are the same. 
You can also run <c>lsmod</c> to see what kernel modules the Installation CD 
uses (it might provide you with a nice hint on what to enable).  Another place
to look for clues as to what components to enable is to check the kernel
message logs from the successful boot that got you this far.  Type <c>dmesg</c>
to see the kernel messages.
</p>

<p>
Now, go to your kernel source directory, it's time to configure your kernel.
It is recommended that you add the default settings to your configuration by
first running <c>make defconfig</c>. After the default configuration has been
generated, run <c>make menuconfig</c> which will fire up an ncurses-based
configuration menu.
</p>

<pre caption="Invoking menuconfig">
# <i>cd /usr/src/linux</i>
# <i>make defconfig</i>
# <i>make menuconfig</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will be greeted with several configuration sections. We'll first list some
options you must activate (otherwise Gentoo will not function, or not function
properly without additional tweaks).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Activating Required Options</title>
<body>

<p>
First of all, activate the use of development and experimental code/drivers.
You need this, otherwise some very important code/drivers won't show up:
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting experimental code/drivers, General setup">
Code maturity level options ---&gt;
  [*] Prompt for development and/or incomplete code/drivers
General setup --->
  [*] Support for hot-pluggable devices
</pre>

<p>
Now go to <c>File Systems</c> and select support for the filesystems you use.
<e>Don't</e> compile them as modules, otherwise your Gentoo system will not be
able to mount your partitions. Also select <c>/proc file system</c> and
<c>Virtual memory</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting necessary file systems">
File systems ---&gt;
  Pseudo Filesystems ---&gt;
    [*] /proc file system support
    [*] Virtual memory file system support (former shm fs)

<comment>(Select one or more of the following options as needed by your system)</comment>
  &lt;*&gt; Reiserfs support
  &lt;*&gt; Ext3 journalling file system support
  &lt;*&gt; Second extended fs support
  &lt;*&gt; XFS filesystem support
</pre>

<p>
If you are using PPPoE to connect to the Internet or you are using a dial-up
modem, you will need the following options in the kernel:
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting PPPoE necessary drivers">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  Networking support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; PPP (point-to-point protocol) support
    &lt;*&gt;   PPP support for async serial ports
    &lt;*&gt;   PPP support for sync tty ports
</pre>

<p>
The two compression options won't harm but are not definitely needed, neither
does the <c>PPP over Ethernet</c> option, that might only be used by 
<c>rp-pppoe</c> when configured to do kernel mode PPPoE.
</p>

<p>
If you require it, don't forget to include support in the kernel for your
ethernet card.
</p>

<p>
Users of NewWorld and OldWorld machines will want HFS support as well.  OldWorld
users require it for copying compiled kernels to the MacOS partition. NewWorld
users require it for configuring the special Apple_Bootstrap partition:
</p>

<pre caption="Activating HFS support">
File Systems ---&gt;
  [*] HFS Support
</pre>

<p>
At this time, kernel preemption is still unstable on PPC and may cause 
compilation failures and random segfaults.  It is <e>strongly</e> suggested
that you do not use this feature.
</p>

<pre caption="Ensure the Preemptible Kernel Option is Off">
Platform options ---&gt;
  [ ] Preemptible Kernel
</pre>

<p>
If you're booting from Firewire, you'll need to enable these options. If you do
not want to compile in support, you'll need to include these modules and their
dependencies in an initrd.
</p>

<pre caption="Enable support for firewire devices on boot">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  IEEE 1394 (FireWire) support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; IEEE 1394 (FireWire) support
    &lt;*&gt;   OHCI-1394 support
    &lt;*&gt;   SBP-2 support (Harddisks etc.)
</pre>

<p>
If you're booting from USB, you'll need to enable these options.  If you do not
want to compile in support, you'll need to include these modules and their
dependencies in an initrd.
</p>

<pre caption="Enable support for USB devices on boot">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  USB support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; Support for Host-side USB
    &lt;*&gt;   OHCI HCD support
    &lt;*&gt;   USB Mass Storage support
</pre>

<p>
Do not turn off kernel framebuffer support as it is required for a successful
boot.  If you are using an NVIDIA based chipset, you should use the OpenFirmware
framebuffer.  If you are using an ATI based chipset, you should select the
framebuffer driver based upon your chipset (Mach64, Rage128 or Radeon).
</p>

<pre caption="Chosing a Framebuffer Driver">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  Graphics support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; Support for frame buffer devices
    [*] Open Firmware frame buffer device support
    &lt;*&gt; ATI Radeon display support
    &lt;*&gt; ATI Rage128 display support
    &lt;*&gt; ATI Mach64 display support
    Console display driver support ---&gt;
      &lt;*&gt; Framebuffer Console support
</pre>

<note>
If you select more than one framebuffer device, it may default to a less than
optimal driver.  Either use only one framebuffer device or specify which
to use by passing the driver to use to the kernel on boot such as 
<c>video=radeonfb</c>.
</note>

<p>
When you're done configuring your kernel, continue with <uri
link="#compiling">Compiling and Installing</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="compiling">
<title>Compiling and Installing</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel is configured, it is time to compile and install it. Exit 
the configuration and run the commands which will compile the kernel:
</p>

<pre caption="Compiling the kernel">
# <i>make &amp;&amp; make modules_install</i>
</pre>

<p>
When the kernel has finished compiling, copy the kernel image to
<path>/boot</path> (be sure that it is mounted properly on Pegasos computers).
If you are using BootX to boot, we'll copy the kernel later.
</p>

<p>
Yaboot and BootX expect to use an uncompressed kernel unlike many other 
bootloaders.  The uncompressed kernel is called vmlinux and it is placed in
<path>/usr/src/linux</path> after the kernel has finished compiling.  If you
are using a Pegasos machine, the Pegasos firmware requires a compressed
kernel called zImage.chrp which can be found in 
<path>/usr/src/linux/arch/ppc/boot/images</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing the kernel">
# <i>cd /usr/src/linux</i>
<comment>replace &lt;kernel-version&gt; with your kernel version</comment>
<comment>(Apple/IBM)</comment>
# <i>cp vmlinux /boot/&lt;kernel-version&gt;</i> 
<comment>(Pegasos)</comment>
# <i>cp arch/ppc/boot/images/zImage.chrp /boot/&lt;kernel-version&gt;</i> 
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#kernel_modules">Installing Separate Kernel
Modules</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="kernel_modules">
<title>Installing Separate Kernel Modules</title>
<subsection>
<title>Configuring the Modules</title>
<body>

<p>
You should list the modules you want automatically loaded in 
<path>/etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6</path>. 
You can add extra options to the modules too if you want.
</p>

<p>
To view all available modules, run the following <c>find</c> command. Don't
forget to substitute "&lt;kernel version&gt;" with the version of the kernel you
just compiled:
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing all available modules">
# <i>find /lib/modules/&lt;kernel version&gt;/ -type f -iname '*.o' -or -iname '*.ko'</i>
</pre>

<p>
For instance, to automatically load the <c>3c59x.o</c> module, edit the
<path>kernel-2.6</path> file and enter the module
name in it.
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6">
# <i>nano -w /etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6">
3c59x
</pre>

<p>
Continue the installation with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=8">Configuring 
your System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="genkernel">
<title>Alternative: Using genkernel</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are reading this section, you have chosen to use our <c>genkernel</c>
script to configure your kernel for you.
</p>

<p>
Now that your kernel source tree is installed, it's now time to compile your 
kernel by using our <c>genkernel</c> script to automatically build a kernel for 
you. <c>genkernel</c> works by configuring a kernel nearly identically to the 
way our Installation CD kernel is configured. This means that when you use 
<c>genkernel</c> to build your kernel, your system will generally detect all 
your hardware at boot-time, just like our Installation CD does. Because genkernel 
doesn't require any manual kernel configuration, it is an ideal solution for 
those users who may not be comfortable compiling their own kernels.
</p>

<p>
Now, let's see how to use genkernel. First, emerge the genkernel ebuild:
</p>

<pre caption="Emerging genkernel">
# <i>emerge genkernel</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next, copy over the kernel configuration used by the Installation CD to the 
location where genkernel looks for the default kernel configuration:
</p>

<pre caption="Copying over the Installation CD kernel config">
# <i>zcat /proc/config.gz > /usr/share/genkernel/ppc/kernel-config-2.6</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you are using firewire or USB to boot, you'll need to add modules to the 
initrd.  Edit <path>/usr/share/genkernel/ppc/modules_load</path> and change
<c>MODULES_FIREWIRE="ieee1394 ohci1394 sbp2"</c> for firewire support or
<c>MODULES_USB="usbcore ohci-hcd ehci-hcd usb-storage"</c> for USB support.
</p>


<p>
Now, compile your kernel sources by running <c>genkernel --genzimage all</c>.
For Pegasos, we will need to use a different config and create a zImage instead
of the vmlinux kernel used on Apple machines. Be aware, as <c>genkernel</c> 
compiles a kernel that supports almost all hardware, this compilation can take 
quite a while to finish!
</p>

<p>
Note that, if your partition where the kernel should be located doesn't use ext2
or ext3 as filesystem you might need to manually configure your kernel using
<c>genkernel --menuconfig --genzimage all</c> and add support for your 
filesystem <e>in</e> the kernel (i.e. <e>not</e> as a module). Users of EVMS2 or
LVM2 will probably want to add <c>--evms2</c> or <c>--lvm2</c> as argument as 
well.
</p>

<pre caption="Running genkernel">
# <i>genkernel --genzimage all</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Running genkernel on the Pegasos">
# <i>genkernel --genzimage --kernel-config=/usr/share/genkernel/ppc/Pegasos all</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once <c>genkernel</c> completes, a kernel, full set of modules and 
<e>initial root disk</e> (initrd) will be created. We will use the kernel 
and initrd when configuring a boot loader later in this document. Write
down the names of the kernel and initrd as you will need it when writing
the bootloader configuration file. The initrd will be started immediately after 
booting to perform hardware autodetection (just like on the Installation CD) 
before your "real" system starts up.  Be sure to also copy down the required
boot arguments, these are required for a successful boot with genkernel.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking the created kernel image name and initrd">
# <i>ls /boot/kernel* /boot/initramfs*</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you want your system to be more like the Installation CD you should,
when your Gentoo installation is over, emerge <c>coldplug</c>. While the 
initrd autodetects hardware that is needed to boot your system, 
<c>coldplug</c> autodetects everything else. <c>coldplug</c> is available as one
of the packages on the Package CD.
</p>

<pre caption="Emerging and enabling coldplug">
<comment>(Do this after the installation, during the GRP installation instructions)</comment>
# <i>emerge -k coldplug</i>
# <i>rc-update add coldplug boot</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you want your system to react to hotplugging events, you will need to install
and setup <c>hotplug</c> as well:
</p>

<pre caption="Emerging and enabling hotplug">
# <i>emerge hotplug</i>
# <i>rc-update add hotplug default</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=8">Configuring your System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</sections>

