<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.0/hb-install-amd64-bootloader.xml,v 1.5 2006/05/28 14:37:42 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>6.2</version>
<date>2006-05-28</date>

<section>
<title>Making your Choice</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel is configured and compiled and the necessary system
configuration files are filled in correctly, it is time to install a
program that will fire up your kernel when you start the system. Such a
program is called a <e>bootloader</e>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Framebuffer</title>
<body>

<!--
Verbatim copy from x86 bootloader framebuffer explanation, minus the section on
vesafb-tng
-->

<p>
<e>If</e> you have configured your kernel with framebuffer support (or you used
<c>genkernel</c>'s default kernel configuration), you can activate it by adding
a <c>vga</c> and/or a <c>video</c> statement to your bootloader configuration 
file.
</p>

<p>
64-bit systems must use the the <c>vesafb</c> driver, and so will need to set
the <c>vga</c> statement. The <c>vga</c> statement controls the resolution and
color depth of your framebuffer screen for <c>vesafb</c>. As stated in
<path>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/fb/vesafb.txt</path> (which gets installed
when you install a kernel source package), you need to pass the VESA number 
corresponding to the requested resolution and color depth to it.
</p>

<p>
The following table lists the available resolutions and colordepths and matches
those against the value that you need to pass on to the <c>vga</c> statement.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <ti></ti>
  <th>640x480</th>
  <th>800x600</th>
  <th>1024x768</th>
  <th>1280x1024</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>256</th>
  <ti>0x301</ti>
  <ti>0x303</ti>
  <ti>0x305</ti>
  <ti>0x307</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>32k</th>
  <ti>0x310</ti>
  <ti>0x313</ti>
  <ti>0x316</ti>
  <ti>0x319</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>64k</th>
  <ti>0x311</ti>
  <ti>0x314</ti>
  <ti>0x317</ti>
  <ti>0x31A</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>16M</th>
  <ti>0x312</ti>
  <ti>0x315</ti>
  <ti>0x318</ti>
  <ti>0x31B</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
The <c>video</c> statement controls framebuffer display options. It needs to be
given the framebuffer driver (<c>vesafb</c> for 2.6 kernels, or <c>vesa</c> for
2.4 kernels) followed by the control statements you wish to enable. All
variables are listed in <path>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/fb/vesafb.txt</path>,
but we'll inform you about three most-used options:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Control</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ywrap</ti>
  <ti>
    Assume that the graphical card can wrap around its memory (i.e. continue at
    the beginning when it has approached the end)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>mtrr:n</ti>
  <ti>
    Setup MTRR registers. <c>n</c> can be:
    0 - disabled
    1 - uncachable
    2 - write-back
    3 - write-combining
    4 - write-through
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
The result of those two statements could be something like <c>vga=0x318
video=vesafb:mtrr:3,ywrap</c> or
<c>video=vesafb:mtrr:3,ywrap,1024x768-32@85</c>.  Remember (or write down) this
setting; you will need it shortly.
</p>

<p>
While LILO does work on AMD64, Gentoo only supports using GRUB. Now continue by
its installation.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Using GRUB</title>
<subsection>
<title>Understanding GRUB's terminology</title>
<body>

<p>
The most critical part of understanding GRUB is getting comfortable with how
GRUB refers to hard drives and partitions. Your Linux partition
<path>/dev/hda1</path> (for IDE drives) or <path>/dev/sda1</path> (for
SATA/SCSI drives) will most likely be called <path>(hd0,0)</path> under GRUB.
Notice the parenthesis around the <path>hd0,0</path> - they are required.
</p>

<p>
Hard drives count from zero rather than "a" and partitions start at zero 
rather than one. Be aware too that with the hd devices, only hard drives are 
counted, not atapi-ide devices such as cdrom players and burners.  Also, the 
same construct is used with SCSI drives. (Normally they get higher numbers 
than IDE drives except when the BIOS is configured to boot from SCSI devices.)
When you ask the BIOS to boot from a different hard disk (for instance your
primary slave), <e>that</e> harddisk is seen as <path>hd0</path>.
</p>

<p>
Assuming you have a hard drive on <path>/dev/hda</path>, a cdrom player on 
<path>/dev/hdb</path>, a burner on <path>/dev/hdc</path>, a second hard drive 
on <path>/dev/hdd</path> and no SCSI hard drive, <path>/dev/hdd7</path> gets 
translated to <path>(hd1,6)</path>. It might sound tricky and tricky it is 
indeed, but as we will see, GRUB offers a tab completion mechanism
that comes handy for those of you having a lot of hard drives and
partitions and who are a little lost in the GRUB numbering scheme.
</p>

<p>
Having gotten the feel for that, it is time to install GRUB.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Installing GRUB</title>
<body>

<p>
To install GRUB, let's first emerge it. 
</p>

<pre caption="Installing GRUB">
# <i>emerge grub</i>
</pre>

<p>
Although GRUB is now installed, we still need to write up a
configuration file for it and install GRUB in the MBR so that GRUB 
automatically boots your newly created kernel. Create 
<path>/boot/grub/grub.conf</path> with <c>nano</c> (or, if applicable, another 
editor):
</p>

<pre caption="Creating /boot/grub/grub.conf">
# <i>nano -w /boot/grub/grub.conf</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now we are going to write up a <path>grub.conf</path>. Below you'll
find two possible <path>grub.conf</path> for the partitioning example we use 
in this guide, with kernel image <path>kernel-2.6.12-gentoo-r10</path>. We've 
only extensively commented the first <path>grub.conf</path>. 
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The first <path>grub.conf</path> is for people who have not used 
    <c>genkernel</c> to build their kernel
  </li>
  <li>
    The second <path>grub.conf</path> is for people who have used
    <c>genkernel</c> to build their kernel
  </li>
</ul>

<note>
If your root filesystem is JFS, you <e>must</e> add " ro" to the <c>kernel</c>
line since JFS needs to replay its log before it allows read-write mounting.
</note>

<pre caption="grub.conf for non-genkernel users">
<comment># Which listing to boot as default. 0 is the first, 1 the second etc.</comment>
default 0
<comment># How many seconds to wait before the default listing is booted.</comment>
timeout 30
<comment># Nice, fat splash-image to spice things up :)
# Comment out if you don't have a graphics card installed</comment>
splashimage=(hd0,0)/boot/grub/splash.xpm.gz

title=Gentoo Linux 2.6.12
<comment># Partition where the kernel image (or operating system) is located</comment>
root (hd0,0)
kernel /boot/kernel-2.6.12-gentoo-r10 root=/dev/hda3

<comment># The next four lines are only if you dualboot with a Windows system.</comment>
<comment># In this case, Windows is hosted on /dev/hda6.</comment>
title=Windows XP
rootnoverify (hd0,5)
makeactive
chainloader +1
</pre>

<pre caption="grub.conf for genkernel users">
default 0
timeout 30
splashimage=(hd0,0)/boot/grub/splash.xpm.gz

title=Gentoo Linux 2.6.12
root (hd0,0)
kernel /boot/kernel-2.6.12-gentoo-r10 root=/dev/ram0 init=/linuxrc ramdisk=8192 real_root=/dev/hda3 udev
initrd /boot/initramfs-genkernel-amd64-2.6.12-gentoo-r10

<comment># Only in case you want to dual-boot</comment>
title=Windows XP
rootnoverify (hd0,5)
makeactive
chainloader +1
</pre>

<p>
If you used a different partitioning scheme and/or kernel image, adjust
accordingly. However, make sure that anything that follows a GRUB-device (such
as <path>(hd0,0)</path>) is relative to the mountpoint, not the root. In other
words, <path>(hd0,0)/grub/splash.xpm.gz</path> is in reality
<path>/boot/grub/splash.xpm.gz</path> since <path>(hd0,0)</path> is
<path>/boot</path>.
</p>

<p>
Besides, if you chose to use a different partitioning scheme and did not put
<path>/boot</path> in a separate partition, the <path>/boot</path> prefix used
in the above code samples is really <e>required</e>. If you followed our
suggested partitioning plan, the <path>/boot</path> prefix it not required, but
a <path>boot</path> symlink makes it work. In short, the above examples should
work whether you defined a separate <path>/boot</path> partition or not.
</p>

<p>
If you need to pass any additional options to the kernel, simply add
them to the end of the kernel command. We're already passing one option
(<c>root=/dev/hda3</c> or <c>real_root=/dev/hda3</c>), but you can pass others 
as well, such as the <c>video</c> statement for framebuffer as we discussed
previously.
</p>

<p>
<c>genkernel</c> users should know that their kernels use the same boot options
as is used for the Installation CD. For instance, if you have SCSI devices, you
should add <c>doscsi</c> as kernel option.
</p>

<p>
Now save the <path>grub.conf</path> file and exit. We still need to install GRUB
in the MBR (Master Boot Record) though.
</p>

<p>
The GRUB developers recommend the use of <c>grub-install</c>. However, if for
some reason <c>grub-install</c> fails to work correctly you still have the
option to manually install GRUB.
</p>

<p>
Continue with <uri link="#grub-install-auto">Default: Setting up GRUB using
grub-install</uri> or <uri link="#grub-install-manual">Alternative: Setting up
GRUB using manual instructions</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="grub-install-auto">
<title>Default: Setting up GRUB using grub-install</title>
<body>

<p>
To install GRUB you will need to issue the <c>grub-install</c> command.
However, <c>grub-install</c> won't work off-the-shelf since we are inside a
chrooted environment. We need to create <path>/etc/mtab</path> which lists all
mounted filesystems. Fortunately, there is an easy way to accomplish this -
just copy over <path>/proc/mounts</path> to <path>/etc/mtab</path>, excluding
the <c>rootfs</c> line if you haven't created a separate boot partition. The
following command will work in both cases:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating /etc/mtab">
# <i>grep -v rootfs /proc/mounts &gt; /etc/mtab</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now we can install GRUB using <c>grub-install</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Running grub-install">
# <i>grub-install /dev/hda</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you have more questions regarding GRUB, please consult the <uri
link="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/grub-faq.html">GRUB FAQ</uri> or the <uri
link="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/manual/">GRUB Manual</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Continue with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="grub-install-manual">
<title>Alternative: Setting up GRUB using manual instructions</title>
<body>

<p>
To start configuring GRUB, you type in <c>grub</c>. You'll be presented
with the <path>grub&gt;</path> grub command-line prompt. Now, you need to type 
in the right commands to install the GRUB boot record onto your hard drive.
</p>

<pre caption=" Starting the GRUB shell">
# <i>grub</i>
</pre>

<note>
If your system does not have any floppy drives, add the <c>--no-floppy</c>
option to the above command to prevent grub from probing the (non-existing) 
floppy drives.
</note>

<p>
In the example configuration we want to install GRUB so that it reads its 
information from the boot-partition <path>/dev/hda1</path>, and installs the 
GRUB boot record on the hard drive's MBR (master boot record) so that the first
thing we see when we turn on the computer is the GRUB prompt. Of course, if you
haven't followed the example configuration during the installation,
change the commands accordingly.
</p>

<p>
The tab completion mechanism of GRUB can be used from within GRUB.
For instance, if you type in "<c>root (</c>" followed by a TAB, you will
be presented with a list of devices (such as <path>hd0</path>). If you
type in "<c>root (hd0,</c>" followed by a TAB, you will receive a list
of available partitions to choose from (such as <path>hd0,0</path>).
</p>

<p>
By using the tab completion, setting up GRUB should be not that hard.
Now go on, configure GRUB, shall we? :-)
</p>

<pre caption=" Installing GRUB in the MBR">
grub&gt; <i>root (hd0,0)</i>          <comment>(Specify where your /boot partition resides)</comment>
grub&gt; <i>setup (hd0)</i>           <comment>(Install GRUB in the MBR)</comment>
grub&gt; <i>quit</i>                  <comment>(Exit the GRUB shell)</comment>
</pre>

<note>
If you want to install GRUB in a certain partition instead of the MBR,
you have to alter the <c>setup</c> command so it points to the right
partition. For instance, if you want GRUB installed in
<path>/dev/hda3</path>, then the command becomes <c>setup (hd0,2)</c>.
Few users however want to do this.
</note>

<p>
If you have more questions regarding GRUB, please consult the <uri
link="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/grub-faq.html">GRUB FAQ</uri> or the <uri
link="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/manual/">GRUB Manual</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Continue with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="reboot">
<title>Rebooting the System</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Exit the chrooted environment and unmount all mounted partitions. Then type in 
that one magical command you have been waiting for: <c>reboot</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Unmounting all partitions and rebooting">
# <i>exit</i>
# <i>cd</i>
# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo/boot /mnt/gentoo/dev /mnt/gentoo/proc /mnt/gentoo</i>
# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Of course, don't forget to remove the bootable CD, otherwise the CD will be
booted again instead of your new Gentoo system.
</p>

<p>
Once rebooted in your Gentoo installation, finish up with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=11">Finalizing your Gentoo Installation</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
