<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.0/hb-installer-about.xml,v 1.2 2006/03/14 19:30:36 neysx Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-02-27</date>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<subsection>
<title>Welcome!</title>
<body>

<p>
First of all, <e>welcome</e> to Gentoo. You are about to enter the world
of customization and performance. When installing Gentoo, this is made clear to
you several times -- you can choose how much you want to compile yourself, how
to install Gentoo, what system logger you want, etc.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo is a fast, modern meta-distribution with a clean and flexible
design. Gentoo is built around free software and doesn't hide from its
users what is beneath the hood. Portage, the package maintenance system
which Gentoo uses, is written in Python, meaning you can easily view and
modify the source code. Gentoo's packaging system uses source code
(although support for precompiled packages is included too) and
configuring Gentoo happens through regular text files. In other words,
openness everywhere.
</p>

<p>
It is very important that you understand that <e>empowerment</e> is what makes
Gentoo run. We try not to force anything on our users and try our best to
empower you to make the choices you wish. If you feel a change should be made,
please file a <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bug report</uri> about it.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>How do I go about Installing Gentoo?</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo Linux comes with two versions of an easy to use Installer. A GTK+ based
installer (for use with an X based environment) and a Dialog based installer for
use on the console. Chapter 3 of the handbook deals with the GTK+ based
installer while Chapter 4 is for the Dialog based one.
</p>

<p>
Sometimes, you are given a certain choice in the handbook. We try our best to
explain what the pros and cons are. We will continue then with a default choice,
identified by &quot;Default: &quot; in the title. The other possibilities are
marked by &quot;Alternative: &quot;. Do <e>not</e> think that the default is
what we recommend. It is however what we believe most users will use.
</p>

<p>
Sometimes you can pursue an optional step. Such steps are marked as
&quot;Optional: &quot; and are therefore not needed to install Gentoo.
However, some optional steps are dependant on a previous decision you
made. We will inform you when this happens, both when you make the
decision, and right before the optional step is described.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>What are my Options?</title>
<body>

<p>
You can install Gentoo in many different ways. You can download and install from
one of our Installation CDs, from an existing distribution, from a bootable CD
(such as Knoppix), from a netbooted environment, from a rescue floppy, etc. 
</p>

<p>
This document covers the installation using a Gentoo Linux Installation CD, a 
bootable CD that contains everything you need to get Gentoo Linux up and 
running.  There are two types of Installation CDs, the InstallCD and the
Installer LiveCD.  The InstallCD is a minimal environment which contains only
those packages necessary for installing Gentoo Linux. The LiveCD is a complete
Gentoo Linux environment and can be used for multiple tasks, one of which is
installing Gentoo Linux. The LiveCD is not available on all architectures at
this time. If your architecture does not have a LiveCD, then this document will
refer to the Universal InstallCD for you.
</p>

<p>
This installation approach however does not immediately use the latest version
of the available packages; if you want this you should check out the
Installation Instructions inside our <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/index.xml">Gentoo Linux Handbooks</uri>.
</p>

<p>
For help on the other installation approaches, 
please read our <uri link="/doc/en/altinstall.xml">Alternative Installation
Guide</uri>. We also provide a <uri
link="/doc/en/gentoo-x86-tipsntricks.xml">Gentoo Installation Tips &amp; 
Tricks</uri> document that might be useful to read as well. If you feel that 
the current installation instructions are too elaborate, feel free to use our 
Quick Installation Guide available from our <uri 
link="/doc/en/index.xml">Documentation Resources</uri> if your architecture
has such a document available.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Troubles?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you find a problem in the installation (or in the installation
documentation), please check the errata from our <uri
link="/proj/en/releng/">Gentoo Release Engineering Project</uri>, 
visit our <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bug tracking
system</uri> and check if the bug is known. If not, please create a bug report 
for it so we can take care of it. Do not be afraid of the developers who are 
assigned to (your) bugs -- they generally don't eat people.
</p>

<p>
Note though that, although the document you are now reading is
architecture-specific, it will contain references to other architectures as
well. This is due to the fact that large parts of the Gentoo Handbook use source
code that is common for all architectures (to avoid duplication of efforts and
starvation of development resources). We will try to keep this to a minimum
to avoid confusion.
</p>

<p>
If you are uncertain if the problem is a user-problem (some error you
made despite having read the documentation carefully) or a
software-problem (some error we made despite having tested the
installation/documentation carefully) you are free to join #gentoo on
irc.freenode.net. Of course, you are welcome otherwise too :)
</p>

<p>
If you have a question regarding Gentoo, check out our <uri
link="/doc/en/faq.xml">Frequently Asked
Questions</uri>, available from the <uri
link="/doc/en/">Gentoo Documentation</uri>. You can
also view the <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum.php?f=40">FAQs</uri> on our
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">forums</uri>. If you can't find the answer
there ask on #gentoo, our IRC-channel on irc.freenode.net. Yes, several of
us are freaks who sit on IRC :-)
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Fast Installation using the Gentoo Reference Platform</title>
<subsection>
<title>What is the Gentoo Reference Platform?</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Reference Platform, from now on abbreviated to GRP, is a snapshot of
prebuilt packages users (that means you!) can install during the installation
of Gentoo to speed up the installation process. The GRP consists of all
packages required to have a fully functional Gentoo installation. They are not
just the ones you need to have a base installation up to speed in no time, but
all lengthier builds (such as xorg-x11, GNOME, OpenOffice, Mozilla, ...)
are available as GRP packages too.
</p>

<p>
However, these prebuilt packages aren't maintained during the lifetime of the
Gentoo distribution. They are snapshots released at every Gentoo release and
make it possible to have a functional environment in a short amount of time. You
can then upgrade your system in the background while working in your Gentoo
environment.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>How Portage Handles GRP Packages</title>
<body>

<p>
Your Portage tree - the collection of <e>ebuilds</e> (files that contain all 
information about a package, such as its description, homepage, sourcecode URLs,
compilation instructions, dependencies, etc.) - must be synchronised with the 
GRP set: the versions of the available ebuilds and their accompanying GRP 
packages must match.
</p>

<p>
For this reason you can only benefit from the GRP packages Gentoo provides while
performing the current installation approach. GRP is not available for those
interested in performing an installation using the latest versions of all
available packages.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Is GRP Available?</title>
<body>

<p>
Not all architectures provide GRP packages. That doesn't mean GRP isn't
supported on the other architectures, but it means that we don't have the 
resources to build and test the GRP packages.
</p>

<p>
At present we provide GRP packages for the following architectures:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The <b>amd64</b> architecture (amd64)
  </li>
  <li>
    The <b>ppc</b> architecture (ppc32, ppc64)
  </li>
  <li>
    The <b>sparc</b> architecture (sparc64)
  </li>
  <li>
    The <b>x86</b> architecture (athlon, athlon-xp, athlon-mp, pentium-pro,
    pentium2, pentium3, pentium4 and pentium-m) Note: The packages are for i686
    and are available on the Installer LiveCD.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
If your architecture (or subarchitecture) isn't on this list, you are not
able to opt for a GRP installation.
</p>

<p>
Now that this introduction is over, let's continue with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=2">Booting the Universal InstallCD/Installer
LiveCD</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
