<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.0/hb-install-config.xml,v 1.5 2006/05/27 13:02:15 neysx Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>6.2</version>
<date>2006-05-27</date>

<section>
<title>Filesystem Information</title>
<subsection>
<title>What is fstab?</title>
<body>

<p>
Under Linux, all partitions used by the system must be listed in
<path>/etc/fstab</path>. This file contains the mountpoints of those partitions
(where they are seen in the file system structure), how they should be mounted
and with what special options (automatically or not, whether users can mount
them or not, etc.)
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Creating /etc/fstab</title>
<body>

<p>
<path>/etc/fstab</path> uses a special syntax. Every line consists of six
fields, separated by whitespace (space(s), tabs or a mixture). Each field has
its own meaning:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
  The first field shows the <b>partition</b> described (the path to the device
  file)
</li>
<li>
  The second field shows the <b>mountpoint</b> at which the partition should be
  mounted
</li>
<li>
  The third field shows the <b>filesystem</b> used by the partition
</li>
<li>
  The fourth field shows the <b>mountoptions</b> used by <c>mount</c> when it
  wants to mount the partition. As every filesystem has its own mountoptions,
  you are encouraged to read the mount man page (<c>man mount</c>) for a full
  listing. Multiple mountoptions are comma-separated.
</li>
<li>
  The fifth field is used by <c>dump</c> to determine if the partition needs to
  be <b>dump</b>ed or not. You can generally leave this as <c>0</c> (zero).
</li>
<li>
  The sixth field is used by <c>fsck</c> to determine the order in which 
  filesystems should be <b>check</b>ed if the system wasn't shut down properly. 
  The root filesystem should have <c>1</c> while the rest should have <c>2</c> 
  (or <c>0</c> if a filesystem check isn't necessary).
</li>
</ul>

<p>
The default <path>/etc/fstab</path> file provided by Gentoo <e>is not a valid
fstab file</e>, so start <c>nano</c> (or your favorite editor) to create your
<path>/etc/fstab</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Opening /etc/fstab">
# <i>nano -w /etc/fstab</i>
</pre>

<p>
Let us take a look at how we write down the options for the <path>/boot</path>
partition. This is just an example, so if your architecture doesn't require a
<path>/boot</path> partition (such as Apple <b>PPC</b> machines), don't copy it
verbatim.
</p>

<p>
In our default x86 partitioning example <path>/boot</path> is the
<path>/dev/hda1</path> partition, with <c>ext2</c> as filesystem. 
It needs to be checked during boot, so we would write down:
</p>

<pre caption="An example /boot line for /etc/fstab">
/dev/hda1   /boot     ext2    defaults        1 2
</pre>

<p>
Some users don't want their <path>/boot</path> partition to be mounted
automatically to improve their system's security. Those people should 
substitute <c>defaults</c> with <c>noauto</c>. This does mean that you need to 
manually mount this partition every time you want to use it.
</p>

<p>
Now, to improve performance, most users would want to add the <c>noatime</c>
option as mountoption, which results in a faster system since access times
aren't registered (you don't need those generally anyway):
</p>

<pre caption="An improved /boot line for /etc/fstab">
/dev/hda1   /boot     ext2    defaults,noatime    1 2
</pre>

<p>
If we continue with this, we would end up with the following three lines (for
<path>/boot</path>, <path>/</path> and the swap partition):
</p>

<pre caption="Three /etc/fstab lines">
/dev/hda1   /boot     ext2    defaults,noatime  1 2
/dev/hda2   none      swap    sw                0 0
/dev/hda3   /         ext3    noatime           0 1
</pre>

<p>
To finish up, you should add a rule for <path>/proc</path>, <c>tmpfs</c>
(required) and for your CD-ROM drive (and of course, if you have other 
partitions or drives, for those too):
</p>

<pre caption="A full /etc/fstab example">
/dev/hda1   /boot     ext2    defaults,noatime     1 2
/dev/hda2   none      swap    sw                   0 0
/dev/hda3   /         ext3    noatime              0 1

none        /proc     proc    defaults             0 0
none        /dev/shm  tmpfs   nodev,nosuid,noexec  0 0

/dev/cdroms/cdrom0    /mnt/cdrom    auto      noauto,user    0 0
</pre>

<p>
<c>auto</c> makes <c>mount</c> guess for the filesystem (recommended for 
removable media as they can be created with one of many filesystems) and 
<c>user</c> makes it possible for non-root users to mount the CD.
</p>

<p>
Now use the above example to create your <path>/etc/fstab</path>. If you are a
<b>SPARC</b>-user, you should add the following line to your 
<path>/etc/fstab</path>
too:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding openprom filesystem to /etc/fstab">
none        /proc/openprom  openpromfs    defaults      0 0
</pre>

<p>
Double-check your <path>/etc/fstab</path>, save and quit to continue.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Networking Information</title>
<subsection>
<title>Hostname, Domainname etc.</title>
<body>

<p>
One of the choices the user has to make is name his/her PC. This seems to be 
quite easy, but <e>lots</e> of users are having difficulties finding the 
appropriate name for their Linux-pc. To speed things up, know that any name you 
choose can be changed afterwards. For all we care, you can just call your system
<c>tux</c> and domain <c>homenetwork</c>. 
</p>

<p>
We use these values in the next examples. First we set the hostname:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the hostname">
# <i>nano -w /etc/conf.d/hostname</i>

<comment>(Set the HOSTNAME variable to your hostname)</comment>
HOSTNAME="<i>tux</i>"
</pre>

<p>
Second we set the domainname:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the domainname">
# <i>nano -w /etc/conf.d/domainname</i>

<comment>(Set the DNSDOMAIN variable to your domain name)</comment>
DNSDOMAIN="<i>homenetwork</i>"
</pre>

<p>
If you have a NIS domain (if you don't know what that is, then you don't have
one), you need to define that one too:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the NIS domainname">
# <i>nano -w /etc/conf.d/domainname</i>

<comment>(Set the NISDOMAIN variable to your NIS domain name)</comment>
NISDOMAIN="<i>my-nisdomain</i>"
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Configuring your Network</title>
<body>

<p>
Before you get that "Hey, we've had that already"-feeling, you should remember
that the networking you set up in the beginning of the Gentoo installation was 
just for the installation. Right now you are going to configure networking for 
your Gentoo system permanently.
</p>

<note>
More detailed information about networking, including advanced topics like
bonding, bridging, 802.1Q VLANs or wireless networking is covered in the <uri
link="?part=4">Gentoo Network Configuration</uri> section.
</note>

<p>
All networking information is gathered in <path>/etc/conf.d/net</path>. It uses
a straightforward yet not intuitive syntax if you don't know how to set up
networking manually. But don't fear, we'll explain everything. A fully
commented example that covers many different configurations is available in
<path>/etc/conf.d/net.example</path>.
</p>

<p>
DHCP is used by default and does not require any further configuration.
</p>

<p>
If you need to configure your network connection either because you need
specific DHCP options or because you do not use DHCP at all, open
<path>/etc/conf.d/net</path> with your favorite editor (<c>nano</c> is used in
this example):
</p>

<pre caption="Opening /etc/conf.d/net for editing">
# <i>nano -w /etc/conf.d/net</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will see the following file:
</p>

<pre caption="Default /etc/conf.d/net">
# This blank configuration will automatically use DHCP for any net.*
# scripts in /etc/init.d.  To create a more complete configuration,
# please review /etc/conf.d/net.example and save your configuration
# in /etc/conf.d/net (this file :]!).
</pre>

<p>
To enter your own IP address, netmask and gateway, you need
to set both <c>config_eth0</c> and <c>routes_eth0</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Manually setting IP information for eth0">
config_eth0=( "192.168.0.2 netmask 255.255.255.0 brd 192.168.0.255" )
routes_eth0=( "default gw 192.168.0.1" )
</pre>

<p>
To use DHCP and add specific DHCP options, define <c>config_eth0</c> and
<c>dhcp_eth0</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Automatically obtaining an IP address for eth0">
config_eth0=( "dhcp" )
dhcp_eth0="nodns nontp nonis"
</pre>

<p>
Please read <path>/etc/conf.d/net.example</path> for a list of all available
options.
</p>

<p>
If you have several network interfaces repeat the above steps for 
<c>config_eth1</c>, <c>config_eth2</c>, etc.
</p>

<p>
Now save the configuration and exit to continue.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Automatically Start Networking at Boot</title>
<body>

<p>
To have your network interfaces activated at boot, you need to add them to the
default runlevel. If you have PCMCIA interfaces you should skip this action as
the PCMCIA interfaces are started by the PCMCIA init script.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding net.eth0 to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add net.eth0 default</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you have several network interfaces, you need to create the appropriate
<path>net.eth1</path>, <path>net.eth2</path> etc. initscripts for those. You can
use <c>ln</c> to do this:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating extra initscripts">
# <i>cd /etc/init.d</i>
# <i>ln -s net.eth0 net.eth1</i>
# <i>rc-update add net.eth1 default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Writing Down Network Information</title>
<body>

<p>
You now need to inform Linux about your network. This is defined in
<path>/etc/hosts</path> and helps in resolving hostnames to IP addresses for
hosts that aren't resolved by your nameserver.  You need to define your system.
You may also want to define other systems on your network if you don't want to
set up your own internal DNS system.
</p>

<pre caption="Opening /etc/hosts">
# <i>nano -w /etc/hosts</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Filling in the networking information">
<comment>(This defines the current system)</comment>
127.0.0.1     tux.homenetwork tux localhost

<comment>(Define extra systems on your network,
they need to have a static IP to be defined this way.)</comment>
192.168.0.5   jenny.homenetwork jenny
192.168.0.6   benny.homenetwork benny
</pre>

<p>
Save and exit the editor to continue.
</p>

<p>
If you don't have PCMCIA, you can now continue with <uri
link="#doc_chap3">System Information</uri>. PCMCIA-users should read the
following topic on PCMCIA.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Get PCMCIA Working</title>
<body>

<note>
pcmcia-cs is only available for x86, amd64 and ppc platforms.
</note>

<p>
PCMCIA-users should first install the <c>pcmcia-cs</c> package. This also
includes users who will be working with a 2.6 kernel (even though they won't be
using the PCMCIA drivers from this package). The <c>USE="-X"</c> is necessary 
to avoid installing xorg-x11 at this moment:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing pcmcia-cs">
# <i>USE="-X" emerge pcmcia-cs</i>
</pre>

<p>
When <c>pcmcia-cs</c> is installed, add <c>pcmcia</c> to the <e>default</e> 
runlevel:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding pcmcia to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add pcmcia default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>System Information</title>
<subsection>
<title>Root Password</title>
<body>

<p>
First we set the root password by typing:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the root password">
# <i>passwd</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you want root to be able to log on through the serial console, add 
<c>tts/0</c> to <path>/etc/securetty</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding tts/0 to /etc/securetty">
# <i>echo "tts/0" &gt;&gt; /etc/securetty</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>System Information</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo uses <path>/etc/rc.conf</path> for general, system-wide configuration.
Open up <path>/etc/rc.conf</path> and enjoy all the comments in that file :)
</p>

<pre caption="Opening /etc/rc.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/rc.conf</i>
</pre>

<p>
When you're finished configuring <path>/etc/rc.conf</path>, save and exit. 
</p>

<p>
As you can see, this file is well commented to help you set up the necessary
configuration variables. You can configure your system to use unicode and
define your default editor and your display manager (like gdm or kdm).
</p>

<p>
Gentoo uses <path>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</path> to handle keyboard configuration.
Edit it to configure your keyboard.
</p>

<pre caption="Opening /etc/conf.d/keymaps">
# <i>nano -w /etc/conf.d/keymaps</i>
</pre>

<p>
Take special care with the <c>KEYMAP</c> variable. If you select the wrong
<c>KEYMAP</c>, you will get weird results when typing on your keyboard.
</p>

<note>
Users of USB-based <b>SPARC</b> systems and <b>SPARC</b> clones might need to 
select an i386 keymap (such as "us") instead of "sunkeymap". <b>PPC</b> uses x86
keymaps on most systems. Users who want to be able to use ADB keymaps on boot
have to enable ADB keycode sendings in their kernel and have to set a mac/ppc
keymap in <path>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</path>.
</note>

<p>
When you're finished configuring <path>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</path>, save and
exit. 
</p>

<p>
Gentoo uses <path>/etc/conf.d/clock</path> to set clock options. Edit it
according to your needs.
</p>

<pre caption="Opening /etc/conf.d/clock">
# <i>nano -w /etc/conf.d/clock</i>
</pre>

<p>
If your hardware clock is not using UTC, you need to add <c>CLOCK="local"</c> to
the file. Otherwise you will notice some clock skew.
</p>

<p>
When you're finished configuring <path>/etc/conf.d/clock</path>, save and
exit. 
</p>

<p>
If you are not installing Gentoo on IBM PPC64 hardware, continue with
<uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=9">Installing Necessary System Tools</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Configuring the Console</title>
<body>

<note>
The following section applies to the IBM PPC64 hardware platforms.
</note>

<p>
If you are running Gentoo on IBM PPC64 hardware and using a virtual console 
you must uncomment the appropriate line in <path>/etc/inittab</path> for the 
virtual console to spawn a login prompt.
</p>

<pre caption="Enabling hvc or hvsi support in /etc/inittab">
hvc0:12345:respawn:/sbin/agetty -L 9600 hvc0
hvsi:12345:respawn:/sbin/agetty -L 19200 hvsi0
</pre>

<p>
You should also take this time to verify that the appropriate console is 
listed in <path>/etc/securetty</path>.
</p>

<p>
You may now continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=9">Installing Necessary 
System Tools</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
