<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2006.1/hb-install-gtkfe.xml,v 1.2 2006/11/01 23:57:49 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<!--  The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!--  See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<sections>

<version>2.1</version>
<date>2006-11-01</date>

<section>
<title>Welcome</title>
<subsection>
<title>Before you begin</title>
<body>

<p>
Once the Gentoo Linux Installer (GLI) has finished loading, you will be
greeted by the welcome screen. It provides a friendly introduction to the
process of installing Gentoo on your computer. Remember to read each option
carefully. There is detailed help available for each step of installation;
just click <c>Help</c> in the lower left corner of the installer. We recommend that
you always read the help pages before making your choices. Note that at any
time during the installation process, you can save your configuration
progress in case you need to resume your installation at a later time.
</p>

<p>
There are two types of installation modes available. Choose <c>Networkless</c>
to begin installing Gentoo Linux.
</p>

<note>
Selecting <c>Networkless</c> will make some later configuration options
unavailable. Simply proceed to the next screen.
</note>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Pre-installation Configuration</title>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Manual Network Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
In the next section, you are required to configure your network. The Installer
should have already detected and set up your network for you, but if it didn't,
you can manually configure your network. On the <e>Misc.</e> tab, you can
specify a location of your choice or keep the default of
<path>/var/log/installer.log</path> where the Installer will store its logs.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Remote Installation</title>
<body>

<p>
If you wish to enable SSH access to the machine, you can start <c>sshd</c> and
specify a root password.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Load Additional Kernel Modules</title>
<body>

<p>
If you need to load more kernel modules to support your hardware, enter their
names into the appropriate line, each separated by a space.
</p>

<warn>
Do not change the <e>Install mode</e> selection to anything besides
<b>Normal</b>. This feature is still experimental and changing it will leave you
with an unbootable system!
</warn>
<!-- still experimental for 2006.1? -->

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Partitioning</title>
<subsection>
<title>Preparing the disks</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to install Gentoo on your machine, you will need to prepare your
disks. The <e>Partitioning</e> screen will show you a list of detected disks and
allow you to specify the filesystems you would like to have on your
partitions. Clicking <c>Clear partitions</c> will erase all previous partitions on
your disk, so be careful with this option! It is also possible to resize
certain partition types.
</p>

<p>
If you choose to go with the <c>Recommended layout</c>, the installer will
create three partitions: 100MB for <path>/boot</path>, a <path>/swap</path>
partition up to 512MB in size, and the rest of the available space on the disk
is used for <path>/</path>, the root partition. If you have more than 4GB of
unpartitioned space, using the "Recommended layout" will automatically configure
your partitions without destroying any data on any existing partitions. 
</p>

<warn>
As with any partitioning application, you should backup your system before
making changes to your partition table, as any possible bugs could cause data
loss.
</warn>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Network Mounts</title>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Define network mounts</title>
<body>

<p>
This screen lets you set up and use any existing network mounts during and after
installation. Click <c>New</c> to begin configuration. At this time, only NFS is
supported.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>make.conf</title>
<subsection>
<title>USE flags</title>
<body>

<p>
Since you are performing a GRP/networkless install, you will not be allowed
to select USE flags before installation. However, you are free to set your own
USE flags in <path>/etc/make.conf</path> after you have rebooted into your
finished system.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>CFLAGS</title>
<body>

<p>
You should, however, select your processor type in the <e>CFLAGS</e> section along
with any custom optimizations you may want, such as <c>-O2</c> and
<c>-pipe</c>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Other</title>
<body>

<p>
Any other options you wish to set for future use should be selected now.
<e>Build binary packages</e> creates ready-to-install binary tarballs of all
packages you compile on your system. <e>DistCC</e> allows you to share the
burden of compiling with another computer via your network connection.
<e>ccache</e> saves compiled code for later use, and thus can greatly speed up
compilation time if you re-install the same package.
</p>

<p>
You will not be allowed to change your <e>CHOST</e>, as this can seriously damage
your installation. In <e>MAKEOPTS</e> you define how many parallel compilations
should occur when you install a package. A good choice is the number of CPUs
in your system plus one, but this guideline isn't always perfect. On a
uniprocessor system, <c>-j2</c> might be used.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Kernel Sources</title>
<subsection>
<title>Using the LiveCD kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
You must use the kernel present on the LiveCD for the GRP/networkless install.
This is merely a <c>gentoo-sources</c> kernel compiled by <c>genkernel</c>,
Gentoo's automated kernel compilation utility and will give you a kernel that
automatically detects and configures your hardware upon boot.
</p>

<p>
If you want to have a nifty background image during system boot, select the
<c>Enable bootsplash</c> option.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Bootloader</title>
<subsection>
<title>Making your choice</title>
<body>

<p>
This screen allows to you choose your bootloader and, optionally, specify
additional kernel parameters that will be used at bootup.
</p>

<p>
You may specify which disk to boot from by choosing the appropriate option
from <e>Boot Drive</e>. In Linux, the first IDE disk in your system is called
<c>hda</c>, the second IDE disk is <c>hdb</c>, and so on. If you have SATA or
SCSI disks, they will be called <c>sda</c>, <c>sdb</c>, etc. Please make the
correct selection for your system.
</p>
<!-- more bootloader inclusions needed about vga, etc. just don't include pure
CLI stuff, but only what can go on the extra kernel params line -->
<p>
If you need to pass any additional options to the kernel, such as video and/or
VGA statements, simply add them to the "Extra kernel parameters" section.
</p>

<p>
If you jumpered your harddrive because the BIOS can't handle large harddrives
you'll need to append <c>hdx=stroke</c>. If you have SCSI devices, you should
add <c>doscsi</c> as a kernel option.
</p>

<!-- do we need to cover all the stuff about lilo/grub and kernel parameter
lines and/or block devices here? -->

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Timezone</title>
<subsection>
<title>Choose your timezone</title>
<body>

<p>
Study the map and select the region closest to your actual location. Later,
you will be asked to select if you want your clock to be set to UTC or local
time.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Networking</title>
<subsection>
<title>Device information</title>
<body>

<p>
On this screen, you will be able to configure the various network interface
devices on your computer. Read the available options carefully.
</p>

<p>
On the <e>Hostname/Proxy Information/Other</e> tab, you will need to choose a
hostname for your machine. You may also specify proxy server and DNS settings
if needed.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Daemons</title>
<subsection>
<title>Cron daemon</title>
<body>

<p>
Cron daemons are helpful programs that run tasks at scheduled times. While you
do not <e>need</e> to install one, they can be quite useful.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>System logger</title>
<body>

<p>
A system logger is a necessity for any Linux operating system. Make your
selection from the available choices.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Extra Packages</title>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: installing extra packages</title>
<body>

<p>
The LiveCD contains a number of available pre-built packages. If you wish to
install any of them, check the appropriate box.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Startup Services</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
This screen allows you to choose various services to load at system boot.
Study the available options and their descriptions carefully, and then select
your desired services. For example, if you have chosen to install
<c>xorg-x11</c> and want to boot straight into a graphical desktop, then you
would select "xdm" from the list.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Other Settings</title>
<subsection>
<title>Miscellaneous options</title>
<body>

<p>
Now you will be able to change various settings, including keyboard layout,
graphical display manager, the default editor, and whether to set your
hardware clock to UTC or local time.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Users</title>
<subsection>
<title>Adding users and groups</title>
<body>

<p>
First set the root password for the system administrator (the <e>root</e>
user).
</p>

<p>
We <e>strongly</e> recommend that you create a regular user for daily work.
Working as root all the time is <e>dangerous</e> and should be avoided! Create
your users, add them to the appropriate groups, and set their passwords. You
can optionally change their home directories, select their login shell, and
set helpful comments.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Review</title>
<subsection>
<title>Finishing up</title>
<body>

<p>
Please take the time to double-check each step of the installation process,
ensuring that your system is properly configured. When you have finished
reviewing, you may save your progress and exit, or click <c>Install</c> to begin
automatically installing Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
You are free to browse around on the LiveCD while the installation proceeds.
The installer window will alert you when it has finished. At that point, can
close the window by clicking the <c>x</c> in the top right corner. When you are
ready, you may log out and reboot. Make sure you remove the LiveCD during the
reboot.
</p>

<p>
Congratulations, your system is now fully equipped! Continue with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=5">Where to go from here?</uri> to learn more about
Gentoo.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
