<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2008.0/hb-install-gli-medium.xml,v 1.8 2009/01/26 07:51:06 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>9.4</version>
<date>2008-06-21</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box using the Installer LiveCD.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr test="func:keyval('arch')='x86'">
  <th>CPU</th>
  <ti>i686 or later</ti>
</tr>
<tr test="func:keyval('arch')='AMD64'">
  <th>CPU</th>
  <ti>Any AMD64 or EM64T CPU</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Memory</th>
  <ti>256 MB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Diskspace</th>
  <ti>1.5 GB (excluding swap space)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Swap space</th>
  <ti>At least 256 MB</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- General description, propagated to other architectures as well -->
<!-- START -->
<section>
<title>The Gentoo Linux Installer LiveCD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
A LiveCD is a bootable medium which contains a self-sustained Gentoo
environment. It allows you to boot Linux from the CD. During the boot process
your hardware is detected and the appropriate drivers are loaded. The Gentoo
Installation CDs are maintained by Gentoo developers.
</p>

<p>
There currently are two Installation CDs available:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The Installer LiveCD contains everything you need to install Gentoo. It
    provides a graphical environment, a graphical as well as console based
    installer which automatically carries out the installation for you, and of
    course, the installation instructions for your architecture.
  </li>
  <li>
    The Minimal Installation CD contains only a minimal environment that allows
    you to boot up and configure your network so you can connect to the
    Internet. It does not contain any additional files and cannot be used
    during the current installation approach.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- STOP -->
<section>
<title>Download, Burn and Boot the Gentoo Linux Installer LiveCD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Downloading and Burning the Installer LiveCD</title>
<body>

<p>
You can download the Installer LiveCDs from one of our <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri>. They are located in the
<path><keyval id="release-dir"/>livecd/</path> directory.
</p>

<p>
Inside that directory you'll find an ISO file. That is a full CD image which
you can write on a CD-R.
</p>

<p>
After downloading the file, you can verify its integrity to see if it is
corrupted or not:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    You can check its MD5 checksum and compare it with the MD5 checksum we
    provide (for instance with the <c>md5sum</c> tool under Linux/Unix or <uri
    link="http://www.etree.org/md5com.html">md5sum</uri> for Windows)
  </li>
  <li>
    You can verify the cryptographic signature that we provide. You need to
    obtain the public key we use (17072058) before you proceed though.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
To fetch our public key using the GnuPG application, run the following command:
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining the public key">
$ <i>gpg --keyserver subkeys.pgp.net --recv-keys 17072058</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now verify the signature:
</p>

<pre caption="Verify the cryptographic signature">
$ <i>gpg --verify &lt;signature file&gt; &lt;downloaded iso&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
To burn the downloaded ISO(s), you have to select raw-burning. How you do this
is highly program-dependent. We will discuss <c>cdrecord</c> and <c>K3B</c>
here; more information can be found in our <uri
link="/doc/en/faq.xml#isoburning">Gentoo FAQ</uri>.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    With cdrecord, you simply type <c>cdrecord dev=/dev/hdc &lt;downloaded iso
    file&gt;</c> (replace <path>/dev/hdc</path> with your CD-RW drive's device
    path).
  </li>
  <li>
    With K3B, select <c>Tools</c> &gt; <c>Burn CD Image</c>. Then you can locate
    your ISO file within the 'Image to Burn' area. Finally click <c>Start</c>.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Booting the Installer LiveCD</title>
<body>

<impo>
Read this whole subsection before continuing, as you will probably not have the
opportunity to read it before doing things later.
</impo>

<p>
Once you have burned your LiveCD, it is time to boot it. Remove all CDs from
your CD drives, reboot your system and enter the BIOS.  This is usually done by
hitting DEL, F1 or ESC, depending on your BIOS. Inside  the BIOS, change the
boot order so that the CD-ROM is tried before the hard disk. This is often
found under "CMOS Setup". If you don't do this, your system will just reboot
from the hard disk, ignoring the CD-ROM.
</p>

<p>
Now place the LiveCD in the CD-ROM drive and reboot. You should see a boot
prompt. At this screen, you can hit Enter to begin the boot process with the
default boot options, or boot the LiveCD with custom boot options by specifying
a kernel followed by boot options and then hitting Enter.
</p>

<p>
Specifying a kernel? Yes, we provide a few kernels on our LiveCD. The default
one is <c>gentoo</c>. Other kernels are for specific hardware needs and the
<c>-nofb</c> variants which disable framebuffer.
</p>

<p>
Below you'll find a short overview on the available kernels:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Kernel</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr test="func:keyval('arch')='x86'">
  <ti>gentoo</ti>
  <ti>Default 2.6 kernel with support for multiple CPUs</ti>
</tr>
<tr test="func:keyval('arch')='AMD64'">
  <ti>gentoo</ti>
  <ti>
    Default kernel with support for K8 CPUS (including NUMA support) and EM64T
    CPUs
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>gentoo-nofb</ti>
  <ti>Same as <c>gentoo</c> but without framebuffer support</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>memtest86</ti>
  <ti>Test your local RAM for errors</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
You can also provide kernel options. They represent optional settings you can
(de)activate at will. The following list is the same as the one you receive
when you press F2 through F7 at the bootscreen.
</p>

</body>

<body>
 <include href="../hb-install-kernelparams.xml"/>
</body>

<body>

<note>
The CD will check for "no*" options before "do*" options, so that you can
override any option in the exact order you specify.
</note>

<p>
Now boot your CD, select a kernel (if you are not happy with the default
<c>gentoo</c> kernel) and boot options. As an example, we show you how
to boot the <c>gentoo</c> kernel, with <c>dopcmcia</c> as kernel
parameters:
</p>

<pre caption="Booting an Installation CD">
boot: <i>gentoo dopcmcia</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will then be greeted with a boot screen and progress bar. If you are
installing Gentoo on a system with a non-US keyboard, make sure you
immediately press Alt-F1 to switch to verbose mode and follow the prompt. If no
selection is made in 10 seconds the default (US keyboard) will be accepted and
the boot process will continue. Once the boot process completes, Gnome will
start up and you will be automatically logged in to the "Live" Gentoo Linux
system as "gentoo" in graphical mode. You will be logged in as "root", the
superuser on the other consoles and should have a root ("#") prompt there. You
can switch to those consoles by pressing Alt-F2, Alt-F3, Alt-F4 Alt-F5, Alt-F6.
Get back to the graphical desktop you started on by pressing Alt-F7. To switch
to other consoles from within X, you must prefix the above with Ctrl. You are
able to run commands as root from any terminal within the graphical environment
by using the <c>sudo</c> application. You can even become root within a
terminal to perform multiple tasks.
</p>

<pre caption="Using sudo to run applications">
<comment>(Example only)</comment>
<comment>(Editing the group file)</comment>
# <i>sudo vi /etc/group</i>
<comment>(Becoming root for a session)</comment>
# <i>sudo su -</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="hardware">
<title>Extra Hardware Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
When the LiveCD boots, it tries to detect all your hardware devices and loads
the appropriate kernel modules to support your hardware. In the vast majority
of cases, it does a very good job. However, in some cases, it may not auto-load
the kernel modules you need. If the PCI auto-detection missed some of your
system's hardware, you will have to load the appropriate kernel modules
manually. These tasks require root access.
</p>

<p>
In the next example we try to load the <c>8139too</c> module (support for
certain kinds of network interfaces):
</p>

<pre caption="Loading kernel modules">
# <i>modprobe 8139too</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="useraccounts">
<title>Optional: User Accounts</title>
<body>

<p>
If you plan on giving other people access to your installation environment or
you want to chat using <c>irssi</c> without root privileges (for security
reasons), you need to create the necessary user accounts and change the root
password. You need root access to change the root password and add new users.
</p>

<p>
To change the root password, use the <c>passwd</c> utility:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the root password">
$ <i>sudo su -</i>
# <i>passwd</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter your new password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter your password)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
To create a user account, we first enter their credentials, followed by its
password. We use <c>useradd</c> and <c>passwd</c> for these tasks. In the next
example, we create a user called "john".
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a user account">
# <i>useradd -m -G users john</i>
# <i>passwd john</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter john's password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter john's password)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
You can change your user id from root to the newly created user by using
<c>su</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing user id">
# <i>su - john</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can also change the password for the "gentoo" user in the graphical
environment. This account is already suitable for use on the Internet.
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the gentoo password">
$ <i>passwd</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter your new password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter your password)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Viewing Documentation while Installing</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to view the Gentoo Handbook (either from the CD or online) during the
installation, you can view it with Mozilla Firefox (from the graphical
environment) or with <c>links</c> (from a terminal environment).
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the on-CD documentation with Firefox">
# <i>firefox /mnt/cdrom/docs/handbook/html/index.html</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you would prefer to use <c>links</c> to see a text-only version of the
handbook, make sure you have created a user account (see <uri
link="#useraccounts">Optional: User Accounts</uri>). Then press <c>Alt-F2</c>
to go to a new terminal and log in.
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the on-CD documentation with links">
# <i>links /mnt/cdrom/docs/handbook/html/index.html</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can go back to your original window by pressing <c>Alt-F7</c>.
</p>

<p>
However, it is preferred that you use the online Gentoo Handbook as it will be
more recent than the one provided on the CD. You can view it using Firefox or
<c>links</c> as well, but only after having completed the <e>Configuring your
Network</e> chapter (otherwise you won't be able to go on the Internet to view
the document):
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the online documentation with Firefox">
# <i>firefox http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/<keyval id="online-book"/></i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Viewing the online documentation with links">
# <i>links http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/<keyval id="online-book"/></i>
</pre>

<p>
You can now choose to proceed by using the <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">GTK+
based installer</uri> (which needs X) or the <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=4">Dialog based installer</uri> that can be run on a
console.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
