<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2008.0/hb-install-gtkfe.xml,v 1.2 2008/03/31 21:48:08 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<!--  The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!--  See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<sections>

<version>4.0</version>
<date>2008-04-01</date>

<section>
<title>Welcome</title>
<subsection>
<title>Before you begin</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Linux Installer (GLI) provides a friendly introduction to the process
of installing Gentoo on your computer. Remember to read each option carefully.
There is detailed help available for each step of installation; just look to
the left of each screen. We recommend that you always read the help pages before
making your choices. Note that at any time during the installation process, you
can save your configuration progress in case you need to resume your
installation at a later time.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Partitioning</title>
<subsection>
<title>Preparing the disks</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to install Gentoo on your machine, you will need to prepare your
disks. The <e>Partitioning</e> screen will show you a list of detected disks and
allow you to specify the filesystems you would like to have on your
partitions. Clicking <c>Clear partitions</c> will erase all previous partitions on
your disk, so be careful with this option! It is also possible to resize
certain partition types.
</p>

<p>
If you choose to go with the <c>Recommended layout</c>, the installer will erase
any previous partitions on your disk and create three partitions: 100MB for
<path>/boot</path>, a <path>/swap</path> partition up to 512MB in size, and the
rest of the available space on the disk is used for <path>/</path>, the root
partition.
</p>

<warn>
As with any partitioning application, you should backup your system before
making changes to your partition table, as any possible bugs could cause data
loss. Any changes you make to your partition table will be performed by the
installer immediately.
</warn>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Timezone</title>
<subsection>
<title>Choose your timezone</title>
<body>

<p>
Study the map and select the region closest to your actual location. Later,
you will be asked to select if you want your clock to be set to UTC or local
time.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Networking</title>
<subsection>
<title>Device information</title>
<body>

<p>
On this screen, you will be able to configure the various network interface
devices on your computer. Read the available options carefully.
</p>

<p>
On the <e>Hostname/Proxy Information/Other</e> tab, you will need to choose a
hostname for your machine. You may also specify proxy server and DNS settings
if needed.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Users</title>
<subsection>
<title>Adding users and groups</title>
<body>

<p>
First set the root password for the system administrator (the <e>root</e>
user).
</p>

<p>
We <e>strongly</e> recommend that you create a regular user for daily work.
Working as root all the time is <e>dangerous</e> and should be avoided! Create
your users, add them to the appropriate groups, and set their passwords. You
can optionally change their home directories, select their login shell, and
set helpful comments.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Extra Packages</title>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: installing extra packages</title>
<body>

<p>
The LiveCD contains a number of available pre-built packages. If you wish to
install any of them, check the appropriate box.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Startup Services</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
This screen allows you to choose various services to load at system boot.
Study the available options and their descriptions carefully, and then select
your desired services. For example, if you have chosen to install
<c>xorg-x11</c> and want to boot straight into a graphical desktop, then you
would select "xdm" from the list.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Other Settings</title>
<subsection>
<title>Miscellaneous options</title>
<body>

<p>
Now you will be able to change various settings, including keyboard layout,
graphical display manager, the default editor, and whether to set your
hardware clock to UTC or local time.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Finishing Up</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
At this point, you're done. You can reboot into your new Gentoo system at any
time.
</p>

<p>
Congratulations, your system is now fully equipped! Continue with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=5">Where to go from here?</uri> to learn more about
Gentoo.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
