<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2004.2/hb-install-ppc-bootloader.xml,v 1.1 2004/11/15 12:43:54 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>1.13</version>
<date>October 23, 2004</date>

<section>
<title>Making your Choice</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel is configured and compiled and the necessary system
configuration files are filled in correctly, it is time to install a
program that will fire up your kernel when you start the system. Such a
program is called a <e>bootloader</e>. But before you start, consider
your options...
</p>

<p>
Several bootloaders exist for Linux/PPC. We have <uri link="#yaboot">yaBoot</uri>
(for NewWorld Apple and IBM machines) and <uri link="#bootx">BootX</uri> (for 
OldWorld Apple and IBM machines). The Pegasos does not require a bootloader.
You cannot use yaBoot or BootX on them at this time. Pegasos users should
therefore continue with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="yaboot">
<title>Default: Using yaBoot</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<impo>
yaBoot can only be used on NewWorld Apple and IBM systems!
</impo>

<p>
There are two ways to configure yaBoot for your system. You can use the
included <c>yabootconfig</c> to automatically set up yaboot. If
for some reason you do not want to run <c>yabootconfig</c> to
automatically set up <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> or you are installing Gentoo
on a G5 (on which <c>yabootconfig</c> does not always work), you can just edit 
the sample file already installed on your system.
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#yabootconfig">Default: Using yabootconfig</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#manual_yaboot">Alternative: Manual yaBoot Configuration</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="yabootconfig">
<title>Default: Using yabootconfig</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>yabootconfig</c> will auto-detect the partitions on your machine and will
set up dual and triple boot combinations with Linux, Mac OS, and Mac OS X.
</p>

<p>
To use <c>yabootconfig</c>, your drive must have a bootstrap partition, and
<path>/etc/fstab</path> must be configured with your Linux partitions. Both of 
these should have been done already in the steps above. To start, ensure that
you have the latest version of yaboot installed by running <c>emerge --update
yaboot</c>. This is necessary as the latest version will be available via
Portage, but it may not have made it into the stage files.
</p>

<pre caption = "Installing yaboot">
# <i>emerge --usepkg --update yaboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now exit the chroot and run <c>yabootconfig --chroot /mnt/gentoo</c>. The program will run and it will confirm
the location of the bootstrap partition. Type <c>Y</c> if it is correct. If
not, double check <path>/etc/fstab</path>. yabootconfig will then scan your
system setup, create <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> and run <c>mkofboot</c> for
you. <c>mkofboot</c> is used to format the bootstrap partition, and install 
the yaboot configuration file into it.
After this enter the chroot again.
</p>
<pre caption="enter chroot">
# <i>chroot /mnt/gentoo /bin/bash</i>
# <i>/usr/sbin/env-update &amp;&amp; source /etc/profile</i>
</pre>

<p>
You might want to verify the contents of <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path>. If 
you make changes to <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> (like setting the 
default/boot OS), make sure to rerun <c>ybin -v</c> to apply changes to the 
bootstrap partition.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="manual_yaboot">
<title>Alternative: Manual yaBoot Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
First make sure you have the latest <c>yaboot</c> installed on your
system:
</p>

<pre caption = "Installing yaboot">
# <i>emerge --usepkg --update yaboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Below you find a completed <path>yaboot.conf</path> file. Alter it at
will. G5 users should be aware that their disks are Serial ATA disks which are
seen as SCSI disks by the Linux kernel (so substitute <path>/dev/hda</path> with
<path>/dev/sda</path>).
</p>

<pre caption = "/etc/yaboot.conf">
<comment>## /etc/yaboot.conf
##
## run: "man yaboot.conf" for details. Do not make changes until you have!!
## see also: /usr/share/doc/yaboot/examples for example configurations.
##
## For a dual-boot menu, add one or more of:
## bsd=/dev/hdaX, macos=/dev/hdaY, macosx=/dev/hdaZ

## our bootstrap partition:</comment>

boot=/dev/hda1

<comment>## ofboot is the openfirmware way to specify the bootstrap partition.
## If this isn't defined, yaboot fails on the G5 (unless you pass the necessary
## arguments to the mkofboot/ybin program).
## hd:X means /dev/sdaX (or /dev/hdaX).
## 
## G5 users should uncomment this line!!

#ofboot=hd:1</comment>

<comment>##hd: is open firmware speak for hda</comment>
device=hd:
partition=3

delay=5
defaultos=macosx
timeout=30
install=/usr/lib/yaboot/yaboot
magicboot=/usr/lib/yaboot/ofboot

<comment>#################
## This section can be duplicated if you have more than one kernel or set of
## boot options - replace 2.6.7 with your kernel-version
#################</comment>
image=/boot/kernel-2.6.7
  label=Linux
  root=/dev/hda3
  sysmap=/boot/System.map-2.6.7
  read-only
<comment>##################</comment>

<comment>## G5 users should set 
##   macos=hd:13
##   macosx=hd:12
## instead of the example values.</comment>
macos=/dev/hda13
macosx=/dev/hda12
enablecdboot
enableofboot
</pre>

<p>
Once <path>yaboot.conf</path> is set up the way you want it, you run 
<c>mkofboot -v</c> to install the settings in the bootstrap partition. <e>Don't 
forget this!</e> If all goes well, and you have the same options as the sample 
above, your next reboot will give you a simple, five-entry boot menu. If you 
update your yaboot config later on, you'll just need to run <c>ybin -v</c> to 
update the bootstrap partition - <c>mkofboot</c> is for initial setup only.
</p>

<p>
For more information on yaboot, take a look at the <uri
link="http://penguinppc.org/projects/yaboot">yaboot project</uri>. For
now, continue the installation with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the
System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="bootx">
<title>Alternative: BootX</title>
<body>

<impo>
BootX can only be used on OldWorld Apple and IBM systems!
</impo>

<p>
BootX requires that you reboot first. So, let's reboot shall we :)
</p>

<p>
First exit the chrooted environment and unmount all mounted partitions, then
type in the one magical command you have been waiting for: <c>reboot</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Exiting the chroot, unmounting all partitions and rebooting">
# <i>exit</i>
cdimage ~# <i>cd</i>
cdimage ~# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo/proc /mnt/gentoo</i>
cdimage ~# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Of course, don't forget to remove the bootable CD, otherwise the CD will be
booted again instead of Mac OS X.
</p>

<p>
Now your machine is booted in MacOS, open the BootX control panel. Select
<c>Options</c> and uncheck <c>Used specified RAM disk</c>. When you return to 
the BootX main screen, you will now find an option to specify your machine's 
root disk and partition. Fill these in with the appropriate values.
</p>

<p>
BootX can be configured to start Linux upon boot. If you do this, you will first
see your machine boot into MacOS then, during startup, BootX will load and start
Linux. See the <uri link="http://penguinppc.org/projects/bootx/">BootX home 
page</uri> for more information.
</p>

<p>
Now reboot again and boot into Linux, then continue with <uri 
link="?part=1&amp;chap=11">Finalizing your Gentoo Installation</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="reboot">
<title>Rebooting the System</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Exit the chrooted environment and unmount all mounted partitions. Then type in 
that one magical command you have been waiting for: <c>reboot</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Exiting the chroot, unmounting all partitions and rebooting">
# <i>exit</i>
cdimage ~# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo/boot /mnt/gentoo/proc /mnt/gentoo</i>
cdimage ~# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Of course, don't forget to remove the bootable CD, otherwise the CD will be
booted again instead of your new Gentoo system.
</p>

<p>
Once rebooted in your Gentoo installation, finish up with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=11">Finalizing your Gentoo Installation</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
