<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2004.2/hb-install-mips-medium.xml,v 1.1 2004/11/15 12:43:54 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>1.3</version>
<date>May 9, 2004</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box. This of course depends on your
architecture.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The MIPS Architecture</title>
<body>

<p>
Check the following requirements before you
continue with the Gentoo installation:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
  You need at least 1 Gb of free disk space
</li>
<li>
  For the <e>MIPS architecture</e>, you should check with the <uri
  link="/doc/en/mips-requirements.xml">MIPS Hardware Requirements</uri> document
</li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Make your Choice</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Still interested in trying out Gentoo? Well, then it is now time to
choose the installation medium you want to use. 
</p>

<p>
The installation media we will describe are:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Net Booting</li>
</ul>

<p>
But first let us take a look at our "stage installation method".
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The Three Stages</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo Linux can be installed using one of three <e>stage</e> tarball files.
The one you choose depends on how much of the system you want to compile
yourself. The <e>stage1</e> tarball is used when you want to bootstrap and
build the entire system from scratch. The <e>stage2</e> tarball is used for
building the entire system from a bootstrapped &quot;semi-compiled&quot; state.
The <e>stage3</e> tarball already contains a basic Gentoo Linux system that has
been built for you. As we will explain later, you can also install
Gentoo without compiling anything (except your kernel and some optional 
packages). If you want this, you have to use a <e>stage3</e> tarball.
</p>

<p>
Now what stage do you have to choose?
</p>

<p>
Starting from a <e>stage1</e> allows you to have total control over the
optimization settings and optional build-time functionality that is
initially enabled on your system. This makes <e>stage1</e> installs good for
power users who know what they are doing. It is also a great
installation method for those who would like to know more about the
inner workings of Gentoo Linux.
</p>

<p>
A <e>stage1</e> installation can only be performed when you have a working
Internet connection.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Stage1</th>
  <th>Pros and Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>
    Allows you to have total control over the optimization settings and optional
    build-time functionality that is initially enabled on your system
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>Suitable for powerusers that know what they are doing</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>Allows you to learn more about the inner workings of Gentoo</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>Takes a long time to finish the installation</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>
    If you don't intend to tweak the settings, it is probably a waste of time
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>
    Not suitable for networkless installations
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
<e>Stage2</e> installs allow you to skip the bootstrap process and doing this
is fine if you are happy with the optimization settings that we chose
for your particular <e>stage2</e> tarball.
</p>

<p>
A <e>stage2</e> installation can only be performed when you have a working
Internet connection.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Stage2</th>
  <th>Pros and Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>You don't need to bootstrap</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>Faster than starting with stage1</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>You can still tweak your settings</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>You cannot tweak as much as with a stage1</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>It's not the fastest way to install Gentoo</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>You have to accept the optimizations we chose for the bootstrap</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>
    Not suitable for networkless installations
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Choosing to go with a <e>stage3</e> allows for the fastest install of Gentoo
Linux, but also means that your base system will have the optimization
settings that we chose for you (which to be honest, are good settings
and were carefully chosen to enhance performance while maintaining
stability). <e>stage3</e> is also required if you want to install Gentoo using
prebuilt packages or without a network connection.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Stage3</th>
  <th>Pros and Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>Fastest way to get a Gentoo base system</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>Suitable for networkless installations</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>You cannot tweak the base system - it's built already</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>You cannot brag about having used stage1 or stage2</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Write down (or remember) what stage you want to use. You need this later when
you decide what LiveCD (or other installation medium) you want to use. You might
be interested to know that, if you decide to use different optimization settings
after having installed Gentoo, you will be able to recompile your entire system
with the new optimization settings.
</p>

<p>
Now take a look at the available installation media.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Net Booting</title>
<body>

<p>
In some cases you do not have the possibility to boot from a CD or use an
existing installation to install Gentoo from. In case your system has a network
interface and BIOS/ROM capable of performing a netboot (PXE) you can have it
download a small system at boot time and install from that system onwards.
</p>

<p>
In case you want to use the net boot method
you should already have a working DHCP and TFTP server. Information on setting
up a <uri link="/doc/en/diskless-howto.xml#doc_chap3">DHCP server</uri> and <uri
link="/doc/en/diskless-howto.xml#doc_chap4">TFTP server</uri> are available in
the <uri link="/doc/en/diskless-howto.xml">Diskless-HOWTO</uri>. 
</p>

<p>
Depending on your setup, you might need to create or download a kernel image for
your system.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Net Booting your MIPS System</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
To be able to install Gentoo, the image you download from the TFTP server should
provide the necessary tools to create filesystems, create and mount partitions,
extract a tarball and chroot. You can download existing net boot images which
have all tools in them...
</p>

<p>
First download one of the available net boot images from 
<uri>http://dev.gentoo.org/~kumba/mips/netboot/</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Now configure your DHCP server to send this file to the booting client. SGI
machines however need some minor tweaks to the host system in order for TFTP to
work properly:
</p>

<pre caption="Some fixes to SGI machines to have TFTP work properly">
<comment>(Disable "Path Maximum Transfer Unit", otherwise SGI Prom won't find the kernel)</comment>
# <i>echo 1 &gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_no_pmtu_disc</i>
<comment>(Set the port range usable by the SGI Prom)</comment>
# <i>echo "2048 32767" &gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_local_port_range</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now power on your machine, get into the PROM monitor and issue the command to
boot the kernel over the network:
</p>

<pre caption="Net booting a MIPS">
        Running power-on diagnostics

System Maintenance Menu

1) Start System
2) Install System Software
3) Run Diagnostics
4) Recover System
5) Enter Command Monitor

Option? <i>5</i>
Command Monitor. Type "exit" to return to the menu.
&gt;&gt; <i>bootp(): root=/dev/ram0</i>
</pre>

<note>
You may have to press the Esc key to get into the menu above, otherwise, the
system will attempt to boot the system directly. 
</note>

<p>
Sometimes netbooting is a tricky endeavour. The following PROM commands below
may help, but this is not guaranteed. If your machine refuses to netboot, double
check things on the host TFTP machine to make sure that:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>dhcpd is giving the SGI Machine an IP Address</li>
  <li>
    Permissions are set properly in your tftp folder (typically 
    <path>/tftpboot</path>)
  </li>
  <li>
    Check system logs to see what the tftp server is reporting (errors
    perhaps)
  </li>
  <li>
    Pray to a Tux plushie (this may or may not work, and is not an officially
    supported troubleshooting technique)
  </li>
</ul>

<pre caption="Net booting tricks">
&gt;&gt; <i>resetenv</i>
&gt;&gt; <i>unsetenv netaddr</i>
&gt;&gt; <i>unsetenv dlserver</i>
&gt;&gt; <i>init</i>
&gt;&gt; <i>bootp(): root=/dev/ram0</i>
</pre>

<p>
If all things go well, you are now dropped off at busybox' <c>ash</c> shell. You
can then continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">Configuring your
Network</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
