<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2004.2/hb-install-tools.xml,v 1.1 2004/11/15 12:43:54 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>1.26</version>
<date>October 9, 2004</date>

<section>
<title>System Logger</title>
<body>

<p>
When we mentioned what <e>stage3</e> was, we said that it contained all
necessary system tools for which we cannot provide a choice to our users. We 
also said that we would install the other tools later on. Well, here we are :)
</p>

<p>
The first tool you need to decide on has to provide logging facilities for your
system. Unix and Linux have an excellent history of logging capabilities -- if
you want you can log everything that happens on your system in logfiles. This
happens through the <e>system logger</e>.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo offers several system loggers to choose from. There are <c>sysklogd</c>,
which is the traditional set of system logging daemons, <c>syslog-ng</c>, an 
advanced system logger, and <c>metalog</c> which is a highly-configurable 
system logger. Others might be available through Portage as well - our number of
available packages increases on a daily basis.
</p>

<p>
If you can't choose one, use <c>metalog</c> as it is very powerful yet comes
with a great default configuration.
</p>

<p>
To install the system logger of your choice, <c>emerge</c> it and have it added
to the default runlevel using <c>rc-update</c>. The following example installs
<c>metalog</c>. Of course substitute with your system logger:
</p>

<warn>
The stage3 tarballs of the 2004.2 release erroneously contain the sysklogd
logger. You will need to unmerge this logger before emerging a new one.
</warn>

<pre caption="Installing a system logger">
<comment>(First unmerge the sysklogd logger if you use a stage3 tarball)</comment>
# <i>emerge unmerge sysklogd</i>
<comment>(You will also need to remove the sysklogd init script)</comment>
# <i>rm /etc/init.d/sysklogd</i>

<comment>(Now install the system logger of your choice)</comment>
# <i>emerge metalog</i>
# <i>rc-update add metalog default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Optional: Cron Daemon</title>
<body>

<p>
Next is the cron daemon. Although it is optional and not required for your
system, it is wise to install one. But what is a cron daemon? A cron daemon 
executes scheduled commands. It is very handy if you need to execute some 
command regularly (for instance daily, weekly or monthly).
</p>

<p>
Gentoo offers three possible cron daemons: <c>dcron</c>, <c>fcron</c> and
<c>vixie-cron</c>. Installing one of them is similar to installing a system 
logger. However, <c>dcron</c> and <c>fcron</c> require an extra configuration 
command, namely <c>crontab /etc/crontab</c>. If you don't know what to choose, 
use <c>vixie-cron</c>.
</p>

<p>
We only provide <c>vixie-cron</c> for networkless installations. If you want
another cron daemon you can wait and install it later on.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a cron daemon">
# <i>emerge vixie-cron</i>
# <i>rc-update add vixie-cron default</i>
<comment>(Only if you have chosen dcron or fcron)</comment> # <i>crontab /etc/crontab</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Optional: File Indexing</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to index your system's files so you are able to quickly
locate them using the <c>locate</c> tool, you need to install
<c>sys-apps/slocate</c>. 
</p>

<note>
If you are not installing Gentoo using cascading profiles slocate will 
already be part of your system. Cascading profiles are not used by default yet 
so if you don't understand it you can assume that you're not using cascading 
profiles.
</note>

<pre caption="Installing slocate">
# <i>emerge slocate</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>File System Tools</title>
<body>

<p>
Depending on what file systems you are using, you need to install the necessary
file system utilities (for checking the filesystem integrity, creating 
additional file systems etc.).
</p>

<p>
The following table lists the tools you need to install if you use a certain
file system:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>File System</th>
  <th>Tool</th>
  <th>Install Command</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>XFS</ti>
  <ti>xfsprogs</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge xfsprogs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ReiserFS</ti>
  <ti>reiserfsprogs</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge reiserfsprogs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>JFS</ti>
  <ti>jfsutils</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge jfsutils</c></ti>
</tr>
</table>

<!-- TODO reactivate when LVM2 instructions are boarded
<p>
If you are an LVM user, you also need to install <c>lvm-user</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing LVM utilities">
# <i>emerge - -usepkg lvm-user</i>
</pre>
-->

<p>
If you don't require any additional networking-related tools (such as rp-pppoe
or a dhcp client) continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=10">Configuring the
Bootloader</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Networking Tools</title>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Installing a DHCP Client</title>
<body>

<p>
If you require Gentoo to automatically obtain an IP address for your network
interface(s), you need to install <c>dhcpcd</c> (or any other DHCP Client) 
on your system. If you don't do this now, you might not be able to connect 
to the internet after the installation!
</p>

<note>
If you are not installing Gentoo using cascading profiles dhcpcd will 
already be part of your system. Cascading profiles are not used by default yet 
so if you don't understand it you can assume that you're not using cascading 
profiles.
</note>

<pre caption="Installing dhcpcd">
# <i>emerge dhcpcd</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Installing a PPPoE Client</title>
<body>

<p>
If you need <c>rp-pppoe</c> to connect to the net, you need to install it.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing rp-pppoe">
# <i>USE="-X" emerge rp-pppoe</i>
</pre>

<p>
The <c>USE="-X"</c> will prohibit xorg-x11 to be installed as a dependency
(<c>rp-pppoe</c> has graphical tools; if you want those enabled, you can
recompile <c>rp-pppoe</c> later on or have xorg-x11 installed now -- which takes a
long time to compile).
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=10">Configuring the
Bootloader</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
