<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2004.2/hb-working-variables.xml,v 1.1 2004/11/15 12:43:54 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>1.8</version>
<date>August 30, 2004</date>

<section>
<title>Environment Variables?</title>
<subsection>
<title>What they are</title>
<body>

<p>
An environment variable is a named object that contains information used by one
or more applications. Many users (and especially those new to Linux) find this
a bit weird or unmanageable. However, this is a mistake: by using environment
variables one can easily change a configuration setting for one or more
applications.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Important Examples</title>
<body>

<p>
The following table lists a number of variables used by a Linux system and
describes their use. Example values are presented after the table.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Variable</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>PATH</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains a colon-separated list of directories in which your 
    system looks for executable files. If you enter a name of an executable 
    (such as <c>ls</c>, <c>rc-update</c> or <c>emerge</c>) but this executable 
    is not located in a listed directory, your system will not execute it 
    (unless you enter the full path as command, such as <c>/bin/ls</c>).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ROOTPATH</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable has the same function as <c>PATH</c>, but this one only lists
    the directories that should be checked when the root-user enters a command.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LDPATH</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains a colon-separated list of directories in which the
    dynamical linker searches through to find a library.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>MANPATH</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains a colon-separated list of directories in which the
    <c>man</c> command searches for the man pages.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>INFODIR</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains a colon-separated list of directories in which the
    <c>info</c> command searches for the info pages.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>PAGER</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains the path to the program used to list the contents of
    files through (such as <c>less</c> or <c>more</c>).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>EDITOR</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains the path to the program used to change the contents
    of files with (such as <c>nano</c> or <c>vi</c>).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>KDEDIRS</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains a colon-separated list of directories which contain
    KDE-specific material.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>CLASSPATH</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains a colon-separated list of directories which contain
    Java classes.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>CONFIG_PROTECT</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains a <e>space</e>-delimited list of directories which
    should be protected by Portage during updates.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>CONFIG_PROTECT_MASK</ti>
  <ti>
    This variable contains a <e>space</e>-delimited list of directories which
    should not be protected by Portage during updates. 
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Below you will find an example definition of all these variables:
</p>

<pre caption="Example definitions">
PATH="/bin:/usr/bin:/usr/local/bin:/opt/bin:/usr/games/bin"
ROOTPATH="/sbin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/local/sbin:/usr/local/bin"
LDPATH="/lib:/usr/lib:/usr/local/lib:/usr/lib/gcc-lib/i686-pc-linux-gnu/3.2.3"
MANPATH="/usr/share/man:/usr/local/share/man"
INFODIR="/usr/share/info:/usr/local/share/info"
PAGER="/usr/bin/less"
EDITOR="/usr/bin/vim"
KDEDIRS="/usr"
CLASSPATH="/opt/blackdown-jre-1.4.1/lib/rt.jar:."
CONFIG_PROTECT="/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/xkb /opt/tomcat/conf \
                /usr/kde/3.1/share/config /usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/config/ \
                /usr/share/texmf/tex/platex/config/ /usr/share/config"
CONFIG_PROTECT_MASK="/etc/gconf
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Defining Variables Globally</title>
<subsection>
<title>The /etc/env.d Directory</title>
<body>

<p>
To centralise the definitions of these variables, Gentoo introduced the
<path>/etc/env.d</path> directory. Inside this directory you will find a number
of files, such as <path>00basic</path>, <path>05gcc</path>, etc. which contain
the variables needed by the application mentioned in their name.
</p>

<p>
For instance, when you installed <c>gcc</c>, a file called <path>05gcc</path>
was created by the ebuild which contains the definitions of the following
variables:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/env.d/05gcc">
PATH="/usr/i686-pc-linux-gnu/gcc-bin/3.2"
ROOTPATH="/usr/i686-pc-linux-gnu/gcc-bin/3.2"
MANPATH="/usr/share/gcc-data/i686-pc-linux-gnu/3.2/man"
INFOPATH="/usr/share/gcc-data/i686-pc-linux-gnu/3.2/info"
CC="gcc"
CXX="g++"
LDPATH="/usr/lib/gcc-lib/i686-pc-linux-gnu/3.2.3"
</pre>

<p>
Other distributions tell you to change or add such environment variable
definitions in <path>/etc/profile</path> or other locations. Gentoo on the other
hand makes it easy for you (and for Portage) to maintain and manage the
environment variables without having to pay attention to the numerous files that
can contain environment variables.
</p>

<p>
For instance, when <c>gcc</c> is updated, the <path>/etc/env.d/05gcc</path> file
is updated too without requesting any user-interaction. 
</p>

<p>
This not only benefits Portage, but also you, as user. Occasionally you might
be asked to set a certain environment variable system-wide. As an example we
take the <c>http_proxy</c> variable. Instead of messing about with
<path>/etc/profile</path>, you can now just create a file
(<path>/etc/env.d/99local</path>) and enter your definition(s) in it:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/env.d/99local">
http_proxy="proxy.server.com:8080"
</pre>

<p>
By using the same file for all your variables, you have a quick overview on the
variables you have defined yourself. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The env-update Script</title>
<body>

<p>
Several files in <path>/etc/env.d</path> define the <c>PATH</c> variable. This
is not a mistake: when you run <c>env-update</c>, it will append the several
definitions before it updates the environment variables, thereby making it easy
for packages (or users) to add their own environment variable settings without
interfering with the already existing values.
</p>

<p>
The <c>env-update</c> script will append the values in the alphabetical order of
the <path>/etc/env.d</path> files. This is why many of the files in
<path>/etc/env.d</path> begin with a number.
</p>

<pre caption="Update order used by env-update">
         00basic        99kde-env       99local
     +-------------+----------------+-------------+
PATH="/bin:/usr/bin:/usr/kde/3.2/bin:/usr/local/bin"
</pre>

<p>
When you run <c>env-update</c>, the script will create all environment variables
and place them in <path>/etc/profile.env</path> (which is used by
<path>/etc/profile</path>). It will also extract the information from the
<c>LDPATH</c> variable and use that to create <path>/etc/ld.so.conf</path>.
After this, it will run <c>ldconfig</c> to recreate the
<path>/etc/ld.so.cache</path> file used by the dynamical linker.
</p>

<p>
If you want to notice the effect of <c>env-update</c> immediately after you run
it, execute the following command to update your environment. Users who have
installed Gentoo themselves will probably remember this from the installation
instructions:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating the environment">
# <i>env-update &amp;&amp; source /etc/profile</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Defining Variables Locally</title>
<subsection>
<title>User Specific</title>
<body>

<p>
You do not always want to define an environment variable globally. For instance,
you might want to add <path>/home/my_user/bin</path> to the <c>PATH</c> variable
but don't want all other users on your system to have that in their <c>PATH</c>
too. If you want to define an environment variable locally, you should use
<path>~/.bashrc</path> or <path>~/.bash_profile</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Extending PATH for local usage in ~/.bashrc">
PATH="${PATH}:/home/my_user/bin"
</pre>

<p>
When you relogin, your <c>PATH</c> variable will be updated.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Session Specific</title>
<body>

<p>
Sometimes even stricter definitions are requested. You might want to be able to
use binaries from a temporary directory you created without using the path to
the binaries themselves or editing <path>~/.bashrc</path> for the short time
you need it.
</p>

<p>
In this case, you can just define the <c>PATH</c> variable in your current
session by using the <c>export</c> command. As long as you don't log out, the
<c>PATH</c> variable will be using the temporary settings.
</p>

<pre caption="Defining a session-specific environment variable">
# <i>export PATH="${PATH}:/home/my_user/tmp/usr/bin"</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
