<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/security/shb-perms.xml,v 1.4 2006/09/18 09:22:48 neysx Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<sections>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2006-09-16</date>

<section>
<title>World readable</title>
<body>

<p>
Normal users should not have access to configuration files or passwords. An
attacker can steal passwords from databases or web sites and use them to
deface--or even worse, delete--data. This is why it is important that your file
permissions are correct. If you are sure that a file is only used by root,
assign it with the permissions <c>0600</c> and assign the file to the correct
user with <c>chown</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>World/Group writable</title>
<body>

<pre caption="Finding world-writable files and directories">
# <i>find / -type f \( -perm -2 -o -perm -20 \) -exec ls -lg {} \; 2>/dev/null >writable.txt</i>
# <i>find / -type d \( -perm -2 -o -perm -20 \) -exec ls -ldg {} \; 2>/dev/null >>writable.txt</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will create a huge file with permission of all files having either write
permission set to the group or everybody. Check the permissions and eliminate
world writable files to everyone, by executing <c>/bin/chmod o-w</c> on the
files.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>SUID/SGID files</title>
<body>

<p>
Files with the SUID or SGID bit set execute with privileges of the <e>owning</e>
user or group and not the user executing the file. Normally these bits are used
on files that must run as root in order to do what they do. These files can lead
to local root compromises (if they contain security holes). This is dangerous
and files with the SUID or SGID bits set should be avoided at any cost. If you
do not use these files, use <c>chmod 0</c> on them or unmerge the package that
they came from (check which package they belong to by using <c>equery</c>; if
you do not already have it installed simply type <c>emerge
gentoolkit</c>). Otherwise just turn the SUID bit off with <c>chmod -s</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Finding setuid files">
# <i>find / -type f \( -perm -004000 -o -perm -002000 \) -exec ls -lg {} \; 2>/dev/null >suidfiles.txt</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will create a file containing a list of all the SUID/SGID files.
</p>

<pre caption="List of setuid binaries">
/bin/su
/bin/ping
/bin/mount
/bin/umount
/var/qmail/bin/qmail-queue
/usr/bin/chfn
/usr/bin/chsh
/usr/bin/crontab
/usr/bin/chage
/usr/bin/expiry
/usr/bin/sperl5.6.1
/usr/bin/newgrp
/usr/bin/passwd
/usr/bin/gpasswd
/usr/bin/procmail
/usr/bin/suidperl
/usr/lib/misc/pt_chown
/usr/sbin/unix_chkpwd
/usr/sbin/traceroute
/usr/sbin/pwdb_chkpwd
</pre>

<p>
By default Gentoo Linux does not have a lot of SUID files (though this depends
on what you installed), but you might get a list like the one above. Most of
the commands should not be used by normal users, only root. Switch off the SUID
bit on <c>ping</c>, <c>mount</c>, <c>umount</c>, <c>chfn</c>, <c>chsh</c>,
<c>newgrp</c>, <c>suidperl</c>, <c>pt_chown</c> and <c>traceroute</c> by
executing <c>chmod -s</c> on every file. Don't remove the bit on <c>su</c>,
<c>qmail-queue</c> or <c>unix_chkpwd</c>. Removing setuid from those files will
prevent you from <c>su</c>'ing and receiving mail. By removing the bit (where
it is safe to do so) you remove the possibility of a normal user (or an
attacker) gaining root access through any of these files.
</p>

<p>
The only SUID files that I have on my system are <c>su</c>, <c>passwd</c>,
<c>gpasswd</c>, <c>qmail-queue</c>, <c>unix_chkpwd</c> and <c>pwdb_chkpwd</c>.
But if you are running X, you might have some more, since X needs the elevated
access afforded by SUID.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>SUID/SGID binaries and Hard links</title>
<body>

<p>
A file is only considered deleted when there are no more links pointing to it.
This might sound like a strange concept, but consider that a filename like
<path>/usr/bin/perl</path> is actually a link to the inode where the data is
stored. Any number of links can point to the file, and until all of them are
gone, the file still exists.
</p>

<p>
If your users have access to a partition that isn't mounted with <c>nosuid</c>
or <c>noexec</c> (for example, if <path>/tmp</path>, <path>/home</path>, or
<path>/var/tmp</path> are not separate partitions) you should take care to
ensure your users don't create hard links to SUID or SGID binaries, so that
after Portage updates they still have access to the old versions.
</p>

<warn>
if you have received a warning from portage about remaining hard links, and your
users can write to a partition that allows executing SUID/SGID files, you
should read this section carefully. One of your users may be attempting to
circumvent your update by keeping an outdated version of a program. If your
users cannot create their own SUID files, or can only execute programs using
the dynamic loader (partitions mounted <c>noexec</c>), you do not have to
worry.
</warn>

<note>
Users do not need read access to a file to create a link to it, they only need
read permission to the directory that contains it.
</note>

<p>
To check how many links a file has, you can use the <c>stat</c> command.
</p>

<pre caption="Stat command">
$ stat /bin/su
  File: `/bin/su'
  Size: 29350           Blocks: 64         IO Block: 131072 regular file
Device: 900h/2304d      Inode: 2057419     Links: 1
Access: (4711/-rws--x--x)  Uid: (    0/    root)   Gid: (    0/    root)
Access: 2005-02-07 01:59:35.000000000 +0000
Modify: 2004-11-04 01:46:17.000000000 +0000
Change: 2004-11-04 01:46:17.000000000 +0000
</pre>

<p>
To find the SUID and SGID files with multiple links, you can use <c>find</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Finding multiply linked suid/sgid binaries">
$ find / -type f \( -perm -004000 -o -perm -002000 \) -links +1 -ls
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</sections>
