<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/security/shb-tight.xml,v 1.4 2008/01/11 21:57:50 nightmorph Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<sections>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2006-03-04</date>

<section>
<title>USE flags</title>
<body>

<p>
The <path>make.conf</path> file contains user defined USE flags and
<path>/etc/make.profile/make.defaults</path> contains the default USE flags for
Gentoo Linux. For this guide's purposes, the important flags are <c>pam</c>
(Pluggable Authentication Modules), <c>tcpd</c> (TCP wrappers), and <c>ssl</c>
(Secure Socket Layer). These are all in the default USE flags.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id = "passwording_GRUB">
<title>Password protecting GRUB</title>
<body>

<p>
GRUB supports two different ways of adding password protection to your boot
loader. The first uses plain text, while the latter uses md5+salt encryption.
</p>

<pre caption="/boot/grub/grub.conf">
timeout 5
password changeme
</pre>

<p>
This will add the password <c>changeme</c>. If no password is entered at boot,
GRUB will simply use the default boot setting.
</p>

<p>
When adding an md5 password, you must convert your password into crypt format,
which is the same format used in <path>/etc/shadow</path>. For more information
see <c>man crypt</c>. The encrypted password <e>changeme</e>, for example, could
look like this: <c>$1$T7/dgdIJ$dJM.n2wZ8RG.oEiIOwJUs</c>.
</p>

<p>
You can encrypt your password directly at the GRUB shell:
</p>

<pre caption="md5crypt in grub shell">
#<i>/sbin/grub</i>

GRUB version 0.92 (640K lower / 3072K upper memory)

   [ Minimal BASH-like line editing is supported. For the first word, TAB lists
     possible command completions. Anywhere else TAB lists the possible
     completions of a device/filename. ]

grub> <i>md5crypt</i>

Password: <i>********</i>
<comment>(Typed changeme at the prompt)</comment>
Encrypted: $1$T7/dgdIJ$dJM.n2wZ8RG.oEiIOwJUs.

grub> <i>quit</i>
</pre>

<p>
Then, cut and paste your password to <path>/boot/grub/grub.conf</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="/boot/grub/grub.conf">
timeout 5
password --md5 $1$T7/dgdIJ$dJM.n2wZ8RG.oEiIOwJUs.
</pre>

<p>
The 5 seconds timeout becomes handy if the system is remote and should be able
to reboot without any keyboard interaction. Learn more about GRUB passwords by
executing <c>info grub</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id = "passwording_LILO">
<title>Password protecting LILO</title>
<body>

<p>
LILO also supports two ways of handling passwords: global and per-image, both in
clear text.
</p>

<p>
The global password is set at the top of the configuration file, and applies to
every boot image:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/lilo.conf">
password=changeme
restricted
delay=3
</pre>

<p>
The per-image password is set as below:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/lilo.conf">
image=/boot/bzImage
      read-only
      password=changeme
      restricted
</pre>

<p>
If the <c>restricted</c> option is not entered, it will prompt for a password
every time.
</p>

<p>
In order to store the new information in <path>lilo.conf</path>, you must run
<c>/sbin/lilo</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Restricting Console Usage</title>
<body>

<p>
The <path>/etc/securetty</path> file allows you to specify which <c>tty</c>
(terminal) devices root is allowed to login to.
</p>

<p>
We suggest that you comment out all lines except <c>vc/1</c> if you are using
devfs and all lines except <c>tty1</c> if you are using udev. This will ensure
that root only can login once and only on one terminal.
</p>

<note>
Users in the group "wheel" can still <c>su -</c> to become root on other TTYs.
</note>

<pre caption="/etc/securetty">
<comment>(For devfs)</comment>
vc/1
<comment>(For udev)</comment>
tty1
</pre>

</body>
</section>


</sections>
