<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/security/shb-uptodate.xml,v 1.3 2006/09/18 09:22:48 neysx Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<sections>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2005-10-13</date>

<section>
<title>Keeping up-to-date</title>
<body>

<p>
Once you have successfully installed your system and ensured a good level of
security you are not done. Security is an ongoing process; the vast majority of
intrusions result from known vulnerabilities in unpatched systems. Keeping your
system up-to-date is the single most valuable step you can take to greater
security.
</p>

<p>
If you have a recent version of <c>portage</c> installed, you can first sync
your portage tree with <c>emerge --sync</c> and then issue the command
<c>glsa-check --list</c> to check if your system is up to date security-wise.
<c>glsa-check</c> is part of <c>app-portage/gentoolkit</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Example output of glsa-check -l">
# <i>glsa-check -l</i>
WARNING: This tool is completely new and not very tested, so it should not be
used on production systems. It's mainly a test tool for the new GLSA release
and distribution system, it's functionality will later be merged into emerge
and equery.
Please read http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/portage/glsa-integration.xml
before using this tool AND before reporting a bug.

[A] means this GLSA was already applied,
[U] means the system is not affected and
[N] indicates that the system might be affected.

200406-03 [N] sitecopy: Multiple vulnerabilities in included libneon ( net-misc/sitecopy )
200406-04 [U] Mailman: Member password disclosure vulnerability ( net-mail/mailman )
.......
</pre>

<warn>
The <c>glsa-check</c> is still experimental, so if security really is your top
priority it would be wise to double check the list with other sources.
</warn>

<p>
All lines with a <c>[A]</c> and <c>[U]</c> can be almost safely ignored as the
system is not affected by this GLSA.
</p>

<impo>
Please note that the usual <c>emerge -vpuD world</c> will not pick up all
package updates. You need to use <c>glsa-check</c> if you want to make sure all
GLSAs are fixed on your system.
</impo>

<pre caption="Check all GLSAs">
<comment>(Check if your system is affected by GLSAs)</comment>
# <i>glsa-check -t all</i>
WARNING: This tool is completely new and not very tested, so it should not be
used on production systems. It's mainly a test tool for the new GLSA release
and distribution system, it's functionality will later be merged into emerge
and equery.
Please read http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/portage/glsa-integration.xml
before using this tool AND before reporting a bug.

This system is affected by the following GLSA:
200504-06
200510-08
200506-14
200501-35
200508-12
200507-16

<comment>(See what packages would be emerged)</comment>
# <i>glsa-check -p $(glsa-check -t all)</i>
     <comment>(partial output)</comment>
Checking GLSA 200504-06
The following updates will be performed for this GLSA:
     app-arch/sharutils-4.2.1-r11 (4.2.1-r10)

     **********************************************************************

     Checking GLSA 200510-08
     The following updates will be performed for this GLSA:
          media-libs/xine-lib-1.1.0-r5 (1.1.0-r4)

<comment>(Apply required fixes)</comment>
# <i>glsa-check -f $(glsa-check -t all)</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you have upgraded a running service, you should not forget to restart it.
</p>

<p>
Keeping your <uri link="/doc/en/kernel-upgrade.xml">kernel up-to-date</uri> is
also recommended.
</p>

<p>
If you want an email each time a GLSA is released subscribe to the
<c>gentoo-announce</c> mailing list. Instructions for joining it and many other
great mailing lists can be found <uri link="/main/en/lists.xml">Gentoo Linux
Mailing List Overview</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Another great security resource is the <uri
link="http://www.securityfocus.com/archive/1">Bugtraq
mailing list</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</sections>
