<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/articles/linux-kernel-compiling.xml,v 1.4 2010/12/10 09:00:54 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="articles">
<title>Compiling the Linux kernel</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>
</author>
<!-- xmlified by: Joshua Saddler (nightmorph@gentoo.org) -->

<abstract>
Daniel Robbins introduces the Linux kernel, and then walks you through locating
and downloading sources, configuring the kernel, compiling and installing the
kernel, and boot configuration.
</abstract>

<!-- The original version of this article was first published on IBM 
developerWorks, and is property of Westtech Information Services. This 
document is an updated version of the original article, and contains
various improvements made by the Gentoo Linux Documentation team -->

<version>2</version>
<date>2010-12-10</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introducing the kernel</title>
<section>
<title>The kernel is... Linux!</title>
<body>

<p>
What do you think of when you hear the word "Linux"? When I hear it, I
typically think of an entire Linux distribution and all the cooperating
programs that make the distribution work.
</p>

<p>
However, you may be surprised to find out that, technically, Linux is a kernel,
and a kernel only. While the other parts of what we commonly call "Linux" (such
as a shell and compiler) are essential parts of a distribution, they are
technically separate from Linux (the kernel). While many people use the word
"Linux" to mean "Linux-based distribution," everyone can at least agree that
the Linux kernel is the <e>heart</e> of every distribution.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Interfacing with hardware</title>
<body>

<p>
The primary role of the Linux kernel is to interface directly with the hardware
in your system. The kernel provides a <e>layer of abstraction</e> between the
raw hardware and application programs.  This way, the programs themselves do
not need to know the details of your specific motherboard chipset or disk
controller -- they can instead operate at the higher level of reading and
writing files to disk, for example.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>CPU abstraction</title>
<body>

<p>
The Linux kernel also provides a level of abstraction on top of the
processor(s) in your system -- allowing for multiple programs to appear to run
simultaneously. Linux does this by allowing several UNIX <e>processes</e> to
run at once -- and the kernel takes care of giving each one a fair share of the
processor(s).
</p>

<p>
A Linux kernel can support either a single or multiple CPUs -- and the kernel
that you are using now is either uniprocessor-aware (UP-aware) or symmetric
multiprocessor-aware (SMP-aware). If you happen to have an SMP motherboard, but
you're using a UP kernel, Linux won't "see" your extra processors! To fix this,
you'll want to compile a special SMP kernel for your hardware. Currently, SMP
kernels will also work on uniprocessor systems, but at a slight performance
hit.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Abstracting I/O</title>
<body>

<p>
The kernel also handles the much-needed task of abstracting all forms of file
I/O. Imagine what would happen if every program had to interface with your
particular hardware directly -- if you changed disk controllers, all your
programs would stop working!  Fortunately, the Linux kernel follows the UNIX
model of providing a simple abstraction of disk I/O that all programs can use.
That way, your favorite database doesn't need to be concerned whether it is
storing data on an IDE disk, a SCSI RAID array, or a network-mounted file
system.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Networking Central</title>
<body>

<p>
One of Linux's main claims to fame is its robust networking, especially TCP/IP
support. And, if you guessed that the TCP/IP stack is in the Linux kernel,
you're right! The kernel provides a nice, high-level interface for programs
that want to send data over the network. Behind the scenes, the Linux kernel
interfaces directly with your particular ethernet card or modem, and handles
the low-level Internet communication details.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Networking goodies</title>
<body>

<p>
One of the greatest things about Linux is all of the useful features that are
available in the kernel, especially those related to networking. For example,
you can configure a kernel that will allow your entire home network to access
the Internet via your Linux modem -- this is called IP Masquerading, or IP NAT
(network address translating).
</p>

<p>
Additionally, the Linux kernel can be configured to export or mount
network-based NFS file systems, allowing for other UNIX machines on your LAN to
easily share data with your Linux system.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Booting, part 1</title>
<body>

<p>
When you turn on your Linux-based system, the kernel is loaded from disk to
memory by a boot loader, such as LILO. At this point, the kernel takes control
of your system. The first thing it does is detect and initialize all the
hardware that it finds -- and it has been compiled to support. Once the
hardware has been initialized properly, it is then ready to run processes. The
first process it runs is called <c>init</c>, which is located in
<path>/sbin</path>. Then, <c>init</c> starts additional processes, as
specified in <path>/etc/inittab</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Booting, part 2</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>init</c> typically starts several copies of a program called <c>getty</c>,
which waits for logins from the console. After <c>getty</c> successfully
processes a login request, your default shell is loaded (which is typically
<c>bash</c>). Once you're in bash, you have the power to launch any program
you'd like.
</p>

<p>
While all these new processes are started, the kernel is still in control,
carefully time-slicing the CPU so that each process has a fair share. In
addition, the kernel continues to provide hardware abstraction and networking
services for the various running processes.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Introducing... modules!</title>
<body>

<p>
All recent Linux kernels support kernel modules. Kernel modules are really neat
things -- they're pieces of the kernel that reside on disk, until needed. As
soon as the kernel needs the functionality of a particular module, it's loaded
from disk, automatically integrated with the kernel, and available for use.  In
addition, if a kernel module hasn't been used for several minutes, the kernel
can voluntarily unload it from memory -- something that's called
"autocleaning."
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Modules, part deux</title>
<body>

<p>
Kernel modules live in <path>/lib/modules</path>, and each module has a
<path>.o</path> or <path>.ko</path> at the end of its name. As you may guess,
modules each represent a particular component of kernel functionality -- one
module may provide FAT filesystem support, while another may support a
particular ISA ethernet card.
</p>

<p>
Modules allow you to have a low kernel memory footprint. You can create a
kernel that contains only the features necessary for booting your computer, and
all other features can be loaded from modules on demand. Because the kernel
autocleans any modules it loads, your system's memory can be put to good use.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Modules -- important stuff!</title>
<body>

<p>
You can't put <e>everything</e> in a module. Because modules are stored on
disk, your bootable kernel image needs to have compiled-in support for your
disk controller as well as for your native file system (typically the ext2
filesystem). If you don't have these essential components compiled into your
kernel image (but compile them as modules instead), then your kernel won't have
the necessary ability to load these modules from disk -- creating a rather ugly
chicken-and-egg problem!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Locating and downloading sources</title>
<section>
<title>Kernel versions</title>
<body>

<p>
To compile a recent kernel, you need to download the sources first. But before
you download the kernel sources, you need to know what you're looking for. The
first question to ask yourself is this -- do you want to use a stable or
<e>experimental</e> kernel?
</p>

<p>
Stable kernels always have an even second digit -- for example, 2.0.38, 2.2.15,
2.2.18, and 2.4.1 are all considered "stable" kernels (due to the 0, 2, 2, and
4, respectively.) If you'd like to test out an experimental kernel, you'll
typically look for the highest-numbered kernel that has an odd second number.
For example, 2.3.99 and 2.1.38 are both experimental kernels (due to their 3
and 1, respectively).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Kernel version history</title>
<body>

<p>
The 2.2 series is considered a modern, stable kernel. If "modern" and "stable"
are things that sound good to you, look for a 2.2 kernel with the highest third
number you can find (2.2.16 is the most recent version at the moment).
</p>

<p>
While the 2.2 series kernel was being developed, the 2.3 series began. This
series was created to serve as a testing ground for new, advanced features that
would eventually show up in the stable 2.4 series. As of right now, the 2.3
series has already reached 2.3.99, and 2.3 development has stopped. These days,
developers are working on getting the 2.4.0 <e>test</e> kernels into shape. If
you'd like to be on the cutting-edge, you'll want to try the most recent
2.4.0-test kernel you can get your hands on. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>2.4 kernel warning</title>
<body>

<p>
Once a <e>real</e> 2.4 series kernel comes out (like 2.4.0), don't assume that
the kernel is ready for use on a mission-critical system like a server. Even
though 2.4 is supposed to be a stable series, early 2.4 kernels are likely to
be not quite up to snuff. As is often the case in the computer industry, the
first version of anything can have fairly sizable bugs. While this may not be a
problem if you're testing the kernel on your home workstation, it is a risk you
may want to avoid when you machine provides valuable services to others.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Downloading the kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
If you simply want to compile a new version of your installed kernel (for
example, to enable SMP support), then no downloading is necessary -- skip past
this and the next section.
</p>

<p>
You can find kernels at <uri>http://www.kernel.org/pub/linux/kernel</uri>.
When you go there, you'll find the kernel sources organized into several
different directories, based on kernel version (v2.2, v2.3, etc.) Inside each
directory, you'll find files labelled "<path>linux-x.y.z.tar.gz</path>" and
"<path>linux-x.y.z.tar.bz2</path>". These are the Linux kernel sources. You'll
also see files labelled "<path>patch-x.y.z.gz</path>" and
"<path>patch-x.y.z.bz2</path>". These files are patches that can be used to
update the previous version of complete kernel sources. If you want to compile
a new kernel release, you'll need to download one of the "linux" files.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Unpacking the kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
If you downloaded a new kernel from kernel.org, now it's time to unpack it. To
do so, <c>cd</c> into <path>/usr/src</path>. If there is an existing
<path>linux</path> directory there, move it to <path>linux.old</path> (<c>mv
linux linux.old</c>, as root.)
</p>

<p>
Now, it's time to extract the new kernel. While still in <path>/usr/src</path>,
type:
</p>

<pre caption="Extracting with gzip">
# <i>tar -xzvf /path/to/my/kernel-x.y.z.tar.gz</i>
</pre>

<p>
or
</p>

<pre caption="Extracting with bzip2">
# <i>tar -xvjf /path/to/my/kernel-x.y.z.tar.bz2</i>
</pre>

<p>
Depending on whether your sources are compressed with <c>gzip</c> or
<c>bzip2</c>. After typing this, your new kernel sources will be extracted into
a new <path>linux</path> directory. Beware: the full kernel sources typically
occupy more than 50 megabytes on disk!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring the kernel</title>
<section>
<title>Let's talk configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
Before you compile your kernel, you need to configure it. Configuration is your
opportunity to control exactly what kernel features are enabled (and disabled)
in your new kernel. You'll also be in control of what parts get compiled into
the kernel binary image (which gets loaded at boot-time), and what parts get
compiled into load-on-demand kernel module files.
</p>

<p>
The old-fashioned way of configuring a kernel was a tremendous pain, and
involved entering <path>/usr/src/linux</path> and typing <c>make config</c>.
While <c>make config</c> still works, please don't try to use this method to
configure your kernel -- unless you like answering hundreds (yes, hundreds!) of
yes/no questions on the command line.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The New Way to configure</title>
<body>

<p>
We more modern folks, instead of typing <c>make config</c>, type either <c>make
menuconfig</c> or <c>make xconfig</c>. If you'd like to configure your kernel,
type one of these options. If you type <c>make menuconfig</c>, you'll get a
nice text-based color menu system that you can use to configure the kernel. If
you type <c>make xconfig</c>, you'll get a very nice X-based GUI that can be
used to configure various kernel options. Here's a screenshot of <c>make
menuconfig</c>:
</p>

<figure link="/images/docs/l-kernel.gif" caption="menuconfig in action"/>

<p>
When using <c>make menuconfig</c>, options that have a <c>&lt; &gt;</c> to
their left can be compiled as a module. When the option is highlighted, hit the
space bar to toggle whether the option is deselected (<c>&lt; &gt;</c>),
selected to be compiled into the kernel image (<c>&lt;*&gt;</c>) or selected to
be compiled as a module (<c>&lt;M&gt;</c>).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuration tips</title>
<body>

<p>
There are tons of kernel options, and there's no room to explain them all here
-- so please take advantage of the kernel's built-in help functionality. Almost
every option is described in at least some detail, and each one normally
contains the line "If you don't know what this means, type Y (or N)." These
hints keep you out of trouble if you happen to have no clue what a particular
option actually does. To access help, highlight the option you have a question
about and press the "?" key.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Compiling and installing the kernel</title>
<section>
<title>make dep; make clean</title>
<body>

<p>
Once your kernel is configured, it's time to get it compiled.  Before we can
compile it, we need to generate dependency information and also clean out any
old "compiled stuff." This can be accomplished by typing: <c>make dep; make
clean</c> while in <path>/usr/src/linux</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Make bzImage</title>
<body>

<p>
Now, it's time to compile the actual binary kernel image. Type <c>make
bzImage</c>. After several minutes, compilation will complete and you'll find
the bzImage file in <path>/usr/src/linux/arch/i386/boot</path> (for an x86 PC
kernel).  We'll show you how to install the new kernel image in a bit, but now
it's time for the modules.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Compiling modules</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that the bzImage is done, it's time to compile the modules.  Even if you
didn't enable any modules when you configured the kernel, don't skip this step
-- it's good to get into the habit of compiling modules immediately after a
bzImage. And, if you really have no modules enabled for compilation, this step
will go really quickly. Type <c>make modules; make modules_install</c>.  This
will cause the modules to be compiled and then installed into
<path>/usr/lib/&lt;kernelversion&gt;</path>.
</p>

<p>
Congratulations! Your kernel is now fully compiled, and your modules are all
compiled and installed. Now, it's time to reconfigure LILO so that you can boot
the new kernel.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Boot configuration</title>
<section>
<title>LILO introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
It's finally time to reconfigure LILO so that it loads the new kernel. LILO is
the most popular Linux boot loader, and is used by all popular Linux
distributions. The first thing you'll want to do is take a look at your
<path>/etc/lilo.conf</path> file.  It will contain a line that says something
like <c>image=/vmlinuz</c> This line tells LILO where it should look for the
kernel.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Boot configuration, part 2</title>
<body>

<p>
To configure LILO to boot the new kernel, you have two options.  The first is
to overwrite your existing kernel -- this is risky unless you have some kind of
emergency boot method, such a boot disk with this particular kernel on it.
</p>

<p>
The safer option is to configure LILO so that it can boot either the new or the
old kernel. LILO can be configured to boot the new kernel by default, but still
provide a way for you to select your older kernel if you happen to run into
problems. This is the recommended option, and the one we'll show you how to
perform.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Boot configuration, part 3</title>
<body>

<p>
Your <path>lilo.conf</path> may look like this:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/lilo.conf">
boot=/dev/hda
delay=20
vga=normal
root=/dev/hda1
read-only

image=/vmlinuz
label=linux
</pre>

<p>
To add a new boot entry to your <path>lilo.conf</path>, do the following.
First, copy <path>/usr/src/linux/arch/i386/boot/bzImage</path> to a file on
your root partition, such as <path>/vmlinuz2</path>. Once it's there, duplicate
the last three lines of your <path>lilo.conf</path> and add them again to the
end of the file... we're almost there...
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Boot configuration, part 4</title>
<body>

<p>
Now, your <path>lilo.conf</path> should look like this:
</p>

<pre caption="the new lilo.conf">
boot=/dev/hda
delay=20
vga=normal
root=/dev/hda1
read-only

image=/vmlinuz
label=linux

image=/vmlinuz
label=linux
</pre>

<p>
Now, change the first <c>image=</c> line to read <c>image=/vmlinuz2</c>. Next,
change the <e>second</e> <c>label=</c> line to read <c>label=oldlinux</c>.
Also, make sure there is a <c>delay=20</c> line near the top of the file -- if
not, add one. If there is, make sure the number is at least twenty.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Boot configuration, part 5</title>
<body>

<p>
Your <e>final</e> <path>lilo.conf</path> file will look something like this:
</p>

<pre caption="The final lilo.conf">
boot=/dev/hda
delay=20
vga=normal
root=/dev/hda1
read-only

image=/vmlinuz2
label=linux

image=/vmlinuz
label=oldlinux
</pre>

<p>
After doing all this, you'll need to run <c>lilo</c> as root.  This is very
important! If you don't do this, the booting process won't work. Running
<c>lilo</c> will give it an opportunity to update its boot map.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Boot configuration, an explanation</title>
<body>

<p>
Now for an explanation of our changes. This <path>lilo.conf</path> file was set
up to allow you to boot two different kernels. It'll allow you to boot your
original kernel, located at <path>/vmlinuz</path>. It'll also allow you to boot
your new kernel, located at <path>/vmlinuz2</path>. By default, it will try to
boot your new kernel (because the image/label lines for the new kernel appear
first in the configuration file).
</p>

<p>
If, for some reason, you need to boot the old kernel, simply reboot your
computer and hold down the Shift key. LILO will detect this, and allow you to
type in the label of the image you'd like to boot. To boot your old kernel,
you'd type <c>oldlinux</c>, and hit enter. To see a list of possible labels,
you'd hit TAB.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Congratulations on compiling your own kernel! I hope everything went well. Here
are some related resources where you can learn more about kernel compilation:
</p>

<ul>
<!-- not accessible as of 2010; bug 348329
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Kernel-HOWTO/">The Linux Kernel
    HOWTO</uri>, another good resource for kernel compilation instructions.
  </li> -->
<!-- not accessible  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO-crash-rescue-HOWTO/">The LILO,
    Linux Crash Rescue HOW-TO</uri>, which shows you how to create an emergency
    Linux boot disk.
  </li> -->
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.kernel.org">www.kernel.org</uri>, the site that hosts
    the Linux Kernel archives.
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://kernelnewbies.org/FAQ">The Kernel Newbies</uri> FAQs.
    Kernel Newbies is an excellent resource for learning how to <uri
    link="http://kernelnewbies.org/FAQ/KernelCompilation">compile the
    kernel</uri>, as well as learning how the different pieces work. The site
    also provides a detailed yet easy-to-read overview of the <uri
    link="http://kernelnewbies.org/LinuxChanges">changes</uri> between each new
    kernel release.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
