<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/bluetooth-guide.xml,v 1.18 2012/06/29 19:09:27 swift Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Bluetooth">
<title>Gentoo Linux Bluetooth Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="deathwing00@gentoo.org">Ioannis Aslanidis</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="puggy@gentoo.org">Douglas Russell</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="marcel@holtmann.org">Marcel Holtmann</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="fox2mike@gentoo.org">Shyam Mani</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="rane@gentoo.org">Łukasz Damentko</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide will explain how to successfully install a host Bluetooth device,
configure the kernel properly, explain all the possibilities that the Bluetooth
interconnection offers and how to have some fun with Bluetooth.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>2</version>
<date>2009-07-16</date>

<chapter id="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>What is Bluetooth?</title>
<body>

<p>
Bluetooth is an industrial specification that provides users a way to connect
and exchange information between devices like personal computers, PDAs or
mobile phones. Using the Bluetooth technology, users can achieve wireless voice
and data transmission between devices at a low cost. Bluetooth also offers the
possibility to create small wireless LANs and to synchronize devices.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>About the content of this guide</title>
<body>

<p>
The first part of this guide explains how to configure the system kernel,
identify the Bluetooth devices installed on the system and detected by the
kernel and install the necessary basic Bluetooth tools.
</p>

<p>
The second part covers how to detect remote devices and how to establish a
connection from or to them by either setting up radio frequency communication
(RFCOMM)<!-- or by setting up a personal area network (PAN)-->.
</p>

<p>
The last part of the guide lists in detail applications that can take
advantage of all the possibilities offered by the Bluetooth technology.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="kernel">
<title>Configuring the system</title>
<section>
<title>Kernel Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
As the latest Linux stable kernel is 2.6, the configuration will be done for
these series of the kernel. Most Bluetooth devices are connected to a USB port,
so USB will be enabled too. Please refer to the <uri
link="/doc/en/usb-guide.xml">Gentoo Linux USB Guide</uri>.
</p>

<pre caption="Configuration for 2.6 kernels">
Networking ---&gt;

&lt;*&gt; Bluetooth subsystem support  ---&gt;

--- Bluetooth subsystem support
&lt;M&gt;   L2CAP protocol support
&lt;M&gt;   SCO links support
&lt;M&gt;   RFCOMM protocol support
[*]     RFCOMM TTY support
&lt;M&gt;   BNEP protocol support
[*]     Multicast filter support
[*]     Protocol filter support
&lt;M&gt;   HIDP protocol support

Bluetooth device drivers  ---&gt;
&lt;M&gt; HCI USB driver
[*]   SCO (voice) support
&lt;M&gt; HCI UART driver
[*]   UART (H4) protocol support
[*]   BCSP protocol support
[*]   Transmit CRC with every BCSP packet
&lt;M&gt; HCI BCM203x USB driver
&lt;M&gt; HCI BPA10x USB driver
&lt;M&gt; HCI BlueFRITZ! USB driver
<comment>(The four drivers below are for PCMCIA Bluetooth devices and will only
show up if you have also selected PCMCIA support in your kernel.)</comment>
&lt;M&gt; HCI DTL1 (PC Card) driver
&lt;M&gt; HCI BT3C (PC Card) driver
&lt;M&gt; HCI BlueCard (PC Card) driver
&lt;M&gt; HCI UART (PC Card) device driver
<comment>(The driver below is intended for HCI Emulation software.)</comment>
&lt;M&gt; HCI VHCI (Virtual HCI device) driver

<comment>(Move back three levels to Device Drives and then check if USB is
enabled. This is required if you use a Bluetooth dongle, which are mostly USB
based.)</comment>
USB support  ---&gt;

&lt;*&gt; Support for Host-side USB
--- USB Host Controller Drivers
&lt;M&gt; EHCI HCD (USB 2.0) support
[ ]   Full speed ISO transactions (EXPERIMENTAL)
[ ]   Root Hub Transaction Translators (EXPERIMENTAL)
&lt;*&gt; OHCI HCD support
&lt;*&gt; UHCI HCD (most Intel and VIA) support
&lt; &gt; SL811HS HCD support
</pre>

<p>
Now we'll reboot with our new kernel. If everything went fine, we will have a
system that is Bluetooth ready.
</p>

<impo>
Your USB device may have two modes the default of which may not be HCI, but HID.
If this is your case, use <c>hid2hci</c> to switch to HCI mode. Your system
will not remember this change when you next reboot.
</impo>

<pre caption="Checking the Bluetooth devices">
<comment>(One way to check for the device)</comment>
# <i>cat /proc/bus/usb/devices | grep -e^[TPD] | grep -e Cls=e0 -B1 -A1</i>
<comment>(The Cls=e0(unk. ) identifies the Bluetooth adapter.)</comment>
T:  Bus=02 Lev=02 Prnt=03 Port=00 Cnt=01 Dev#=  4 Spd=12  MxCh= 0
D:  Ver= 1.10 Cls=e0(unk. ) Sub=01 Prot=01 MxPS=64 #Cfgs=  1
P:  Vendor=0a12 ProdID=0001 Rev= 5.25
<comment>(Some might show up on lsusb from sys-apps/usbutils)</comment>
# <i>lsusb</i>
Bus 003 Device 002: ID 046d:c00e Logitech, Inc. Optical Mouse
Bus 003 Device 001: ID 0000:0000
Bus 002 Device 002: ID 0db0:1967 Micro Star International Bluetooth Dongle
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="bluez">
<title>BlueZ - The Bluetooth Stack</title>
<section>
<title>Installing BlueZ</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that the device is detected by the kernel, we need a layer that lets
applications communicate with the Bluetooth device. BlueZ provides the official
Linux Bluetooth stack. The ebuilds that provide what we need are
<c>bluez-libs</c> and <c>bluez-utils</c>. Devices that need Broadcom firmware
files or the like may need <c>bluez-firmware</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing bluez-libs and bluez-utils">
# <i>emerge net-wireless/bluez-libs net-wireless/bluez-utils</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>BlueZ configuration and PIN pairing</title>
<body>

<p>
Now it's time to see if the Bluetooth device is being picked up correctly by the
system. We start up the required Bluetooth services first.
</p>

<pre caption="Running hciconfig">
<comment>(Start up Bluetooth)</comment>
# <i>/etc/init.d/bluetooth start</i>
* Starting Bluetooth ...
*     Starting hcid ...                                                 [ ok ]
*     Starting sdpd ...                                                 [ ok ]
*     Starting rfcomm ...                                               [ ok ]

# <i>hciconfig</i>
hci0:   Type: USB
        BD Address: 00:01:02:03:04:05 ACL MTU: 192:8  SCO MTU: 64:8
        DOWN
        RX bytes:131 acl:0 sco:0 events:18 errors:0
        TX bytes:565 acl:0 sco:0 commands:17 errors:0
</pre>

<p>
This shows that the Bluetooth device has been recognised. As you might have
noticed the device is <e>DOWN</e>. Let's configure it so that we can bring it
up. The configuration file is at <path>/etc/bluetooth/hcid.conf</path>. The
required changes to the config file are shown below. For additional details
please refer to <c>man hcid.conf</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/bluetooth/hcid.conf">
<comment>(Recommended changes to be made to the file are shown)</comment>

# HCId options
options {
        # Automatically initialize new devices
        autoinit yes;

<comment>(Change security to "auto")</comment>
        # Security Manager mode
        #   none - Security manager disabled
        #   auto - Use local PIN for incoming connections
        #   user - Always ask user for a PIN
        #
        security auto;

        # Pairing mode
        pairing multi;

<comment>(You only need a pin helper if you are using &lt;=bluez-libs-2.x and &lt;=bluez-utils-2.x)
(Change pin_helper to use /etc/bluetooth/pin-helper)</comment>
        # PIN helper
        pin_helper /etc/bluetooth/pin-helper;
}

# Default settings for HCI devices
device {
<comment>(Set your device name here, you can call it anything you want)</comment>
        # Local device name
        #   %d - device id
        #   %h - host name
        name "BlueZ at %h (%d)";

        # Local device class
        class 0x3e0100;

        # Inquiry and Page scan
        iscan enable; pscan enable;

        # Default link mode
        lm accept;

        # Default link policy
        lp rswitch,hold,sniff,park;

<comment>(Leave as is, if you don't know what exactly these do)</comment>
        # Authentication and Encryption (Security Mode 3)
        #auth enable;
        #encrypt enable;
}
</pre>

<p>
After that, we have to configure the Bluetooth device PIN. That will help in
pairing this device with another one.
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/bluetooth/pin">
<comment>(Replace 123456 with your desired pin number.)</comment>
123456
</pre>

<impo>
This number (of your choice) must be the same in all your hosts with Bluetooth
devices so they can be paired. This number must also be kept secret since anyone
with knowledge of this number can essentially establish connections with your
devices.
</impo>

<note>
Beginning with <c>>=bluez-libs-3.x</c> and <c>>=bluez-utils-3.x</c>, pin helpers
have been replaced by passkey agents. There are a few different graphical
passkey agents available to help manage your PIN, such as <c>bluez-gnome</c> and
<c>kdebluetooth</c>. You can also use <c>passkey-agent</c> (found in
<c>bluez-utils</c>) from the command line.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Services configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that we have concluded with the configuration of BlueZ, it's time to restart
the necessary services.
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the Bluetooth daemons">
# <i>/etc/init.d/bluetooth restart</i>
<comment>(We can also add it to the default runlevel.)</comment>
# <i>rc-update add bluetooth default</i>
 * bluetooth added to runlevel default
 * rc-update complete.
</pre>

<p>
Let's be sure that the Bluetooth daemons started correctly. If we can see that
both <c>hcid</c> and <c>sdpd</c> are running, then we configured Bluetooth the
right way. After that, we can see if the devices are now up and running with
the configured options.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking whether Bluetooth daemons started correctly">
<comment>(Check to see if the services are running)</comment>
# <i>ps -ae | grep hcid</i>
26050 ?        00:00:00 hcid
# <i>ps -ae | grep sdpd</i>
26054 ?        00:00:00 sdpd

# <i>hciconfig -a</i>
hci0:   Type: USB
        BD Address: 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E ACL MTU: 192:8 SCO MTU: 64:8
        UP RUNNING PSCAN ISCAN
        RX bytes:125 acl:0 sco:0 events:17 errors:0
        TX bytes:565 acl:0 sco:0 commands:17 errors:0
        Features: 0xff 0xff 0x0f 0x00 0x00 0x00 0x00 0x00
        Packet type: DM1 DM3 DM5 DH1 DH3 DH5 HV1 HV2 HV3
        Link policy: RSWITCH HOLD SNIFF PARK
        Link mode: SLAVE ACCEPT
        Name: 'BlueZ at bluehat (0)'
        Class: 0x3e0100
        Service Classes: Networking, Rendering, Capturing, Object Transfer,
        Audio
        Device Class: Computer, Uncategorized
        HCI Ver: 1.1 (0x1) HCI Rev: 0x1e7 LMP Ver: 1.1 (0x1) LMP Subver: 0x1e7
        Manufacturer: Cambridge Silicon Radio (10)
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="detect">
<title>Detecting and Connecting to Remote Devices</title>
<section>
<title>Detecting Bluetooth devices in other hosts</title>
<body>

<p>
At this point we are now ready to detect Bluetooth devices installed in other
machines. This is independent of the host Operating System. We will make use of
the <c>hcitool</c> command for the same.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking for local devices">
# <i>hcitool dev</i>
Devices:
        hci0    00:01:02:03:04:05
</pre>

<pre caption="Scanning for remote devices">
# <i>hcitool scan</i>
Scanning ...
        00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E       Grayhat
</pre>

<pre caption="Inquiring remote devices">
# <i>hcitool inq</i>
Inquiring ...
        00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E       clock offset: 0x5579    class: 0x72010c
</pre>

<p>
Now that we know the MAC address of the remote Bluetooth devices, we can check
if we paired them correctly.
</p>

<pre caption="Running l2ping">
# <i>l2ping 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E</i>
Ping: 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E from 00:01:02:03:04:05 (data size 20) ...
20 bytes from 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E id 200 time 69.85ms
20 bytes from 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E id 201 time 9.97ms
20 bytes from 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E id 202 time 56.86ms
20 bytes from 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E id 203 time 39.92ms
4 sent, 4 received, 0% loss
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Setting up Radio Frequency Communication (RFCOMM)</title>
<body>

<note>
Please note that setting up radio frequency communication is optional.
</note>

<p>
We can establish a radio frequency connection to another Bluetooth device using
the <c>rfcomm</c> command. To make things a little easier especially for users
with multiple devices that support Bluetooth, it is advisable to make a few
changes to the default rfcomm config at <path>/etc/bluetooth/rfcomm.conf</path>.
</p>

<p>
The whole segment of the config starting from <c>rfcomm0 {</c> and ending with
<c>}</c> is the config for the device that will establish a connection at
<path>/dev/rfcomm0</path>. In this case, we will only show one example, rfcomm0.
You can add more devices as you see fit.
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/bluetooth/rfcomm.conf">
<comment>(Only changes that might be needed are shown)</comment>
rfcomm0 {
        # Automatically bind the device at startup
        <comment>(Creates the device node, /dev/rfcomm0 at start up)</comment>
        bind yes;

        # Bluetooth address of the device
        <comment>(Enter the address of the device you want to connect to)</comment>
        device 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E;

}
</pre>

<p>
After configuring RFCOMM, we can connect to any device. Since we've made the
required settings to the <path>/etc/bluetooth/rfcomm.conf</path> file, we just
issue the command shown below. In case you've not made changes to the config
file, an alternative method is also shown in the code listing that follows
</p>

<pre caption="Establishing an RFCOMM connection">
<comment>(The 0 refers to the rfcomm0 in the config file)</comment>
# <i>rfcomm connect 0 </i>
Connected /dev/rfcomm0 to 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E on channel 1
Press CTRL-C for hangup

<comment>(If you did not edit /etc/bluetooth/rfcomm.conf)</comment>
# <i>rfcomm connect 0 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E 1</i>
Connected /dev/rfcomm0 to 00:0F:DE:69:50:24 on channel 1
Press CTRL-C for hangup
</pre>

<p>
The first parameter after the connect command is the RFCOMM TTY device node
that will be used (usually 0). The second parameter is the MAC address of the
remote device. The third parameter is optional and specifies the channel to be
used. Please, note that in order to connect to a device, that device must be
listening for incoming connections. To do that, we have to explicitly tell it
to listen. We can cancel the communication at any moment by just hitting
CTRL+C.
</p>

<pre caption="Listening for incoming RFCOMM connections">
# <i>rfcomm listen 0 1</i>
Waiting for connection on channel 1
</pre>

<p>
In a similar way to the connect command, the listen command can receive two
parameters. The first one explicits the RFCOMM TTY device node (usually 0) that
will be used to accept a connection, while the second is the channel that will
be used.
</p>

<p>
Each time you call the <c>rfcomm</c> command, you can also specify the physical
device you want to use. Below you can see a small example specifiying the
physical device on the above two commands.
</p>

<pre caption="RFCOMM connections specifying physical device">
# <i>rfcomm -i hci0 listen 0 1</i>
Waiting for connection on channel 1
<comment>(To listen to a determined device) </comment>
# <i>rfcomm -i hci0 connect 0 00:0A:0B:0C:0D:0E 1</i>
<comment>(To use a determined device when connecting to another one)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<!-- Deleting pan chapter, bug 266690, until we know how the hell to do this -->
</chapter>

<chapter id="apps">
<title>Desktop Applications for Bluetooth</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
We have quite a few Bluetooth applications that run on the desktop and this
chapter has been divided into 3 parts, one each for Gnome, KDE and Miscellaneous
applications.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>For Gnome</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are a gnome user, you will most probably go with <c>gnome-bluetooth</c>.
It provides the most basic yet most used functionalities, as you can see below.
</p>

<ul>
  <li><c>gnome-bluetooth-manager</c>: To manage Bluetooth remote devices.</li>
  <li><c>gnome-obex-send</c>: To send files to other devices.</li>
  <li><c>gnome-obex-server</c>: To receive files.</li>
</ul>

<pre caption="Installing gnome-bluetooth">
# <i>emerge gnome-bluetooth</i>
</pre>

<p>
This adds menu entries under Applications &gt; System Tools from where you can
easily start up the manager or File sharing to transfer files between devices.
</p>

<p>
To transfer files (the easy way):
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    From the Phone to the Computer - Send the file from the phone via Bluetooth
    and it will be picked up and saved to your <path>/home</path> always.
  </li>
<!--FIXME : Doesn't work on Nautilus 2.10.x. Bug #103464 for details -->
<!--
  <li>
    From the Computer to the Phone - Fire up <c>nautilus</c> and select the
    file you want to send and right click on it. Select the Send via Bluetooth
    option and ask your phone to accept the file.
  </li>
-->
</ul>

<p>
<c>gnome-phone-manager</c> is a nifty app that you can use to send and receive
messages to and from your phone, using only your system. You do not have to
touch your phone to read or send messages since all that happens through the
application. You are also notified of a new message on your screen if the option
is enabled under Preferences. Installation is a breeze as always.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing gnome-phone-manager">
# <i>emerge gnome-phone-manager</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>For KDE</title>
<body>

<p>
KDE makes use of <c>kdebluetooth</c> and provides more utilities than its Gnome
counterpart as seen below.
</p>

<ul>
  <li><c>kbluetoothd</c>: Bluetooth Meta Server.</li>
  <li><c>kbtsearch</c>: Bluetooth device/service search utility.</li>
  <li><c>khciconfig</c>: KDE Bluetooth Monitor.</li>
  <li><c>kioclient</c>: KIO command line client.</li>
  <li><c>qobexclient</c>: Swiss army knife for obex testing/development.</li>
  <li><c>kbtobexclient</c>: A KDE Bluetooth Framework Application.</li>
  <li><c>kioobex_start</c></li>
  <li><c>kbtserialchat</c></li>
  <li><c>kbemusedsrv</c>: KDE Bemused Server.</li>
  <li><c>kbtobexsrv</c>: KDE OBEX Push Server for Bluetooth.</li>
  <li><c>kbluepin</c>: A KDE KPart Application.</li>
  <li>
    <c>auth-helper</c>: A helper program for kbtobexsrv that sends an
    authentication request for a given ACL link.
  </li>
</ul>

<pre caption="Installing kdebluetooth">
# <i>emerge kdebluetooth</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Other Interesting Applications</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>app-mobilephone/obexftp</c>: File transfer over OBEX for mobile phones
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>app-mobilephone/bemused</c>: Bemused is a system which allows you to
    control your music collection from your phone, using Bluetooth.
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>app-pda/multisync</c>: Multisync allows you to sync contacts, calendar
    entries and notes from your mobile phone with your computer, over a
    Bluetooth connection (amongst other things). It includes such features as
    backing up this information and restoring it later, and syncing with the
    Evolution e-mail client. You will need the <c>irmc</c> USE flag set to
    ensure that <c>multisync</c> has Bluetooth support.
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>net-wireless/opd</c> and <c>net-wireless/ussp-push</c> are command line
    tools (server and client) that can be used to send files to your mobile
    phone.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Special thanks to <mail link="marcel@holtmann.org">Marcel Holtmann</mail>
for his time and dedication to the Bluetooth development and for reviewing this
guide. And big thanks to <mail link="puggy@gentoo.org">Douglas Russell</mail>
for performing additional hardware tests and improving this guide.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
