<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/cvs-tutorial.xml,v 1.21 2011/09/04 17:53:40 swift Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>

<title>Gentoo Linux CVS Tutorial</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">Xavier Neys</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This tutorial introduces readers to CVS, the Concurrent Versions System, used
by developers around the world to develop software in a flexible and
collaborative manner.  Intended for those new to CVS, this tutorial will get
both general users and new developers up to speed quickly.  Whether you'd like
to use CVS to "check out" the latest sources of a particular software package,
or whether you'd like to begin using CVS as a full-fledged developer, this
tutorial is for you.
</abstract>

<version>1.9</version>
<date>2008-05-20</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>Tutorial layout</title>
<body>

<p>
This tutorial has two parts.  The first shows you how to use CVS as a
non-developer, i.e. how to get sources from CVS and keep them updated.  The
second part introduces you to using CVS as a developer, showing you how to
modify, add and remove files on CVS and perform other developer-related tasks.
If you are new to CVS, it's recommended that you begin in the first section and
proceed to the second section; if you have some basic CVS experience but are
going to be using CVS as a full-fledged developer for the first time, you
should find everything you need in the second section, but you may want to go
through the first section as a review.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What is CVS and what does it do?</title>
<body>

<p>
CVS is a client/server system allowing developers to store their projects in a
central location, called a repository.  Using the cvs client tools, developers
can make changes to the contents of the repository.  In turn, the cvs repository
tracks every change made to every file, creating a complete
history of the evolution of the development project.  Developers can request
older versions of a particular source file, view a log of changes, and perform
other useful tasks as needed.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The role of CVS</title>
<body>

<p>
A lot of open software projects have their own CVS servers, which are used by
the project developers as a central repository for all their work.  Developers
often make improvements to the sources in the CVS repository on a daily basis;
and often, these developers are scattered around the world, yet CVS provides
the necessary mechanism to unite their project into a centralized, cohesive
whole.  CVS creates the "organizational glue" that allows these developers to
make improvements to the code without stepping on each other's toes, losing
important data or missing each other's critical updates to particular source
files.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>CVS -- the latest developer sources</title>
<body>

<p>
When the developers are ready, they'll roll some their current work on CVS into
a .tar.gz file and release it as a new official version of their software
package.  However, the latest official release sometimes isn't recent enough,
for a variety of possible reasons.  In the first section of this tutorial, I'll
show you how to use CVS for this purpose -- acquiring the latest and greatest
developer version of the sources for your own personal use.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing CVS</title>
<body>

<p>
To install cvs, just type in <c>emerge cvs</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing CVS">
# <i>emerge cvs</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The CVSROOT</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we begin, there are a few CVS fundamentals that you need to know.  The
first is that in order to connect to a CVS repository, you first need to know a
path called the "CVSROOT".  The CVSROOT is a string, like a URL, that tells
the cvs command where the remote repository is and how we'd like to connect to
it.  Just to make things interesting, CVS has a number of CVSROOT formats,
depending on whether the CVS repository is local or remote and what method
you're going to use to connect to it.  Here are some example CVSROOTs, along
with explanations...
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>A local CVSROOT</title>
<body>

<pre caption="Setting CVSROOT">
CVSROOT=/var/cvsroot
</pre>

<p>
This is an example of a local CVSROOT path; you'd use a CVSROOT like this if
you wanted to connect to a local repository that exists at /var/cvsroot; or
maybe you have a repository mounted via NFS at /var/cvsroot.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>A remote password server CVSROOT</title>
<body>

<pre caption="Setting CVSROOT with authentification">
CVSROOT=:pserver:cvs@foo.bar.com:/var/cvsroot
</pre>

<p>
Here's an example of a CVSROOT for a remote repository that exists on the
foo.bar.com host and lives in the /var/cvsroot directory on that machine.  The
leading ":pserver:" part tells our client to connect to this remote machine
using the CVS password server protocol, a protocol that's built-in to CVS.
Typically, public CVS repositories use the password server protocol to allow
access to anonymous users.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>A remote rsh/ssh CVSROOT</title>
<body>

<pre caption="RSH/SSH CVSROOT">
CVSROOT=drobbins@foo.bar.com:/data/cvs
</pre>

<p>
Here's an example of a CVSROOT that uses the RSH or SSH protocol; in this
example, the CVS server will attempt to access the repository on foo.bar.com
using the drobbins account.  If the CVS_RSH environment variable is set to
"ssh", then our cvs client will attempt to use ssh to connect; otherwise rsh
will be used.  The ssh access method is popular with those who are concerned
about security; however, neither the RSH or SSH method provides a way for
anonymous users to get the sources.  In order to use this method, you must have
a login account at foo.bar.com.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>A few more things...</title>
<body>

<p>
In addition to the CVSROOT, you'll also need to know the name of the module
(collection of sources) that you'd like to check out, as well as an anonymous
password that you'll need to log in to the CVS password server.  Unlike
anonymous ftp, there is no "standard" format for the anonymous password, so
you'll need to get the specific password from the developer web site or the
developers themselves.  Once you have all this info, you're ready to begin.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Interacting with CVS, part 1</title>
<body>

<p>
Grabbing the sources is a two-stage process.  First, we log in to the password
server.  Then, we grab the sources with a <c>checkout</c> command.  Here's an
example set of commands that can be used to check out the latest Samba sources,
a popular UNIX/Windows integration project:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting up CVSROOT">
# <i>export CVSROOT=:pserver:cvs@pserver.samba.org:/cvsroot</i>
</pre>

<p>
This first command sets the CVSROOT environment variable.  If you don't set
this variable, the following two commands will require an additional <c>-d
:pserver:cvs@pserver.samba.org:/cvsroot</c> following the <c>cvs</c> command.
Exporting the CVSROOT saves a us bit of typing.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Interacting with CVS, part 2</title>
<body>

<p>
Here are the commands needed to get a current copy of the developer sources.
You may want to jump forward to the next panel to read the explanation of
these commands, and then jump back here:
</p>

<pre caption="Checking out sources">
# <i>cvs login</i>
(Logging in to cvs@pserver.samba.org)
CVS password: <comment>(enter password here)</comment>

# <i>cvs -z5 co samba</i>
U samba/COPYING
U samba/Manifest
U samba/README
U samba/Read-Manifest-Now
U samba/Roadmap
U samba/WHATSNEW.txt
<comment>(this is just a snippet of the complete cvs co output)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Interacting with CVS -- the explanation</title>
<body>

<p>
The first cvs command above logs us in to the pserver, and the second tells our
CVS client to check out ("co") the samba module using a gzip compression level
of 5 ("-z5") to speed up the transfer over a slow link.  For every new file
that is created locally, cvs prints out a "U [path]" indicating that this
particular file has been updated on disk.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Checkout complete</title>
<body>

<p>
Once the checkout command completes, you'll see a "samba" directory in your
current working directory that contains the latest sources.  You'll also notice
that all the directories have a "CVS" directory inside them -- CVS stores
accounting information inside these directories, and they can safely be ignored.
From this point forward, we don't need to worry about having the CVSROOT
environment variable set nor do we need to specify it on the command line
because it's now cached inside all those extra "CVS" directories.  Remember --
you only need to have the CVSROOT set for the initial login and checkout.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Updating the sources</title>
<body>

<p>
Well, there you are -- fresh sources!  Now that you have the sources, you can
go ahead and compile and install them, inspect them, or do whatever you like
with them.
</p>

<p>
Every now and then, you may want to bring your checked-out source directory
in-sync with the current version on CVS.  To do this, you don't need to log in
to the pserver again; your authentication info is also cached by cvs inside
those "CVS" accounting directories.  First, enter the main checked-out
directory (in this case "samba"), and type:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating your sources">
# <i>cvs update -dP</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Looking at "cvs update", part 1</title>
<body>

<p>
If there are any new files, cvs will output "U [path]" lines for each one as it
updates them.  Also, if you compiled the sources, you will probably see a lot
of "? [path]" lines; these are object files that cvs notices are not from the
remote repository.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Looking at "cvs update", part 2</title>
<body>

<p>
Also, notice the two command-line options we used for "cvs update".  "-d" tells
cvs to create any new directories that may have been added to the repository
(this doesn't happen by default), and "-P" tells cvs to remove any empty
directories from your locally checked-out copy of the sources.  "-P" is a good
idea, because cvs has a tendency to collect a lot of empty (once used, but now
abandoned) directory trees over time.
</p>

<p>
When it comes to simply grabbing the latest sources, that's about all you need
to know.  Now, we take a look at how to interact with CVS as a developer.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>CVS for developers</title>
<section>
<title>Modifying files</title>
<body>

<p>
As a developer, you'll need to modify files on CVS.  To do this, simply make
the appropriate changes to your local copy of the repository.  The changes you
make to the sources are not applied to the remote repository until you
explictly tell cvs to "commit" your changes.  When you've tested all your
modifications to ensure that they work properly and you're ready to apply your
changes to the repository, follow this two-step process.  First, update your
sources by typing the following command in your main source directory:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating sources and directories">
# <i>cvs update -dP</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>CVS merges others' changes</title>
<body>

<p>
As we've seen earlier, "cvs update" will bring your sources up-to-date with the
current version in the repository -- but what happens to the changes you've
made?  Don't worry, they aren't thrown away.  If another developer made changes
to a file that you haven't touched, your local file will be updated so that
it's in-sync with the version on the repository.
</p>

<p>
And, if you modified lines 1-10 of a local file, and another developer deleted
lines 40-50, added 12 new lines at the end of the file, modified lines 30-40 and
then committed their changes to the repository before you, cvs will
intelligently merge these changes into your locally modified copy so that none
of your changes are lost. This allows two or more developers to work on
different parts of the same file at the same time.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Merging isn't perfect</title>
<body>

<p>
However, if two or more developers have made changes to the <e>same region of
the same file</e>, then things get a bit more complicated.  If that happens,
then cvs will tell you that there's been a conflict.  No work will be lost, but
a bit of manual intervention will be required, since cvs now requires your
input on how to merge the conflicting changes.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The commit</title>
<body>

<p>
We'll look at exactly how conflicts can be resolved in just a little bit, but
for now, let's assume that there are no conflicts after you typed "cvs update
-dP" -- there usually aren't.  With no conflicts, your local sources are
up-to-date, and you're ready to commit your changes to the repository by typing
the following command in your main source directory:
</p>

<pre caption="Committing changes">
# <i>cvs commit</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What commit does</title>
<body>

<p>
"cvs commit" doesn't <e>just</e> apply your changes to the repository.
Before actually committing your changes to the remote repository, cvs will fire
up your default editor so that you can type in a description of your
modifications.  Once you've entered your comments, saved the file and exited
the editor, your changes (and comments) will be applied to the remote
repository and will be available to the other developers in your team.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Viewing the log</title>
<body>

<p>
It's really easy to view the complete history of a particular file, along
with any comments that the developers (including you) may have made when
committing. To view this information, type:
</p>

<pre caption="View log information">
# <i>cvs log myfile.c</i>
</pre>

<p>
The "cvs log" command is recursive, so if you want to see the complete log for
an entire directory tree, just enter the directory and type:
</p>

<pre caption="View log information with a pager">
# <i>cvs log | less</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Commit options</title>
<body>

<p>
You may want to use another editor than the one cvs starts by default when you
type "cvs commit". If so, simply set the EDITOR environment variable to the name
of the editor you want to use.  Putting a setting such as this one in your
<path>~/.bashrc</path> would be a good idea:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting your editor">
export EDITOR=jpico
</pre>

<p>
Alternatively, you can also specify a log message as a command line option so
that cvs doesn't need to load up an editor in the first place:
</p>

<pre caption="Committing changes with a small log information">
# <i>cvs commit -m 'I fixed a few silly bugs in portage.py'</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The .cvsrc file</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we continue looking at more cvs commands, I recommend setting up a
<path>~/.cvsrc</path> file.  By creating a <path>.cvsrc</path> file in your
home directory, you can tell cvs to use preferred command-line options by
default so that you don't have to remember to type them in each time.  Here's a
recommended default <path>.cvsrc</path> file:
</p>

<pre caption="Recommended defaults">
cvs -q
diff -u -b -B
checkout -P
update -d -P
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The .cvsrc file, continued</title>
<body>

<p>
In addition to setting useful options for a bunch of cvs commands, the first
line of the <path>.cvsrc</path> puts cvs into quiet mode, which has the primary
benefit of making the <c>cvs update</c> output more consise and readable.  Also,
once you have this .cvsrc in place, you can type <c>cvs update</c> instead of
typing <c>cvs update -dP</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adding a file to the repository</title>
<body>

<p>
It's really easy to add a source file to CVS.  First, create the file with your
favorite text editor.  Then, type the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding a file">
# <i>cvs add myfile.c</i>
cvs server: use 'cvs commit' to add this file permanently
</pre>

<p>
This will tell cvs to add this file to the repository the next time you do a
<c>cvs commit</c>.  Until then, other developers won't be able to see it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adding a directory to the repository</title>
<body>

<p>
The process of adding a directory to CVS is similar:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding a directory">
# <i>mkdir foo</i>
# <i>cvs add foo</i>
Directory /var/cvsroot/mycode/foo added to the repository
</pre>

<p>
Unlike adding a file, when you add a directory it appears on the repository
immediately; a cvs commit isn't required.  Once you add a local directory to
cvs, you'll notice that a "CVS" directory will be created inside it to serve as
a container for cvs accounting data.  Thus, you can easily tell if a particluar
directory has been added to cvs by looking inside it for a "CVS" directory.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>"cvs add" notes</title>
<body>

<p>
Oh, and as you might guess, before you add a file or directory to the
repository, you must make sure that its parent directory has already been added
to CVS.  Otherwise, you'll get an error that looks like this:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding a file, but receive a failure">
# <i>cvs add myfile.c</i>
cvs add: cannot open CVS/Entries for reading: No such file or directory
cvs [add aborted]: no repository
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Getting familiar with "cvs update", part 1</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we take a look at how to resolve conflicts, let's get familiar with the
output of the "cvs update" command.  If you created a ~/.cvsrc file that
contains a "cvs -q" line, you'll find "cvs update" output a lot easier to read.
"cvs update" informs you of what it does and sees by printing out a single
character, a space, and a filename; as an example:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating CVS">
# <i>cvs update -dP</i>
? distfiles
? packages
? profiles
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Getting familiar with "cvs update", part 2</title>
<body>

<p>
"cvs update" uses the "?" character to tell you that it doesn't know anything
about these particular files that it finds in the local copy of your repository.
They're not officially part of the repository, nor have they been scheduled for
addition. Here's a list of all the other single-character informational messages
that CVS uses:
</p>

<pre caption="Informational message: U">
U [path]
</pre>

<p>
Used when a new file is created in your local repository, or an untouched (by
you) file has been updated.
</p>

<pre caption="Informational message: A">
A [path]
</pre>

<p>
This file is scheduled for addition and will be officially added to the
repository when you do a <c>cvs commit</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Getting familiar with "cvs update", part 3</title>
<body>

<pre caption="Informational message: R">
R [path]
</pre>

<p>
Like "A", an "R" lets you know that this file is scheduled for removal.  The
file will be removed from the repository as soon as you <c>cvs commit</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Informational message: M">
M [path]
</pre>

<p>
This means that this file has been modified by you; additionally, it's possible
that new changes from the repository were merged into this file successfully.
</p>

<pre caption="Informational message: C">
C [path]
</pre>

<p>
The "C" character indicates that this file has a conflict and requires manual
fixing before you can "cvs commit" your changes.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Resolving conflicts intro</title>
<body>

<p>
Now, let's take a look at how to resolve a conflict.  I'm very involved in the
Gentoo Linux project, and we have our own cvs server set up at cvs.gentoo.org.
We developers spend most of our time hacking away at the sources inside the
"gentoo-x86" module.  Inside the gentoo-x86 module, we have a file called
"ChangeLog" that houses (you guessed it) a description of the major changes we
make to the files in the repository.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>An example conflict</title>
<body>

<p>
Because this file is modified nearly
every time a developer makes a major change to CVS, it's a primary source of
conflicts -- here's an example conflict.  Let's say I add the following lines
to the top of the ChangeLog:
</p>

<pre caption="ChangeLog entry">
date 25 Feb 2001

This is the thing I added myself
</pre>

<p>
However, let's say that before I'm able to commit these three new lines, another
developer adds these lines to the top of the ChangeLog and commits their
changes:
</p>

<pre caption="ChangeLog entry 2">
date 25 Feb 2001

This is the part added by another developer
</pre>


</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>An example conflict, continued</title>
<body>

<p>
Now, when I run <c>cvs update -dP</c> (as you should before every commit), cvs
isn't able to merge the changes into my local copy of ChangeLog because we
both have added lines to the exact same part of the file -- how is cvs to know
which version to use? So, I get the following error from CVS:
</p>

<pre caption="CVS error">
RCS file: /var/cvsroot/gentoo-x86/ChangeLog,v
retrieving revision 1.362
retrieving revision 1.363
Merging differences between 1.362 and 1.363 into ChangeLog
rcsmerge: warning: conflicts during merge
cvs server: conflicts found in ChangeLog
C ChangeLog
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Conflict resolution, part 1</title>
<body>

<p>
Argh -- a conflict!  Fortunately, fixing conflicts is easy.  If I fire up my
favorite text editor, I see the following text at the top of the ChangeLog
file:
</p>

<pre caption="ChangeLog conflict">
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; ChangeLog
date 25 Feb 2001

This is the thing I added myself

=======
date 25 Feb 2001

This is the part added by another developer

&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt; 1.363
</pre>


</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Conflict resolution, part 2</title>
<body>

<p>
Instead of choosing one version over the other, cvs has added both versions to
the ChangeLog file, and surrounded them with special separators to clearly mark
the conflict in question.  Now, it's up to me to replace this region with the
text that <e>should</e> appear in ChangeLog; in this case, the replacement text
is neither one or the other version but a combination of both:
</p>

<pre caption="ChangeLog entry">
date 25 Feb 2001

This is the thing I added myself

This is the part added by another developer
</pre>

<p>
Now that I've replaced the conflicting region of the file with the appropriate
text (and removed the "=======", etc markers), I can now commit my changes to
cvs without any problems.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Conflict resolution tips</title>
<body>

<p>
Whenever you need to edit a file for conflicts, make sure that you scan the
entire file so that you catch all of them; if you forget to address a
particular conflict, cvs won't allow you to commit until it's resolved!  It's
also obviously very important to remove the special markers that cvs added to
the conflicting file.  Another tip -- if you make a mistake while fixing the
conflict and then ("D'oh!") accidentally save your changes, you can find an
original copy of your version in the file ".#filename.version".
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Removing a file</title>
<body>

<p>
Now, it's time to learn our final CVS skill -- removing files from the
repository.  Removing a file is a two-stage process.  First, delete the file
from your local copy of the sources, and then execute the appropriate <c>cvs
remove</c> command:
</p>

<pre caption="Removing a file">
# <i>rm myoldfile.c</i>
# <i>cvs remove myoldfile.c</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Removing a file, continued</title>
<body>

<p>
The file will then be scheduled for removal from the repository the next time
you do a commit.  Once committed, the file will be officially deleted from the
current version of the repository.  However, cvs won't throw this file away,
and will still keep a complete record of its contents and its history, just
in case you need it back in the future.  This is just one of the many ways that
cvs protects your valuable source code.
</p>

<p>
<c>cvs remove</c> is recursive, which means that you can delete a bunch of
files, and then run the <c>cvs remove</c> command with no other arguments from
a parent directory. Doing this will cause all of the deleted files to be tagged
for removal at the next commit.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Removing a directory</title>
<body>

<p>
If you'd like to remove an entire directory, I recommend the following process.
First, physically delete and "cvs remove" all files in the directory:
</p>

<pre caption="Removing a directory">
# <i>rm *.c</i>
# <i>cvs remove</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Removing a directory, continued</title>
<body>

<p>
Then, perform a commit:
</p>

<pre caption="Commit your changes">
# cvs commit
</pre>

<p>
Here comes the trick.  Perform the following steps to delete the directory:
</p>

<pre caption="Removing a directory">
# <i>cd ..</i>
# <i>cvs remove mydir</i>
# <i>rm -rf mydir</i>
</pre>

<p>
Notice that removing the directory didn't require another commit -- directories
are added to and removed from the repository in real-time.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Retrieving an older version</title>
<body>

<p>
CVS wouldn't be a good versioning system if you can't retrieve older versions
from the repository. You can pull back files based on a specific date, but of
course also on the revision number. The next example pulls back revision 1.202
of <path>filename</path> and overwrites the current <path>filename</path> with
this version:
</p>

<pre caption="Retrieving a file based on the revision number">
$ <i>cvs update -p -r 1.202 filename &gt; filename</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you want to pull back files based on their date, use the <c>-D</c> argument.
You can use entire date/timestamps, but also relative names such as
<e>yesterday</e> or <e>last week</e>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Complete!</title>
<body>

<p>
Your introduction to CVS is complete -- I hope that this tutorial has been
helpful. There's much more to CVS than I've been able to cover in this
introductory tutorial, but thankfully there are a bunch of great CVS resources
you can use to further expand your CVS knowledge:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri>http://www.cvshome.org</uri> is the home of CVS development,
    and offers a bunch of documentation on CVS, including the <uri
    link="http://www.cvshome.org/docs/manual">official CVS
    documentation online</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="http://www.durak.org/cvswebsites/">CVS Version Control for
    Web Site Projects site</uri> has good info on how to use CVS for developing
    web sites
  </li>
  <li>
    Karl Fogel has written a book called <uri
    link="http://cvsbook.red-bean.com/">Open Source Development with CVS</uri>.
    A number of chapters are available for free from the website.
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.freebsd.org/projects/cvsweb.html">cvsweb</uri>
    is a really great CGI script that provides a web interface to your CVS
    repository; excellent for browsing.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="http://www.loria.fr/~molli/cvs-index.html">CVS Bubbles</uri>
    site has a bunch of good resources including a CVS FAQ-o-matic.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>About this document</title>
<body>

<p>
The original version of this article was first published on IBM
developerWorks, and is property of Westtech Information Services. This
document is an updated version of the original article, and contains
various improvements made by the Gentoo Linux documentation team.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
