<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/gentoo-amd64-faq.xml,v 1.42 2013/07/22 13:23:01 swift Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Linux/AMD64 Frequently Asked Questions</title>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="blubb@gentoo.org">Simon Stelling</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="metalgod@gentoo.org">Luis Medinas</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="gerrynjr@gentoo.org">Gerald J. Normandin Jr.</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">Xavier Neys</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This is the Gentoo Linux/AMD64 Frequently Asked Questions
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>7</version>
<date>2013-07-22</date>

<faqindex>
<title>Questions</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction to Gentoo/AMD64 FAQ</title>
<body>

<p>
This document contains the most commonly asked questions about Gentoo/AMD64. We
intend to help and provide useful information about Gentoo/AMD64. Some of these
questions can be found in forums, IRC, or mailing lists. If you have
suggestions or questions about this FAQ, you are welcome to send an e-mail to
<mail>amd64@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</faqindex>

<chapter>
<title>Installation</title>
<section id="difference">
<title>What's the difference between AMD64 and EM64T?</title>
<body>

<p>
Both refer to 64-bit processors from AMD (AMD64) and Intel (EM64T). AMD's 64-bit
processors include the Athlon 64, Turion, Neo, Phenom, and Opteron families.
Intel's 64-bit processors include the Core2, Core i<e>X</e>, Celeron, Xeon, and
Pentium (all based on the Core2 architecture). The <uri
link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Em64t#Intel_64">last few versions</uri> of
the old Pentium 4 and Xeon chips also support EM64T.
</p>

<p>
The AMD line of 64-bit processors were released well ahead of Intel's offering.
Therefore, for historical reasons the arch keyword for all x86-64 compatible
architectures is amd64. As such, <e>AMD64</e> is a generic reference to 64-bit
chips, whether AMD or Intel.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="cflags">
<title>What CFLAGS should I use for AMD64/EM64T?</title>
<body>

<p>
You should use simple <c>CFLAGS</c> to avoid future problems with your system.
Supported <c>CFLAGS</c> are <c>-O2 -march=native -pipe</c> for AMD and Intel
(EM64T) systems.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="kernel">
<title>What kernel should I use for AMD64?</title>
<body>

<p>
You can use almost all kernel sources available in Portage. We recommend using
<c>gentoo-sources</c> because it is a special kernel designed for Gentoo Linux.
It contains lots of AMD64-specific patches and therefore is the only kernel
officially supported by Gentoo/AMD64.
</p>

<p>
Make sure you have the <c>IA32_EMULATION</c> option activated in the kernel.
</p>

<pre caption="Activating IA32 Emulation in Kernel source">
# <i>cd /usr/src/linux</i>
# <i>make menuconfig</i>

Executable file formats / Emulations  ---&gt;
  [*] IA32 Emulation
</pre>

<warn>
You may experience build failures on multilib-systems if you deactivate this
option.
</warn>

</body>
</section>
<section id="perfup">
<title>Will I have a performance upgrade if I use a 64bit system instead of 32bit?</title>
<body>

<p>
That is a difficult question to answer. In some cases, you will experience a
performance improvement, in other cases you will not. For everyday use, there is
nearly no difference between 64bit and 32bit. 64bit is generally faster when it
comes to floating point computing which is normally the case in multimedia
applications and 3D rendering. This <uri
link="http://www.linux.com/articles/114024?tid=121">article</uri> (and a <uri
link="http://www.linux.com/feature/43873">related</uri> article) may interest
you. There's also a nice <uri
link="https://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-349691.html">thread</uri> in our <uri
link="https://forums.gentoo.org">forums</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="multilib">
<title>What is multilib and how can I use it?</title>
<body>

<p>
Every AMD64 processor is able to run 32bit code as well as 64bit code.
However, when you have a 32bit application, you are unable to mix it with
64bit libraries or vice versa. You can, however, natively run 32bit
applications if all shared libraries it needs are available as 32bit objects.
You can choose whether you want multilib support or not by selecting the
according profile. The default is a multilib-enabled profile.
</p>

<warn>
Currently you cannot switch from a no-multilib to a multilib-enabled profile,
so think over your decision twice before you use the no-multilib profile.
</warn>

</body>
</section>
<section id="chroot32">
<title>How do I create a 32bit chroot?</title>
<body>

<p>
Please read the <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/howtos/chroot.xml">32bit chroot
guide</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="upgradex86">
<title>Can I upgrade from my x86 system to amd64 by doing emerge -e world?</title>
<body>

<p>
Due to several differences between an <c>x86</c> and an <c>amd64</c>
installation, it is impossible to upgrade. Please perform a fresh install. The
installation is slightly different than an x86 one, so please use the
<uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml">AMD64 Handbook</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Also, binary files created on an x86 system most likely cannot be read by
packages on an amd64 system. In particular, databases such as MySQL, innoDB,
Berkeley DB, SQLite, OpenLDAP, etc. cannot simply be copied as-is. You will need
to dump the database into an architecture-independent format, such as a text
file, before attempting to restore it on an amd64 system.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="reiser4">
<title>Can I use Reiser4?</title>
<body>

<p>
Reiser4 is not available from any kernel offered by the Gentoo Kernel project,
thus the AMD64 team doesn't support it. The answer is no.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardware</title>
<section id="videobindrivers">
<title>Will my binary NVIDIA/ATI drivers work?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes, NVIDIA and ATI provide drivers that work on AMD64. You can install them by
executing <c>emerge nvidia-drivers</c> or <c>emerge ati-drivers</c>. If you have
more questions about these drivers, you should read the <uri
link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/NVidia/nvidia-drivers">Nvidia guide</uri> or the <uri
link="/doc/en/ati-faq.xml">ATI FAQ</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="coolnquiet">
<title>How do I use Cool'n'Quiet/PowerNow/SpeedStep features?</title>
<body>

<p>
You have to compile your kernel with support for these features. You just need
to enable the features below:
</p>

<pre caption="Kernel options for Cool'n'Quiet/PowerNow/SpeedStep">
Power management options ---&gt;
  [*] Run-time PM core functionality
  [*] ACPI (Advanced Configuration and Power Interface) Support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt;   Processor
    &lt;*&gt;     Thermal Zone
  CPU Frequency scaling ---&gt;
  [*] CPU Frequency scaling
         Default CPUFreq governor (ondemand) ---&gt;
  -*-   'performance' governor
  &lt;*&gt;   'userspace' governor for userspace frequency scaling
  -*-   'ondemand' cpufreq policy governor
  &lt;*&gt;   ACPI Processor P-States driver
  &lt;*&gt;   AMD Opteron/Athlon64 PowerNow!
-*- CPU idle PM support
</pre>

<p>
Then <c>emerge cpufrequtils</c> and edit <path>/etc/conf.d/cpufrequtils</path>
with your favorite editor.
</p>

<pre caption="Example of /etc/conf.d/cpufrequtils">
# Options when starting cpufreq (given to the 'cpufreq-set' program)
START_OPTS="--governor ondemand"

# Options when stopping cpufreq (given to the 'cpufreq-set' program)
STOP_OPTS="--governor performance"
</pre>

<p>
Now you only have to run <c>rc-update add cpufrequtils boot</c> to make sure it is
started every time you boot.
</p>

<note>
You may want to read the <uri
link="/doc/en/power-management-guide.xml#doc_chap3">Power Management Guide</uri>
for more tips on CPU power management.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Applications</title>
<section id="flash">
<title>Can I get Adobe Flash working?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes. Just <c>emerge adobe-flash</c>. Be sure to read any messages displayed by
the ebuild once it has been emerged.
<!-- Adobe killed 10.0 for security reasons, and 10.1 is only 32-bit -->
<!--
Adobe has provided a 64-bit Flash plugin starting with version 10.0.22.87. If
you don't need the 32-bit plugin, then run <c>echo "www-plugins/adobe-flash
-32bit" >> /etc/portage/package.use</c>. This will install only the 64-bit Flash
plugin.
-->
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="masked">
<title>I want to install package foo, but emerge says: (masked by: ~amd64 keyword)</title>
<body>

<p>
This means that the package is still in the 'testing' tree. Please read <c>man
portage</c> or the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=3&amp;chap=3">Mixing Software
Branches</uri> chapter of the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml">AMD64 Handbook</uri> for more
information.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="keyword">
<title>I want to install package foo, but emerge says: (masked by: missing keyword)</title>
<body>

<p>
This means that the package has not been tested yet. It does <e>not
necessarily</e> mean that the package does not work. You can unmask it by
accepting another architecture for the package. The following example shows you
can tell Portage to accept any keyword for a given package.
</p>

<pre caption="Example of adding package keywords">
# <i>echo "category/packagename **" >> /etc/portage/package.accept_keywords</i>
# <i>emerge packagename</i>
</pre>

<p>
If it works fine for you, please let us know and file a bug on <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/">Gentoo's Bugzilla</uri>, so that the AMD64 team
can keyword the package and other users can benefit from your test.
</p>

<warn>
Do not try commands like <c>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS="~x86" emerge packagename</c>. It
will most certainly break your tree.
</warn>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>How can I help the Gentoo/AMD64 project?</title>
<section id="project">
<title>How can I help?</title>
<body>

<p>
With a growing popularity of the amd64 architecture, we also increasingly need
more help. There's still much work to be done to improve the quality of
Gentoo/AMD64. An average user can help us by:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Filing general bug reports</li>
  <li>Testing software that does not yet have the <c>~amd64</c> keyword</li>
  <li>
    Participating in the <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/at/">Arch Testers
    project</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    Help answering questions on the mailing lists, forums and IRC channels
  </li>
  <li>Sending patches</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Other Resources</title>
<section id="other">
<title>Where can I get more help or information about Gentoo/AMD64?</title>
<body>

<p>
If any of your questions wasn't answered here, you can try other resources
listed on <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/">our project homepage</uri>. You can
also ask us at <c>#gentoo-amd64</c> on <c>irc.freenode.net</c>, <uri
link="https://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-46.html">Gentoo/AMD64 Forums</uri>,
or on the <c>gentoo-amd64@lists.gentoo.org</c> mailing list.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
