<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/gentoo-sparc-faq.xml,v 1.20 2013/12/09 10:42:40 swift Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Sparc/FAQ">
<title>Gentoo Linux/SPARC Frequently Asked Questions</title>

<author title="SPARC Developer">
  <mail link="weeve"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This FAQ is designed to help answer the most commonly asked questions about
Gentoo/SPARC and Linux on SPARC architecture.  Feel free to send revisions and
corrections to the Gentoo/SPARC team or the doc team.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.12</version>
<date>2010-03-02</date>

<faqindex>
<title>Questions</title>
<section>
<title>Documentation Notes</title>
<body>

<p>
These are some notes to elaborate on acronyms and terms used in this document.
</p>

<p>
When mentioning <c>SPARC</c>, this refers to the type of <c>sun4x</c> system.
SPARC represents the <c>sun4u</c> architecture seen in the UltraSPARC series of
systems (Ultras, Blades, SunFires, etc). Older 32-bit systems are no longer
supported by the Gentoo/SPARC team.
</p>

<p>
Acronyms: <c>OBP</c> = OpenBoot PROM, <c>SS</c> = SPARCstation.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</faqindex>

<chapter>
<title>Installation</title>
<section>
<title>How do I install/use my SPARC over a serial console?</title>
<body>

<p>
First, make sure you do not have a keyboard and monitor plugged in. OBP will
use the monitor for output by default if either are plugged in. You will need a
null modem cable or a regular serial cable with a null modem adapter to be able
to view output.
</p>

<p>
Standard serial port settings:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>9600 baud</li>
  <li>8 data bits</li>
  <li>None for parity</li>
  <li>1 stop bits</li>
</ul>

<p>
Below is a list of commonly used programs for viewing a serial console. Check
to see if your serial console application has the ability to send a break, as
it can be very useful on a SPARC. The break signal on a serial console is the
equivalent to issuing the Stop+A command on the keyboard.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Linux</th>
  <th>Windows</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Minicom</ti>
  <ti>Hyperterm</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Kermit</ti>
  <ti>TeraTerm Pro</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Console</ti>
  <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Seyon</ti>
  <ti></ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>I have a CRT/LCD monitor attached to my SPARC that selects a resolution
my monitor can't handle when the kernel boots. How do I get a visible and/or
non-distorted display on my monitor?</title>
<body>

<p>
This problem is a result of the framebuffer support the Linux kernel loads at
boot time, and the modelines available on SPARC systems.  Here we will assume
your monitor and video card will agree on a resolution of 1024 by 768 at a
refresh rate of 60 Hz. In OBP, you can set the resolution by adjusting the
setting for <c>output-device</c>. To view the current setting, use the command:
</p>

<pre caption="View current settings">
ok <i>printenv output-device</i>

<comment>&lt;output-device&gt;        &lt;screen&gt;          &lt;screen&gt;</comment>
</pre>

<p>
Now, to set this so it will start the display using the above mentioned
resolution, we will use the <c>setenv</c> command as follows:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting display">
ok <i>setenv output-device screen:r1024x768x60</i>

output-device =       screen:r1024x768x60
</pre>

<p>
In order for this to take effect, you will need to reset the machine:
</p>

<pre caption="Resetting the machine">
ok <i>reset</i>
</pre>

<p>
Additionally, for users using the onboard video card based on the ATI Mach64
chipset (Ultra 5/10 and Blade 100/150), you will want to append the following
to your kernel boot options:
</p>

<pre caption="Appending a kernel boot option">
video=atyfb:1024x768@60
</pre>

<p>
If you are booting from SILO, you can append the above string onto the end of a
given boot image. The following example would be if you were booting from the
LiveCD.
</p>

<pre caption="Booting a Gentoo LiveCD">
boot: <i>gentoo video=atyfb:1024x768@60</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you were booting from the network, you would append the string onto the end
of the boot net command in OBP as illustrated below:
</p>

<pre caption="Booting from the net">
ok <i>boot net video=atyfb:1024x768@60</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I'm new to SPARC and am not sure what kernel options to use,
HELP!</title>
<body>

<p>
Most of the time, the default kernel options will be acceptable for hardware
support. You will need to make sure that <c>virtual memory</c> and <c>/proc
filesystem</c> support is enabled in the kernel as instructed in the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-sparc.xml">Installation Handbook</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>How do I dual boot Gentoo Linux/SPARC with Solaris?</title>
<body>

<p>
Dual booting Gentoo/SPARC and Solaris can be done one of two ways. The two ways
are: having both Gentoo/SPARC and Solaris on the same drive, or having them on
separate drives. Below are example SILO configurations for each scenario. In the
example configs, the following things are assumed:
</p>

<p>
Single Drive Setup:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Boot drive is SCSI ID 0</li>
  <li>Gentoo boots from partition 1</li>
  <li>Solaris boots from partition 5</li>
</ul>

<p>
Separate Drive Setup:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Second drive is SCSI ID 1</li>
  <li>Gentoo is on SCSI ID 0</li>
  <li>Solaris is on SCSI ID 1</li>
  <li>boot-device in OBP is SCSI ID 0</li>
</ul>


<pre caption="Sample silo.conf for a single drive installation">
<comment># Generic config options</comment>
partition = 1
timeout = 50

<comment># Gentoo/SPARC options</comment>
image = /boot/vmlinux
    label = linux
    root=/dev/sda4

<comment># Solaris options</comment>
other=5
    label = Solaris
</pre>

<pre caption="Sample silo.conf for separate disk installation">
<comment># Generic config options</comment>
parition = 1
timeout = 50

<comment># Gentoo/SPARC options</comment>
image = /boot/vmlinux
    label = linux
    root=/dev/sda4

<comment># Solaris options</comment>
other = /sbus/espdma/esp/sd@1,0;1
    label = solaris
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardware</title>
<section>
<title>Will Gentoo run on my SPARC?</title>
<body>

<p>
It depends on the type of SPARC, but chances are yes. One exception seems to be
the SPARC based laptops from Tadpole, particularly the newer models. If you
have a working Tadpole on Gentoo/SPARC, please contact us and let us know the
details on the model and anything special needed to get it to work.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo/SPARC team maintains a <uri
link="/proj/en/base/sparc/sunhw.xml">hardware compatibility list</uri> for
SPARC64 systems. In general, support for SPARC64 systems is good enough to
allow some users to run it successfully in production environments.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What additional hardware is supported under Gentoo/SPARC?</title>
<body>

<p>
For a list of additionally supported Sun hardware, consult the following list
from the <uri link="http://www.ultralinux.org/faq.html#q_2_2.">UltraLinux
homepage</uri>.
</p>

<p>
A partial list of Sun devices which do NOT currently have support under
Gentoo/SPARC or SPARC/Linux in general are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>SunPCI cards</li>
  <li>SBUS or PCI PCMCIA controllers</li>
  <li>Smart card readers on some Sun Blade workstations</li>
  <li>Floppy drive on some Sun Blade workstations</li>
</ul>

<p>
Also, the Gentoo/SPARC team maintains a <uri
link="/proj/en/base/sparc/hwlist.xml">list of non-Sun PCI hardware that has
been tested on Gentoo/SPARC</uri>. To submit additions to the list, email
<mail>sparc@gentoo.org</mail> with the information on the hardware as displayed
in the existing hardware list.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>How do I know which SPARC I have?</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.ultralinux.org/faq.html#q_2_1">UltraLinux FAQ</uri>
has the answer.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>My box has more than one Sun Ethernet device. Why do they all have the
same MAC address and how do I fix it?</title>
<body>

<p>
First, the reason they all they all have the same setting is due to a value in
OpenBoot PROM (OBP). The story goes that in times past, it was assumed that if a
host had multiple interfaces, the interfaces would not reside on the same
Ethernet and therefore having the MAC address unique to a machine rather than to
a NIC wouldn't be a problem. As time went on and different technologies
developed, the opposite was proven.
</p>

<p>
As for fixing the issue, there are two ways to it; from OBP and from Linux. The
OBP variable <c>local-mac-address?</c> controls this behavior. The following
commands will help you to determine what <c>local-mac-address?</c> is set to:
</p>

<pre caption="View local-mac-address? setting from OBP">
ok <i>printenv local-mac-address?</i>
local-mac-address? =  false
</pre>

<pre caption="View local-mac-address? setting from Linux">
# <i>eeprom local-mac-address?</i>
local-mac-address?=false
</pre>

<p>
As you'll notice from the samples above, <c>local-mac-address?</c> is set to
<b>false</b>. This will cause all interfaces on a SPARC to use the same MAC
address. To change this behavior, use either of the commands below (depending
on whether you do it from OBP or Linux):
</p>

<pre caption="Set local-mac-address? from OBP">
ok <i>setenv local-mac-address?=true</i>
local-mac-address? =  true
</pre>

<pre caption="Set local-mac-address? from Linux">
# <i>eeprom local-mac-address?=true</i>
</pre>

<p>
Note that you may need to reboot to see the changes take affect.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Is SPARC big-endian or little-endian?</title>
<body>

<p>
The version supported by Gentoo/SPARC (v9) is bi-endian. It uses big-endian
instructions, but can access data in little-endian byte-order, such as PCI
devices, which are little-endian by nature.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Applications</title>
<section>
<title>
How do I get Xorg to find a usable modeline on my Ultra 5/10 or Blade 100/150?
</title>
<body>

<p>
The ATI Framebuffer normally expects a PC's BIOS to set the Reference Clock
speed for the video card. However, on non-x86 architectures, this doesn't
happen. So what needs to be done is to set the Reference Clock speed in the
<path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path>.
</p>

<p>
In the "Device" section of your <path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path>, you will
want to add a line similar to the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Add to xorg.conf">
Option      "reference_clock"   "28.636 MHz"
</pre>

<p>
Other common speeds are 14.318 MHz and 29.5 MHz. If you have issues you might
want to try without a similar setting first.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>How come package foo is masked on SPARC?</title>
<body>

<p>
Chances are this is due to the fact that none of the Gentoo/SPARC developers
have gotten around to testing this yet, and/or the package is currently marked
with the <c>~sparc</c> keyword (meaning it's in a testing phase).
</p>

<p>
If you still want to install the package, you can follow the instructions from
the <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-sparc.xml?part=3&amp;chap=3">Portage
Handbook</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>How can I help get package foo marked stable?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to help ensure a package gets marked stable in a timely fashion,
particularly if it's an application with a small userbase (i.e.
net-im/bitlbee), install the package and test to make sure it works. If it
appears to be working well, feel free to file a bug via the
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo Bugzilla</uri> and assign it to the
Gentoo/SPARC team.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I tried to emerge a package, but emerge failed complaining that a
dependency is masked. How can I fix this?</title>
<body>

<p>
This is a bug. Please file a bug report via the <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo Bugzilla</uri> for the Gentoo/SPARC team
indicating what package you tried to emerge, the error message emerge gave you,
and the output of <c>emerge --info</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Why am I getting an error related to 32/64-bit when compiling a
kernel?</title>
<body>

<p>
The way SPARC/Linux handles the cross-compiler has changed with 2.6.25 (<uri
link="http://git.kernel.org/?p=linux/kernel/git/torvalds/linux-2.6.git;a=commitdiff;h=54cd6ddec77b75e6926d73d263aec72255b24030">commit</uri>),
thus when building a recent kernel you'd get the following error message:
</p>

<pre caption="SPARC/Linux compile error message">
CHK     include/linux/version.h 
CHK     include/linux/utsrelease.h 
CC      arch/sparc64/kernel/asm-offsets.s 
arch/sparc64/kernel/asm-offsets.c:1: error: -m64 is not supported by this configuration 
arch/sparc64/kernel/asm-offsets.c:1: error: -mlong-double-64 not allowed with -m64 
arch/sparc64/kernel/asm-offsets.c:1: error: -mcmodel= is not supported on 32 bit systems 
make[1]: *** [arch/sparc64/kernel/asm-offsets.s] Error 1 
make: *** [prepare0] Error 2
</pre>

<p>
Because, for the moment (there's an <b>experimental</b> <uri
link="/proj/en/base/sparc/multilib.xml">multilib</uri> profile),
Gentoo/SPARC native compiler can't generate 64-bit code (that's what
sys-devel/kgcc64 is for).
</p>

<p>
What you need to do is to tell the SPARC/Linux Makefile what is your
cross-compiler's binary, by issuing the following commands:
</p>

<pre caption="Gentoo/SPARC kernel >=2.6.25 kernel compilation">
# <i>cd /usr/src/linux</i>
# <i>make CROSS_COMPILE=sparc64-unknown-linux-gnu-</i>
# <i>make CROSS_COMPILE=sparc64-unknown-linux-gnu- image modules_install</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Miscellaneous</title>
<section>
<title>I'm interested in becoming more involved with Gentoo/SPARC. How do I go
about doing that?</title>
<body>

<p>
There are various ways to improve the project:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>The best way is to become an <uri
    link="/proj/en/base/sparc/at/index.xml">Arch Tester</uri>, and aid the
    developers with package testing.
  </li>
  <li>File bug reports such as <uri
    link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~tcunha/reports/imlate-sparc.txt">stable, and
    keyword</uri> requests.
  </li>
  <li>Join the <uri
    link="irc://irc.gentoo.org/gentoo-sparc">#gentoo-sparc</uri> IRC channel
    on the FreeNode IRC network.
  </li>
  <li>Make use of the <uri
    link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum.php?f=27">Gentoo/SPARC forum</uri>.
  </li>
  <li>Propose solutions for Gentoo/SPARC related bugs via the <uri
    link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo Bugzilla</uri>. The bugs will be
    assigned, or CCed to sparc@gentoo.org.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Additional Resources</title>
<section>
<title>Where can I get more help or information about SPARC/Linux?</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://docs.sun.com/app/docs/coll/216.2">OBP Reference
    Guide</uri> - Sun's guide to the OpenBoot PROM
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.sunstuff.org">OSIAH</uri> - Online Sun Information
    Archive
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.obsolyte.com">Obsolyte</uri> - Information on older
    SPARC systems and links to a lot of other great SPARC related sites
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://docs.sun.com">Sun Microsystems Documentation</uri> -
    Additional hardware and software information for SPARC systems, including
    instructions for flashing OBP
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://sunsolve.sun.com">Sunsolve</uri> - Great resource for Sun
    hardware documentation
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.ultralinux.org">UltraLinux Homepage</uri> - Homepage
    of the SPARC/Linux port
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
