<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/gentoo-alpha-faq.xml,v 1.10 2013/07/22 13:23:01 swift Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>

<title>Gentoo Linux/Alpha Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tcort@gentoo.org">Thomas Cort</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="grknight2k@bluebottle.com">Brian Evans</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="mattst88">Matt Turner</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This FAQ is intended to answer some of the most frequently asked questions
relating to Gentoo/Alpha and Linux/Alpha in general.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>3</version>
<date>2013-07-22</date>

<faqindex>
<title>About this Document</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
This document contains answers to the most commonly asked questions about
Gentoo/Alpha and Alpha/Linux. It's aimed at both new users and experienced
users alike.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</faqindex>

<chapter>
<title>About the Gentoo/Alpha Project</title>
<section id="what">
<title>What is Gentoo/Alpha?</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo/Alpha project is responsible for keeping the Gentoo distribution
updated and current for the Alpha platform. This primarily includes keywording
packages, porting software, and making new releases. The Gentoo/Alpha project
aims to provide a usable environment for both desktops and servers.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The Alpha Architecture</title>
<section id="dead">
<title>Isn't the Alpha architecture dead?</title>
<body>

<p>
Kind of, yes. HP stopped taking orders for new Alpha systems on April 27, 2007.
and for Alpha options and upgrades on April 25, 2008. See their <uri
link="http://h18002.www1.hp.com/alphaserver/evolution.html">planning page</uri>
for more details.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="bitapps">
<title>Can I run 32-bit applications?</title>
<body>

<p>
No, all Alpha systems use a pure 64 bit kernel and a pure 64 bit userland. You
cannot even force gcc to output 32 bit code using the <c>-m32</c> compiler
flag.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="endian">
<title>Is Alpha big endian or little endian?</title>
<body>

<p>
Alpha systems are little endian. A large Cray system using Alphas was big
endian, but Linux will never support it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="i386">
<title>Can I run Linux/x86 applications on Alpha?</title>
<body>

<p>
No, not without a x86 emulator like <uri
link="http://wiki.qemu.org/Main_Page">qemu</uri>. In the past DEC/Compaq/HP
maintained a program called <c>em86</c> which allowed Linux/x86 applications to
be run on Linux/Alpha systems. However, the program is closed source and no
longer maintained upstream. There are no <c>em86</c> binaries available that
are compatible with gcc-3's ABI.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="why">
<title>Why install Gentoo on Alpha?</title>
<body>

<p>
Admittedly, you can find faster 64-bit systems out there, like amd64. However,
that doesn't mean that Alpha systems are useless. The following are a few good
reasons why you'd want to install Linux on this sort of hardware:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    You can turn an old computer into something useful. Older Alphas make great
    routers and servers. Their desktop performance isn't that bad either.
  </li>
  <li>You will learn about unusual computer hardware.</li>
  <li>
    It's cool. How many people can say they've got Linux running on an Alpha?
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section id="where">
<title>Where can I buy Alpha hardware?</title>
<body>

<p>
Alpha hardware generally isn't available at your local computer store. 
<uri link="http://ebay.com">eBay</uri> is usually a
good option, assuming that the shipping doesn't cost you too much.  There are
several used equipment dealers that can be found via Google, however most of
them charge too much.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardware</title>
<section id="ascase">
<title>I opened up the case on an AlphaServer and now it won't power
on, what do I do?</title>
<body>

<p>
Make sure the top panel of the case is on and properly in place.  The middle of
the top panel of the case has a small piece of metal oriented downwards. When
the top panel is put back in place properly, the small piece of metal will
press down on a switch. When the switch isn't pressed down, the system will
refuse to power on.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Alpha Specific Compiler Flags</title>
<section id="CFLAGS">
<title>Is the use of Alpha specific compiler flags recommended?</title>
<body>

<p>
As with all compiler optimizations, don't over do it. Use these flags with care
and they will give you a stable, speedy system; use them too aggressively and
you could seriously break your system. When in doubt, leave it out. If you need
further clarification, check the <c>gcc</c> man page.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="MCPU">
<title>
  How do I optimize for a specific instruction set and scheduling model?
</title>
<body>

<p>
You can optimize for a specific instruction set and scheduling model with
<c>-mcpu=XXX</c>, where XXX is your cpu type. Valid cpu types are <c>ev4</c>,
<c>ev45</c>, <c>ev5</c>, <c>ev56</c>, <c>pca56</c>, <c>ev6</c> and <c>ev67</c>.
If you do not use the <c>-mcpu=XXX</c> flag, then <c>gcc</c> will  default to
the cpu type of the machine it was compiled on. <c>-mcpu=</c> is equivalent to
the <c>-march=</c> flag on x86.
</p>

<note>
AlphaServer 800 users should set <c>ev5</c>.  There are known issues setting
<c>ev56</c> particularly with Xorg causing a full system lock up.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section id="MTUNE">
<title>
  How do I specify the scheduling model without changing the instruction set?
</title>
<body>

<p>
You can specify the scheduling model without changing the instruction set with
<c>-mtune=XXX</c>, where XXX is your cpu type. Valid cpu types are <c>ev4</c>,
<c>ev45</c>, <c>ev5</c>, <c>ev56</c>, <c>pca56</c>, <c>ev6</c> and <c>ev67</c>.
<c>-mtune=</c> is implied by <c>-mcpu=</c>, so you don't need to specify this
with if you set <c>-mcpu=</c>. <c>-mtune=</c> is equivalent to the
<c>-mcpu=</c> flag on x86.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="mieee">
<title>How do I enable software assisted floating point numbers?</title>
<body>

<p>
You can enable software assisted floating point numbers with <c>-mieee</c>.
This will enable software assistance to correctly support denormalized numbers
and exceptional IEEE values such as not-a-number and plus/minus infinity.
</p>

<p>
This should be in your global <c>CFLAGS</c> unless you really know what you are
doing.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="MEMLAT">
<title>How do I specify the memory latency of my system?</title>
<body>

<p>
You can specify the memory latency of your system with
<c>-mmemory-latency=XXX</c>, where XXX is the number of clock cycles. This sets
the latency time that the scheduler should assume for memory references.
<c>gcc</c> has some predefined "typical" values that are also accepted by
<c>-mmemory-latency=XXX</c>. Those values are <c>L1</c> for Dcache, <c>L2</c>
for Scache, <c>L3</c> for Bcache, and <c>main</c> for main memory.
</p>

<p>
This flag should probably not be use in your global <c>CFLAGS</c> as the value
you choose is highly dependent on the memory access pattern of the application
you are compiling.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="SMALLDATA">
<title>
  How do I specify that static data should be placed in the small data area?
</title>
<body>

<p>
You can specify that static data should be placed in the small data area with
<c>-msmall-data</c>. This will cause <c>gcc</c> to take advantage of some
features of the Alpha architecture by storing heavily used pieces of data in
specific sections called the small memory sections. The sections are limited to
64KiB which means accessing anything stored in them will only take one
instruction.
</p>

<p>
<c>-fPIC</c> will override <c>-msmall-data</c>, so you should use the
<c>-fpic</c> flag instead if you do not want <c>-msmall-data</c> to be
overridden.
</p>

<p>
This flag should probably not be used in your global <c>CFLAGS</c> as some
objects require more than 64KiB to be stored, and this will cause a gp_overflow
ld error.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="SMALLTEXT">
<title>
  How do I specify that object code should be placed in the small text area?
</title>
<body>

<p>
You can specify that object code should be placed in the small text area with
<c>-msmall-text</c>. This will cause <c>gcc</c> to assume that the entire
program (or library) fits in 4MB, and is thus reachable with a branch
instruction.  This reduces the number of instructions required for a function
call from 4 to 1.
</p>

<p>
This flag should probably not be used in your global <c>CFLAGS</c> as some
programs (or libraries) are larger than 4MB, and this will cause an ld error.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="CFLAGSERR">
<title>
  What do I do if any of these compiler flags cause a compile, linker, or
  runtime error?
</title>
<body>

<p>
As <uri link="#CFLAGS">already mentioned</uri>, please use these <c>CFLAGS</c>
cautiously. They may break your system. If you experience problems, try using
less aggressive <c>CFLAGS</c> before <uri link="#bugs">filing a bug
report</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Alpha Booting and Bootloaders</title>
<section id="SRM">
<title>What is SRM?</title>
<body>

<p>
SRM is based on the Alpha Console Subsystem specification, which provides an
operating environment for OpenVMS, Tru64 UNIX, and Linux operating systems. See
the <uri link="http://www.alphalinux.org/faq/SRM-HOWTO/"> SRM Howto</uri> for
more information about SRM.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="ARC">
<title>What is ARC?</title>
<body>

<p>
ARC is based on the Advanced RISC Computing (ARC) specification, which provides
an operating environment for Windows NT.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="ARCvsSRM">
<title>How can I tell if which firmware my Alpha has, ARC or SRM?</title>
<body>

<p>
When you power your system on you will see a screen with a blue background and
white text if it is using SRM. You will see a graphical boot system if it is
using ARC.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="whichbootloader">
<title>Which bootloader do I use?</title>
<body>

<p>
If your Alpha system supports SRM, then you should use aboot. If your system
supports both SRM and ARCs (ARC, AlphaBIOS, ARCSBIOS), then you should follow
<uri link="http://www.alphalinux.org/faq/x31.html">the SRM Firmware Howto</uri>
for switching to SRM and use aboot. If your system can only use ARCs (Ruffian,
xl, etc.) then you will need to choose milo.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="abootfs">
<title>Can aboot boot kernels from EXT4, XFS, ReiserFS, or JFS partitions?</title>
<body>

<p>
No, <c>aboot</c> only supports booting kernels from <c>ext2</c> and <c>ext3</c>
partitions. You may still use other files systems for your root partition, you
just need to create a <path>/boot</path> partition with either <c>ext2</c> or
<c>ext3</c> on it.
</p>

<p>
Support for ext4 is planned. In fact, there are patches floating
around that add support for <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=106855">ReiserFS</uri>, <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=107103">XFS</uri>, and <uri
link="http://alphalinux.org/wiki/index.php/Aboot_EXT4_support">ext4</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Software</title>

<section id="javasupport">
<title>How is Java support in Gentoo/Alpha?</title>
<body>

<p>
Compaq/HP offered binary packages, called <c>compaq-jre</c> and <c>compaq-jdk</c>.
They stopped all support, and the packages were removed from Gentoo on October
11, 2006. Since then, we haven't supported Java.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section id="currentjava">
<title>Will there ever be working Java support?</title>
<body>

<p>
It's possible to use <c>icedtea</c> on Alpha, but we have no plans to
support it, due to the high maintenance costs involved with testing hundreds of
additional packages.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="dotnetsupport">
<title>How is .NET support in Gentoo/Alpha?</title>
<body>

<p>
Neither of the two main open source efforts, <uri
link="http://www.mono-project.com/Main_Page">mono</uri> nor <uri
link="http://www.dotgnu.org/">DotGNU</uri>, support the alpha architecture.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="dotnetneeded">
<title>What is needed for .NET support?</title>
<body>

<p>
Bringing .NET to Alpha isn't a simple task. It requires coding all of the
assembly language code generation macros for the JIT (just in time) compiler
and coding architecture specific functions (register allocators, etc).
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Alpha Linux Kernel</title>
<section id="whichkernel">
<title>Which kernel sources should I use?</title>
<body>

<p>
We recommend using <c>gentoo-sources</c> but <c>vanilla-sources</c> is
also supported by Gentoo/Alpha. You should read the <uri
link="/doc/en/gentoo-kernel.xml">Gentoo Kernel Guide</uri> to determine which
one is right for your needs.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="kernel24">
<title>My system is broken with kernel-2.6, Can I build a 2.4 bassed system?</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo/Alpha stopped supporting 2.4 kernel and profile in January 2008.
Technically you can build a 2.4 Gentoo System (the kernel is in the tree) but
you will have to mask all the 2.6 only packages by yourself and you won't have
support from developers.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo/Alpha will review all bug reports about non-working 2.6 systems and
will try to help as much as we can.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section id="selinux">
<title>Are hardened-sources supported?</title>
<body>

<p>
Short answer is no. They were supported some time ago, but we lost the hardware
and the maintainer so now they are not supported. If you are interested
and want to continue the initial work, please let us know.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="smpkernel">
<title>Does the 2.6 kernel support Alpha SMP?</title>
<body>

<p>
There were some times in the past when it was broken. However, modern kernel
versions are known to work well.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Helping out the Gentoo/Alpha Project</title>
<section id="bugs">
<title>How do I report bugs?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you find a bug or you want to send us patches, then you need to file a bug
report. It only takes you a little bit of your time, and your help is really
appreciated. Please follow the <uri
link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Bugzilla_HOWTO">Gentoo Bug Reporting Guide</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="project">
<title>How can I help the Gentoo/Alpha Project?</title>
<body>

<p>
Users can help us by:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Filing clear and concise <uri link="#bugs">bug reports</uri>.</li>
  <li>Testing software that does not yet have the <c>~alpha</c> keyword.</li>
  <li>
    Answering questions on the <uri link="/main/en/lists.xml">mailing
    lists</uri>, <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-32.html">
    forum</uri> and IRC channel.
  </li>
  <li>Sending patches</li>
  <li>Becoming an <uri
      link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/base/alpha/AT/index.xml">AT</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section id="archtest">
<title>Is there an Alpha Arch Testers Project?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes, see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/base/alpha/AT/index.xml">
Gentoo Linux Alpha Arch Testers Project</uri> page for details.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<section id="tshoot-xorg">
<title>Why is Xorg locking up my Alpha?</title>
<body>

<p>
This is usually caused by a bad -mcpu setting.  For example, the AlphaServer
800 needs to be compiled with the <c>ev5</c> flag for xorg <b>and</b> glibc.
Failing to do so will cause undesired results.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Other Resources</title>
<section id="noforum">
<title>Why is there no Gentoo on Alpha forum?</title>
<body>

<p>
On the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri> there are
several arch specific categories like <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-24.html">Gentoo on PPC</uri> and
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-24.html">Gentoo on
Sparc</uri>.  There is no Gentoo on Alpha category because there simply isn't
enough Gentoo/Alpha activity on the forums to warrant one. All Alpha related
posts should go in the <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-32.html"> Gentoo on Alternative
Architectures</uri> category.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="othergentoo">
<title>Where can I get more help or information about Gentoo/Alpha?</title>
<body>

<p>
If any of your questions weren't answered here, you can try other resources
like the <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-alpha.xml">Alpha Handbook</uri>
or <uri link="/proj/en/base/alpha/">our project homepage</uri>. You can also
ask us at <c>#gentoo-alpha</c> on <c>irc.freenode.net</c>, <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-32.html">Gentoo on Alternative
Architectures Forum</uri>, or on the <mail>gentoo-alpha@lists.gentoo.org</mail>
mailing list.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="other">
<title>Where can I get more help or information about Alpha/Linux?</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://alphalinux.org/wiki/index.php/Main_Page">AlphaLinux.org</uri>
is a central repository for all things Alpha/Linux.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
