<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/gentoolkit.xml,v 1.39 2013/09/17 07:17:09 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Gentoolkit">
<title>Gentoolkit</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="mbutcher@aleph-null.tv">Matt Butcher</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <!-- zhen@gentoo.org -->John P. Davis
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="erwin@gentoo.org">Erwin</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="fox2mike@gentoo.org">Shyam Mani</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">Xavier Neys</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="karltk@gentoo.org">Karl Trygve</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="yoswink@gentoo.org">José Luis Rivero</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Joshua Saddler</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="douglasjanderson@gmail.com">Douglas Anderson</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoolkit is a suite of tools to ease the administration of a Gentoo system.
This document covers the basics of some of the tools present in Gentoolkit.
</abstract>

<!-- Licensed under GFDL -->

<version>6</version>
<date>2012-11-30</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>What is Gentoolkit?</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo is a unique distribution and presents some complexities that simply
don't exist for other distributions. As Gentoo developers and contributors
discovered some of these complexities, they also wrote tools to help users and
administrators work around them. Many of these tools have been contributed to
the Gentoo project and are included in the package
<c>app-portage/gentoolkit</c>.
</p>

<note>
As of now, there are two versions of gentoolkit: <c>app-portage/gentoolkit</c>
and <c>app-portage/gentoolkit-dev</c>. While the former contains administration
scripts, the latter contains scripts specific to help development on Gentoo.
If you are a developer, you can have your scripts included into
<c>gentoolkit-dev</c> by contacting the Gentoolkit maintainer. This document
discusses gentoolkit only.
</note>

<p>
Gentoolkit contains a whole bunch of useful tools to help manage your packages
and keep track of what is going on in your system. Most users
--&nbsp;particularly those who update systems often&nbsp;-- will benefit from
having gentoolkit installed.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installation</title>
<body>

<p>
Just as with any Gentoo package, installation is just a simple emerge.
</p>

<pre caption="Getting gentoolkit">
# <i>emerge gentoolkit</i>
</pre>

<note>
Many of the tools in gentoolkit reveal important information about your system
or require root privilege. For that reason, some of the programs may only be
executed (or only function properly) if run by a user with root privileges.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Finding Documentation</title>
<body>

<p>
Any documentation that a program might have (other than man pages) is stored in
<path>/usr/share/doc/gentoolkit-[version]/[program-name]/</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>equery</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>equery</c> is a tool that displays useful information about the packages on
your system. <c>equery</c> is based on a system of modules.
Every module has a shorthand name. For example, <c>equery l gcc</c> is the same
as <c>equery list gcc</c>.  <c>equery --help</c> explains global options
and lists all available modules and their shorthand names.
<c>equery --help module</c> will display the help screen for a specific
module. Lastly, <c>man equery</c> provides a detailed explanation of all
available modules and options, and provides useful examples.
</p>

<p>
Below is a list of features that work over the majority of modules.
</p>

<pre caption="Examples of Acceptable Input">
<comment>(Many modules require a package argument. equery accepts all emerge-like input):</comment>
$ <i>equery --quiet list gcc</i>                  # <comment>package</comment>
sys-devel/gcc-4.3.2-r3
$ <i>equery --quiet list sys-devel/gcc</i>        # <comment>category/package</comment>
sys-devel/gcc-4.3.2-r3
$ <i>equery --quiet list '>=sys-devel/gcc-4'</i>  # <comment>atom syntax</comment>
sys-devel/gcc-4.3.2-r3

<comment>(Like emerge, equery doesn't understand partial package names):</comment>
$ <i>equery check zilla</i>
!!! No package found matching zilla

<comment>(Unlike emerge, equery can accept shell-like globbing in the category and/or package name):</comment>
$ <i>equery check '*zilla*'</i>
 * Checking www-client/mozilla-firefox-3.0.14 ...
    90 out of 90 files passed
$ <i>equery check www-c*/*</i>
 * Checking www-client/links-2.2 ...
   30 out of 30 files passed
 * Checking www-client/mozilla-firefox-3.0.14 ...
   90 out of 90 files passed

<comment>(Most equery modules take multiple input):</comment>
$ <i>equery hasuse sse sse2</i>
 * Searching for USE flag sse ...
[IP-] [  ] media-libs/flac-1.2.1-r3 (0)
[IP-] [  ] media-libs/speex-1.2_beta3_p2 (0)

 * Searching for USE flag sse2 ...
[IP-] [  ] dev-libs/openssl-0.9.8k (0)
[IP-] [  ] x11-libs/pixman-0.16.0 (0)

<comment>(A few modules also allow full regular expressions):</comment>
$ <i>equery -q list --portage-tree --full-regex '[kr]?flickr.*'</i>
dev-dotnet/flickrnet-bin-2.2
dev-ruby/flickr-1.0.2-r1
dev-ruby/flickr-1.0.2-r2
dev-ruby/rflickr-20060201
media-gfx/kflickr-0.6
[...]
</pre>

<note>
Globbing support replaced a number of older options in <c>equery</c>.
For example, to act on all packages in a certain set, use <c>'*'</c>.
To act on all packages in a category, use <c>'category-name/*'</c>.
</note>

<warn>
Don't forget to quote input when using special shell characters
like asterisks or greater than/less than signs.
</warn>

<p>
The next few sections in this document give a quick introduction to the
different <c>equery</c> modules.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Finding the Package That a File Came From with belongs (b)</title>
<body>

<pre caption="Finding the Package that Installed a Given File">
$ <i>equery belongs -e /usr/bin/glxgears</i>
 * Searching for /usr/bin/glxgears ...
 x11-apps/mesa-progs-7.5.1 (/usr/bin/glxgears)
</pre>

<p>
<c>belongs</c> can search for files matching a regular expression with the
<c>-f</c> option. The <c>-e</c> option stops searching after it finds a match.
Since no file on your system should be owned by two packages, this is a safe
optimization.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Viewing ChangeLog Entries with changes (c)</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>changes</c> lets you view ChangeLog entries for a package version or range
of versions. Imagine after an <c>emerge --sync</c>, you
notice Portage is going to be upgraded and want to check what has changed:
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing Gentoo ChangeLog Entries">
<comment>(Show the latest installable version's entry):</comment>
$ <i>equery changes portage</i>
*portage-2.1.6.13 (03 May 2009)

  03 May 2009; Zac Medico &lt;zmedico@gentoo.org&gt; +portage-2.1.6.13.ebuild:
  2.1.6.13 bump. This fixes bug #268398 (document econf automatic die)
  and bug #267104 (handle insufficient space interaction with userfetch).
  Bug #268228 tracks all bugs fixed since 2.1.6.11.
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Verifying Package Integrity with check (k)</title>
<body>

<p>
Sometimes it is useful to check a package's integrity. <c>equery</c> can
verify MD5 sums as well as timestamps to indicate when a package might
have been corrupted, replaced, or removed.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking Package Integrity">
$ <i>equery check gentoolkit</i>
 * Checking app-portage/gentoolkit-0.3.0_rc7 ...
   71 out of 71 files passed
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Listing All Packages Depending on Package X with depends (d)</title>
<body>

<p>
Ever wonder why a certain package has been installed on your system?
<c>equery</c> can tell which packages list it as a dependency with
<c>depends</c>. Include indirect dependencies with the <c>-D</c>
option.
</p>

<pre caption="Looking for Packages Depending on pygtk">
$ <i>equery depends pygtk</i>
 * Searching for pygtk ...
app-admin/pessulus-2.24.0 (>=dev-python/pygtk-2.6.0)
app-editors/gedit-2.24.3 (python ? >=dev-python/pygtk-2.12)
dev-libs/libgweather-2.24.3 (python ? >=dev-python/pygtk-2)
dev-python/gnome-python-base-2.22.3 (>=dev-python/pygtk-2.10.3)
dev-python/gnome-python-desktop-base-2.24.1 (>=dev-python/pygtk-2.10.3)
[...]
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Getting Dependency Graphs with depgraph (g)</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>depgraph</c> is the opposite of <c>depends</c>. You pass it a package, and
it will find the packages <e>it</e> depends on (not that depend on it).
When it finds a dependency, it will recursively search for all of
<e>that</e> package's dependencies. Control how deep the tree gets with
the <c>--depth</c> option.
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing Dependency Graph for mozilla-firefox">
$ <i>equery depgraph mozilla-firefox</i>
 * Searching for mozilla-firefox ...
 * dependency graph for www-client/mozilla-firefox-2.0.0.19:
`-- www-client/mozilla-firefox-2.0.0.19
 `-- virtual/jre-1.6.0 (virtual/jre) [java]
  `-- virtual/jdk-1.6.0 (virtual/jdk-1.6.0*)
  `-- dev-java/icedtea6-bin (unable to resolve: package masked or removed)
   `-- dev-java/sun-jdk-1.6.0.15
    `-- dev-java/java-sdk-docs-1.6.0.10 [doc]
     `-- app-arch/unzip-6.0-r1
      `-- app-arch/bzip2-1.0.5-r1 [bzip2]
    `-- sys-libs/glibc-2.9_p20081201-r2
     `-- sys-devel/gettext-0.17 [nls]
      `-- virtual/libiconv-0 (virtual/libiconv)
[...]
</pre>

<p>
Notice how <c>jre</c> is a direct dependency and <c>jdk</c> is an indirect
dependency if the <c>java</c> USE flag is set.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Listing Files Installed by a Package with files (f)</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>equery</c> can list all the files installed by an ebuild with the
<c>files</c> module. Try <c>--tree</c> to get an easy to read directory
layout. Use <c>--filter</c> to only find a certain type of file. For example,
to find where executables were installed, use <c>--filter=cmd</c>, and to
quickly find the configuration file location, try <c>--filter=conf</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Listing Installed Files in Tree Format">
$ <i>equery files --tree gentoolkit</i>
 * Searching for gentoolkit ...
 * Contents of app-portage/gentoolkit-0.3.0_rc7:
 /etc
   > /eclean
      + distfiles.exclude
      + packages.exclude
   > /env.d
      + 99gentoolkit-env
   > /revdep-rebuild
      + 99revdep-rebuild
 /usr
   > /bin
      + eclean
      + eclean-dist -> eclean
      + eclean-pkg -> eclean
      + epkginfo
      + equery
      + eread
      + euse
      + glsa-check
      + revdep-rebuild
   > /lib
      > /python2.6
         > /site-packages
            > /gentoolkit
            + gentoolkit-0.3.0_rc7-py2.6.egg-info
               + __init__.py
               > /equery
                  + __init__.py
                  + belongs.py
                  + changes.py
                  + check.py
                  + depends.py
                  + depgraph.py
                  + files.py
[...]
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Looking for Packages that Have a Specific USE Flag with hasuse (h)</title>
<body>

<p>
You can use <c>hasuse</c> to find out which packages have a given USE flag.
<c>hasuse</c> won't tell you if the flag is enabled, only if the ebuild lists
it as an option. See the EXAMPLES section of <c>hasuse</c> in the
<c>equery</c> man page for more tip on getting that information.
</p>

<pre caption="Searching For Installed Packages that Use the qt3 or qt4 USE Flags">
$ <i>equery hasuse qt3 qt4</i>
 * Searching for USE flag qt3 ...
[IP-] [  ] app-crypt/pinentry-0.7.5 (0)
[IP-] [  ] net-dns/avahi-0.6.24-r2 (0)
[IP-] [  ] net-wireless/wpa_supplicant-0.6.9 (0)

 * Searching for USE flag qt4 ...
[IP-] [  ] net-dns/avahi-0.6.24-r2 (0)
[IP-] [  ] net-wireless/wpa_supplicant-0.6.9 (0)
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Listing Packages with list (l)</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>list</c> is a simple, yet powerful module to list packages that are
installed, in the Portage tree or in an overlay.
</p>

<pre caption="Listing Installed Packages with list">
$ <i>equery list '*'</i>
 * Searching for * ...
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/eselect-1.2.3 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/eselect-ctags-1.10 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/eselect-esd-20060719 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/eselect-fontconfig-1.0 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/eselect-opengl-1.0.8-r1 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/eselect-python-20090824 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/eselect-ruby-20081227 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/eselect-vi-1.1.5 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/perl-cleaner-1.05 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/pessulus-2.24.0 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/python-updater-0.7 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-admin/sudo-1.7.2_p1 (0)
[...]
</pre>

<p>
The standard query will search installed packages for the given package name.
Passing in '*' displays all packages in the set. In the leftmost field, we
see that all the above packages are <c>I</c>nstalled and from the <c>P</c>ortage
tree. They're not masked (the second field is blank), and they're all installed
in the default slot (0).
</p>

<p>
This time we are going to use local options to look for packages in the
Portage tree and overlays.
</p>

<pre caption="Using Local Options with list">
$ <i>equery list -po vim</i>
 * Searching for vim ...
[-P-] [  ] app-editors/vim-7.0.235 (0)
[-P-] [ ~] app-editors/vim-7.0.243 (0)
[-P-] [  ] app-editors/vim-7.1.123 (0)
[-P-] [ ~] app-editors/vim-7.1.330 (0)
[-P-] [  ] app-editors/vim-7.2 (0)
[-P-] [ ~] app-editors/vim-7.2.108 (0)
[IP-] [  ] app-editors/vim-7.2.182 (0)
[-P-] [ ~] app-editors/vim-7.2.238 (0)
[-P-] [ ~] app-editors/vim-7.2.264 (0)
</pre>

<p>
In this example you can see version 7.2.182 is installed and there are no
versions available from an overlay. You can see which versions are keyword
masked by the <c>~</c> in the second field.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Viewing Package Metadata with meta (m)</title>
<body>

<p>
Each package in the Portage tree provides at least some metadata about
its maintainer, herd, etc. Read about <uri
link="http://devmanual.gentoo.org/ebuild-writing/misc-files/metadata/index.html">
Gentoo Metadata</uri>. The amount of useful information depends on how much
package maintainers decide to provide. With no options, <c>meta</c> returns
some basic useful information.
</p>

<pre caption="Getting Package Metadata with meta">
$ <i>equery meta gnucash</i>
 * app-office/gnucash [gentoo]
 Herd:        gnome-office (gnome-office@gentoo.org)
 Maintainer:  tove@gentoo.org (Torsten Veller)
 Upstream:    None specified
 Location:    /usr/portage/app-office/gnucash
 Keywords:    2.2.9-r1:0: alpha amd64 ppc sparc x86
 Keywords:    2.2.9-r2:0:
 Keywords:    2.3.8:0:
 Keywords:    2.3.10:0: ~alpha ~amd64 ~ppc ~sparc ~x86
</pre>

<p>
When the maintainer provides extra information, it can be very useful:
</p>

<pre caption="Getting Long Package Descriptions with meta">
$ <i>equery meta --description emacs</i>
 * app-editors/emacs
  GNU Emacs is an extensible, customizable text editor - and more. At its core
  is an interpreter for Emacs Lisp, a dialect of the Lisp programming language
  with extensions to support text editing. The features of GNU Emacs include:
   * Content-sensitive editing modes, including syntax coloring, for a wide
     variety of file types including plain text, source code, and HTML.
   * Complete built-in documentation, including a tutorial for new users.
   * Support for many languages and their scripts, including all the European
     "Latin" scripts, Russian, Greek, Japanese, Chinese, Korean, Thai,
     Vietnamese, Lao, Ethiopian, and some Indian scripts.
   * Highly customizable, using Emacs Lisp code or a graphical customization
     interface.
   * A large number of extensions that add other functionality, including a
     project planner, mail and news reader, debugger interface, calendar, and
     more. Many of these extensions are distributed with GNU Emacs; others are
     available separately.
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Finding Package Sizes with size (s)</title>
<body>

<p>
Have you ever been curious to find out how much space a specific package is
occupying? Since a package could have its files over a number of directories,
the usual <c>du -hc</c> might not give you the correct figure. Not to worry,
here comes <c>equery</c> to the rescue!
</p>

<pre caption="Displaying Package Size">
$ <i>equery size openoffice-bin</i>
 * app-office/openoffice-bin-3.1.1
         Total files : 4624
         Total size  : 361.38 MiB
</pre>

<p>
As you can see, <c>size</c> prints the total space used in human-readable
units and lists the total number of files the package has. To get the
total size in bytes, use <c>--bytes</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Listing Per-Package USE Flags with uses (u)</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>equery</c>'s <c>uses</c> module can provide information about what USE
flags are available for a specific package, and which of those flags is
currently enabled.
</p>

<pre caption="Showing Set and Unset USE Flags">
$ <i>equery uses gst-plugins-meta</i>
 * Searching for gst-plugins-meta ...
[ Legend : U - flag is set in make.conf       ]
[        : I - package is installed with flag ]
[ Colors : set, unset                         ]
 * Found these USE flags for media-plugins/gst-plugins-meta-0.10-r2:
 U I
 + + X      : Adds support for X11
 - - a52    : Enables support for decoding ATSC A/52 streams used in DVD
 + + alsa   : Adds support for media-libs/alsa-lib (Advanced Linux Sound
              Architecture)
 - - dvb    : Adds support for DVB (Digital Video Broadcasting)
 + + dvd    : Adds support for DVDs
 + + esd    : Adds support for media-sound/esound (Enlightened Sound Daemon)
 + + ffmpeg : Enable ffmpeg-based audio/video codec support
 + + flac   : Adds support for FLAC: Free Lossless Audio Codec
 - - mad    : Adds support for mad (high-quality mp3 decoder library and cli
              frontend)
 + + mpeg   : Adds libmpeg3 support to various packages
 - - mythtv : Support for retrieval from media-tv/mythtv backend
 + + ogg    : Adds support for the Ogg container format (commonly used by
              Vorbis, Theora and flac)
 - - oss    : Adds support for OSS (Open Sound System)
 + + theora : Adds support for the Theora Video Compression Codec
 + + vorbis : Adds support for the OggVorbis audio codec
 - - xv     : Adds in optional support for the Xvideo extension (an X API for
              video playback)
</pre>

<p>
Here, a number of USE flags are enabled in <c>gstreamer</c>'s plugin
meta-package, but you can see that there are other USE flags available.
For more information on USE flags, please refer to the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-x86.xml?part=2&amp;chap=2">USE Flags</uri>
chapter of the <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/">Gentoo Handbook</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Finding the Ebuild Path with which (w)</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>which</c> is a simple script to help you quickly find the file path to an
ebuild. If you pass an unversioned package name, <c>which</c> will return the
path to the newest installable ebuild version, in other words, the ebuild
Portage would use if you typed <c>emerge package</c>. Pass in a versioned
package to get the path to that ebuild.
</p>

<pre caption="Displaying the Latest Installable Ebuild Path">
$ <i>equery which gnome</i>
/usr/portage/gnome-base/gnome/gnome-2.26.3.ebuild
</pre>

<p>
Lastly, if none of the above features of <c>equery</c> have answered your
question, try using <c>which</c> to manually search an ebuild with programs
like <c>cat</c>, <c>less</c> or <c>grep</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Other Useful Ways to Use which">
$ <i>grep HOMEPAGE $(equery which gentoolkit)</i>
HOMEPAGE="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/portage/tools/index.xml"
</pre>

<warn>
Be aware that <c>equery</c> currently changes the format of the output if it
is sent through a pipe. The piped format is intended to be easier to parse by
tools, but you can also turn it off by adding the <c>--no-pipe</c> option. If
you write scripts that employ <c>equery</c>, you should be aware of this.
</warn>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>euse</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>euse</c> is a tool to see, set and unset USE flags at various places. For
more information on USE flags, please refer to the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-x86.xml?part=2&amp;chap=2">USE Flags</uri>.
Please see <c>euse -h</c> for complete help and all options.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Viewing, Setting and Unsetting USE Flags</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>euse -a</c> command reads the current active USE flags and displays
them.
</p>

<note>
There are 5 &quot;columns&quot; that <c>euse</c> now uses to show whether a
flag is set/unset and where all the flag has been set. The columns are as
follows -- +/-, set in the Environment, set in make.Conf, set in make.Defaults,
and set in make.Globals. The output looks like [+ECDG].
</note>

<pre caption="Viewing all active USE flags">
# <i>euse -a</i>
X                   [+ CD ]
aalib               [+    ]
acpi                [+ C  ]
alsa                [+ C  ]
apache2             [+ C  ]
apm                 [+  D ]
avi                 [+  D ]
berkdb              [+  D ]
bitmap-fonts        [+  D ]
bonobo              [+    ]
cdr                 [+ C  ]
crypt               [+ CD ]
cscope              [+ C  ]
cups                [+ CD ]
curl                [+    ]
emboss              [+  D ]
encode              [+  D ]
esd                 [+    ]
fam                 [+    ]
fbcon               [+ C  ]
firefox             [+ C  ]
font-server         [+  D ]
foomaticdb          [+  D ]
fortran             [+  D ]
gd                  [+ C  ]
gdbm                [+  D ]
gif                 [+ CD ]
gimpprint           [+ C  ]
gnome               [+ CD ]
gphoto2             [+    ]
gpm                 [+ CD ]
gstreamer           [+ C  ]
gtk                 [+  D ]
gtkhtml             [+ C  ]
guile               [+    ]
imagemagick         [+    ]
imlib               [+ CD ]
innodb              [+    ]
ipv6                [+  D ]
javascript          [+ C  ]
jpeg                [+ CD ]
kde                 [+  D ]
ldap                [+    ]
libg++              [+ CD ]
libwww              [+ CD ]
mad                 [+ CD ]
mbox                [+ C  ]
md5sum              [+ C  ]
mikmod              [+ CD ]
mmx                 [+ C  ]
motif               [+ CD ]
mp3                 [+    ]
mpeg                [+ CD ]
mpeg4               [+ C  ]
mysql               [+ C  ]
ncurses             [+ CD ]
nls                 [+  D ]
nvidia              [+ C  ]
odbc                [+    ]
offensive           [+    ]
ogg                 [+ CD ]
opengl              [+ CD ]
oss                 [+  D ]
pam                 [+ CD ]
pdflib              [+ CD ]
perl                [+ CD ]
png                 [+ CD ]
python              [+ CD ]
qt                  [+  D ]
quicktime           [+ CD ]
readline            [+ CD ]
ruby                [+    ]
sdl                 [+ CD ]
slang               [+  D ]
spell               [+ CD ]
sse                 [+ C  ]
ssl                 [+ CD ]
svga                [+ CD ]
tcltk               [+ C  ]
tcpd                [+  D ]
tiff                [+ C  ]
truetype            [+ CD ]
usb                 [+ C  ]
vanilla             [+ C  ]
x86                 [+ C  ]
xml                 [+    ]
xosd                [+ C  ]
xv                  [+ CD ]
xvid                [+ C  ]
zlib                [+ CD ]
</pre>

<p>
Similarly you can use the <c>euse -a -g</c> command to only view active global
USE flags. The <c>euse -a -l</c> command does the same for active local USE
flags.<c>-g</c> &amp; <c>-l</c> are suboptions to <c>euse</c> and need an
option before them (like <c>-a</c>) to function correctly.
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing active local USE flags">
# <i>euse -a -l</i>
bitmap-fonts        [+  D ]
font-server         [+  D ]
fortran             [+  D ]
gimpprint           [+ C  ]
md5sum              [+ C  ]
mpeg4               [+ C  ]
nvidia              [+ C  ]
offensive           [+    ]
truetype            [+ CD ]
</pre>

<p>
We can also use <c>euse</c> to set or unset use flags. The commands used for
this are <c>euse -E flagname</c> (enable a flag) and <c>euse -D flagname</c>
(disable a flag).
</p>

<warn>
Do not use the <c>euse -E</c> or <c>euse -D</c> commands by themselves (without
a flag). It will set/unset ALL USE flags in <c>/etc/portage/make.conf</c>. Although a
backup is kept at <path>/etc/portage/make.conf.euse_backup</path>, please be careful
while using <c>euse -E</c> or <c>euse -D</c>.
</warn>

<pre caption="Setting and Unsetting USE flags">
<comment>(Enabling a USE Flag)</comment>
# <i> euse -E 3dfx</i>
/etc/portage/make.conf was modified, a backup copy has been placed at /etc/portage/make.conf.euse_backup

<comment>(/etc/portage/make.conf after the command)</comment>
USE="alsa acpi apache2 -arts cups cdr crypt cscope -doc fbcon \
     firefox gd gif gimpprint gnome gpm gstreamer gtkhtml imlib \
     innodb -java javascript jpeg libg++ libwww mad mbox md5sum \
     mikmod mmx motif mpeg mpeg4 mysql ncurses nvidia \
     ogg odbc offensive opengl pam pdflib perl png python \
     quicktime readline sdl spell sse ssl svga tcltk tiff truetype usb \
     vanilla X xosd xv xvid x86 zlib 3dfx"

<comment>(Disabling the USE Flag)</comment>
# <i> euse -D 3dfx</i>
/etc/portage/make.conf was modified, a backup copy has been placed at /etc/portage/make.conf.euse_backup

<comment>(/etc/portage/make.conf after the command)</comment>
USE="alsa acpi apache2 -arts cups cdr crypt cscope -doc fbcon \
     firefox gd gif gimpprint gnome gpm gstreamer gtkhtml imlib \
     innodb -java javascript jpeg libg++ libwww mad mbox md5sum \
     mikmod mmx motif mpeg mpeg4 mysql ncurses nvidia \
     ogg odbc offensive opengl pam pdflib perl png python \
     quicktime readline sdl spell sse ssl svga tcltk tiff truetype usb \
     vanilla X xosd xv xvid x86 zlib -3dfx"
</pre>

<note>
<c>euse</c> does not physically remove the flag from make.conf. It just adds a
- (minus) before the flag to unset it. You may have to manually clean up your
make.conf to avoid unwanted variables.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Other tools</title>
<section>
<title>revdep-rebuild</title>
<body>

<p>
This tool is Gentoo's Reverse Dependency rebuilder.  It will scan your installed
ebuilds to find packages that have become broken as a result of an upgrade of a
package they depend on. It can emerge those packages for you but it can also
happen that a given package does not work any more with the currently installed
dependencies, in which case you should upgrade the broken package to a more
recent version. revdep-rebuild will pass flags to emerge which lets you use the
<c>--pretend</c> flag to see what is going to be emerged again before you go any
further.
</p>

<pre caption="Running revdep-rebuild in pretend mode">
# <i>revdep-rebuild -p</i>

 * Configuring search environment for revdep-rebuild

 * Checking reverse dependencies
 * Packages containing binaries and libraries broken by a package update
 * will be emerged.

 * Collecting system binaries and libraries
 * Generated new 1_files.rr
 * Collecting complete LD_LIBRARY_PATH
 * Generated new 2_ldpath.rr
 * Checking dynamic linking consistency
[ 48% ]  *   broken /usr/lib/gstreamer-0.10/libgsttaglib.la (requires /usr/lib/libtag.la)
[ 64% ]  *   broken /usr/lib/libgdkglext-x11-1.0.la (requires /usr/lib/libGLU.la)
[ 67% ]  *   broken /usr/lib/libgtkglext-x11-1.0.la (requires /usr/lib/libGLU.la)
[ 85% ]  *   broken /usr/lib/python2.6/site-packages/gtk-2.0/gtk/gdkgl/_gdkgl.la (requires /usr/lib/libGLU.la)
 *   broken /usr/lib/python2.6/site-packages/gtk-2.0/gtk/gtkgl/_gtkgl.la (requires /usr/lib/libGLU.la)
[ 97% ]  *   broken /usr/qt/3/lib/libqt-mt.la (requires -lpng)
[ 100% ]
 * Generated new 3_broken.rr
 * Assigning files to packages
 *   /usr/lib/gstreamer-0.10/libgsttaglib.la -> media-plugins/gst-plugins-taglib
 *   /usr/lib/libgdkglext-x11-1.0.la -> x11-libs/gtkglext
 *   /usr/lib/libgtkglext-x11-1.0.la -> x11-libs/gtkglext
 *   /usr/lib/python2.6/site-packages/gtk-2.0/gtk/gdkgl/_gdkgl.la -> dev-python/pygtkglext
 *   /usr/lib/python2.6/site-packages/gtk-2.0/gtk/gtkgl/_gtkgl.la -> dev-python/pygtkglext
 *   /usr/qt/3/lib/libqt-mt.la -> x11-libs/qt
 * Generated new 4_raw.rr and 4_owners.rr
 * Cleaning list of packages to rebuild
 * Generated new 4_pkgs.rr
 * Assigning packages to ebuilds
 * Generated new 4_ebuilds.rr
 * Evaluating package order
 * Generated new 5_order.rr
 * All prepared. Starting rebuild
emerge --oneshot --pretend  dev-python/pygtkglext:0
media-plugins/gst-plugins-taglib:0.10
x11-libs/gtkglext:0
x11-libs/qt:3

These are the packages that would be merged, in order:

Calculating dependencies... done!
[ebuild   R   ] media-plugins/gst-plugins-taglib-0.10.17
[ebuild   R   ] x11-libs/gtkglext-1.2.0
[ebuild   R   ] x11-libs/qt-3.3.8b-r2
[ebuild   R   ] dev-python/pygtkglext-1.1.0
 * Now you can remove -p (or --pretend) from arguments and re-run revdep-rebuild.
</pre>

<p>
If you need to rebuild some packages, you may run <c>revdep-rebuild</c> without
the <c>-p</c> flag and the listed packages will be emerged again.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>glsa-check</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>glsa-check</c> is mainly a test tool that keeps track of the various GLSA's
(Gentoo Linux Security Advisory) and will eventually be integrated into
<c>emerge</c> and <c>equery</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>eread</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>eread</c> is a simple utility to display elog files produced by
>=<c>portage-2.1</c>. You can set the saving of elog files by setting a couple
of variables in <path>/etc/portage/make.conf</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Enabling elog in /etc/portage/make.conf">
PORTAGE_ELOG_CLASSES="log"
PORTAGE_ELOG_SYSTEM="save"
</pre>

<note>
This is just one way of saving elog messages. For more information on how
Portage's elog system works, please refer to the appropriate page in the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-x86.xml?part=3&amp;chap=1#doc_chap4">Portage
Handbook</uri>.
</note>

<p>
Once you've set up elog to your satisfaction, just run <c>eread</c> to view your
log files.
</p>

<pre caption="Using eread">
$ <i>eread</i>

This is a list of portage log items. Choose a number to view that file or type
q to quit.

1) app-portage:gentoolkit-0.2.4_pre2:20070320-000256.log
2) app-portage:gentoolkit-0.2.4_pre2:20070320-000258.log
3) app-portage:gentoolkit-0.2.4_pre2:20070320-000319.log
4) app-portage:gentoolkit-0.2.3:20070320-000408.log
Choice?
</pre>

<p>
Select a number and the file will be displayed using the paging program
specified in the PAGER environment variable. If PAGER is not set, it will use
<c>less</c>.
</p>

<p>
After displaying the elog item, you will be prompted if you want to delete the
file.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>eclean</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>eclean</c> is a tool to remove old source files and old binary packages from
your system.
</p>

<p>
When you build and install packages, the source files are downloaded and
preserved in DISTDIR, usually <path>/usr/portage/distfiles</path>. This can
accumulate several gigs of material over time if you don't clean it
periodically. You can run <c>eclean-dist</c> to clean only source files from
DISTDIR.
</p>

<p>
You can create archives of installed packages by using <c>quickpg</c> or
FEATURES="buildpkg". These archived packages are kept in PKGDIR, usually
<path>/usr/portage/packages</path>. When you no longer need to keep them around,
or if they're too old, you can run <c>eclean-pkg</c> to remove them from PKGDIR.
It's a good way to ensure that any binary packages you have are only the latest
versions.
</p>

<p>
For more information on <c>eclean</c> and tips on maintaining a cruft-free
system, please read <c>man eclean</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
