<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/gentoo-ppc-faq.xml,v 1.74 2013/07/23 17:03:52 swift Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Linux/PowerPC Frequently Asked Questions</title>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="rajiv@gentoo.org">Rajiv Manglani</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="sejo@gentoo.org">Jochen Maes </mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="josejx@gentoo.org">Joseph Jezak</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
The Gentoo/PPC FAQ is a collection of questions and answers collected from the
Gentoo/PPC mailing lists and from IRC.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>5</version>
<!-- Last content change: 2012-12-29 -->
<date>2013-07-23</date>

<faqindex>
<title>Questions</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction to the Gentoo/PPC FAQ</title>
<body>

<p>
This FAQ is a collection of questions and answers collected from the
Gentoo/PPC mailing lists and from IRC.  If you have any questions (or
answers!), please contact either an author or a member of the
documentation team.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</faqindex>

<chapter>
<title>Installation</title>
<section id="powerpc">
<title>
What kind of PowerPC computer do I have and where can I find more information
about it?
</title>
<body>

<p>
Welcome to Gentoo PPC!  The PowerPC processor has been used in a number of
popular computing devices, here are some links to help you figure out what
type of hardware is in the machine on your desk.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.info.apple.com/support/applespec.html">
      Apple Product Pages
    </uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://lowendmac.com/profiles.htm">
      Apple Product History and Details
    </uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.pegasosppc.com/products.php">
      Genesi Model Information
    </uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://publib.boulder.ibm.com/infocenter/pseries/v5r3/index.jsp?topic=/com.ibm.pseries.doc/hardware_docs/selectbysystem.htm">
      IBM Documentation by Model
    </uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://kurobox.com/">KuroBox</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://penguinppc.org/">
      PenguinPPC - Linux on PowerPC Information
    </uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section id="osxverify">
<title>How can I verify with OSX that the downloaded ISO is not corrupted?</title>
<body>

<p>
First be sure you did not mount the ftp server with <e>Finder</e> and then copy
the file with drag'n'drop. This will corrupt the ISO. Instead, use <c>curl</c>
(with <c>curl -O http://path/to/iso</c>).
</p>

<p>
You can check your MD5 sum using the <c>md5sum</c> tool provided with OSX. On
versions of OSX without md5sum, you can use <c>openssl</c> capability to
produce an md5 checksum.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating an md5sum with openssl">
<comment>(This could take some time depending of the size of the ISO and your CPU)</comment>
$ <i>openssl md5 /path/to/iso</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now compare this output with the appropriate file found on the server where you
downloaded the ISO (the file will end with <path>.md5</path>). If it is the
same, the ISO image downloaded correctly. Be sure you have <e>not</e> mounted
it (e.g. with Disk Copy) yet!
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="dualboot">
<title>Can I dual-boot Gentoo Linux and Mac OS X?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes you can! In fact, <e>yabootconfig</e> will automatically detect and setup
<path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> with Linux, Mac OS X and even classic Mac OS (see
the <uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-ppc.xml?part=1&amp;chap=10">Gentoo
Handbook</uri> for details on yabootconfig). The trick is in how you partition
your hard drive. Before installing Gentoo, startup with the Mac OS X Install
CD. Use the <c>Disk Utility</c> to partition the drive in your machine into two
or three partitions. Alternatively, use <c>parted</c> from a recent Gentoo
InstallCD, since that has been patched to handle HFS and HFS+ partitions.
Parted is also able to shrink a partition so you don't need to delete your
existing install. The first partition should be big enough to contain all your
Linux partitions (root+swap+/home etc.). The format of this partition does not
matter. The second partition should be for OS X. The third (and optional)
partition should be for classic Mac OS. It is only required if you intend of
being able to triple boot, since OS9 must be on a separate partition from OSX
for this to work.
</p>

<p>
After partitioning, install Mac OS X and Mac OS 9 onto their respective
partitions. Once installation is complete, start following the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-ppc.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>. When you get to
the section on partitioning, use <c>mac-fdisk</c> to <e>delete</e> the large
partition you created for Gentoo. In its place, create a bootstrap partition,
root, swap, and any other partitions you wish to use with Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
If you have an OldWorld Macintosh (pre-iMac), follow a similar procedure as
described above. However, use the Mac OS 9 install CD and the <c>Drive
Setup</c> utility. OldWorld machines do not need a bootstrap partition.
</p>

<note>
If yabootconfig does not detect your MacOS partitions, you can manually add
them to your yaboot.config. See the example yaboot.conf in the <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-ppc.xml?part=1&amp;chap=10#doc_chap2_pre6">
handbook</uri> for details.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section id="bwof">
<title>
I have an early NewWorld Mac such as the Blue and White G3. It should be
compatible with the InstallCD, but on boot it returns an "Unknown or corrupt
filesystem" error.
</title>
<body>

<p>
As a workaround, boot into Open Firmware by holding down the Apple + Option + O
+ F keys on startup. When the prompt appears, type:
</p>

<pre caption="Early NewWorld Mac Open Firmware work around">
<i>boot cd:,\\yaboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
The CD should boot as expected now, thanks to John Plesmid for this workaround.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="bootxarchive">
<title>
I have an OldWorld Macintosh and need to use BootX. However, I am having trouble
opening the BootX installer archive. What can I do?
</title>
<body>

<p>
You will need a new version of <e>StuffIt Expander</e> to open the archive.
You can <uri link="http://www.stuffit.com/expander/download.html">download
it</uri> for free.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="beigehd">
<title>
I have a Beige G3 machine. Can I install Gentoo Linux/PPC on a second IDE hard
drive?
</title>
<body>

<p>
Early Beige G3 machines (those with a "Rev 1" motherboard with an ATI RageII+
chip) do not support slave IDE drives. To use a second hard drive with this
machine, you would have to attach it to the internal or external SCSI
connector or install a PCI IDE card. Later G3 machines do not have this
limitation. See <uri>http://www.xlr8yourmac.com/G3-ZONE/IDE/index.html</uri>
for more information.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="gblimit">
<title>
I have a revision A or B iMac. I've replaced the hard drive with a larger one
and now I can't boot into anything!
</title>
<body>

<p>
There is an 8GB limit for the root partition on these machines. Ensure that
your root partition is less than 8GB and it should work as expected. This also
applies to OS X and later versions of OS 9.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="fstabboot">
<title>
My /etc/fstab file has /dev/BOOT in it. Do I need to setup this line for my
Apple bootstrap partition?
</title>
<body>

<p>
Maybe. If you are not using a separate boot partition (<path>/boot</path>) then
you do not need this line and can safely just delete it from
<path>/etc/fstab</path>. The Apple bootstrap partition is <e>not</e>
<path>/boot</path> and is not related in any way.
</p>

<p>If you are using a partition type that's not natively supported by the
bootloader (such as ext4 and yaboot), you will need to use a separate boot
partition. In this case, you will want to specify <path>/dev/BOOT</path> in
your fstab.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="fixit">
<title>
When I rebooted, yaboot didn't work! Now, I'm stuck. How can I fix this?
</title>
<body>

<p>
It's probably just a misconfigured yaboot.conf. The easiest way to fix this is
to boot the InstallCD again, mount your gentoo partition and check yaboot.conf
for errors. You'll also need to run
<c>ybin -v -C /mnt/gentoo/etc/yaboot.conf</c> to update the boot loader once
you have finished. This can all be done without chrooting back into your
install.
</p>

<note>
If you <e>really</e> just need to get back to OSX, try holding down the Option
key on startup. This should give you a graphical selection of bootable disks.
Choose OSX and remember to fix your boot problems later.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section id="xfs">
<title>
When I try to boot, yaboot only says "read error"!  Why can't I boot?
</title>
<body>

<p>
You're probably using XFS for your root partition.  While this is an option,
yaboot has some issues accessing files with holes.  To ensure that your kernel
will boot, instead of copying the vmlinux file to /boot, simply <c>cat</c>
the kernel as shown below.
</p>

<pre caption="Fixing yaboot read errors on XFS with cat">
# <i>cat /usr/src/linux/vmlinux &gt; /boot/vmlinux</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="applebrokeit">
<title>
I installed an OSX update and now my computer only boots into OSX! How can I
fix it?
</title>
<body>

<p>
Hold down the option key on boot.  This will bring you to a graphical boot
device selector.  Wait until a hard drive with a penguin shows up and click
on the icon.  This will boot your linux install as usual.  Once you've
booted, rerun <c>ybin -v</c> to fix the bootloader.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="stupidclock">
<title>
I want to set the hardware clock from Open Firmware, is that possible?
</title>
<body>

<p>
To set the clock boot into Open Firmware (using the key combination of 
Apple + O + F). Once you are at the Open Firmware prompt, you can set the clock
using the command below:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the clock at the open firmware prompt">
<comment># decimal dev rtc sec min hour day month year set-time</comment>
<comment># The example below sets the clock to 1:23:45 June, 7th, 2000</comment>
 ok
0 > decimal dev rtc 45 23 1 6 7 2000 set-time
 ok
1 >
</pre>

<p>
Open Firmware will return with an ok after the clock is set. Type 
<c>mac-boot</c> to continue booting after the clock is set.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardware Support</title>
<section id="laptoppkgs">
<title>
I'm running Gentoo on a PowerPC laptop. What packages should I install to
enable laptop-specific functionality?
</title>
<body>

<p>
There are four main packages you will need to install.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <e>pbbuttonsd</e> is a tool that enables the brightness and volume keys on
    most ppc laptops as well as other apple laptop specific functionality. The
    current versions also work as a power manager and replaces <e>pmud</e>.
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>powerprefs</e> provides a graphical configuration editing tool for
    configuring pbbuttonsd including settings such as power-management, trackpad
    options and various other preferences.
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>powernowd</e> allows cpu speed scaling for longer battery life. Other
    packages also provide the same functionality, such as <e>cpudyn</e>,
    <e>cpufreqd</e> and <e>speedfreq</e>.  It doesn't really matter which you
    chose, just ensure that you have the <e>userspace</e> cpu frequency scaling
    governor enabled in your kernel. This is the only governor that will work on
    PPC.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
These packages can be installed by running the appropriate commands from the
list below:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing laptop-specific packages">
# <i>emerge pbbuttonsd</i>
# <i>emerge powerprefs</i>
# <i>emerge powernowd</i>
</pre>

<note>
You should edit <path>/etc/pbbuttonsd.conf</path> or use <e>powerprefs</e> to
better suit your needs. The behaviour of the Fx-keys can be controlled here as
well as many sleep options. To switch the Fx-keys to the OSX behaviour, set
KBDMode to fkeyslast. You can turn off touchpad tapping by setting TPMode to
notap. Many other options are available, see man pbbuttonsd.conf for details.
</note>

<p>
It is useful to add pbbuttonsd and powernowd to your boot runlevel so that
they're started when your computer starts. To do this:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding pbbuttonsd and cpudyn to the boot runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add pbbuttonsd boot</i>
# <i>rc-update add powernowd boot</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="onebutton">
<title>
I only have one mouse-button. How can I make use of the second and third one,
since ctrl-button does not work?
</title>
<body>

<p>
There is no way to use ctrl-button like on Mac OS X, but you can map just about
any key or combination of keys to emulate the second and third mouse-button.
The values can be obtained with the command line utility <c>showkey</c> from
the console. Note that this program does not work as expected from X and should
only be run from the console. To use this feature, enable the following options
in your kernel:
</p>

<pre caption="Macintosh Device Drivers">
[*] Apple Desktop Bus (ADB) support
[*]    Use input layer for ADB devices
[*]      Support for mouse button 2+3 emulation
</pre>

<p>
You will also need to set the keyboard to mouse button mapping values in
<path>/etc/sysctl.conf</path>. Here is an example using F11 and F12:
</p>

<pre caption="Mouse button emulation with F11 and F12">
<comment># Enable mouse button emulation</comment>
dev.mac_hid.mouse_button_emulation = 1
<comment># Set 2nd button to 87 - F11</comment>
dev.mac_hid.mouse_button2_keycode = 87
<comment># Set 3rd button to 88 - F12</comment>
dev.mac_hid.mouse_button3_keycode = 88
</pre>

<note>
Other commonly used keycodes are 125 (The Apple key) and 96 (The Keypad Enter).
</note>

<p>
To activate these settings:
</p>

<pre caption="Applying the sysctl changes">
# <i>sysctl -p /etc/sysctl.conf</i>
</pre>

<p>
Apple Powerbooks and iBooks that use the Appletouch driver, can alternatively
configure multi-finger tapping to allow 2nd and 3rd button control. See the
documentation for this driver for configuration options.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="airport">
<title>How can I configure my Airport card?</title>
<body>

<p>
The Airport card is an 802.11b device based on the Lucent Orinoco chipset.  To
use this card in Linux, enable these kernel options:
</p>

<pre caption="Wireless LAN">
[*] Wirless LAN Drivers &amp; Wireless Extensions
&lt;*&gt; Hermes chipset 802.11b support (Orinoco/Prism2/Symbol)
&lt;*&gt;   Apple Airport support (build-in)
</pre>

<p>
Once the kernel is configured, you'll also need some userland tools to
configure the wireless settings.  Emerge the <c>wireless-tools</c>
for iwconfig and other wireless tools.
</p>

<p>
As an example of using iwconfig, to set your ESSID to home_essid:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting an ESSID">
# <i>iwconfig eth1 essid home_essid</i>
</pre>

<p>
For a generic guide to setting up wireless with Gentoo, please see the
<uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-ppc.xml?part=4&amp;chap=4">Gentoo Wireless
Guide</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="airportextreme">
<title>How can I configure my Airport Extreme card?</title>
<body>

<p>
The Airport Extreme is an 802.11b/g card that is included with modern Apple
portable computers.  It is based on the Broadcom 43xx chipset which is supported
by the native b43 driver project.  It has been included in the 2.6.24 kernel.
Note that the driver should select the proper driver between b43 and b43-legacy.
The firmware used for these two drivers is different, with the legacy version
supporting older 4306 cards.  If you have a 4306 card, build both, otherwise,
it should be safe to only build b43. To enable either driver, mac80211 must be
selected first.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding b43 support to the kernel">
Networking --&gt; Wireless --&gt;
     &lt;M&gt;   Generic IEEE 802.11 Networking Stack (mac80211)

Device Drivers --&gt; Network device support --&gt;
     [*] Wireless LAN (IEEE 802.11)
     &lt;M&gt;   Broadcom 43xx wireless support (mac80211 stack)
     [*]     Broadcom 43xx debugging
     &lt;M&gt;   Broadcom 43xx-legacy wireless support (mac80211 stack)
     [*]     Broadcom 43xx-legacy debugging
</pre>

<p>
After compiling your kernel, you'll need to emerge <c>b43-fwcutter</c> to
install the firmware and get a copy of the firmware. The instructions for this
are found at:
<uri link="http://linuxwireless.org/en/users/Drivers/b43#Other_distributions_not_mentioned_above">
linuxwireless.org</uri>, and follow the directions for extracting the firmware.
</p>

<p>
For a generic guide to setting up wireless with Gentoo, please see the
<uri link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-ppc.xml?part=4&amp;chap=4">Gentoo Wireless
Guide</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="modem">
<title>Will the internal modem work?</title>
<body>

<p>
On older Macs, the internal modem is a regular serial device.  In addition to
ppp support and i2c support, enable this kernel option to use it:
</p>

<pre caption="Serial Drivers">
&lt;*&gt; PowerMac z85c30 ESCC support (CONFIG_SERIAL_PMACZILOG)
</pre>

<p>
Newer Macs use a USB device which only has a driver from Linuxant. Unless you
have purchased a key from Linuxant, this driver will only work at 14.4 and will
not support FAX.  To install the driver, emerge <c>net-dialin/hcfusbmodem</c>
which will provide <path>/dev/ttySHCF0</path>. Then set up ppp like usual.
Further information about the installation can be found at
<uri>http://www.linuxant.com/drivers/hcf/install.html</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="sleep">
<title>Does sleep work on my iBook/PowerBook?</title>
<body>

<p>
Sleep used to work well with the User Mode Setting kernel drivers, but modern
X servers using KMS do not sleep properly at this time.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="sound">
<title>How do I get sound playback working?</title>
<body>

<p>
There are two approaches to sound on modern kernels: OSS or ALSA. OSS is the
older of the two options and has been deprecated, but still functions well for
many older Macs. ALSA is the newer method and will continue to be supported in
the future. We recommend that you use ALSA unless you have problems with it.
</p>

<note>
If you include the OSS driver in your kernel, the ALSA driver will not load.
</note>

<p>
In addition to configuring the kernel, users who should have access to the
audio devices need to be added to the appropriate group with the command:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding users to the audio group">
# <i>gpasswd -a username audio</i>
</pre>

<p>
If the kernel is set up correctly, but you can't hear any sound, ensure that
the main mixer volume is turned up and that the device isn't muted!
</p>

<note>
The sound card on Macs is connected through the i2c Keywest/PowerMac bus, not
the PCI bus.  You will not see the card listed when viewing the PCI bus or when
using alsaconf. This is less of a problem then you might imagine, because all
Macs use the same driver for sound, but you will need to insure that you have
i2c Keywest/PowerMac support in your kernel.
</note>

<impo>
If you compile in ALSA support, you need to also compile in i2c
Keywest/PowerMac support. Failure to do this will result in kernel panics on
boot!
</impo>

</body>
</section>
<section id="alsa">
<title>Sound setup with ALSA</title>
<body>

<p>
For ALSA, we'll set up both the regular ALSA drivers and the OSS emulation
layer so that we can still use legacy OSS only programs. In <c>make
menuconfig</c> you'll need to select:
</p>

<pre caption="Kernel options for ALSA">
Device Drivers - I2c support ---&gt;
  I2C Hardware Bus Support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; Powermac I2C interface (Keywest on 2.6.15 and older)

Device Drivers - Sound ---&gt;
&lt;*&gt; Sound card support
    Advanced Linux Sound Architecture ---&gt;
    &lt; &gt;   PowerMac DMA sound support
      &lt;*&gt; Advanced Linux Sound Architecture
      &lt;*&gt; Sequencer support
      &lt;*&gt; Sequencer dummy client
      &lt;*&gt; OSS Mixer API
      &lt;*&gt; OSS PCM (digital audio) API
      [*] OSS Sequencer API
</pre>

<p>
Depending on the age of the machine, the correct sound driver should also be
enabled.  On more modern machines such as Aluminum PowerBooks, new iBooks or
G5's the <c>Apple On-board Audio</c> driver should be used.  For older machines,
try the ALSA PowerMac driver instead.
</p>

<pre caption="ALSA Drivers - Choose only one">
<comment>Older Machines</comment>
    ALSA PowerMac devices ---&gt;
        &lt;*&gt; PowerMac (AWACS, DACA, Burgundy, Tumbler, Keywest)
<comment>Newer Machines</comment>
    Apple Onboard Audio driver ---&gt;
        &lt;*&gt; Apple Onboard Audio driver
        &lt;*&gt;   layout-id fabric
        &lt;*&gt;   support Onyx chip
        &lt;*&gt;   support TAS chip
        &lt;*&gt;   support Toonie chip
</pre>

<p>
You can also configure these as modules and ensure they're loaded on boot, but
it's easier to simply compile it all in.
</p>

<note>
Please make sure that <c>PowerMac DMA sound support</c> is turned off,
otherwise the ALSA module will not be able to load.
</note>

<p>
For more information on configuring ALSA, please see the <uri
link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/ALSA">ALSA article</uri> on the Gentoo Wiki.
</p>

<note>
If you are using the alsa-driver package instead of building it into your
kernel, the ALSA_CARDS variable should be set to <c>powermac</c> for older
Macs or all of <c>aoa</c>, <c>aoa-fabric-layout</c>, <c>aoa-soundbus</c>,
<c>aoa-soundbus-i2c</c>, <c>aoa-onyx</c>, <c>aoa-tas</c> and <c>aoa-toonie</c>
for newer Macs.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section id="oss">
<title>Sound setup with OSS</title>
<body>

<note>Again, only use this if you're not using ALSA.</note>

<p>
In <c>make menuconfig</c> you'll need to select:
</p>

<pre caption="Kernel options for OSS">
Device Drivers - I2c support ---&gt;
  I2C Hardware Bus Support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; Powermac I2C interface (Keywest on 2.6.15 and older)

Device Drivers - Sound ---&gt;
&lt;*&gt; Sound card support
  &lt;*&gt;   PowerMac DMA sound support
</pre>

<p>
(or configure as modules and ensure they're loaded on boot).
</p>

<p>
If the <c>dmasound_pmac</c> module does not load, you probably need to enable
<c>i2c-core</c> in the kernel or as a module.
</p>

<note>
If you are still using OSS sound, please test the ALSA drivers instead and
report any regressions to the ALSA bugzila.  Thanks!
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section id="wakeon">
<title>How do I make my Mac power up after a power failure?</title>
<body>

<p>
The Power Management Unit (PMU) in most Macs has the ability to turn the Mac
on again after a power loss.  This feature is controlled by the PMU options
found in <path>/proc</path>.  To enable this feature, set <c>server_mode</c>
to 1, to disable it, set <c>server_mode</c> to 0.
</p>

<pre caption="Enabling power on after power failure">
# <i>echo "server_mode=1" > /proc/pmu/options</i>
</pre>

<p>
Unfortunately, this setting is turned off again after the machine restarts. To
ensure that your system always starts with power on after power failure
enabled, add the line above to <path>/etc/conf.d/local.start</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="infrombadport">
<title>
I see lots of "IN from bad port" errors in my kernel dmesg, how do I fix that?
</title>
<body>

<p>
This is caused by drivers written for devices that you don't have on your
system.  These messages are usually harmless, but it's a good idea to
disable the unused drivers anyway.  See below to match up port numbers with
kernel configuration options.  Note that even if the numbers don't match,
try disabling these kernel options anyway, most PPC machines don't use these
drivers.
</p>

<pre caption="IN from bad port 61 - Disable PC Speaker support">
Device Drivers - Input device support ---&gt;
[*] Miscellanous devices ---&gt;
      &lt; &gt; PC Speaker Support
</pre>

<pre caption="IN from bad port 64 - Disable i8042 keyboard support">
Device Drivers - Input device support ---&gt;
Hardware I/O Ports ---&gt;
      &lt; &gt; Serial I/O support
        &lt; &gt; i8042 PC Keyboard controller
</pre>

<pre caption="IN from bad port 2E9,2F9,3E9,3F9 - Disable 8250/16550 support">
Device Drivers - Character devices ---&gt;
Serial drivers ---&gt;
      &lt; &gt; 8250/16550 and compatible serial support
</pre>

<p>
If you have another IN from bad port message that you're not sure about, please
let us know!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Applications</title>
<section id="masked">
<title>
I can't emerge a package, and get an error about it being masked. What should I
do?
</title>
<body>

<p>
There are two common reasons why a package will not emerge: either it hasn't
been tested on PPC or it has been tested, but hasn't yet been marked stable.
</p>

<pre caption="The Package Hasn't Been Tested on PPC">
!!! All ebuilds that could satisfy "bar" have been masked.
!!! One of the following masked packages is required to complete your request:
- app-foo/bar-1.0 (masked by: missing keyword)
</pre>

<p>
If your package hasn't yet been tested on PPC, you'll need to first mark the
ebuild with the ppc keyword. This is done using the ekeyword tool which is part
of the <c>gentoolkit-dev</c> package. To mark the ebuild ppc and regenerate the
manifest file so that it reflects the changes:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding the ppc keyword to app-foo/bar">
# <i>ekeyword ppc /usr/portage/app-foo/bar/bar-1.0.ebuild</i>
# <i>ebuild /usr/portage/app-foo/bar/bar-1.0.ebuild manifest</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once the ebuild has been keyworded, you can now emerge it as usual. Test the
application and if it works, <b>please</b> report it as a bug so one of the
developers can add the keyword.
</p>

<note>
This change will only last until the next sync. If you need a more permanent
fix, you can maintain a portage overlay. See the portage documentation for more
information on maintaining an overlay.
</note>

<pre caption="The Package Hasn't Been Marked Stable on PPC">
!!! All ebuilds that could satisfy "bar" have been masked.
!!! One of the following masked packages is required to complete your request:
- app-foo/bar-1.0 (masked by: ~ppc keyword)
</pre>

<p>
If your package already has the ~ppc keyword, you have two options. Either
follow the above instructions and replace the ~ppc keyword with ppc, or you can
use /etc/portage to unmask the specific package.  The second option is
preferred simply because it won't be undone by an emerge sync.
</p>

<pre caption="Using /etc/portage to unmask app-foo/bar">
$ <i>echo "=app-foo/bar-1.0" > /etc/portage/package.accept_keywords</i>
</pre>

<note>
If the /etc/portage directory does not exist, make sure to create it first.
</note>

<p>
Now emerge the package as normal. Once you're sure the app is stable,
<b>please</b> report this as a bug so the developers can add the keyword.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="flash">
<title>Does Gentoo/PPC have support for Flash?</title>
<body>

<p>
Well, not really. Macromedia has not supplied a linux/ppc binary and open
source implementations are incomplete at this time.  However, there are two
projects that can play many flash objects,
<uri link="http://www.gnu.org/software/gnash/">gnash</uri> and
<uri link="http://swfdec.freedesktop.org/">swfdec</uri>.
Both are capable of playing back Youtube movies and lots of other popular
content.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="java">
<title>Does Gentoo/PPC have a Java plugin?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes, a Java plugin is now available with IBM's Java 1.5 and 1.6.  Note that not
all Java applications work with these Java versions yet.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section id="drm">
<title>What is required for DRM?</title>
<body>

<p>
When emerging xorg-server, make sure the dri use flag is enabled.  You should
also set the VIDEO_CARDS variable in make.conf with your video card,
VIDEO_CARDS="radeon" for radeon support, VIDEO_CARDS="nouveau" for nvidia 
support and so on.  For a backup option, add fbdev to the list of VIDEO_CARDS,
this driver should always work.
</p>

<p>
Make sure in your kernel config you have the following options set:
</p>

<pre caption="Rage128 DRM kernel configuration">
Device Drivers - Graphics Support ---&gt;
  &lt;*&gt; /dev/agpgart (AGP Support)
    [*] Apple UniNorth support
  [*] Direct Rendering Manager (DRI support)
    &lt;*&gt;   ATI Rage 128
  -*- Support for frame buffer devices
    &lt;*&gt;   ATI Rage 128 display support
</pre>

<pre caption="Radeon DRM kernel configuration">
Device Drivers - Graphics Support ---&gt;
  &lt;*&gt; /dev/agpgart (AGP Support)
    [*] Apple UniNorth support
  [*] Direct Rendering Manager (DRI support)
    &lt;*&gt;   ATI Radeon
    [*]   Enable modesetting on radeon by default - NEW DRIVER
</pre>

<pre caption="nVidia kernel configuration">
Device Drivers - Graphics Support ---&gt;
  &lt;*&gt; /dev/agpgart (AGP Support)
    [*] Apple UniNorth support
  [*] Direct Rendering Manager (DRI support)
    &lt;*&gt; Nouveau (nVidia) cards
    [*]   Support for backlight control
</pre>

<note>
For nVidia and Radeon devices using KMS, be sure to disable the built in frame
buffer devices, these prevent the KMS drivers from starting.
</note>

<impo>
You may need to edit your <path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path> file depending on
your card setup. Ensure that the device driver selected is the specific driver
for your device, (such as radeon or nouveau). Also check that the DRI extension
is loaded and not commented out.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
<section id="noati">
<title>
I've installed X.org and configured it correctly, but the radeon or nouveau 
driver is missing.  What's wrong?
</title>
<body>

<p>
Add the appropriate VIDEO_CARDS line to <path>/etc/portage/make.conf</path> and
recompile <c>xorg-server</c> and <c>mesa</c> to build the drivers.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="xorgerror">
<title>
I have a VBIOS or "Invalid I/O allocation" error in my xorg.log.  Is this
a problem?
</title>
<body>

<p>
No, this is simply X.org probing your video card.  It attempts to open the
x86 only video BIOS and fails, leaving one of these messages.  It's
harmless, don't worry about it!
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="glfreeze">
<title>
When using OpenGL DRI or playing movies, the system sometimes freezes hard
unexpectedly. What can I do?
</title>
<body>

<p>
Your system may not cope properly with AGP support. The easiest solution is to
add the following line to the "Device" section of
<path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Forcing PCI mode for AGP-Cards">
Option       "ForcePCIMode"
</pre>

<p>
If you are still having trouble, please try disabling dri in your xorg.conf to 
see if the problems go away.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="keymap">
<title>
I recently emerged Xorg, but when using it, my international keyboard layout
does not work correctly. The main keys work fine but I am unable to compose
special characters like the "at" sign. The startx output says something like
"could not load keymap, falling back to default keymap". What is wrong?
</title>
<body>

<p>
Check that the permissions on <path>/var/tmp</path> are set to
<path>drwxrwxrwx</path>. If not, change them by typing <c>chmod a+rwx
/var/tmp</c>. This will allow Xorg to load keymaps properly again.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="audiocd">
<title>How do I play Audio CDs?</title>
<body>

<p>
NewWorld machines have no audio connection between their CD-ROM drive and their
sound hardware. Therefore, audio information must be read as data and then
piped to the sound hardware. This is possible using <e>Audacious</e>, which
reads the audio off the CD over the ATA cable, decodes it in software and sends
it to the sound card over the PCI bus as digital data.
</p>

<pre caption="Emerge audacious">
# <i>emerge audacious</i>
</pre>

<p>
To play a CD, just fire up <c>audacious</c>. If you're having playback trouble,
you may need to open up the Preferences-->Plugins-->CD Audio Plugin menu and
select your CD drive. Make sure that "Digital audio extraction" is checked.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section id="ext">
<title>Can I access my ext2/ext3 partitions from OSX?</title>
<body>

<p>
OSX can support the reading and writing of ext2/ext3 partitions by using the
kernel extension provided by the <uri
link="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ext2fsx">ext2fsx project.</uri>
</p>

<note>
When using MOL, you cannot access a partition that is currently being used by
Linux.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section id="useflags">
<title>Which Portage USE flags do not work on PowerPC machines?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you're using an old flat profile, (deprecated, pre 2005.0) look at
<path>/etc/portage/make.profile/use.mask</path> for a list.
</p>

<p>
If you're using a cascaded profile, (2005.0 and onwards) look at
<path>/usr/portage/profiles/default-linux/ppc/use.mask</path> for a list.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="distcc">
<title>How can I set up distcc with my x86 box?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you've got another faster computer, you can set up distcc to compile binaries
for your slower ppc processor. It's better to do as much building as possible on
the faster machine; if possible, don't even build on the slower computer. Read
the <uri link="/doc/en/cross-compiling-distcc.xml">DistCC Cross-compiling
Guide</uri> to learn how. You may also want to read the <uri
link="/proj/en/base/embedded/handbook/">Gentoo Embedded Handbook</uri> to learn
more about cross-compiling.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section id="cd">
<title>Can I buy a CD of Gentoo Linux/PPC?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes! We sell Gentoo on CD-ROM in our <uri
link="http://store.gentoo.org/">Gentoo store</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="notanswered">
<title>This FAQ hasn't answered my question. What do I do now?</title>
<body>

<p>
A good first step is to browse through the relevant <uri
link="/doc/en/index.xml">documentation on www.gentoo.org</uri>. Two
PPC-specific <uri link="/main/en/lists.xml">mailing lists</uri> currently
exist, gentoo-ppc-dev and gentoo-ppc-user. <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum.php?f=24">Gentoo on PPC</uri> (on
forums.gentoo.org) is an open bulletin-board for discussion of all PowerPC
issues. Also, there is usually a lively discussion on IRC. Join us on
<c>#gentoo-ppc</c> on <c>irc.freenode.net</c>.
</p>

<p>
General information about Linux on PowerPC can be found at <uri
link="http://penguinppc.org/">penguinppc.org</uri>. General Linux information
is at <uri link="http://www.linuxdoc.org/">www.linuxdoc.org</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
