<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/gentoo-sparc-obpreference.xml,v 1.7 2013/12/09 11:01:49 swift Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Sparc/OBP_Reference">
<title>OpenBoot PROM (OBP) Reference</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="ciaranm@gentoo.org">Ciaran McCreesh</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The OpenBoot PROM (OBP) Reference provides a list of useful OBP commands that
can help when booting, configuring and performing diagnostics upon Sun SPARC
hardware and clones.
</abstract>

<license />
<version>1.2</version>
<date>2004-08-27</date>

<chapter>
<title>About this Document</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This document provides a list of useful OBP commands that can be helpful when
booting, configuring and performing diagnostics upon Sun SPARC hardware and
clones.
</p>

<p>
Note that not all commands are available on all PROM versions. In particular,
sun4c systems have a different input mode, and some JavaStation models are
missing a lot of OBP functionality.
</p>

<p>
OBP is somewhat inconsistent when it comes to command names. Sometimes hyphens
are used to seperate words, sometimes they are not. Some commands which display
information start with or contain a dot (this is a FORTH convention).
</p>

<p>
The terms "OBP", "OpenBoot PROM" and "PROM" are used interchangably in this
document.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Entering OBP</title>
<section>
<title>Systems with Sun Keyboards</title>
<body>

<p>
On regular Sun systems (and clones which use Sun keyboards), press
<c>Stop+A</c> when the system boots to enter OBP. The <c>Stop</c> key is the
top left key on the extra block of keys on the left hand side of the keyboards
(on really old systems it might be marked <c>L1</c>).
</p>

<p>
The <c>Stop+N</c> keyboard combination at boot will reset many systems to the
default PROM settings. <c>Stop+D</c> will enable diagnostics on some boards.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Over Serial Console</title>
<body>

<p>
To enter OBP over serial console, send a break. In minicom, do this by pressing
<c>ctrl+A F</c>. In xc, use <c>ctrl+A B</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Systems with Non-Sun (PC Style) Keyboards</title>
<body>

<p>
On systems with PC-style keyboards (such as JavaStations and some Ultra
clones), <c>ctrl+break</c> or <c>alt+ctrl+break</c> is generally used.
</p>

<p>
Note that on the JavaStation JK, <c>ctrl+break</c> will restart the box rather
than enter PROM. To get at OBP, you will need to set jumper J1300 pins 7-8 on
the mainboard.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Basic System Commands</title>
<section>
<title>Halting and Restarting</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>power-off</c> command will halt the box and turn off power. This command
is sometimes screwy on Ultra5/10 systems.
</p>

<p>
The <c>reset</c> command will perform a soft reset. If diagnostics are enabled,
they will <e>not</e> be rerun. In some documents, this command is refered to as
<c>reset-all</c>.
</p>

<p>
The <c>boot</c> command boots the system. A parameter may be provided to
override the default boot device -- this can be a full device name or a device
alias such as <c>disk</c>, <c>cdrom</c> or <c>net</c>. Any additional arguments
are passed to the bootloader or operating system.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PROM and System Information</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>.version</c> command will show the OBP version.
</p>

<pre caption=".version output">
{0} ok .version
Release 3.7 Version 0 created 1997/01/09 13:06
OBP 3.7.0 1997/01/09 13:06
POST 3.2.1 1996/12/20 03:01
</pre>

<p>
The <c>banner</c> command will show the system information banner.
</p>

<pre caption="banner output">
{0} ok banner
Sun Ultra 2 UPA/SBus (2 X UltraSPARC-II 296MHz), No Keyboard
OpenBoot 3.7, 704 MB memory installed, Serial #9705521.
Ethernet address 8:0:20:94:18:31, Host ID: 80941831
</pre>

<p>
The <c>.speed</c> command will show bus speeds.
</p>

<pre caption=".speed output">
{0} ok .speed
CPU  Speed : 296.00 MHz
UPA  Speed : 098.66 MHz
SBus Speed : 025.00 MHz
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section><title>Device Information</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>show-devs</c> command will give a list of devices available to the
system.
</p>

<p>
The <c>probe-scsi</c> command will show internal SCSI devices available to the
system. The <c>probe-scsi-all</c> command will show both internal and external
devices on every SCSI interface. After running either of these commands, you
<e>must</e> issue a <c>reset-all</c> before trying to boot an operating
system.
</p>

<pre caption="probe-scsi-all output">
{0} ok probe-scsi-all
This command may hang the system if a Stop-A or halt command
has been executed.  Please type reset-all to reset the system
before executing this command.
Do you wish to continue? (y/n) y
/sbus@1f,0/SUNW,fas@e,8800000
Target 1
  Unit 0   Disk     SEAGATE ST34371W SUN4.2G74629710B00491
                    Copyright (c) 1997 Seagate
                    All rights reserved
</pre>

<p>
The <c>probe-ide</c> command is also available on IDE-based systems.
</p>

<pre caption="probe-ide output">
ok probe-ide
  Device 0  ( Primary Master )
          ATA Model: ST320420A

  Device 1  ( Primary Slave )
          ATA Model: Maxtor 6E040L0

  Device 2  ( Secondary Master )
         Not Present

  Device 3  ( Secondary Slave )
         Not Present
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Environment Variables and Device Aliases</title>
<section>
<title>Getting and Setting Environment Variables</title>
<body>

<p>
Use <c>printenv</c> to get a list of environment variables. To see the value of
a specific variable, use <c>printenv fnord</c>.
</p>

<p>
To set a variable, use <c>setenv myvar the new value</c>.
</p>

<p>
To restore a variable's default value, use <c>set-default blah</c>. To revert
<e>all</e> variables to default, use <c>set-defaults</c>.
</p>

<p>
Note that boolean variables usually end in a <c>?</c>, and that they are
seperate from variables of the same name without the question mark. The values
<c>true</c> and <c>false</c> are used for booleans.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Useful Environment Variables</title>
<body>

<p>
Some useful environment variables:
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Variable</th>
    <th>Meaning</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>ttya-mode</c></ti>
    <ti>
      Sets the baud rate and related settings used by the serial console. By
      default <c>9600,8,n,1,-</c> is used, meaning 9600 baud, 8 bits, no
      parity, one stop bit, no flow control.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>auto-boot?</c></ti>
    <ti>
      By default OBP will automatically boot upon startup. Set this to
      <c>false</c> if you'd rather send the boot command manually.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>boot-device</c></ti>
    <ti>
      When auto-booting, and when <c>boot</c> is issued with no arguments, this
      variable is used to determine the boot device. More than one value can be
      provided (space seperated), in which case each is tried in turn. Each
      value can be a full device path or a device alias.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>diag-device</c></ti>
    <ti>
      As <c>boot-device</c>, but used when <c>diag-switch?</c> is enabled.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>local-mac-address?</c></ti>
    <ti>
      If set, network interfaces will use their own MAC rather than the
      system-wide MAC. This is consistent with how PCs behave, and in violation
      of the Ethernet specification.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>diag-switch?</c></ti>
    <ti>
      If set, additional diagnostic checks will be run at power on. Note that
      this can take a <e>very</e> long time on SMP and / or HyperSparc systems.
      In addition, the <c>diag-device</c> variable will also be used to
      determine the boot device rather than <c>boot-device</c>. Some systems
      have a mainboard jumper or a switch on the front of the machine which
      forces this setting on.
    </ti>
  </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Getting and Setting Device Aliases</title>
<body>

<p>
Device aliases can be used to simplify the arguments to many commands.  Instead
of typing <c>boot /sbus/SUNW,hme@e,8c00000</c>, for example, one could use
<c>boot net</c>. A number of device aliases are defined by default on every
system.
</p>

<p>
To view all device aliases, use the <c>devalias</c> command. To view a specific
alias, use <c>devalias whatever</c>. To set a device alias, use <c>devalias
whatever newvalue</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changing Monitor Resolutions</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>output-device</c> variable can be used to control which framebuffer is
used, and at what resolution it is run, for PROM console.  For example, to use
the Creator card on an Ultra 1C or 2 at a resolution of 1024x768@76Hz:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing Monitor Settings">
{0} ok devalias screen /SUNW,ffb
{0} ok setenv output-device screen:r1024x768x76
</pre>

<p>
Changes will not take effect until after a reset. Not all resolutions and
refresh are available on all cards.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Diagnostics</title>
<section>
<title>Entering Diagnostic Mode</title>
<body>

<p>
Before running any diagnostics, it is best to enable <c>diag-switch?</c> and do
a full power off / on cycle (hard power off). Additional diagnostic information
will be provided over the serial console when the machine boots.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Basic Tests</title>
<body>

<p>
If the power on self test (POST) succeeds, additional tests can be performed
using the <c>test</c>, <c>test-all</c>, <c>watch-net</c> and <c>watch-clock</c>
commands.
</p>

<p>
The <c>test somedevice</c> command will perform checks upon the specified
device (this can be a full device path or a device alias).
</p>

<pre caption="Example Tests">
{0} ok test scsi
        CE DMA fill from address fff8e000 for 80 bytes   succeeded.
         Dma register test -- succeeded.
         Esp register test -- succeeded.
         Dma read test -- succeeded.
         Dma write test -- succeeded.
{0} ok test /sbus/SUNW,hme
Internal loopback test -- succeeded.
Transceiver check  -- Using Onboard Transceiver - Link Up.
passed
{0} ok test ttya
 !"#$%&amp;'()*+,-./0123456789:;&lt;=&gt;?@ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZ[\]^_`abcdefghijklmn
</pre>

<p>
The <c>test-all</c> command will perform checks upon every device capable of
self tests.
</p>

<p>
The <c>watch-net</c> command can be used to watch for broadcast packets being
sent over the network.
</p>

<p>
The <c>watch-clock</c> command can be used to verify that the internal clock is
working. It should count from 0 to 59 in a loop with an interval of one
second.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Extended Diagnostics Using obdiag</title>
<body>

<note>
The <c>obdiag</c> routines are only available on the Ultra 5/10 and later.
</note>

<p>
To enable extended diagnostics mode, run the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Entering obdiag">
ok setenv mfg-mode on
mfg-mode =            on
ok setenv diag-switch? true
diag-switch? =        true
ok setenv auto-boot? false
auto-boot? =          false
ok reset-all
ok obdiag
</pre>

<p>
This should display a menu. First, select <c>16</c> to enable verbose
messages.
</p>

<pre caption="obdiag menu">
          OBDiag Menu

  0 ..... PCI/Cheerio
  1 ..... EBUS DMA/TCR Registers
  2 ..... Ethernet
  3 ..... Keyboard
  4 ..... Mouse
  5 ..... Floppy
  6 ..... Parallel Port
  7 ..... Serial Port A
  8 ..... Serial Port B
  9 ..... NVRAM
 10 ..... Audio
 11 ..... EIDE
 12 ..... Video
 13 ..... All Above
 14 ..... Quit
 15 ..... Display this Menu
 16 ..... Toggle script-debug
 17 ..... Enable External Loopback Tests
 18 ..... Disable External Loopback Tests

 Enter (0-13 tests, 14 -Quit, 15 -Menu) ===> 16
 Enter (0-13 tests, 14 -Quit, 15 -Menu) ===>
</pre>

<p>
Individual tests can then be run by selecting the relevant number. Note that
some tests (for example, serial ports) assume that an external loopback
connector is attached. The Ethernet test assumes that a cable is attached and
connected to a switch.
</p>

<p>
To exit, use <c>14</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>References</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    OpenBoot 3.x Quick Reference, Sun P/N 802-3240 (<uri
    link="http://sunsolve.sun.com/data/802/802-3240/pdf/802-3240-10.pdf">PDF
    Version)</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    OpenBoot 3.x Command Reference, Sun P/N 802-3242 (<uri
    link="http://sunsolve.sun.com/data/802/802-3242/html/TOC.html">HTML
    Version)</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    OpenBoot 3.x Supplement for PCI, Sun P/N 802-7679 (<uri
    link="http://sunsolve.sun.com/data/802/802-7679/pdf/">Collection of PDF
    files)</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://firmworks.com/QuickRef.html">Open Firmware Quick
    Reference</uri> (Not Sun OBP specific)
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
