<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/gnome-config.xml,v 1.40 2013/12/09 11:33:44 swift Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/GNOME/Configuration">
<title>The GNOME Configuration HOWTO</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="lars@strojny.net">Lars Strojny</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
A frequently used environment is GNOME. This HOWTO tries to describe
all aspects of GNOME, including installation, configuration, usage, ...
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>8</version>
<!-- 2012-12-09 -->
<date>2013-07-27</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is GNOME?</title>
<section>
<title>The Project</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.gnome.org">GNOME</uri> project is a free software
project dedicated to the development of GNOME, a Unix/Linux desktop suite and
development platform. The <uri link="http://foundation.gnome.org">GNOME
Foundation</uri> coordinates the development and other aspects of the GNOME
Project.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Software</title>
<body>

<p>
GNOME is a desktop environment and a development platform. This piece of free
software is the desktop of choice for several industry leaders. It is
interesting both for business users, home users as well as developers.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Community</title>
<body>

<p>
Like with any big free software project, GNOME has an extensive user- and
development base. <uri link="http://planet.gnome.org">GnomePlanet</uri> is
a popular blog aggregator for GNOME hackers and contributors whereas <uri
link="http://developer.gnome.org">Developer.Gnome.Org</uri> is for the GNOME
developers. <uri link="http://library.gnome.org/users/">GNOME Library</uri>
contains a huge list of GNOME resources for end users. The <uri
link="http://worldofgnome.org/">World of GNOME</uri> is also a popular
aggregator for GNOME-related news.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Installing GNOME</title>
<section>
<title>What do you need?</title>
<body>

<impo>
First read and follow the instructions in the <uri
link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Xorg/Configuration">X Server Configuration Howto</uri> to setup your
X environment.
</impo>

<p>
Before you start installing GNOME, you might want to edit your USE variables.
Make sure that <c>X</c>, <c>gtk</c>, and <c>gnome</c> are in your USE variable
listed in <path>/etc/portage/make.conf</path>. If you want support for <c>dbus</c>, a
system message bus Gnome uses extensively, add it to your USE flags. If you
don't want KDE support (the other big desktop environment), remove <c>qt4</c>
and <c>kde</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Example USE in /etc/portage/make.conf">
USE="-qt4 -kde X dbus gtk gnome"
</pre>

<p>
You can add the <c>branding</c> USE flag to get a lovely Gentoo-branded
splashscreen instead of the default Gnome splashscreen:
</p>

<pre caption="Enabling Gentoo branding">
# <i>echo "gnome-base/gnome-session branding" &gt;&gt; /etc/portage/package.use</i>
</pre>

<note>
If you use the <c>desktop</c> profile, these USE flags will be set for you. You
can check your profile by running <c>eselect profile list</c> and <c>eselect
profile set &lt;profile-name&gt;</c> as root.
</note>

<p>
Once done, start installing GNOME by emerging <c>gnome</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing GNOME">
# <i>emerge gnome</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can also opt for a minimal Gnome installation using <c>gnome-light</c>.
If you do so, you will have a lightweight Gnome installation without
the additional tools that a full Gnome installation provides so you might need
to install additional packages afterwards.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a minimal GNOME environment">
# <i>emerge gnome-light</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will take a while, so you might want to start reading all those books your
mother bought you but you never opened. Done? Great, now update your
environment variables:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating environment variables">
# <i>env-update &amp;&amp; source /etc/profile</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next we'll clean up the remaining services and user groups. 
</p>

<pre caption="Setting up the DBUS service">
# <i>/etc/init.d/dbus start</i>
# <i>rc-update add dbus default</i>
</pre>

<p>
Check if the <e>plugdev</e> group exists. If it does, it is adviseable to make
yourself member of that group, but this is optional (the group is not that
common anymore).
</p>

<pre caption="Checking and adding users to plugdev">
~# <i>getent group plugdev</i>
plugdev:x:104:

<comment># Substitute yourUserName with your user name ;-)</comment>
~# <i>gpasswd -a yourUserName plugdev</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>First Impressions</title>
<body>

<p>
Let us first take a look at what we just built. Exit your root shell and log on
as a regular user. We will configure our session to run GNOME when we issue the
<c>startx</c> command (see also
<uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Xorg/Configuration#Using_startx">Using startx</uri> in the
<uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Xorg/Configuration">X Server Configuration Howto</uri>):
</p>

<pre caption="Setting GNOME as the default desktop environment">
$ <i>echo "exec gnome-session" &gt; ~/.xinitrc</i>
</pre>

<p>
Starting with <c>gnome-base/gnome-session-2.26.2</c>, you will need to prepend
the XDG_MENU_PREFIX variable to get the Gnome menus if you're using the
<path>~/.xinitrc</path> method to start your desktop. (If you're not using
<path>~/.xinitrc</path>, it will be handled automatically for you; no additional
configuration is needed.)
</p>

<pre caption="Prepending XDG_MENU_PREFIX to ~/.xinitrc">
$ <i>sed -i '1i\export XDG_MENU_PREFIX=gnome-' ~/.xinitrc</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now start your graphical environment by running <c>startx</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting GNOME">
$ <i>startx</i>
</pre>

<p>
If all goes well, you should be greeted by GNOME. Congratulations. Now let us
take a look at how you can configure GNOME to suit your needs.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Configuring GNOME</title>
<section>
<title>GNOME's Graphical Login Manager</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want the GNOME Display Manager (GDM) to run automatically when you boot
(so you can log on graphically), you must add the <c>xdm</c> init script to the
default runlevel:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding xdm to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add xdm default</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now edit <path>/etc/conf.d/xdm</path> and alter the DISPLAYMANAGER variable.
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/conf.d/xdm">
DISPLAYMANAGER="gdm"
</pre>

<p>
If you installed Gnome using the <c>gnome-light</c> package, you will need to
install <c>gdm</c> too (as it is not defined as part of the <c>gnome-light</c>
package).
</p>

<pre caption="Installing the gdm application">
# <i>emerge gdm</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you reboot now, the GNOME Display Manager will prompt you for your username
and password and will default to using GNOME as Desktop Environment (even though
you will have the option of selecting a different one of course, choosing from
those available in <path>/usr/share/xsessions/</path>). Thus, if you use GDM,
you don't need to edit <path>~/.xinitrc</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
