<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/gpm.xml,v 1.6 2013/08/03 16:42:39 swift Exp $ -->

<guide redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/GPM">
<title>Using a Mouse within the Console</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Joshua Saddler</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide shows you how to set up and use GPM (the General Purpose Mouse
server) from within a command line interface. This is especially useful for new
Gentoo installations or for systems that cannot or do not use an X server.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.2</version>
<date>2006-02-17</date>

<chapter>
<title>Getting GPM</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
If you've just installed Gentoo, you almost certainly don't have your mouse set
up to work within a command line interface (CLI) yet. Or perhaps you can't use
or don't need an X server, yet you still need to use a mouse. The solution is
simple: <c>gpm</c>, the General Purpose Mouse server.
</p>

<p>
First, you will need to get GPM:
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining GPM">
# <i>emerge gpm</i>
</pre>

<p>
You might have noticed a few messages during the compilation that warned about
configuring the server. You must do this before starting GPM.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring GPM</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Before you can use GPM, you will need to uncomment the lines corresponding to
the location and protocol of your mouse. You do this by editing the GPM
configuration file:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting up GPM">
# <i>nano /etc/conf.d/gpm</i>
</pre>

<p>
In my case, I have a USB mouse on <path>/dev/input/mouse0</path>. So, I have
uncommented <path>/dev/input/mice</path>, as this is the cumulative device for
all mice on the system, and the appropriate protocol. Try using
<path>/dev/input/mice</path> before <path>/dev/psaux</path>, as the latter is
deprecated and can be disabled in the latest 2.6 kernels. If
<path>/dev/input/mice</path> fails, then fall back to other devices. Here is my
example <path>/etc/conf.d/gpm</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Example GPM config">
<comment>(Please uncomment the type of mouse you have and the appropriate MOUSEDEV entry)</comment>

#MOUSE=ps2
MOUSE=imps2
#MOUSEDEV=/dev/psaux
MOUSEDEV=/dev/input/mice
</pre>

<p>
If you have a wheelmouse, you will want to use the imps2 protocol, so uncomment
that line. If imps2 and ps2 both fail to work for you, please refer to the GPM
info page (<c>info gpm</c>) for other protocols to try. Also, if you want to be
able to click on hyperlinks in terminals to navigate to a website, it is a good
idea to follow the suggestion in the <c>/etc/conf.d/gpm</c> file:
</p>

<pre caption="Other options">
<comment>(Please uncomment this line if you want GPM to understand charsets
used in URLs and names with ~ or : in them, etc.
This is a good idea to turn on!)</comment>

APPEND="-l \"a-zA-Z0-9_.:~/\300-\326\330-\366\370-\377\""
</pre>

<p>
The rest of the conf.d file contains other suggestions for your mouse server;
uncomment the various options according to your needs. See <c>man gpm</c> for
more information.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Running GPM</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Now that your mouse server is installed and configured, it's time to start
using it:
</p>

<pre caption="The GPM init script">
# <i>/etc/init.d/gpm start</i>
</pre>

<p>
You should see a block cursor appear. Remember that only root can run the GPM
init script. However, to avoid having to <c>su</c> and run the script every
single time you begin a new session, why not set GPM to begin every time you
turn on your computer?
</p>

<pre caption="Adding GPM to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add gpm default</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now, whenever you start your computer, you'll be greeted by the console cursor
by the time you get to the login prompt. The mouse server will continue to run
even if you're not logged in as root.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Working with GPM</title>
<section>
<title>Copying and pasting</title>
<body>

<p>
Copying and pasting large blocks of text with a working mouse server is very
easy. Simply highlight the text with the left mouse button (it will stay
highlighted when you release the button), switch to a different terminal if you
wish, position the cursor, and press the middle mouse button to paste the text
where you placed the cursor. Note that you can copy and paste without ever
leaving the terminal you started. This makes posting the output of error
messages to the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri>
extremely simple.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Text-mode browsing and GPM</title>
<body>

<p>
If you have a message on one screen and a text-mode web browser on the other,
you can copy the error message by highlighting it, then change to the other
terminal, left-click the appropriate text entry box to select it, and then
press the middle mouse button. Voilà! Your error message can now be posted to
the forums.
</p>

<p>
Though discussion of text-only browsers is somewhat beyond the scope of this
guide, inevitably users will need to find a compatible console browser. Though
<c>lynx</c> is most likely the oldest and well established browser, its
interface has poor mouse support and recognition. Instead, try using
<c>links</c> which has excellent mouse integration.
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining links">
# <i>emerge links</i>
</pre>

<p>
This concludes the guide to using a mouse within the console. Happy mousing!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
