<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/guide-localization.xml,v 1.65 2012/07/24 12:12:51 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Linux Localization Guide</title>
<author title="Author">
  Alexander Holler
</author>
<author title="Translator/Editor">
  <mail link="slucy@uchicago.edu">Steven Lucy</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="bennyc@gentoo.org">Benny Chuang</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="flammie@gentoo.org">Flammie Pirinen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="klondike"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide should help users localize their Gentoo Linux distribution to any
European locale. It uses Germany as a case-study, since it is translated from
the German doc. Includes configuration for use of the euro currency symbol.
</abstract>

<version>3</version>
<date>2012-07-24</date>

<chapter>
<title>Time zone</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
In order to keep time properly, you need to select your timezone so that your
system knows where it is located. Look for your timezone in
<path>/usr/share/zoneinfo</path>. You then set your timezone in
<path>/etc/timezone</path>. Please avoid the
<path>/usr/share/zoneinfo/Etc/GMT*</path> timezones as their names do not
indicate the expected zones. For instance, <path>GMT-8</path> is in fact GMT+8.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the timezone information">
# <i>ls /usr/share/zoneinfo</i>
<comment>(Suppose you want to use Brussels)</comment>
<comment>(First copy the proper zone to localtime)</comment>
# <i>cp /usr/share/zoneinfo/Europe/Brussels /etc/localtime</i>
<comment>(Now specify your timezone)</comment>
# <i>nano -w /etc/timezone</i>
Europe/Brussels

# <i>date</i>
Wed Mar  8 00:46:05 CET 2006
</pre>

<note>
Make sure that the timezone indicator (in this case "CET")
is correct for your area.
</note>

<note>
You can set the value of <c>TZ</c> to be everything after the
<path>/usr/share/zoneinfo</path> in your shell rc file
(<path>.bash_profile</path> for bash) for a user-level setting.  In this case
<c>TZ="Europe/Berlin"</c>.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardware Clock</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
In most Gentoo Linux installations, your hardware clock is set to
UTC (or GMT, Greenwich Mean Time) and then your timezone is
taken into account to determine the actual, local time.  If,
for some reason, you need your hardware clock not to be in UTC,
you will need to edit <path>/etc/conf.d/hwclock</path> (or if you use Gentoo
BSD: <path>/etc/conf.d/adjkerntz</path>) and change the
value of <c>clock</c> from <c>UTC</c> to <c>local</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="local vs. GMT clock">
<comment>(recommended:)</comment>
clock="UTC"
<comment>(or:)</comment>
clock="local"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Locale system</title>
<section>
<title>What are locales?</title>
<body>

<p>
A Locale is a set of information that most programs use for determining country
and language specific settings. The locales and their data are part of the
system library and can be found at <path>/usr/share/locale</path> on most
systems. A locale name is generally named <c>ab_CD</c> where <c>ab</c> is your
two (or three) letter language code (as specified in ISO-639) and <c>CD</c> is
your two letter country code (as specified in ISO-3166). Variants are often
appended to locale names, e.g. <c>en_GB.UTF-8</c> or <c>de_DE@euro</c>. Please
explore <uri link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Locale">Wikipedia</uri> to read
more about locales and related articles.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="variables">
<title>Environment variables for locales</title>
<body>

<p>
Locale settings are stored in environment variables. These are typically
set in the <path>/etc/env.d/02locale</path> (for system-wide
settings) and <path>~/.bashrc</path> (for user-specific settings) file.
The variables controlling different aspects of locale settings
are given in the table below. All of them
take one name of a locale in <c>ab_CD</c> format given above.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Variable name</th>
  <th>Explanation</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LANG</ti>
  <ti>
    Defines all locale settings at once, while allowing further individual
    customization via the LC_* settings below.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LC_COLLATE</ti>
  <ti>
    Define alphabetical ordering of strings. This affects e.g. output of sorted
    directory listing.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LC_CTYPE</ti>
  <ti>
    Define the character handling properties for the system. This determines 
    which characters are seen as part of alphabet, numeric and so on. This also
    determines the character set used, if applicable.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LC_MESSAGES</ti>
  <ti>
    Programs' localizations for applications that use message based localization
    scheme (majority of Gnu programs, see next chapters for closer information
    which do, and how to get the programs, that don't, to work).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LC_MONETARY</ti>
  <ti>Defines currency units and formatting of currency type numeric values.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LC_NUMERIC</ti>
  <ti>
    Defines formatting of numeric values which aren't monetary. Affects things
    such as thousand separator and decimal separator.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LC_TIME</ti>
  <ti>Defines formatting of dates and times.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LC_PAPER</ti>
  <ti>Defines default paper size.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LC_ALL</ti>
  <ti>
    A special variable for overriding all other settings.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<note>
Some programs are written in such a way that they expect traditional English
ordering of the alphabet, while some locales, most notably the Estonian one, use
a different ordering. Therefore it's recommended to explicitly set LC_COLLATE to C
when dealing with system-wide settings.
</note>

<warn>
Using LC_ALL is strongly discouraged as it can't be overridden later on. Please
use it only when testing and <e>never</e> set it in a startup file.
</warn>

<p>
Most typically users only set the LANG variable on the global basis. This
example is for a unicode German locale:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the default system locale in /etc/env.d/02locale">
LANG="de_DE.UTF-8"
LC_COLLATE="C"
</pre>

<note>
Use <c>de_DE@euro</c> as your LANG if you want to use the Euro currency symbol
(€) on non UTF-8 based locales.
</note>

<p>
It's also possible, and pretty common especially in a more traditional UNIX
environment, to leave the global settings unchanged, i.e. in the "<c>C</c>"
locale. Users can still specify their preferred locale in their own shell RC
file:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the user locale in ~/.bashrc">
export LANG="de_DE.UTF-8"
export LC_COLLATE="C"
</pre>

<p>
Another way of configuring system is to leave it in the default C locale, but
enable UTF-8 character representation at the same time. This option is achieved
using the following settings in <path>/etc/env.d/02locale</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Using traditional C locale while specifying UTF-8">
LC_CTYPE=de_DE.UTF-8
</pre>

<p>
Using the above snippet, users will be able to see localized file names
properly, while not being forced to your preferred language.
</p>

<p>
For message based localization to work in programs that support it, you will
probably need to have programs compiled with the <c>nls</c> (Native language
support) USE flag set. Most of the programs using nls also need the gettext
library to extract and use localized messages. Of course, Portage will
automatically install it when needed.
</p>

<p>
Once you have set the right locale, be sure to update your environment
variables to make your system aware of the change:
</p>

<pre caption="Update the environment">
<comment>(For system-wide default locale:)</comment>
# <i>env-update &amp;&amp; source /etc/profile</i>

<comment>(For user-specific locale:)</comment>
$ <i>source ~/.bashrc</i>
</pre>

<p>
After this, you will need to kill your X server by pressing
<c>Ctrl-Alt-Backspace</c>, log out, then log in as user.
</p>

<p>
Now, verify that the changes have taken effect:
</p>

<pre caption="Verify env changes">
$ <i>locale</i>
</pre>

<p>
There is also additional localisation variable called LINGUAS, which affects
to localisation files that get installed in gettext-based programs, and decides
used localisation for some specific software packages, such as 
<c>kde-base/kde-l10n</c> and <c>app-office/openoffice</c>. The variable
takes in <e>space</e>-separated list of language codes, and suggested
place to set it is <path>/etc/portage/make.conf</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting LINGUAS in make.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/portage/make.conf</i>
<comment>(Add in the LINGUAS variable. For instance, 
for German, Finnish and English:)</comment>
LINGUAS="de fi en"
</pre>


</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Generating Specific Locales</title>
<body>

<p>
You will probably only use one or maybe two locales on your system. You can
specify locales you will need in <path>/etc/locale.gen</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding locales to /etc/locale.gen">
en_GB ISO-8859-1
en_GB.UTF-8 UTF-8
de_DE ISO-8859-1
de_DE@euro ISO-8859-15
</pre>

<p>
The next step is to run <c>locale-gen</c>. It will generate all the locales you
have specified in the <path>/etc/locale.gen</path> file.
</p>

<note>
<c>locale-gen</c> is available in <c>glibc-2.3.6-r4</c> and newer. If you have
an older version of glibc, you should update it now.
</note>

<p>
You can verify that your selected locales are available by running <c>locale
-a</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Keyboard layout for the console</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The keyboard layout used by the console is set in
<path>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</path> by the <c>keymap</c> variable.
Valid values can be found in
<path>/usr/share/keymaps/<c>{arch}</c>/</path>.
<path>i386</path> has further subdivisions into layout
(<path>qwerty/</path>, <path>azerty/</path>, etc.).  Some
languages have multiple options, so you may wish to experiment
to decide which one fits your needs best.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the console keymap">
keymap="de"
keymap="de-latin1"
keymap="de-latin1-nodeadkeys"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Keyboard layout for the X server</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The keyboard layout to be used by the X server is specified
in <path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path> by the <c>XkbLayout</c>
option.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the X keymap">
Section "InputClass"
	Identifier "keyboard-all"
	Driver "evdev"
	Option "XkbLayout" "de"
	#Option "XkbModel" "pc105"
	MatchIsKeyboard "on"
EndSection
</pre>

<p>
If you have an international keyboard layout, you should set the option
<c>XkbModel</c> to <c>pc102</c> or <c>pc105</c>, as this will allow mapping of the
additional keys specific to your keyboard.
</p>

<p>
Deadkeys allow you to press keys that will not show immediately but will be
combined with another letter to produce a single character such as é,è,á,à,
etc. Setting <c>XkbVariant</c> to <c>nodeadkeys</c> allows input these special
characters into X terminals.
</p>

<p>
If you would like to switch between more than one keyboard layout (for example
English and Russian), all you have to do is add a few lines to
<path>xorg.conf</path> that specify the desired layouts and the shortcut
command.
</p>

<pre caption="Switching between two keyboard layouts">
Section "InputClass"
	Identifier "keyboard-all"
	Driver "evdev"
	Option "XkbLayout"    "us,ru"
	Option "XkbOptions"   "grp:alt_shift_toggle,grp_led:scroll"
	MatchIsKeyboard "on"
EndSection
</pre>

<p>
Here, <c>XkbOptions</c> allows you to toggle between keyboard layouts by simply
pressing <c>Alt-Shift</c>. This will also toggle the Scroll Lock light on or
off, thanks to the <c>grp_led:scroll</c> option. This is a handy visual
indicator of which keyboard layout you are using at the moment.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>KDE</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
For KDE you have to install the <c>kde-base/kde-l10n</c> and
<c>app-office/calligra-l10n</c> packages. These respect the <uri
link="#variables">LINGUAS variable</uri> described earlier.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The Euro Symbol for the Console</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
In order to get your console to display the Euro symbol, you will need to set
<c>consolefont</c> in <path>/etc/conf.d/consolefont</path> to a file found in
<path>/usr/share/consolefonts/</path> (without the <c>.psfu.gz</c>).
<c>lat9w-16</c> has the Euro symbol.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the console font">
consolefont="lat9w-16"
</pre>

<p>
You should verify that <c>consolefont</c> is in the boot runlevel:
</p>

<pre caption="Verify the proper runlevel">
# <i>rc-update -v show | grep consolefont</i>
</pre>

<p>
If no runlevel is displayed for <c>consolefont</c>, then add it to the proper level:
</p>

<pre caption="Add consolefont to boot">
# <i>rc-update add consolefont boot</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The Euro Symbol in X</title>
<section>
<title>Most Applications</title>
<body>

<p>
Getting the Euro symbol to work properly in X is a little bit tougher.  The
first thing you should do is change the <c>fixed</c> and <c>variable</c>
definitions in <path>/usr/share/fonts/misc/fonts.alias</path> to end in
<c>iso8859-15</c> instead of <c>iso8859-1</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting default X fonts">
fixed        -misc-fixed-medium-r-semicondensed--13-120-75-75-c-60-iso8859-15
variable     -*-helvetica-bold-r-normal-*-*-120-*-*-*-*-iso8859-15
</pre>

<p>
Some applications use their own font, and you will have to tell them separately
to use a font with the Euro symbol.  You can do this at a user-specific level in
<path>.Xdefaults</path> (you can copy this file to <path>/etc/skel/</path> for
use by new users), or at a global level for any application with a resource file
in <path>/usr/share/X11/app-defaults/</path> (like xterm).  In these files you
generally have to change an existing line, rather than adding a new one.  To
change our xterm font, for instance:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting fonts for xterm">
<comment>(in your home directory)</comment>
$ <i>echo 'XTerm*font: fixed' >> .Xresources </i>
$ <i>xrdb -merge .Xresources</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Euro symbol in (X)Emacs</title>
<body>

<p>
To use the Euro symbol in (X)Emacs, add the following to
<path>.Xdefaults</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="setting the font for emacs">
Emacs.default.attributeFont: -*-courier-medium-r-*-*-*-120-*-*-*-*-iso8859-15
</pre>

<p>
For XEmacs (not plain Emacs), you have to do a little
more.  In <path>/home/user/.xemacs/init.el</path>, add:
</p>

<pre caption="setting the font for xemacs">
(define-key global-map '(EuroSign) '[€])
</pre>

<note>
The symbol in the []s is the Euro symbol.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>OpenOffice.Org</title>
<body>

<p>
The current stable <c>app-office/openoffice</c> and
<c>app-office/openoffice-bin</c> ebuilds support the <uri
link="#variables">LINGUAS variable</uri> for selecting installed GUI language
packs. To see the status of GUI translation, hyphenation, spell checking and
other localisations on your language, please refer to <uri
link="http://l10n.openoffice.org/languages.html">OpenOffice.Org localisation
web site</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
