<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/lxde-howto.xml,v 1.3 2013/07/27 21:06:37 swift Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>The LXDE Configuration HOWTO</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="nathanzachary"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="yngwin"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide introduces the user to LXDE, explains its components, and leads the
user through the installation.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1</version>
<!-- 2009-11-30 -->
<date>2013-07-27</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>What is LXDE?</title>
<body>

<p>
After installing your base Gentoo system, and <uri
link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Xorg/Configuration">the X Server</uri>, you have to make many
choices regarding your graphical environment, if you want one at all. There
are many options available to you, ranging from minimalistic window managers
like <uri link="/doc/en/openbox.xml">Openbox</uri>, to full-featured
desktop environments like <uri link="/proj/en/desktop/kde/kde-config.xml">
KDE</uri>, and <uri link="/doc/en/gnome-config.xml">GNOME</uri>.
</p>

<p>
You may find yourself saying "well, I like the idea of having a lightweight
graphical environment, but I don't want to install and configure every
component individually like with Openbox." For quite some time, such users
installed <uri link="/doc/en/xfce-config.xml">Xfce</uri>. While it provides
a nice full-featured environment without the extensive resource usage of KDE or
GNOME, it could still become a bit on the heavy side. Now, you have another
choice: the <uri link="http://www.lxde.org">Lightweight X11 Desktop
Environment</uri>, or <uri link="http://www.lxde.org">LXDE</uri> for short.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Components of LXDE</title>
<body>

<p>
LXDE, being a desktop environment, is comprised of several components. Each
program offers a certain functionality, and together they form the complete
desktop environment. Currently, there are eleven core components, and several
other programs necessary to make a complete LXDE installation. These programs
are the ones pulled in by the <uri
link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxde-meta">LXDE meta</uri>
package, discussed in the installation section.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Core Components</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxappearance">LXappearance</uri>
    is a GTK theme and icon configurator that allows you to customise the look
    of LXDE
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxde-common">LXDE-common</uri>
    is a collection of default configuration files and the main set of icons
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxmenu-data">LXmenu-data</uri>
    is the application menu manager
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxinput">LXinput</uri> is
    a keyboard and mouse configurator
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxpanel">LXpanel</uri> is
    the panel that includes the application menu, system tray, and clock
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxrandr">LXrandr</uri> is
    a graphical interface to X Resize and Rotate, allowing for display
    manipulation
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxsession">LXsession</uri>
    is a session manager, providing options to shutdown, reboot, and suspend the
    system
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxsession-edit">
    LXsession-edit</uri> allows you to enable/disable applications at startup
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxshortcut">LXshortcut</uri>
    is an easy way to edit application shortcuts, especially for desktop icons
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxtask">LXtask</uri>
    is the task manager used to view/edit running services and programs
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/lxde-base/lxterminal">LXterminal</uri>
    is the vte-based tabbed terminal emulator
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Other Applications used by LXDE</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/x11-wm/openbox">OpenBox</uri>
    is the window manager, responsible for drawing the containers for programs
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/x11-misc/pcmanfm">PCManFM</uri> is
    the incredibly fast, tabbed file manager
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/x11-misc/obconf">ObConf</uri> is
    the configurator for OpenBox, allowing you to change window decorations
    and more
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/media-gfx/gpicview">GPicView
    </uri> is the default image viewer
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Installation</title>
<section>
<title>Initial installation</title>
<body>

<p>
After you have emerged and configured <uri
link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Xorg/Configuration">xorg-server</uri>, you are ready to install LXDE.
While you may install each component individually, the more efficient and
preferred method is to emerge the meta package set:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing LXDE">
# <i>emerge -av lxde-meta</i>
</pre>

<p>
If everything looks to your liking (meaning the current set of USE flags, 
etc.), then say "yes" when asked if you want to emerge the packages.  
Just like with other desktop environments, you will need to tell the
X Server to load LXDE automatically, by adding it to your
<path>~/.xinitrc</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding LXDE to your .xinitrc">
$ <i>echo "exec startlxde" >> ~/.xinitrc</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will automatically start your LXDE session when you type <c>startx</c>
at the console.
</p>

<note>
If you use a login manager like SLiM, XDM, GDM, or KDM, you do not need to
edit your <path>~/.xinitrc</path>. LXDE will simply show up as a choice in
your login manager's screen.
</note>

<impo>
As each user has his or her own <path>.xinitrc</path>, you need to make sure to
issue that command as <e>your user</e>, not as root.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuration</title>
<section>
<title>GTK icon warning</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that the X server knows to start LXDE on command, type in <c>startx</c> to
fire up LXDE. The first thing you may notice is that you get a warning about an
improper GTK icon set. To fix this minor hangup, you simply need to change the
icon theme. To do so, click on the LXDE application menu (in the lower left-hand
corner of the panel), and go to Preferences --> Appearance.  In the LXappearance
menu, click on the "Icon" tab, and choose nuoveXT.2.2.  Hit "Apply," and then
"Close." The next time you login to LXDE, the error message will not appear.
However, you are not limited to using the nuoveXT.2.2 icon theme. You may
install any other icon theme through LXappearance, and when it is selected, the
GTK icon warning will no longer appear when starting PCManFM.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Right-click menu</title>
<body>

<p>
In LXDE, every appearance option is not handled through LXappearance as one
might believe. Rather, there are some common options that are handled through
a right-click menu on the desktop. At the bottom of that menu is the
"Desktop Settings" menu. In here, you can find icon sizes, single-click and
double-click behavior, maximum thumbnail size, and desktop wallpaper
settings. It may behoove you to look through the these tabs for additional
appearance settings.
</p>

<note>
These "Desktop Settings" can also be found by opening up the file manager
(PCManFM), and going to Edit --> Preferences.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Further documentation</title>
<section>
<title>External resources</title>
<body>

<p>
Though this guide will help you get LXDE installed, the documentation does not
stop here. There are many resources available to you regarding the various
facets of the Lightweight X11 Desktop Environment. Some such resources are
listed below:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    On the <uri link="http://www.lxde.org">Official LXDE website</uri> you
    will find information regarding developmental progress, a community
    of support, and recommend system specifications for running LXDE
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="http://wiki.lxde.org/en/Main_Page">LXDE wiki</uri> contains
    instructions for customising your LXDE installation, including
    keyboard layouts, autostarting applications, changing the default window
    manager, and much more
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
