<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/mailfilter-guide.xml,v 1.29 2013/07/23 14:24:02 swift Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo mailfiltering gateway guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="jaervosz@gentoo.org">Sune Kloppenborg Jeppesen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="gentoo@hilli.dk">Jens Hilligsøe</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Joshua Saddler</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide is step-by-step guide for installing spam fighting technologies for
Postfix. Among them Amavisd-new using Spamassassin and ClamAV, greylisting and
SPF.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>7</version>
<date>2013-07-23</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This guide describe step by step how to install a spam and virus filtering mail
gateway. It is quite simple to adopt this to a single server solution.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The big picture</title>
<body>

<p>
This document describe how to setup a spam filtering mail gateway with
multiple domains. This server is meant to run in front of the mail
servers actually keeping the mail accounts i.e. Microsoft Exchange or
Lotus Notes.
</p>

<p>
In this setup applications with good security records and readable
configuration files have been chosen. The email MTA is postfix which
has a good security record and is fairly easy to setup right.
Postfix will listen normally on port 25 for incoming mail. Upon reception it
will forward it to Amavisd-new on port 10024. Amavisd-new will then filter
the mail through different filters before passing the mail back to Postfix
on port 10025 which in turn will forward the mail to the next mail server.
</p>

<p>
Amavisd-new is a content filtering framework utilizing helper applications for
virus filtering and spam filtering. In this setup we will be using two helper
applications one ClamAV for filtering virus mails and Spamassassin for filtering
spam. Spamassassin itself can function as yet another layer of content filtering
framework and utilize the helper applications Vipul's Razor2 and DCC.
</p>

<p>
Unlike many other spam fighting technologies like RBLs and others Spamassassin
does not simply accept or reject a given email based on one single test. It uses
a lot of internal tests and external helper applications to calculate a spam
score for every mail passed through. This score is based on the following tests:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Bayesian filtering</li>
  <li>Static rules based on regular expressions</li>
  <li>Distributed and collaborative networks:
  <ul>
    <li>RBLs</li>
    <li>Razor2</li>
    <li>Pyzor</li>
    <li>DCC</li>
  </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
The first part (chapters 1 to 4) of the guide will describe the basic setup
of a mailfiltering gateway. The next chapters can be implemented individually
with no dependence between each chapter. These chapters describe how to:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    setup special IMAP folders for learning of the Bayesian
    filter and for delivery of false positives
  </li>
<!--
  <li>setup log analyzers to create daily reports</li>
-->
  <li>setup greylisting with Postfix</li>
  <li>setup Amavisd-new to use a MySQL backend for user preferences</li>
  <li>setup Spamassassin to use a MySQL backend for AWL and Bayes data</li>
</ul>

<note>
The IMAP folders will be using the maildir format. Having each mail in a
separate file makes handling much simpler. If you're using mbox I propose to
give maildir a try. If you're not already using maildir emerge the necessary
tools with <c>emerge courier-imap</c>.
</note>

<p>
A planned fifth part will contain various tips regarding performance and things
you may want to know (running chrooted, postfix restrictions, etc.).
</p>

<note>
Delegating responsibility to third parties is not without risks. You have to
know and trust these third parties. In this setup only the decision to
quarantine virus mails are based on a single third party. Using Spamassassin's
scoring system the decision to stop spam mails are not made by a single
authority except perhaps Spamassassins own static rules.
</note>

<warn>
When rejecting spam mails at the MTA level you have to be very careful when
selecting the RBL's you want to use, i.e. SpamCop is a bad RBL to use at the MTA
level because you will experience false positives because sometimes their
listing is just too aggressive. Further info at <uri
link="http://www.geekcomix.com/cgi-bin/classnotes/wiki.pl?UNIX03/Realtime_Blackhole_Lists_Are_Bad">Realtime
Blackhole Lists Are Bad</uri> and <uri
link="http://theory.whirlycott.com/~phil/antispam/rbl-bad/rbl-bad.html">The Spam
Problem: Moving Beyond RBLs</uri>
</warn>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Preparations</title>
<body>

<p>
Before you start make sure that you have a working Postfix installation where
you can send and receive mails also you need a backend mailserver. If you're not
experienced with setting up Postfix it might quickly become too complicated if
all should be set up at once. If you need help you can find it in the excellent
<uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Complete_Virtual_Mail_Server">Complete
Virtual Mail Server</uri> in the Gentoo Wiki.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Installing the programs needed</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
We start out by installing the most important programs: Amavisd-new,
Spamassassin and ClamAV.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing Amavis, Spamassassin and Clamav">
# <i>emerge amavisd-new spamassassin clamav </i>
</pre>

<note>
As previously mentioned you should already have a working <c>postfix</c>
instance running on the box. Basically this shouldn't be much more than
<c>emerge postfix</c> <e>and</e> have a basic understanding of how Postfix is
working.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Setting up DNS</title>
<body>

<note>
If you're not setting up a gateway server but have the mailboxes on
the same server you only have to create the MX-Record.
</note>

<p>
While the programs are emerging fire up another shell and create the needed DNS
records.
</p>

<p>
Start out by creating a <c>MX</c> record for the mail gateway and an <c>A</c>
record for the next destination.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting up DNS">
<comment>(Create a MX record for the gateway server)</comment>
                MX      10      mailgateway.mydomain.tld.
<comment>(Create an A record for the gateway server)</comment>
mailgateway     A       mgw.ip.add.here
<comment>(Create an A record for the next hop mail server)</comment>
mail            A       ms.ip.add.here
</pre>

<note>
Some ADSL providers might block port 25 and force you to relay mail through one
of their servers. Typically you have to create a secondary MX-Record
like <c>MX      20      backup-mx.some-isp.tld</c>
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Opening the firewall</title>
<body>

<p>
In addition to allowing normal mail traffic you have to allow a
few services through your firewall to allow the network checks to
communicate with the servers.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Application</th><th>Protocol</th><th>Port</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>DCC</ti><ti>UDP</ti><ti>6277</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Razor(outgoing ping)</ti><ti>TCP</ti><ti>7</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Razor</ti><ti>TCP</ti><ti>2703</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Razor uses pings to discover what servers are closest to it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring Postfix</title>
<body>

<p>
First we have to tell <c>postfix</c> to listen on port 10025 and we remove most
of the restrictions as they have already been applied by the <c>postfix</c>
instance listening on port 25. Also we ensure that it will only listen for local
connections on port 10025.  To accomplish this we have to add the following at
the end of <path>/etc/postfix/master.cf</path>
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the master.cf file">
smtp-amavis     unix -        -       n     -       2  smtp
  -o smtp_data_done_timeout=1200
  -o smtp_send_xforward_command=yes
<comment>#Equivalently when using lmtp:
#lmtp-amavis    unix -        -       n     -       2  lmtp
#   -o lmtp_data_done_timeout=1200
#   -o lmtp_send_xforward_command=yes</comment>

127.0.0.1:10025 inet n        -       n     -       -  smtpd
  -o content_filter=
  -o local_recipient_maps=
  -o relay_recipient_maps=
  -o smtpd_restriction_classes=
  -o smtpd_client_restrictions=
  -o smtpd_helo_restrictions=
  -o smtpd_sender_restrictions=
  -o smtpd_recipient_restrictions=permit_mynetworks,reject
  -o mynetworks=127.0.0.0/8
  -o strict_rfc821_envelopes=yes
  -o smtpd_error_sleep_time=0
  -o smtpd_soft_error_limit=1001
  -o smtpd_hard_error_limit=1000

<comment>#If you want to use proxy filtering instead
#smtp            inet n         -       n      -       8 smtpd
# -o smtpd_proxy_filter=127.0.0.1:10024
# -o smtpd_client_connection_count_limit=4
#If you don't want to scan outgoing mail use this
#10.0.0.2:smtp   inet n         -       n       -      - smtpd
#-o content_filter=</comment>
</pre>

<note>
The <c>smtp-amavis</c> line specifies that a maximum of two of these processes
may run at any time. If you need a greater degree of concurrency tune this
number to fit your needs. Remember that to match the number with
<c>$max_servers</c> in <path>amavisd.conf</path>. Keep in mind that
<c>amavisd-new</c> is quite memory-intensive and raising the amount of
<c>amavisd-new</c> processes too high can easily lead to memory starvation and
heavy swapping, which leads to drastically reduced performance.
</note>

<note>
If you want to reject spam early on in the process you can use the
Before-Queue (proxy) method instead of the filter method. If you uncomment
the three lines you will have to set <c>content_filter=</c> in
<path>main.cf</path>. This is not recommended for high traffic servers
as the number of concurrent connections are limited to the number of
amavisd instances.
</note>

<warn>
The Before-Queue(proxy) method is still not properly tested.
</warn>

<note>
If you, for any reason whatsoever, want to send mail from this box and don't
want it scanned, add another postfix instance by uncommenting the last two
lines and substitute with a proper IP.
</note>

<p>
The file <path>master.cf</path> tells the postfix master program how
to run each individual postfix process. More info with <c>man 8
master</c>.
</p>

<p>
Next we need the main <c>postfix</c> instance listening on port 25 to filter the
mail through <c>amavisd-new</c> listening on port 10024.
</p>

<p>
We also need to set the next hop destination for mail. Tell Postfix to filter
all mail through an external content filter and enable explicit routing to let
Postfix know where to forward the mail to.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying /etc/postfix/main.cf">
biff = no
empty_address_recipient = MAILER-DAEMON
queue_minfree = 120000000

content_filter = smtp-amavis:[127.0.0.1]:10024
<comment>#Equivalently when using lmtp:
#content_filter = lmtp-amavis:[127.0.0.1]:10024

# TRANSPORT MAP
#
# Insert text from sample-transport.cf if you need explicit routing.</comment>
transport_maps = hash:/etc/postfix/transport

relay_domains = $transport_maps
</pre>

<p>
Postfix has a lot of options set in <path>main.cf</path>. For further
explanation of the file please consult <c>man 5 postconf</c> or the
same online <uri link="http://www.postfix.org/postconf.5.html">Postfix
Configuration Parameters</uri>.
</p>

<p>
The format of the <path>transport</path> file is the normal Postfix hash file.
Mail to the domain on the left hand side is forwarded to the destination on the
right hand side.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/postfix/transport">
mydomain.tld                          smtp:mail.mydomain.tld
</pre>

<p>
After we have edited the file we need to run the <c>postmap</c> command. Postfix
does not actually read this file so we have to convert it to the proper format
with <c>postmap /etc/postfix/transport</c>. This creates the file
<path>/etc/postfix/transport.db</path>. There is no need to reload Postfix as it
will automatically pick up the changes.
</p>

<note>
If the next hop mail server is not listening on the standard SMTP port 25 you
can tell postfix to use a given port number, like
<c>smtp:mail.mydomain.tld:25000</c>.
</note>

<p>
If your first attempts to send mail result in messages bouncing, you've likely
made a configuration error somewhere. Try temporarily enabling
<c>soft_bounce</c> while you work out your configuration issues. This prevents
postfix from bouncing mails on delivery errors by treating them as temporary
errors. It keeps mails in the mail queue until <c>soft_bounce</c> is disabled or
removed.
</p>

<pre caption="Enabling soft_bounce">
# <i>postconf -e "soft_bounce = yes"</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/postfix reload</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once you've finished creating a working configuration, be sure to disable
or remove <c>soft_bounce</c> and reload postfix.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring Amavisd-new</title>
<body>

<p>
Amavisd-new is used to handle all the filtering and allows you to easily glue
together severel different technologies. Upon reception of a mail message it
will extract the mail, filter it through some custom filters, handle white and
black listing, filter the mail through various virus scanners and finally it
will filter the mail using SpamAssassin.
</p>

<p>
Amavisd-new itself has a number of extra features:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    it identifies dangerous file attachments and has policies to handle them
  </li>
  <li>
    per-user, per-domain and system-wide policies for:
    <ul>
      <li>whitelists</li>
      <li>blacklists</li>
      <li>spam score thresholds</li>
      <li>virus and spam policies</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Apart from <c>postfix</c> and <c>freshclam</c> we will run all applications as
the user <c>amavis</c>.
</p>

<!--
<pre caption="/etc/passwd">
amavis:x:1010:413:added by portage for amavisd-new:/var/amavis:/bin/bash
</pre>
-->

<!--
<p>
Create the new home directory and set the proper permissions.
</p>

<pre caption="Create the new home directory and set the proper permissions">
# <i>mkdir /var/amavis</i>
# <i>chown amavis:amavis /var/amavis</i>
# <i>chmod 750 /var/amavis</i>
</pre>
-->

<p>
Edit the following lines in <path>/etc/amavisd.conf</path>
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/amavisd.conf">
<comment>(Insert the domains to be scanned)</comment>
$mydomain = 'example.com';
<comment>(Bind only to loopback interface)</comment>
$inet_socket_bind = '127.0.0.1';
<comment>(Forward to Postfix on port 10025)</comment>
$forward_method = 'smtp:127.0.0.1:10025';
$notify_method = $forward_method;
<comment>(Define the account to send virus alert emails)</comment>
$virus_admin = "virusalert\@$mydomain";
<comment>(Always add spam headers)</comment>
$sa_tag_level_deflt  = -100;
<comment>(Add spam detected header aka X-Spam-Status: Yes)</comment>
$sa_tag2_level_deflt = 5;
<comment>(Trigger evasive action at this spam level)</comment>
$sa_kill_level_deflt = $sa_tag2_level_deflt;
<comment>(Do not send delivery status notification to sender.  It does not affect
delivery of spam to recipient. To do that, use the kill_level)</comment>
$sa_dsn_cutoff_level = 10;
<comment>Don't bounce messages left and right, quarantine
instead</comment>
$final_virus_destiny      = D_DISCARD;  # (defaults to D_DISCARD)
$final_banned_destiny     = D_DISCARD;  # (defaults to D_BOUNCE)
$final_spam_destiny       = D_DISCARD;  # (defaults to D_BOUNCE)
</pre>

<note>
With this line <c>$sa_tag2_level_deflt = 5;</c> you set the Spamassassin spam
score to 5. This might be a bit low. As you might have noticed the Amavisd-new
default is <c>6.3</c>. If you don't want to see a single spam mail in your
mail folder choose <c>5</c>, but if you don't want to deal with false positives
choose <c>6.3</c>.
</note>

<p>
Create a quarantine directory for the virus mails as we don't want these
delivered to our users.
</p>

<pre caption="Create a quarantine directory for the virus mails">
# <i>mkdir /var/amavis/virusmails</i>
# <i>chown amavis:amavis /var/amavis/virusmails</i>
# <i>chmod 750 /var/amavis/virusmails</i>
</pre>

<note>
Amavisd-new offers finer policy tuning by using policy banks.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring ClamAV</title>
<body>

<p>
As virus scanner we use ClamAV as it has a fine detection rate comparable with
commercial offerings, it is very fast and it is Open Source Software.  We love
log files, so make <c>clamd</c> log using <c>syslog</c> and turn on
verbose logging. Also do not run <c>clamd</c> as <c>root</c>.  Now edit
<path>/etc/clamd.conf</path>
</p>

<pre caption="Edit /etc/clamd.conf">
<comment>(Verbose logging with syslog)</comment>
LogSyslog
LogVerbose
LogFacility LOG_MAIL
<comment>(Change pid file location)</comment>
PidFile /var/run/amavis/clamd.pid
<comment>(Set the clamav socket)</comment>
LocalSocket /var/amavis/clamd
<comment>(Close the connection when this limit is exceeded)</comment>
StreamMaxLength 10M
<comment>(Don't run clamd as root)</comment>
User amavis
<comment>(Newer versions require you to uncomment this)</comment>
ScanMail
ScanArchive
</pre>

<note>
Also remember to remove the Example directive to make ClamAV work
</note>

<p>
ClamAV comes with the <c>freshclam</c> deamon dedicated to periodical checks
of virus signature updates.  Instead of updating virus signatures twice a day
we will make <c>freshclam</c> update virus signatures every two hours.
</p>

<pre caption="Edit /etc/freshclam.conf">
<comment>(Syslog logging)</comment>
LogSyslog
<comment>(Verbose logging)</comment>
LogVerbose
<comment>(Explicitly drop root privileges)</comment>
DatabaseOwner clamav
<comment>(Check for updates every two hours. That is the official recommendation)</comment>
Checks 12
<comment>(Use the mirror closest to you. Replace XY with your country code</comment>
DatabaseMirror db.XY.clamav.net
</pre>

<p>
Start <c>clamd</c> with <c>freshclam</c> using the init scripts by modifying
<path>/etc/conf.d/clamd</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying /etc/conf.d/clamd">
START_CLAMD=yes
FRESHCLAM_OPTS="-d"
</pre>

<p>
At last modify <path>amavisd.conf</path> with the new location of the
socket.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying /etc/amavisd.conf">
<comment>(Uncomment the clamav scanner and modify socket location)</comment>
['ClamAV-clamd',
\&amp;ask_daemon, ["CONTSCAN {}\n", "/var/amavis/clamd"],
  qr/\bOK$/, qr/\bFOUND$/,
  qr/^.*?: (?!Infected Archive)(.*) FOUND$/ ],
</pre>

<warn>
Do NOT modify the <c>$unix_socketname</c> unless you know what you're doing.
</warn>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring Vipul's Razor</title>
<body>

<p>
Razor2 is a collaborative and distributed spam checksum network. Install it
with <c>emerge razor</c> and create the needed configuration files. Do this
as user <c>amavis</c> by running <c>su - amavis</c> followed <c>razor-admin
-create</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the required configuration files">
# <i>emerge razor</i>

<comment>(Temporarily set amavis' shell to bash)</comment>
# <i>usermod -s /bin/bash amavis</i>
# <i>su - amavis</i>
$ <i>razor-admin -create</i>
$ <i>exit</i>

<comment>(Reset the shell to /bin/false)</comment>
# <i>usermod -s /bin/false amavis</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring Distributed Checksum Clearinghouse (dcc)</title>
<body>

<p>
Like Razor2, dcc is a collaborative and distributed spam checksum network. Its
philosopy is to count the number of recipients of a given mail identifying each
mail with a fuzzy checksum.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing DCC">
# <i>emerge dcc</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring Spamassassin</title>
<body>

<p>
Amavis is using the Spamassassin Perl libraries directly so there is no need to
start the service. Also this creates some confusion about the configuration as
some Spamassassin settings are configured in
<path>/etc/mail/spamassassin/local.cf</path> and overridden by options in
<path>/etc/amavisd.conf</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Create /etc/mail/spamassassin/local.cf">
<comment># Enable the Bayes system</comment>
use_bayes               1

<comment># Enable all network checks</comment>
skip_rbl_checks         0

<comment># Mail using languages used in these country codes will not be marked
# as being possibly spam in a foreign language.
# - danish english norwegian swedish</comment>
ok_languages            da en no sv

<comment># Mail using locales used in these country codes will not be marked
# as being possibly spam in a foreign language.</comment>
ok_locales              en

<comment># Use a sensible bayes path</comment>
bayes_path              /var/amavis/.spamassassin/bayes
</pre>

<note>
With Spamassassin version 3.1 you have to enable DCC, Razor2 by uncommenting
the corresponding lines in <path>v310.pre</path>.
</note>

<note>
You can find inspiration for your <path>local.cf</path> file by trying the <uri
link="http://www.yrex.com/spam/spamconfig.php">SpamAssassin Configuration
Generator</uri>.
</note>

<note>
You might also want to switch the <c>ok_languages</c> and <c>ok_locales</c>.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Every good rule has good exceptions as well</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Once mail really starts passing through this mail gateway you will probably
discover that the above setup is not perfect. Maybe some of your customers like
to receive mails that others wouldn't. You can whitelist/blacklist
envelope senders quite easily. Uncomment the following line in
<path>amavisd.conf</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying amavisd.conf to do sitewide scoring">
read_hash("/var/amavis/sender_scores_sitewide"),
</pre>

<p>
In the <path>sender_scores_sitewide</path> file you put complete email
addresses or just the domian parts and then note a positive/negative score
to add to the spam score.
</p>

<pre caption="whitelist_sender example">
<comment>(Whitelist all emails from the specific email address)</comment>
postmaster@example.net                -3.0
<comment>(Whitelist all emails from the example.net excluding subdomains)</comment>
.example.net                          1.0
</pre>

<note>
See <path>/etc/amavisd.conf</path> for more examples.
</note>

<note>
Placing these addresses outside <path>amavisd.conf</path> is a cleaner and safer
solution.
</note>

<note>
Alternatively it can be done in Spamassassin's configuration file
<path>/etc/mail/spamassassin/local.cf</path> but I think it is cleaner
to do it in <path>/etc/amavisd.conf</path>.
</note>

<note>
In a later chapter I will show how to implement per-user policies using
MySQL.
</note>

<p>
While waiting for a better method you can add the following to
<path>amavisd.conf</path> to bypass spam checks for <c>postmaster</c> and
<c>abuse</c> mailboxes.
</p>

<pre caption="By pass spam filters for all postmaster and abuse mails">
map { $bypass_spam_checks{lc($_)}=1 } (qw(
        postmaster@
        abuse@
));
</pre>

<impo>
While we are at it we should <e>never</e> automatically discard mails to the
<c>postmaster</c> or the <c>abuse</c> accounts. See <uri
link="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2142.txt">RFC 2142 MAILBOX NAMES FOR COMMON
SERVICES, ROLES AND FUNCTIONS</uri>. Otherwise your domains might end up listed
in some of the evil lists over at <uri
link="http://www.rfc-ignorant.org/">rfc-ignorant.org</uri>.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Adding more rules</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
If you want to use more rules provided by the SARE Ninjas over at the
<uri link="http://www.rulesemporium.com/">SpamAssassin Rules
Emporium</uri> you can easily add and update them using
the <c>sa-update</c> mechanism included in Spamassassin.
</p>

<p>
A brief guide to using SARE rulesets with <c>sa-update</c> can be found <uri
link="http://daryl.dostech.ca/sa-update/sare/sare-sa-update-howto.txt">here</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Testing and finishing up</title>
<section>
<title>Testing the setup</title>
<body>

<p>
Now before you start <c>freshclam</c> you can manually verify that it works.
</p>

<pre caption="Testing freshclam">
# <i>freshclam</i>
ClamAV update process started at Sun May  2 09:13:41 2004
Reading CVD header (main.cvd): OK
Downloading main.cvd [*]
main.cvd updated (version: 22, sigs: 20229, f-level: 1, builder: tkojm)
Reading CVD header (daily.cvd): OK
Downloading daily.cvd [*]
daily.cvd updated (version: 298, sigs: 1141, f-level: 2, builder: diego)
Database updated (21370 signatures) from database.clamav.net (193.1.219.100).
</pre>

<p>
Now you have updated virus definitions and you know that
<path>freshclam.conf</path> is working properly.
</p>

<p>
Test freshclam and amavisd from the cli and amavisd testmails.
Start <c>clamd</c> and <c>amavis</c> with the following commands:
</p>

<pre caption="Start amavisd and clamd and reload postfix configuration">
# <i>/etc/init.d/clamd start</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/amavisd start</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/postfix reload</i>
</pre>

<p>
If everything went well <c>postfix</c> should now be listening for mails on port
25 and for reinjected mails on port 10024. To verify this check your log file.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking log files">
# <i>tail -f /var/log/mail.log</i>
</pre>

<note>
Depending on your log settings the correct path might be
<path>/var/log/messages</path>.
</note>

<p>
Now if no strange messages appear in the log file it is time for a new
test.
</p>

<p>
Use <c>netcat</c> to manually connect to <c>amavisd</c> on port 10024
and <c>postfix</c> on port 10025.
</p>

<note>
Netcat can be used as an advanced replacement for <c>telnet</c>. Install it with
<c>emerge netcat</c>.
</note>

<note>
For some unknown reason you can not complete a manual mail injection to
<c>amavisd</c> with netcat. Use <c>telnet</c> instead.
</note>

<pre caption="Manually checking that amavisd and postfix are listning to the new ports">
# <i>nc localhost 10024</i>
<comment>(Amavis working)</comment>
220 [127.0.0.1] ESMTP amavisd-new service ready
<i>nc localhost 10025</i>
<comment>(Postfix reinject working)</comment>
220 example.com ESMTP Postfix
</pre>

<note>
If you want to see the complete output from amavisd-new start
<c>amavisd debug-sa</c> as the <c>amavis</c> user and send a mail.
For this to work you might have to change the default shell in
<path>/etc/passwd</path>.
</note>

<p>
Add <c>amavisd</c> and <c>clamd</c> to the <c>default</c> runlevel.
</p>

<pre caption="Add amavisd and clamd to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add clamd default</i>
# <i>rc-update add amavisd default</i>
</pre>

<note>
We do not add <c>spamd</c> to the default runlevel as <c>amavisd</c>
uses the Spamassassin Perl libraries directly.
</note>

<note>
You might notice <c>Net::Server: Couldn't POSIX::setuid to ...
[]</c> lines in your log. According to
<uri link="http://www.ijs.si/software/amavisd/README.chroot">amavis chroot
README</uri>, if the process UID remains 0 (<c>root</c>), the program will
terminate, otherwise you can consider the message just as informative.
This is because <c>POSIX::setuid()</c> returns a string <c>0 but
true</c>.
</note>

<impo>
If you enabled login for amavis remember to set back the login shell in
<path>/etc/passwd</path> to <c>/bin/false</c>.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Autolearning and sidelining emails</title>
<section>
<title>Creating the spamtrap user</title>
<body>

<p>
Create the spamtrap account and directories.
</p>

<pre caption="Create spamtrap account">
# <i>useradd -m spamtrap</i>
# <i>maildirmake /home/spamtrap/.maildir</i>
# <i>chown -R spamtrap:spamtrap /home/spamtrap/.maildir</i>
<comment>(Give the spamtrap user a sensible password)</comment>
# <i>passwd spamtrap</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you manually want to check some of the mails to ensure that you have no false
positives you can use the following <c>procmail</c> recipe to sideline spam
found into different mail folders.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Creating .procmailrc</title>
<body>

<pre caption="Creating /home/spamtrap/.procmailrc">
<comment>#Set some default variables</comment>
MAILDIR=$HOME/.maildir

SPAM_FOLDER=$MAILDIR/.spam-found/

LIKELY_SPAM_FOLDER=$MAILDIR/.likely-spam-found/

<comment>#Sort mails with a spamscore of 7+ to the spamfolder</comment>
:0:
* ^X-Spam-Status: Yes
* ^X-Spam-Level: \*\*\*\*\*\*\*
$SPAM_FOLDER

<comment>#Sort mail with a spamscore between 5-7 to the likely spam folder</comment>
:0:
* ^X-Spam-Status: Yes
$LIKELY_SPAM_FOLDER

<comment>#Sort all other mails to the inbox</comment>
:0
*
./
</pre>

<warn>
If your mail server is going to receive a lot of mail you should NOT
use the likely-spam recipe. Instead set <c>$sa_tag2_level_deflt</c>
high enough to avoid false positives and filter it directly to
<c>$SPAM_FOLDER</c>.
</warn>

<note>
If you haven't already installed <c>procmail</c> do it with <c>emerge
procmail</c>.
</note>

<p>
Now make sure that Postfix uses <c>procmail</c> to deliver mail.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying /etc/postfix/main.cf">
mailbox_command = /usr/bin/procmail -a "DOMAIN"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Create mailfolders</title>
<body>

<p>
Now we will create shared folders for ham and spam.
</p>

<pre caption="Create the necessary mailfolders">
# <i>maildirmake /var/amavis/.maildir</i>
# <i>maildirmake -S /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes</i>
# <i>maildirmake -s write -f spam /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes</i>
# <i>maildirmake -s write -f ham /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes</i>
# <i>maildirmake -s write -f redeliver /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes</i>
</pre>

<p>
Amavisd-new needs to be able to read these files as well as all mailusers.
Therefore we add all the relevant users to the mailuser group along with amavis.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the proper permissions">
# <i>groupadd mailusers</i>
# <i>usermod -G mailusers spamtrap</i>
# <i>chown -R amavis:mailusers /var/amavis/.maildir/</i>
# <i>chown amavis:mailusers /var/amavis/</i>
# <i>chmod -R 1733 /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes/</i>
# <i>chmod g+rx /var/amavis/.maildir/</i>
# <i>chmod g+rx /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes/</i>
</pre>

<warn>
This grants members of the <c>mailusers</c> groups access to <c>amavis</c>
mail.
</warn>

<p>
This makes the spam and ham folders writable but not readable. This way
users can safely submit their ham without anyone else being able to read it.
</p>

<p>
Then run the following command as the <c>spamtrap</c> user:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding the shared folders to the users mailfolder">
$ <i>maildirmake --add Bayes=/var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes $HOME/.maildir</i>
</pre>

<note>
We have to give the group read permissions on the <path>Bayes</path>
folder in order for the mail client to be able to see the subdirectories used by
IMAP.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adding cron jobs</title>
<body>

<p>
Now run <c>crontab -u amavis -e</c> to edit the amavis crontab to
enable automatic learning of the Bayes filter every hour.
</p>

<pre caption="amavis crontab">
<comment>#Auto learn</comment>
0 * * * *          /usr/bin/sa-learn --spam /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes/.spam/{cur,new} \
                    > /dev/null 2>&amp;1
0 * * * *          /usr/bin/sa-learn --ham /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes/.ham/{cur,new} > \
                   /dev/null 2>&amp;1
</pre>

<note>
<c>amavis</c> has to be a member of the <c>cron</c> group to run
crons.
</note>

<note>
It seems like the shared maildir folders will make <c>sa-learn</c> examine all
messages twice. This should not be a problem. The output will also show that the
maximum of messages learned from is half or less than the messages examined.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Modifying amavisd.conf</title>
<body>

<p>
Now modify amavis to redirect spam emails to the <c>spamtrap</c> account and
keep spamheaders.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying /etc/amavisd.conf">
<comment>(Define the account to send virus spam emails)</comment>
$spam_quarantine_to = "spamtrap\@$myhostname";
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Cleaning up</title>
<body>

<p>
We don't want to keep mail forever so we use <c>tmpwatch</c> to clean up
regularily. Emerge it with <c>emerge tmpwatch</c>.  Only <c>root</c> is able to
run <c>tmpwatch</c> so we have to edit the <c>root</c> crontab.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying root crontab">
<comment># Clean up
# Keep virusmails for a week (24*7 hours)</comment>
15 0 * * *      /usr/sbin/tmpwatch -c -f -d --quiet 168 /var/amavis/virusmails/
<comment># Delete spam and ham learned after a week</comment>
15 0 * * *      /usr/sbin/tmpwatch -c -f -d --quiet 168 /var/amavis/.maildir/Bayes/
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!--
<chapter>
<title>Log analyzers</title>
<section>
<title>General Postfix statistics</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that we have set up our gateway mail server it would be nice to be
able to monitor it. To this end we install two small Perl scripts that
will mail you daily summaries about mail and spam statistics. First
download and install <c>pflogsumm</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Download and installing pflogsumm">
# <i>wget http://jimsun.linxnet.com/downloads/pflogsumm-1.1.0.tar.gz</i>
# <i>tar xzf pflogsumm-1.1.0.tar.gz</i>
# <i>cp pflogsumm-1.1.0/pflogsumm.pl /usr/local/bin/</i>
</pre>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Postfix spam statistics</title>
<body>

<p>
Next we download and install the script that generates daily
statistics about spam caught:
</p>

<pre caption="Downloading and installing spamreport">
# <i>wget http://www.flakshack.com/anti-spam/nosack-spamreport.pl</i>
# <i>mv nosack-spamreport.pl /usr/local/bin/</i>
# <i>chmod +x /usr/local/bin/nosack-spamreport.pl</i>
</pre>
<p>
We want a daily mail from each of the scripts so we add two entries to
the <c>root</c> crontab:
</p>
<pre caption="Adding report scripts to root crontab">
15 0 * * *      /usr/local/bin/pflogsumm.pl -d yesterday \
                /var/log/mail.log 2&gt;&amp;1 | /bin/mailx \
                -s "`uname -n` daily mail stats" postmaster
10 0 * * *      /usr/local/bin/nosack-spamreport.pl \
                /var/log/mail.log 2&gt;&amp;1 | /bin/mailx \
                -s "`uname -n` daily spam stats" postmaster
</pre>

<note>
You might need to do an <c>emerge Date-Calc</c> and <c>emerge
mailx</c>. Alternatively you can use <c>mail</c> installed with
<c>emerge mailutils</c>
</note>

<note>
If you rotate your logs on a weekly basis (like I do) you might want
to ensure that the scripts are run just before the logs are rotated.
</note>

<note>
Currently investigating another amavis log analyzer
<uri link="http://homepages.hs-bremen.de/~renegat/amavislogsumm">amavislogsumm</uri>
</note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
-->

<chapter>
<title>Greylisting</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Greylisting is one of the newer weapons in the spam fighting
arsenal. As the name implies it is much like whitelisting and
blacklisting. Each time an unknown mailserver tries to deliver
mail the mail is rejected with a <e>try again later</e> message.
This means that mail gets delayed but also that stupid spam bots
that do not implement the RFC protocol will drop the attempt to
deliver the spam and never retry.  With time spam bots will probably
adjust, however it will give other technologies more time to identify
the spam.
</p>

<note>
If your ISP blocks incoming traffic on port 25 and relays all mail to you
through their own mail server greylisting will not work.
</note>

<p>
Postfix 2.1 come with a simple Perl greylisting policy server that
implements such a scheme. However it suffers from unpredictable
results when the partition holding the greylisting database run
out of space. There exists an improved version that do not suffer
this problem. First I will show how to install the builtin
greylisting support that come with Postfix and then I will show
how to configure the more robust replacement.
</p>

<note>
There are other greylisting policy servers for Postfix around (such as <uri
link="http://www.gasmi.net/gld.html">Gld</uri>, which is in Portage, and <uri
link="http://sqlgrey.sourceforge.net/">SQLgrey</uri>). Some of them support
database backends, auto whitelisting and other neat features.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Simple greylisting</title>
<body>

<note>
If you prefer to use the improved greylisting with postgrey you can
safely skip this section.
</note>

<p>
We need the file <path>greylist.pl</path> but unfortunately
the ebuild does not install it as default.
</p>

<pre caption="Getting greylist.pl">
# <i>cp /usr/portage/distfiles/postfix-your-version-here.tar.gz /root/</i>
# <i>tar xzf postfix-your-version-here.tar.gz</i>
# <i>cp postfix-2.1.0/examples/smtpd-policy/greylist.pl /usr/bin/</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now we have the file in place we need to create the directory
to hold the greylisting database:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating directory for the greylisting database">
# <i>mkdir /var/mta</i>
# <i>chown nobody /var/mta</i>
</pre>

<warn>
Do not create the greylisting database directory on a partition that
might run out of space. While postfix can recover from no-space-left
situations for the mail queue and mail box situations, this is not the
case with the greylisting database. If the file becomes corrupted
you may not be able to receive mail at all until you delete the file
by hand.
</warn>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring greylisting</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that we have all this ready all that is left is to add it to the
postfix configuration. First we add the necessary information to the
<path>master.cf</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying master.cf to use greylisting">
policy-greylist  unix  -       n       n       -       -       spawn
   user=nobody argv=/usr/bin/perl /usr/bin/greylist.pl
</pre>

<p>
The postfix spawn daemon normally kills its child processes after 1000
seconds but this is too short for the greylisting process so we have
to increase the timelimit in <path>main.cf</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying main.cf to use greylisting">
policy-greylist_time_limit = 3600
<comment>(Under smtpd_recipient_restrictions add:)</comment>
check_sender_access hash:/etc/postfix/sender_access
<comment>(Later on add:)</comment>
restriction_classes = greylist
greylist = check_policy_service unix:private/policy-greylist
</pre>

<warn>
Be sure to specify <c>check_sender_access</c> AFTER
<c>reject_unauth_destination</c> or else your system could become an
open mail relay.
</warn>

<note>
The greylist database gets polluted quickly with bogus addresses. It
helps if you protect greylist lookups with other restrictions that
reject unknown senders and/or recipients.
</note>

<p>
We don't want to use greylisting for all domains but only for those
frequently abused by spammers. After all it will delay mail delivery.
A list of frequently forged MAIL FROM domains can be found <uri
link="http://www.monkeys.com/anti-spam/filtering/sender-domain-validate.in">online</uri>.
Add the domains you receive a lot of spam from to
<path>/etc/postfix/sender_access</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Format of sender_access">
aol.com     greylist
hotmail.com greylist
bigfoot.com greylist
</pre>

<p>
If you want a more extensive list:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding all domains to sender_access">
# <i>wget http://www.monkeys.com/anti-spam/filtering/sender-domain-validate.in</i>
# <i>cat sender-domain-validate.in | sort | awk {'print $1 "\t\t greylist"'} > /etc/postfix/sender_access</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now we only have to initialize the <path>sender_access</path>
database:
</p>

<pre caption="Initialize sender_access">
# <i>postmap /etc/postfix/sender_access</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now the setup of simple greylisting is complete.
</p>

<warn>
I tried this on one box handling thousands of mails daily and the
results were almost a complete disaster. After four days the box was
bogged down with hundreds of old <c>greylist.pl</c> processes.
</warn>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring improved greylisting with postgrey</title>
<body>

<p>
You can install the enhanced greylisting policy server with a simple
<c>emerge</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing postgrey">
# <i>emerge postgrey</i>
</pre>

<p>
After installing <c>postgrey</c> we have to edit <path>main.cf</path>.
Changes are almost exactly like the built in greylisting.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying main.cf to use greylisting">
<comment>(Under smtpd_recipient_restrictions add:)</comment>
check_sender_access hash:/etc/postfix/sender_access
<comment>(Later on add:)</comment>
smtpd_restriction_classes = greylist
greylist = check_policy_service inet:127.0.0.1:10030
</pre>

<note>
The Postfix SMTPD_POLICY_README only uses <c>restriction_classes</c>
but that does not appear to work.
</note>

<note>
If you want to greylist everything instead add <c>check_policy_service
inet:127.0.0.1:10030</c>.
</note>

<p>
Finally, start the server and add it to the proper runlevel.
</p>

<pre caption="Starting postgrey">
# <i>/etc/init.d/postgrey start</i>
# <i>rc-update add postgrey default</i>
</pre>

<note>
Some people like to get their mail fast and thus greylisting is
worthless. However if you employ a backup mail server you can safely
setup greylisting on that server. My limited experiences tell me that
it can stop up to a third of the spam received.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>SPF (Sender Policy Framework)</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
SPF allows domain owners to state in their DNS records which IP
addressess should be allowed to send mails from their domain. This
will prevent spammers from spoofing the <c>Return-Path</c>.
</p>

<note>
If your ISP blocks incoming traffic on port 25 and relays all mail to you
through their own mail server SPF will not work.
</note>

<p>
First domain owners have to create a special <c>TXT</c> DNS record.
Then an SPF-enabled MTA can read this and if the mail originates from a
server that is not described in the SPF record the mail can be
rejected. An example entry could look like this:
</p>

<pre caption="Example SPF record">
example.com.  IN TXT  "v=spf1 a mx ptr -all"
</pre>

<p>
The <c>-all</c> means to reject all mail by default but allow mail
from the <c>A</c>(<c>a</c>), <c>MX</c>(<c>mx</c>) and
<c>PTR</c>(<c>ptr</c>) DNS records. For more info consult further
resources below.
</p>

<note>
If you relay outgoing mail through your ISP you will have to add:
<c>include:yourisp.com</c>.
</note>

<p>
Spamassassin 3.0 has support for SPF, however it is not enabled by default
and the new policy daemon in Postfix supports SPF so let's install SPF support
for Postfix.
</p>

<note>
If you want to use SPF with Spamassassin instead simply
<c>emerge&nbsp;dev-perl/Mail-SPF-Query</c> and restart Amavisd-new.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Preparations</title>
<body>

<p>
First you have to
install Postfix 2.1 as described above. When you have fetched the
source grab the <path>spf.pl</path> with:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing spf.pl">
# <i>cp postfix-&lt;version&gt;/examples/smtpd-policy/spf.pl /usr/local/bin/</i>
</pre>

<note>
The <path>spf.pl</path> coming with Postfix is slightly buggy so find
and uncomment the following line: <c>push @HANDLERS, "sender_permitted_from";
use Mail::SPF::Query;</c>. Furthermore in about line 199 substitute
<c>comemnt</c> with <c>comment</c>. Alternatively you can download a
<uri link="http://spf.pobox.com/postfix-policyd.txt">development
version</uri>.
</note>

<p>
This Perl script also needs some Perl libraries that are not in
portage but it is still quite simple to install them:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing the needed Perl libraries">
# <i>emerge Mail-SPF-Query Net-CIDR-Lite Sys-Hostname-Long</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now that we have everything in place all we need is to configure
Postfix to use this new policy.
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying master.cf to use SPF">
policy-spf  unix  -       n       n       -       -       spawn
   user=nobody argv=/usr/bin/perl /usr/local/bin/spf.pl
</pre>

<p>
Now add the SPF check in <path>main.cf</path>. Properly configured SPF
should do no harm so we could check SPF for all domains:
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying main.cf to use SPF">
<comment>(Under smtpd_recipient_restrictions add:)</comment>
check_policy_service unix:private/policy-spf
</pre>

<note>
If you're experiencing problems with SPF, e.g. when using
<c>fetchmail</c>, you might want to enable SPF for certain domains only.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring amavisd-new to use MySQL</title>
<section>
<title>Configuring MySQL</title>
<body>

<note>
This has not been tested on versions higher than 2.2. Feedback is welcome :)
</note>

<p>
For large domains the default values you can set in
<path>amavisd.conf</path> might not suit all users. If you configure
amavisd-new with MySQL support you can have individual settings for
users or groups of users.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the MySQL database and user">
# <i>mysql -u root -p mysql</i>
Enter password:
Welcome to the MySQL monitor.  Commands end with ; or \g.
Your MySQL connection id is 78 to server version: 4.0.18-log

Type 'help;' or '\h' for help. Type '\c' to clear the buffer.
mysql> <i>create database maildb;</i>
mysql> <i>GRANT INSERT,UPDATE,DELETE,SELECT ON maildb.* TO 'mail'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'very_secret_password';</i>
mysql> <i>use maildb;</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now that the database is created we'll need to create the necessary tables.
You can cut and paste the following into the mysql prompt:
</p>

<pre caption="MySQL table layout">
CREATE TABLE users (
    id         int unsigned NOT NULL auto_increment,
    priority   int          NOT NULL DEFAULT '7',  -- 0 is low priority
    policy_id  int unsigned NOT NULL DEFAULT '1',
    email      varchar(255) NOT NULL,
    fullname   varchar(255) DEFAULT NULL,    -- not used by amavisd-new
    local      char(1),     -- Y/N  (optional field, see note further down)
    PRIMARY KEY (id),
    KEY email (email)
    );
CREATE UNIQUE INDEX users_idx_email ON users(email);

<comment>(any e-mail address, external or local, used as senders in wblist)</comment>
CREATE TABLE mailaddr (
   id         int unsigned NOT NULL auto_increment,
   priority   int          NOT NULL DEFAULT '7',  -- 0 is low priority
   email      varchar(255) NOT NULL,
   PRIMARY KEY (id),
   KEY email (email)
   );
CREATE UNIQUE INDEX mailaddr_idx_email ON mailaddr(email);

<comment>(-- per-recipient whitelist and/or blacklist,</comment>
<comment>-- puts sender and recipient in relation wb)</comment>
(white or blacklisted sender)
CREATE TABLE wblist (
   rid        int unsigned NOT NULL,     -- recipient: users.id
   sid        int unsigned NOT NULL,     -- sender:    mailaddr.id
   wb         char(1) NOT NULL, -- W or Y / B or N / space=neutral
   PRIMARY KEY (rid,sid)
   );

CREATE TABLE policy (
   id               int unsigned NOT NULL auto_increment,
   policy_name      varchar(32),     -- not used by amavisd-new
   virus_lover          char(1),     -- Y/N
   spam_lover           char(1),     -- Y/N  (optional field)
   banned_files_lover   char(1),     -- Y/N  (optional field)
   bad_header_lover     char(1),     -- Y/N  (optional field)
   bypass_virus_checks  char(1),     -- Y/N
   bypass_spam_checks   char(1),     -- Y/N
   bypass_banned_checks char(1),     -- Y/N  (optional field)
   bypass_header_checks char(1),     -- Y/N (optional field)
   spam_modifies_subj   char(1),     -- Y/N (optional field)
   spam_quarantine_to   varchar(64) DEFAULT NULL, -- (optional field)
   spam_tag_level  float,  -- higher score inserts spam info headers
   spam_tag2_level float DEFAULT NULL,  -- higher score inserts
               -- 'declared spam' info header fields
   spam_kill_level float,  -- higher score activates evasive actions, e.g.
               -- reject/drop, quarantine, ...
               -- (subject to final_spam_destiny setting)
   PRIMARY KEY (id)
  );
</pre>

<note>
If you have problems using copy/paste you might have to copy this
somewhere else and clean out the unneeded characters.
</note>

<note>
Lookups trying to match email are done with raw (rfc2821-unquoted
and unbracketed) addresses as a key, i.e.:
<c>John "Funny" Smith@example.com</c>
</note>

<note>
Lookups are performed in the following order: <c>SQL</c>, <c>LDAP</c>,
<c>hash</c>, <c>ACL</c>, <c>regexp</c>, <c>constant</c>. The first that
returns a definitive answer (not <c>undef/NULL</c>) stops the search.
</note>

<p>
If you wish to use whitelisting and blacklisting you must add the
sender and receiver to <c>mailadr</c> after which you create the relation
between the two e-mail addresses in <c>wblist</c> and state if it is
whitelisting (<c>W</c>) or blacklisting (<c>B</c>).
</p>

<p>
Now that we have created the tables let's insert a test user and a test
policy:
</p>

<pre caption="Create test user and test policy">
INSERT INTO users
   SET
      id         =1,
      priority   =9,
      policy_id  =1,
      email      ="johndoe@example.com",
      fullname   ="John Doe",
      local      ="Y";

INSERT INTO policy
   SET
      id                     =1,
      policy_name            ="Test policy 1",
      virus_lover            ="N",
      spam_lover             ="N",
      banned_files_lover     ="N",
      bad_header_lover       ="N",
      bypass_virus_checks    ="N",
      bypass_spam_checks     ="N",
      bypass_banned_checks   ="N",
      bypass_header_checks   ="N",
      spam_modifies_subj     ="N",
      spam_quarantine_to     =NULL,
      spam_tag_level         =-50.0,
      spam_tag2_level        =7.0,
      spam_kill_level        =10.0;
</pre>

<note>
Copy this to somewhere else and adjust to suit your own environment.
</note>

<note>
<c>local</c> should be set to <c>Y</c> otherwise the mail will not be
scanned for spam.
</note>

<p>
This inserts a test user and a Test policy. Adjust these examples to
fit your needs. Further explanation of the configuration names can be
found in <path>amavisd.conf</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring amavisd to use MySQL</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that MySQL is ready we need to tell amavis to use it:
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying amavisd.conf">
@lookup_sql_dsn =
   ( ['DBI:mysql:maildb:host1', 'mail', 'very_secret_password']  );

<comment>(For clarity uncomment the default)</comment>
$sql_select_policy = 'SELECT *,users.id FROM users,policy'.
   ' WHERE (users.policy_id=policy.id) AND (users.email IN (%k))'.
   ' ORDER BY users.priority DESC';

<comment>(If you want sender white/blacklisting)</comment>
   $sql_select_white_black_list = 'SELECT wb FROM wblist,mailaddr'.
     ' WHERE (wblist.rid=?) AND (wblist.sid=mailaddr.id)'.
     '   AND (mailaddr.email IN (%k))'.
     ' ORDER BY mailaddr.priority DESC';
</pre>
</body>

</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring Spamassassin to use MySQL</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As of Spamassassin 3.0 it is possible to store the Bayes and AWL data in a MySQL
database. We will use MySQL as the backend as it can generally outperform other
databases. Also, using MySQL for both sets of data makes system management much
easier. Here I will show how to easily accomplish this.
</p>

<p>
First start out by creating the new MySQL user and then create
the needed tables.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the new MySQL database and user">
# <i>mysql -u root -p mysql</i>
Enter password:
Welcome to the MySQL monitor.  Commands end with ; or \g.
Your MySQL connection id is 78 to server version: 4.0.18-log

Type 'help;' or '\h' for help. Type '\c' to clear the buffer.
mysql> <i>create database dbname;</i>
mysql> <i>GRANT INSERT,UPDATE,DELETE,SELECT ON dbname.* TO 'dbuser'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'another_very_secret_password';</i>
mysql> <i>use dbname;</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now that the database is created we'll create the necessary tables. You can cut
and paste the following into the mysql prompt:
</p>

<pre caption="MySQL table layout">
      CREATE TABLE bayes_expire (
          id                    int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          runtime               int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          KEY bayes_expire_idx1 (id)
          ) TYPE=MyISAM;

      CREATE TABLE bayes_global_vars (
          variable              varchar(30)     NOT NULL default '',
          value                 varchar(200)    NOT NULL default '',
          PRIMARY KEY           (variable)
          ) TYPE=MyISAM;

      INSERT INTO bayes_global_vars VALUES ('VERSION','3');

      CREATE TABLE bayes_seen (
          id                    int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          msgid                 varchar(200) binary NOT NULL default '',
          flag                  char(1)         NOT NULL default '',
          PRIMARY KEY           (id,msgid)
          ) TYPE=MyISAM;

      CREATE TABLE bayes_token (
          id                    int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          token                 char(5)         NOT NULL default '',
          spam_count            int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          ham_count             int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          atime                 int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          PRIMARY KEY           (id, token),
          INDEX (id, atime)
          ) TYPE=MyISAM;

      CREATE TABLE bayes_vars (
          id                    int(11)         NOT NULL AUTO_INCREMENT,
          username              varchar(200)    NOT NULL default '',
          spam_count            int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          ham_count             int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          token_count           int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          last_expire           int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          last_atime_delta      int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          last_expire_reduce    int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          oldest_token_age      int(11)         NOT NULL default '2147483647',
          newest_token_age      int(11)         NOT NULL default '0',
          PRIMARY KEY           (id),
          UNIQUE bayes_vars_idx1 (username)
          ) TYPE=MyISAM;

      CREATE TABLE awl (
          username              varchar(100)    NOT NULL default '',
          email                 varchar(200)    NOT NULL default '',
          ip                    varchar(10)     NOT NULL default '',
          count                 int(11)         default '0',
          totscore              float           default '0',
          PRIMARY KEY           (username,email,ip)
          ) TYPE=MyISAM;
</pre>

<impo>
The <c>INSERT</c> line is needed otherwise Spamassassin
will not work.
</impo>

<note>
This is also available in the source tarball in the files
<path>awl_mysql.sql</path> and <path>bayes_mysql.sql</path>.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring Spamassassin to use the MySQL backend</title>
<body>

<p>
If you have an old Bayes database in the DBM database and want
to keep it follow these instructions:
</p>

<pre caption="Converting Bayes data from a DBM Database">
<i>su - amavis</i>
<i>sa-learn --sync</i>
<i>sa-learn --backup > backup.txt</i>
<i>sa-learn --restore backup.txt</i>
</pre>

<note>
Note that the last step should only be performed after the MySQL database and
<path>secrets.cf</path> have been updated.
</note>

<p>
Now give Spamassassin the required info:
</p>

<pre caption="Modifying /etc/mail/spamassassin/secrets.cf">
<comment>(Tell Spamassassin to use MySQL for bayes data</comment>
bayes_store_module              Mail::SpamAssassin::BayesStore::SQL
bayes_sql_dsn                   DBI:mysql:sa_bayes:localhost:3306
bayes_sql_username              db_name
bayes_sql_password              another_very_secret_password

<comment>(Tell Spamassassin to use MySQL for AWL data</comment>
auto_whitelist_factory          Mail::SpamAssassin::SQLBasedAddrList
user_awl_dsn                    DBI:mysql:sa_bayes:localhost:3306
user_awl_sql_username           db_name
user_awl_sql_password           another_very_secret_password
</pre>

<p>
Next, change its permissions for proper security:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing permissions">
# <i>chmod 400 /etc/mail/spamassassin/secrets.cf</i>
</pre>

<note>
To create a very secret password use <c>emerge
app-admin/makepasswd</c> and <c>makepasswd -chars=8</c>
</note>

<p>
Now all you have to do is <c>/etc/init.d/amavisd restart</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<section>
<title>Amavisd-new</title>
<body>

<p>
To troubleshoot Amavisd-new start out by stopping it with <c>/etc/init.d/amavisd
stop</c> and then start it manually in the foreground with <c>amavisd debug</c>
and watch it for anomalies in the output.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Spamassassin</title>
<body>

<p>
To troubleshoot Spamassassin you can filter an email through it with
<c>spamassassin -D &lt; mail</c>. To ensure that the headers are intact you can
move it from another machine with IMAP.
</p>

<note>
If you need to troubleshoot you have to enable login for the user
<c>amavis</c> by changing the login shell in <path>/etc/passwd</path> to
<path>/bin/bash</path>.
</note>

<p>
If you want you can make get the same information and more with Amavisd-new
using <c>amavisd debug-sa</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Repeating tasks after installation</title>
<body>

<p>
Some of the activities mentioned in this guide will need to be repeated after
upgrades. For instance, the <c>chown -R amavis:mailusers</c> in the section on
<uri link="#doc_chap6">Autolearning and sidelining emails</uri> will need to be
repeated after every update of amavisd-new.
</p>

<p>
Luckily, Gentoo provides you with the means to perform these steps
automatically. In <uri
link="/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=3&amp;chap=6#doc_chap3">Hooking in
the Emerge Process</uri>, the Gentoo Handbook explains how to execute tasks
after installations of a particular package, like so:
</p>

<pre caption="Example bashrc snippet for running the mentioned chown">
if [ "${PN}" == "amavisd-new" ] &amp;&amp;
   [ "${EBUILD_PHASE}" == "postinst" ]; 
then
  chown -R amavis:mailusers /var/amavis/.maildir
fi
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Getting help</title>
<body>

<p>
If you need help a good place to go is the amavis-user mailing
list. Before postting a question try searching the <uri
link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=amavis-user">Amavis User
mailing list archives</uri>. If you find no answer here you can
subscribe to the <uri
link="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/amavis-user">Amavis User
mailing list</uri>
</p>

<p>
If your question is specific to SpamAssassin, DCC, Razor, or
Postfix, please refer to their respective home pages listed below.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section>
<title>For further information</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.ijs.si/software/amavisd/INSTALL">Amavisd-new
    INSTALL</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.ijs.si/software/amavisd/README.postfix">Amavisd-new
    Postfix README</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.ijs.si/software/amavisd/amavisd-new-docs.html#pbanks">Amavisd-new
    Policy bank documentation</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://spamassassin.apache.org/full/3.0.x/dist/sql/README">Spamassassin
    SQL README</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.greylisting.org">Greylisting</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.postfix.org/FILTER_README.html">Postfix
    SMTPD_POLICY_README</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.unixwiz.net/techtips/postfix-HELO.html">Blocking
    spammers with Postfix HELO controls</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.linuxjournal.com/article.php?sid=7327">SPF
    Overview</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://jimsun.linxnet.com/misc/postfix-anti-UCE.txt">Jim
    Seymour's Postfix Anti-UCE Cheat Sheet</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>General resources</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="http://www.spamassassin.org">Spamassassin</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.ijs.si/software/amavisd/">Amavisd-new</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.ijs.si/software/amavisd/amavisd-new-docs.html">Amavisd-new
    documentation bits and pieces</uri>
  </li>
  <li><uri link="http://razor.sourceforge.net/">Vipuls's Razor</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://pyzor.sourceforge.net/">Pyzor</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.rhyolite.com/anti-spam/dcc/">Distributed Checksum
    Clearinghouse</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.renaissoft.com/projects/maia/">Maia
    Mailguard</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Other howtos</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.flakshack.com/anti-spam/">Fairly-Secure Anti-SPAM
    Gateway Using OpenBSD, Postfix, Amavisd-new, SpamAssassin, Razor
    and DCC</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
