<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/management-structure.xml,v 1.21 2013/08/03 15:53:37 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- Merged to wiki:
https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User:SwifT/Wikified_but_not_merged_documents/Management_structure
-->
<guide disclaimer="obsolete">
<title>Gentoo Top-Level Management Structure</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="pauldv@gentoo.org">Paul de Vrieze</mail>
</author>


<abstract>
Gentoo top-level management structure (work in progress)
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.4</version>
<date>2003-07-20</date>


<chapter>
<title>Gentoo top-level management structure</title>
<section>
<title></title>
<body>

<impo>
<brite>As of May 2005, this document is no longer valid but kept for historical
purposes.</brite>
</impo>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What was the purpose of the new management structure?</title>
<body>

<p>
The purpose of the new management structure was to solve chronic
management, coordination and communication issues in the Gentoo project. In
particular, we had no clearly defined top-level management structure, and no
official, regular meetings to communicate status updates between developers
serving in critical roles. In general, most communication took place on irc
and irregularly via email. There was also little to no accountability, even
at a high level, to complete projects on time.
</p>

<p>
Because of this prior state of affairs, it was difficult to set goals and
track the status of projects. This lack of communication and coordination
also made it difficult for top-level developers to manage their own
projects. In addition, we had other chronic problem of not having
clearly-defined roles and scopes of executive decision-making authority for
top-level developers, which resulted in many top-level developers doubting
that they even have the authority to manage their own projects and
sub-projects. While this had *never* been the intention of top-level
developers, it is the unfortunate result of an unstructured development
process: no one knew what was going on, and everyone deferred to the Chief
Architect for all executive decisions.
</p>

<p>
Clearly, a plan was needed to swiftly and permanently address these issues by
increasing communication, coordination, and accountability. Roles and scopes
of executive decision-making authority needed to be defined for top developers
so that they have a clear mandate as well as accountability to manage their
projects and thus ensure their projects completed their appointed work
efficiently and on-schedule.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Initial implementation</title>
<body>

<p>
Initial implementation of the new management structure began by creating
official top-level management structure. This management structure consists
of the Chief Architect and a group of developers that will be given the title
of Top-level Managers. Top-level Managers will be accountable for the
projects they manage, and be responsible for communicating the status of
their projects to the rest of the Top-level Managers and Chief Architect,
as well as other responsibilities detailed later in this document.
</p>

<p>
All the top-level projects in the Gentoo project are in the process of
being clearly defined, including goals, sub-projects, members, roadmap and
schedules.  The "Hardened Gentoo" page at
<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/</uri> is an excellent example
of such a top-level project definition, and many other top-level projects
currently exist today.
</p>

<p>
Certain executive decision-making authority will be granted to these
projects, as agreed upon by the Chief Architect, Top-level Managers and
project members.  Then, as part of the initial implementation of the new
management structure, a Top-level Manager or managers will be officially
adopt projects and ebuild herds.  These managers will be responsible for
tracking the status of the project, ensuring that the project meets targets
and is generally managed properly.  Manager responsibilities are described
in detail later in this document.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Management team</title>
<body>

<p>
The current top-level management team is as follows (in no particular order):
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Seemant Kulleen (seemant)</li>
  <li>Jay Pfeifer (pfeifer)</li>
  <li>Joshua Brindle (method)</li>
  <li>Kurt Lieber (klieber)</li>
  <li>Pieter Van den Abeele (pvdabeel)</li>
  <li>Jon Portnoy (avenj)</li>
  <li>Paul de Vrieze (pauldv)</li>
  <li>Sven Vermeulen (swift)</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Management charter</title>
<body>

<p>
1) Constructive, professional communication: All communication should be
focused on improving the management of Gentoo projects, should be
constructive in nature and should be shared in a friendly, professional
manner.
</p>

<p>
2) Accountability to peers: Allow fellow members of this list to hold us
accountable to follow-through on projects and meet deadlines. Keep fellow
members accountable.
</p>

<p>
3) Management of projects: empower managers to have the authority and
strategic direction necessary to properly manage thier projects and efforts
to ensure projects complete their appointed work on time.
</p>

<p>
4) Results: our expectation is that our efforts, when properly executed,
will result in the Gentoo project's ability to meet deadlines, have much
better communication and coordination throughout the entire project, higher
overall quality and a more positive experience for all.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Manager responsibilities</title>
<body>

<p>
Every top-level Gentoo project will have a clearly defined scope, and
clearly defined and explicit executive decision-making authority that will
be granted to managers of the project to exercise and/or delegate as they
see fit. Both the scope and any necessary decision-making authority must be
agreed upon by both the Chief Architect and project members. The scope and
executive authority of a project can be expanded over time as required as
approved by the Top-level Managers and Chief Architect.
</p>

<p>
In addition to decision-making authority, managers have the following
responsibilities:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    Keep a complete list of all projects and efforts you are managing,
    and associated gentoo.org project page up-to-date
  </li>

  <li>
    Manage and track the status of these efforts. This includes active
    direction as well as passive tracking of progress.
  </li>

  <li>
    Define clear goals, roadmaps and timelines (preliminary if necessary) for
    every effort.
  </li>

  <li>Proactively identify efforts that have problems and need help.</li>

  <li>
    Ensure that your efforts are completed on-time, or that any efforts that
    are behind-schedule are reported in a timely manner.
  </li>

  <li>
    Remain focused. Make sure that you are not managing more than you can
    handle.
  </li>

  <li>
    Fulfill formal communication and coordination responsibilities required by
    top-level managers (weekly meetings, etc.)
  </li>

  <li>
    Fulfill formal communication and coordination responsibilities required
    by individual efforts (project meetings, communication with project members,
    etc.) This is important as our management of projects means that we
    have the responsibility not only to communicate with our peers but
    also those who we are managing. This communication should be frequent,
    have a formal component (planned meetings, official status updates,
    etc.) and model good management practices to members of our teams.
  </li>

  <li>
    <b>RECURSIVE FUNCTIONALITY</b>: At an appropriate time, implement these
    management practices for *sub*-projects (define managers, clear sub-project
    goals, grant executive authority) with you serving as primary authority.
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Meetings, logs and status updates</title>
<body>

<p>
Currently, weekly manager meetings are held on irc, and all Gentoo developers
are welcome to join the meeting channel and view the meeting in progress. In
addition, after the meeting completes, the floor is opened for questions and
comments by developers. The weekly meetings generally take place on
Monday. After the meeting and open-floor session is concluded, a log of the
meeting is posted to the gentoo-core mailing list.
</p>

<p>
Status updates are very important to the proper functioning of our
management structure. Currently, managers make an effort to email each other
weekly status updates. Soon, we hope to post weekly status updates to our
respective project pages so that the public can be apprised on the status of
every top-level project.
</p>

<note>
Inability to attend due to time zone can be addressed by posting
the full IRC log to gentoo-managers and allowing non-attending members
to post ideas, comments and follow-ups.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Decision-making</title>
<body>

<p>
Currently, GLEPs (Gentoo Linux Enhancement Proposals) can be approved or
rejected by the appropriate top-level manager under which the GLEP falls. If
there is no clearly-defined manager under which the GLEP falls, the GLEP will be
voted upon by the Managers and Chief Architect, and must be approved
unanimously. In all cases, a public, written explanation must be provided
detailing why the GLEP was approved or rejected, either by the manager who
approved/rejected it, or the head of the GLEP sub-project (Grant Goodyear) if
the GLEP was voted upon by the management team. This summary is meant to reflect
the decision that was made by some of the managers at an early manager meeting.
</p>

<p>
Currently, there is no formal general voting procedure in place. In the interim,
any item to be voted upon must be approved by "votable" by the Chief Architect.
Before voting takes place, all managers must have an opportunity to present
their ideas before the other managers, with the general originator(s) of the
idea having the opportunity to present first. After that, the Chief Architect
and Managers can present their ideas, with the Chief Architect having the
opportunity to present last. After this has happened, voting can take place, and
the item will be approved on an unanimous vote. Managers or the Chief Architect
can choose to abstain from voting, and the vote can still pass with abstainers
as long as at least 50% of the members have voted. The voting must take place at
an official managers meeting. Non-attending managers are allowed to vote via
email. The vote must be officially tallied and posted to the managers list.
</p>

<p>
The reason for the "Chief Architect approval" clause it to prevent the voting
process from being abused by allowing voting items that make no sense, such as
those that begin with a "Should we continue to," where a "nay" result would
result in a change in existing policy, as well as preventing managers for
requesting that every small decision be voted upon. We currently have no clear
policy to determine what is a "votable" item, and without this policy there
needs to be some method to determine what is "votable" and what affects some
immutable part of Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
This section is subject to additional clarification and refinement in the
future, as is the rest of this document. The purpose of this section is to
document our currently-existing procedures rather than define ideal or "final"
procedures.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Top-level projects</title>

<body>

<p>
It is the responsibility of the <uri
link="/proj/en/metastructure/">metastructure</uri> top-level project to
officially document and get changes approved to our management structure. The
<uri link="/proj/en/metastructure/projects.xml">official top-level project
list</uri> can be viewed, and can be expected to change/expand slightly at the
new management structure is implemented.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
