<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/nano-basics-guide.xml,v 1.29 2013/12/09 14:19:43 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Nano/Basics_Guide">

<title>Nano Basics Guide</title>

<author title="Gentoo Doc Editor"><!-- meekrob@gentoo.org -->
  Sherman Boyd
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide is meant to be a simple introduction to nano. It will quickly help
you to become familiar with its basic operation.
</abstract>

<version>2</version>
<date>2012-12-25</date>

<chapter>
<title>Nano Basics</title>
<section>
<title>Purpose</title>
<body>

<p>
This guide was written to cover basic operations in nano, and is meant to be
very concise.  For more information about nano check out:
</p>

<p>
<uri>http://www.nano-editor.org</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Opening and creating files</title>
<body>

<p>
Opening and creating files is simple in nano, simply type:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating or opening a file">
# <i>nano filename</i>
</pre>

<p>
Nano is a modeless editor so you can start typing immediately to insert text. If
you are editing a configuration file like <path>/etc/fstab</path> use the
<c>-w</c> switch to disable wrapping on long lines as it might render the
configuration file unparseable by whatever tools depend on it. For example:
</p>

<pre caption="Disable the word wrapping">
# <i>nano -w /etc/fstab</i>
</pre>

<warn>
It is very, very important that you use the <c>-w</c> switch when opening a
config file.  Failure to do so may keep your system from booting or cause other
bad things.
</warn>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Saving and exiting</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to save the changes you've made, press <c>Ctrl+O</c>. To exit nano,
type <c>Ctrl+X</c>. If you ask nano to exit from a modified file, it will ask
you if you want to save it. Just press <c>N</c> in case you don't, or <c>Y</c>
in case you do. It will then ask you for a filename. Just type it in and press
<c>Enter</c>.
</p>

<p>
If you accidentally confirmed that you want to save the file but you actually
don't, you can always cancel by pressing <c>Ctrl+C</c> when you're prompted for
a filename.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Cutting and pasting</title>
<body>

<p>
To cut a single line, you use <c>Ctrl+K</c> (hold down <c>Ctrl</c> and then
press <c>K</c>).  The line disappears.  To paste it, you simply move the cursor
to where you want to paste it and punch <c>Ctrl+U</c>. The line reappears. To
move multiple lines, simply cut them with several <c>Ctrl+K</c>s in a row, then
paste them with a single <c>Ctrl+U</c>. The whole paragraph appears wherever you
want it.
</p>

<p>
If you need a little more fine-grained control, then you have to mark the text.
Move the cursor to the beginning of the text you want to cut. Hit <c>Ctrl+6</c>
(or <c>Alt+A</c>).  Now move your cursor to the end of the text you want to cut:
the marked text gets highlighted.  If you need to cancel your text marking,
simply hit <c>Ctrl+6</c> again.  Press <c>Ctrl+K</c> to cut the marked text. Use
<c>Ctrl+U</c> to paste it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Searching for text</title>
<body>

<p>
Searching for a string is easy as long as you think <e>"WhereIs"</e> instead of
<e>"Search"</e>.  Simply hit <c>Ctrl+W</c>, type in your search string, and
press <c>Enter</c>.  To search for the same string again, hit <c>Alt+W</c>.
</p>

<note>
In nano's help texts the Ctrl-key is represented by a caret (<c>^</c>), so
<c>Ctrl+W</c> is shown as <c>^W</c>, and so on.  The Alt-key is represented by
an <c>M</c> (from "Meta"), so <c>Alt+W</c> is shown as <c>M-W</c>.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>More options</title>
<body>

<p>
If you're interested in tweaking nano, be sure to read <path>/etc/nanorc</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Wrap up</title>
<body>

<p>
That is all!  Thanks to kiyose and quazion from #gentoo.  Again, for more
information about nano check out:
</p>

<p>
<uri>http://www.nano-editor.org</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>

