<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/printing-howto.xml,v 1.86 2013/12/09 20:21:57 swift Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Printing">
<title>Gentoo Printing Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This document covers the installation and maintenance of printers using CUPS and
Samba. It covers local installation and networked installations and you'll
also find instructions on using shared printers from other operating systems.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>8</version>
<date>2013-07-22</date>

<chapter>
<title>Printing and Gentoo Linux</title>
<section>
<title>Use the Right Tools</title>
<body>

<p>
Linux has great support for printers; the right tool for the job is called CUPS
(<uri link="http://www.cups.org">Common Unix Printing System</uri>). Since the
beginning of the project, back in 1999, the installation and maintenance of CUPS
has improved dramatically.
</p>

<p>
In this document we will cover how to use CUPS to setup a local or networked
printer. We will not go in too much detail since the project has <uri
link="http://www.cups.org/documentation.php">great documentation</uri> available
for advanced usage.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configure your Kernel</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
When you want to install a printer on your system you need to know how your
printer will be attached to your system. Is it through a local port like LPT or
USB, or is it networked? And if it is, does it use the Internet Printing
Protocol (IPP) or is it through the Microsoft Windows SMB-CIFS protocol
(Microsoft Windows Sharing)?
</p>

<p>
The next few sections explain what minimal kernel configuration you need. Of
course, this depends on how your printer is going to be attached to your system,
so for your convenience we have separated the instructions:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#lpt">Locally Attached Printer (LPT)</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#usb">Locally Attached Printer (USB)</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#ipp">Remotely Attached Printer (IPP)</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#smb-cifs">Remotely Attached Printer (SMB-CIFS)</uri></li>
</ul>

<p>
So navigate to <path>/usr/src/linux</path> and run <c>make menuconfig</c> to
enter the kernel configuration. If you used <c>genkernel</c> to configure your
kernel, you should still perform these steps just to make sure nothing was
missed out.
</p>

<p>
In the next configuration examples, we will add the necessary support <e>in</e>
the kernel, not as modules. This is not mandatory; if you want you can easily
use modular support. Don't forget to load the appropriate modules afterwards.
</p>

<p>
Now go to the appropriate section to configure (or check) your kernel.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="lpt">
<title>Locally Attached Printer (LPT)</title>
<body>

<p>
The LPT port is generally used to identify the parallel printer port. You need
to enable parallel port support first, then PC-style parallel port support
(unless you are a SPARC user) after which you enable parallel printer support.
</p>

<pre caption="Parallel Port Printer Configuration">
Device Drivers --&gt;
  &lt;*&gt; Parallel port support
  &lt;*&gt;   PC-style hardware

Device Drivers --&gt;
  Character Devices --&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; Parallel printer support
       [*]      IEEE 1284 transfer modes)
</pre>

<note>
Some users might need to enable other options in the <c>Parallel port
support</c> section. Check the kernel configuration <c>Help</c>
function for more information.
</note>

<p>
That's it; quit the kernel configuration and rebuild your kernel. Don't forget
to copy the new kernel image to the <path>/boot</path> location (and don't
forget to mount <path>/boot</path> if needed) and update your boot loader
configuration prior to rebooting your system.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#cups">Installing and Configuring CUPS</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="usb">
<title>Locally Attached Printer (USB)</title>
<body>

<p>
To enable USB printing, you just need USB support in your kernel:
</p>

<pre caption="USB Port Printer Configuration">
Device Drivers --&gt;
  USB Support --&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; Support for Host-side USB
    <comment>(...)</comment>
    --- USB Host Controller Drivers
    <comment>(Select the HCD that your system uses. If you do not know which one
     to select, run "lspci -v | grep HCI" from another terminal)</comment>
    &lt;*&gt; EHCI HCD (USB 2.0) support <comment>( or )</comment>
    &lt;*&gt; OHCI HCD support           <comment>( or )</comment>
    &lt;*&gt; UHCI HCD (most Intel and VIA) support
</pre>

<p>
That's it; quit the kernel configuration and rebuild your kernel. Don't forget
to copy the new kernel image to the <path>/boot</path> location (and don't
forget to mount <path>/boot</path> if needed) and update your boot loader
configuration prior to rebooting your system.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#cups">Installing and Configuring CUPS</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="ipp">
<title>Remotely Attached Printer (IPP)</title>
<body>

<p>
To be able to connect to a remotely attached printer through the Internet
Printing Protocol your kernel just needs to have networking support. Assuming
your kernel has that already, continue with <uri link="#cups">Installing and
Configuring CUPS</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="smb-cifs">
<title>Remotely Attached Printer (SMB-CIFS)</title>
<body>

<p>
Your kernel must support SMB CIFS:
</p>

<pre caption="SMB-CIFS Printer Configuration">
File systems --&gt;
  Network File Systems --&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; SMB file system support (to mount Windows shares etc.)
    &lt;*&gt; CIFS support (advanced network file system for Samba, Windows and other CIFS compliant servers)
</pre>

<p>
That's it; quit the kernel configuration and rebuild your kernel. Don't forget
to copy the new kernel image to the <path>/boot</path> location (and don't
forget to mount <path>/boot</path> if needed) and update your boot loader
configuration prior to rebooting your system.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#cups">Installing and Configuring CUPS</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="cups">
<title>Installing and Configuring CUPS</title>
<section>
<title>Installation</title>
<body>

<p>
Installing CUPS with Gentoo is a breeze. CUPS has a few optional features that
might interest you. To enable or disable those features, use the USE flags
associated with them.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>USE flag</th>
  <th>Impact on CUPS</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>dbus</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for the <c>dbus</c> system message bus.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>jpeg</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for printing JPEG images.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>nls</ti>
  <ti>
    Enable National Language Support. With nls in place, CUPS is able to deliver
    localized feedback so you can hopefully enjoy CUPS in your native
    language.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>pam</ti>
  <ti>
    If you need print job authentication through the Pluggable Authentication
    Modules, this will activate PAM support for CUPS.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>php</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for php scripting.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>png</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for printing PNG images.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ppds</ti>
  <ti>
    Adds support for automatically generated ppd (printing driver) files. See
  <uri link="#installing_best">Installing the Best Driver</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>samba</ti>
  <ti>
    If you want to be able to share locally attached printers to Windows systems
    on your network using the SMB-CIFS protocol, or you want to be able to use
    shared printers from Windows systems, you need SAMBA support.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>slp</ti>
  <ti>
    In a managed environment the printer might be made available as a service to
    others. With the Service Location Protocol you can easily find and configure
    a service on your system. Enable this USE flag if your printer is available
    as a service or should be made available as one.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ssl</ti>
  <ti>
    If you want remote authentication and/or privacy, you need support for the
    Secure Socket Layer, allowing for encrypted printing sessions. Support for
    SSL must be available on all participating systems in your network.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>tiff</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for printing TIFF images.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>X</ti>
  <ti>
    Allows you to use your desktop menu to load the CUPS configuration webpage
    into your preferred browser.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Check the current USE settings. If you want to deviate from your current USE
settings for CUPS alone, add the appropriate USE flags to
<path>/etc/portage/package.use</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="USE flag settings for CUPS">
# <i>emerge -pv cups</i>
[ebuild N     ] net-print/cups-1.2.6  "X dbus jpeg nls pam png ppds ssl -php -samba -slp -tiff" 0 kB

<comment>(For instance, to enable SAMBA support for CUPS)</comment>
# <i>nano -w /etc/portage/package.use</i>
net-print/cups samba
</pre>

<p>
If you are happy with the result, have Portage install CUPS.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing CUPS">
# <i>emerge cups</i>
</pre>

<impo>
Any users that need to print should be added to the <c>lp</c> group. Add them by
running (as root) <c>gpasswd -a username lp</c>.
</impo>

<p>
If the printer is attached to your system locally, you need to load CUPS
automatically on start-up. Make sure your printer is attached and powered on
before you start CUPS.
</p>

<pre caption="Automatically starting CUPS">
# <i>/etc/init.d/cupsd start</i>
# <i>rc-update add cupsd default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
The default CUPS server configuration in <path>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</path>
is sufficient for most users. However, several users might need some changes
to the CUPS configuration.
</p>

<p>
In the next sections we cover a few changes that are often needed:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    In <uri link="#remote_usage">Remote Printer Access</uri> we allow other
    systems to use the printer attached to this Linux workstation.
  </li>
  <li>
    In <uri link="#remote_admin">CUPS Remote Administration</uri> we grant
    access to the CUPS administration from remote systems
  </li>
  <li>
    In <uri link="#windows_pcl">Enable Support for Windows PCL Drivers</uri> you
    configure CUPS to support Windows PCL drivers. This is advised if you want
    Windows systems to be able to use a Samba-shared printer as most Windows
    drivers are PCL drivers.
  </li>
  <li>
    In <uri link="#setup_remote">Setting Up a Remote Printer</uri> we
    configure this system to use a printer attached to another system (not
    Windows share).
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section id="remote_usage">
<title>Remote Printer Access</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want other systems to use your printer through IPP you need to
explicitly grant access to the printer in <path>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</path>. If
you want to share your printer using SAMBA, this change is not needed.
</p>

<p>
Open up <path>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</path> in your favorite editor and add in an
<c>Allow</c> line for the system(s) that should be able to reach to your
printer. In the next example, we grant access to the printer from localhost and
from any system whose IP address starts with <c>192.168.0</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Allowing remote access to the printer">
&lt;Location /&gt;
  Order allow,deny
  <i>Allow localhost</i>
  <i>Allow from 192.168.0.*</i>
&lt;/Location&gt;

<comment>(This broadcasts browsing information to the clients on the network)
(This is so that they know the printer is available)</comment>
BrowseAddress 192.168.0.*:631
</pre>

<p>
Also, you will need to specify which port CUPS listens to, so that it will
respond to printing requests from other machines on your network.
</p>

<pre caption="Port configuration in /etc/cups/cupsd.conf">
Listen *:631
<comment>(Make sure that localhost is commented out)</comment>
#Listen localhost:631
</pre>

<note>
If you are still using CUPS 1.1 (which is now deprecated), then you will need to
use a different syntax for remote printing requests:
</note>

<pre caption="Deprecated CUPS 1.1 configuration">
Port 631
<comment>(Make sure the next two lines are commented out)</comment>
#Listen 127.0.0.1:631
#Listen localhost:631
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="remote_admin">
<title>CUPS Remote Administration</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are interested in remote administration, you need to grant access from
other systems than just localhost to the CUPS administration. Edit
<path>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</path> and have it explicitly grant access to the
systems you want. For instance, to grant access to the system with IP address
of 192.168.0.3:
</p>

<pre caption="Allowing remote access in /etc/cups/cupsd.conf">
&lt;Location /admin&gt;
<comment>(...)</comment>
  Encryption Required
  Order allow,deny
  <i>Allow localhost</i>
  <i>Allow 192.168.0.3</i>
&lt;/Location&gt;
</pre>

<p>
Do not forget to restart CUPS after making changes to
<path>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</path> by running <c>/etc/init.d/cupsd restart</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="windows_pcl">
<title>Enable Support for Windows PCL Drivers</title>
<body>

<p>
PCL drivers send raw data to the print server. To enable raw printing on CUPS,
you need to edit <path>/usr/share/cups/mime/mime.types</path> and uncomment the
line <c>application/octet-stream</c> if it is not already uncommented. Then you
need to edit <path>/usr/share/cups/mime/mime.convs</path> and do the same, if
it is not already uncommented.
</p>

<pre caption="Enable support for raw printing">
# <i>vim /usr/share/cups/mime/mime.types</i>
<comment>(Uncomment the line so that the file contains:)</comment>
application/octet-stream

# <i>vim /usr/share/cups/mime/mime.convs</i>
<comment>(Uncomment the line so that the file contains:)</comment>
application/octet-stream     application/vnd.cups-raw    0    -
</pre>

<p>
Do not forget to restart CUPS after making these changes by running
<c>/etc/init.d/cupsd restart</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="setup_remote">
<title>Setting Up a Remote Printer</title>
<body>

<p>
If the printers are attached to a remote CUPS-powered server you can easily
set up your system to use the remote printer by changing the
<path>/etc/cups/client.conf</path> file.
</p>

<p>
Assuming the printer is attached to a system called <c>printserver.mydomain</c>,
open up <path>/etc/cups/client.conf</path> with your favorite editor and set the
<c>ServerName</c> directive:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing client.conf">
# <i>vim /etc/cups/client.conf</i>

<comment>(Substitute printserver.mydomain with your print server name)</comment>
ServerName <i>printserver.mydomain</i>
</pre>

<p>
The remote system will have a default printer setting which you will be using.
If you want to change the default printer, use <c>lpoptions</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the default printer">
<comment>(First list the available printers)</comment>
# <i>lpstat -a</i>
hpljet5p accepting requests since Jan 01 00:00
hpdjet510 accepting requests since Jan 01 00:00

<comment>(Set the HP LaserJet 5P as the default printer)</comment>
# <i>lpoptions -d hpljet5p</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="configure_printer">
<title>Configuring a Printer</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
If the printer you want to configure is remotely available through a different
print server (running CUPS) you do not need to follow these instructions.
Instead, read <uri link="#setup_remote">Setting Up a Remote Printer</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Detecting the Printer</title>
<body>

<p>
If you have a USB printer or your parallel port printer was powered on when you
booted your Linux system, you might be able to retrieve information from the
kernel stating that it has successfully detected your printer. However this is
merely an indication and not a requirement.
</p>

<pre caption="Retrieving kernel information">
<comment>(For a parallel port printer)</comment>
$ <i>dmesg | grep -i print</i>
parport0: Printer, Hewlett-Packard HP LaserJet 2100 Series

<comment>(For a USB printer)</comment>
$ <i>lsusb</i>
<comment>(...)</comment>
Bus 001 Device 007: ID 03f0:1004 Hewlett-Packard DeskJet 970c/970cse
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing the Printer</title>
<body>

<p>
To have the printer installed on your system, fire up your browser and have it
point to <uri link="http://localhost:631">http://localhost:631</uri>. You will
be greeted by the CUPS web interface from which you can perform all
administrative tasks.
</p>

<note>
If you use an HTTPS connection to CUPS, the first time you access the interface
it <e>may</e> take a very long time before the site comes up. This is because
the first request triggers the generation of the CUPS SSL certificates which can
be a very time-consuming job.
</note>

<p>
Go to <e>Administration</e> and enter your root login and password information
at the box. Then, when you have reached the administrative interface, click on
<e>Add Printer</e>. You will be greeted by a new screen allowing you to enter
the following information:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The <e>spooler name</e>, a short but descriptive name used on your system to
    identify the printer. This name should not contain spaces or any special
    characters. For instance, for the HP LaserJet 5P you could say
    <c>hpljet5p</c>.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <e>location</e>, a description where the printer is physically located
    (for instance in your room, or in the kitchen right next to your dish
    washer, ...). This is to help maintaining several printers.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <e>description</e> in which you should place a full description of the
    printer. A common use is the full printer name (like "HP LaserJet 5P").
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
The next screen asks you for the device where the printer listens to. You will
have the choice of several devices. The next table covers a few possible
devices, but the list is not exhaustive.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Device</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>AppSocket/HP JetDirect</ti>
  <ti>
    This special device allows for network printers to be accessible through a
    HP JetDirect socket. Only specific printers support this.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Internet Printing Protocol (IPP or HTTP)</ti>
  <ti>
    Use this to reach your remote printer through the IPP protocol either
    directly (IPP) or through HTTP.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>LPD/LPR Host or Printer</ti>
  <ti>
    Select this if the printer is remote and attached to a LPD/LPR server.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Parallel Port #1</ti>
  <ti>
    Select this when the printer is locally attached to your parallel port
    (LPT). When the printer is automatically detected its name will be appended
    to the device as well.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>USB Printer #1</ti>
  <ti>
    Select this when the printer is locally attached to a USB port. The printer
    name should automatically be appended to the device name.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
If you are installing a remote printer, you will be asked for the URI to the
printer:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    An LPD printer server requires a <c>lpd://hostname/queue</c> syntax
  </li>
  <li>
    An HP JetDirect printer requires a <c>socket://hostname</c> syntax
  </li>
  <li>
    An IPP printer requires a <c>ipp://hostname/printers/printername</c> or
    <c>http://hostname:631/printers/printername</c> syntax.
    <!-- If for some reason a user wants to use HP's internal ipp syntax,
    they'd use ipp://hostname/ipp/<name> , which used to be mentioned here.
    However, this document describes using CUPS' ipp syntax, so that one was
    dropped in favor of the correct working syntax, which is the first
    example. -->
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Next, select the printer manufacturer in the adjoining screen and the model
type and number in the subsequent one. For many printers you will find
multiple drivers. You can either select one now or search on
<uri link="http://www.linuxprinting.org/printer_list.cgi">LinuxPrinting.org's
Printer List</uri> for a good driver. You can change drivers easily later on.
</p>

<p>
Once the driver is selected, CUPS will inform you that the printer has been
added successfully to the system. You can now go to the printer management page
on the administration interface and select <c>Configure Printer</c> to change
the printer settings (resolution, page format, ...).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Testing and Reconfiguring the Printer</title>
<body>

<p>
To verify if the printer is working correctly, go to the printer administration
page, select your printer and click on <c>Print Test Page</c>.
</p>

<p>
If the printer does not seem to work correctly, click on <c>Modify Printer</c>
to reconfigure the printer. You will be greeted with the same screens as
during the first installation but the defaults will now be your current
configuration.
</p>

<p>
If you have no idea why your printer does not function, you might get a clue by
looking at <path>/var/log/cups/error_log</path>. In the next example we find out
that there is a permission error, probably due to a wrong <c>Allow</c> setting
in <path>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Looking for CUPS errors">
# <i>tail /var/log/cups/error_log</i>
<comment>(...)</comment>
E [11/Jun/2005:10:23:28 +0200] [Job 102] Unable to get printer status (client-error-forbidden)!
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="installing_best">
<title>Installing the Best Driver</title>
<body>

<p>
Many printer drivers exist; to find out which one has the best performance for
your printer, visit the <uri
link="http://www.linuxprinting.org/printer_list.cgi">LinuxPrinting Printer
List</uri>. Select your brand and type to find out what driver the site
recommends. For instance, for the HP LaserJet 5P, the site recommends the
<c>ljet4</c> driver.
</p>

<p>
Download the PPD file from the site and place it in
<path>/usr/share/cups/model</path>, then run <c>/etc/init.d/cupsd restart</c>
as root. This will make the driver available through the CUPS web interface.
Now reconfigure your printer as described above.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Using Special Printer Drivers</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Some printers require specific drivers or provide additional features that are
not enabled through the regular configuration process as described above. This
chapter will discuss a selection of printers and how they are made to work with
Gentoo Linux.
</p>

<p>
The following printers and/or drivers are covered:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#gutenprint">Gutenprint Driver</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#hplip">HPLIP Driver</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#pnm2ppa">PNM2PPA Driver</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section id="gutenprint">
<title>Gutenprint Driver</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://gutenprint.sourceforge.net">gutenprint</uri> drivers are
high-quality, open source printer drivers for various Canon, Epson, HP,
Lexmark, Sony, Olympus and PCL printers supporting CUPS, ghostscript, The Gimp
and other applications.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo's Portage Tree contains an ebuild for the gutenprint drivers. Just use
<c>emerge</c> to install them. Note that the ebuild listens to quite a few USE
flags (such as <c>cups</c> and <c>ppds</c>). You must have enabled at least
these two flags!
</p>

<pre caption="Installing gutenprint drivers">
# <i>emerge gutenprint</i>
</pre>

<p>
When the emerge process has finished, the gutenprint drivers will be available
through the CUPS web interface.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="hplip">
<title>HPLIP Driver</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://hplipopensource.com/hplip-web/index.html">HPLIP
Project</uri> uses the hpcups printer driver. It also includes scanner and fax
support and service tools for various multi-purpose peripherals. For printing
support, it is recommended to use the new hpcups driver, which you can enable
with the <c>hpcups</c> USE flag. The old hpijs driver is still included when you
build <c>net-print/hplip</c> with the <c>hpijs</c> USE flag.
</p>

<p>
The default install enables dynamically generated ppd files at runtime. Some
printers may still require static ppd files. If you encounter problems when
using <c>hp-setup</c> try enabling the <c>static-ppds</c> USE flag and
rebuild <c>net-print/hplip</c>.
</p>

<p>
For USB printers <c>net-print/cups</c> has to be built with the <c>usb</c> USE
flag. This way it makes use of the <c>dev-libs/libusb</c> user space tool which
replaces kernel usb printer support (CONFIG_USB_PRINTER). In case of problems
you can disable the <c>usb</c> USE flag for <c>net-print/cups</c> and activate
the kernel functionality again. All users who need to access the printer have
to be a member of the <c>lp</c> group.
</p>

<p>
To be able to set up a network printer <c>net-print/cups</c> has to be built
with USE <c>slp</c>. With recent versions of <c>net-print/hplip</c> the default
lookup method for networked printers is mDNS which requires
<c>net-print/cups</c> to be built with USE <c>zeroconf</c>. (Note: this method
does not work with the upcoming <c>net-print/cups-1.4</c> series). To be able
to print on a network printer <c>net-print/hplip</c> needs to be built with USE
<c>snmp</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing the hplip drivers">
# <i>emerge -vp hplip</i>
These are the packages that would be merged, in order:

Calculating dependencies            ... done!
[ebuild  N    ] net-print/hplip-3.10.9  USE="X hpcups hpijs libnotify qt4 udev-acl
-doc -fax -kde -minimal -parport -policykit -scanner -snmp -static-ppds" 21,307 kB

Total: 1 package (1 new), Size of downloads: 21,307 kB

# <i>emerge hplip</i>
<comment>(Make sure your USB printer is plugged into your computer or your network
printer into the network socket.)</comment>
# <i>hp-setup</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/cupsd restart</i>
</pre>

<p>
When the emerge process has finished, the <c>hp-setup</c> tool will attempt to
detect and install the printer drivers for your printer on the system. Once
finished, your printer will be available in the CUPS configuration. When
upgrading <c>net-print/hplip</c> you should run <c>hp-setup -r</c> to remove
all printers and configure them again. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="pnm2ppa">
<title>PNM2PPA Driver</title>
<body>

<p>
PPA is an HP technology that focuses on sending low-level processing to the
system instead of to the printer which makes the printer cheaper but more
resource consuming.
</p>

<p>
If the <uri
link="http://www.linuxprinting.org/printer_list.cgi">LinuxPrinting</uri> site
informs you that the <uri link="http://pnm2ppa.sourceforge.net/">pnm2ppa</uri>
driver is your best option, you need to install the <c>pnm2ppa</c> filter on
your system:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing the pnm2ppa filter">
# <i>emerge pnm2ppa</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once installed, download the PPD file for your printer from the <uri
link="http://www.linuxprinting.org/printer_list.cgi">LinuxPrinting</uri> site
and put it in <path>/usr/share/cups/model</path>. Next, configure your printer
using the steps explained above.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="windows">
<title>Printing From and To Microsoft Windows</title>
<section>
<body>

<note>
You should read our <uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Samba/HOWTO">Samba/CUPS
Guide</uri> for more detailed information on setting up CUPS with Samba.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring a Windows Client for IPP</title>
<body>

<p>
Microsoft Windows supports IPP (Windows 9x and ME users need to <uri
link="http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;en-us;294439">install</uri>
it separately). To install a printer that is attached to your Linux box on
Windows, fire up the <c>Add Printer</c> wizard and select <c>Network
Printer</c>. When you are asked for the URI, use the
<c>http://hostname:631/printers/queue</c> syntax.
</p>

<p>
Make sure that your systems <uri link="#remote_usage">can reach</uri> your
printer!
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring a Windows Client for a Samba Shared Printer</title>
<body>

<p>
To share the printer on the SMB-CIFS network, you must have SAMBA installed and
configured correctly. How to do this is beyond the scope of this document, but
we will quickly deal with the configuration of SAMBA for shared printers.
</p>

<p>
Open <path>/etc/samba/smb.conf</path> with your favorite editor and add a
<c>[printers]</c> section to it:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding a [printers] section">
[printers]
  comment      = All printers
  path         = /var/spool/samba
  browseable   = no
  guest ok     = no
  writable     = no
  printable    = yes
  public       = yes
  printer name = hpljet5p
</pre>

<p>
Now navigate to the top of the <path>smb.conf</path> file until you are inside
the <c>[global]</c> section. Then locate the <c>printcap name</c> and
<c>printing</c> settings and set each of them to <c>cups</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the [global] section">
[global]
  <comment>(...)</comment>
  printcap name = <i>cups</i>
  printing      = <i>cups</i>
</pre>

<p>
Make sure you enabled the <uri link="#windows_pcl">Windows PCL drivers</uri>
support in CUPS. Then, restart the <c>smb</c> service to have the changes take
effect.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring a Linux Client for a Windows Print Server</title>
<body>

<p>
First of all, make sure that the printer is shared on your Windows system.
</p>

<p>
Next, in the CUPS web interface, configure your printer as described previously.
You will notice that CUPS has added another driver called <c>Windows Printer via
SAMBA</c>. Select it and use the
<c>smb://username:password@workgroup/server/printername</c> or
<c>smb://server/printername</c> syntax for the URI.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Printing-related Applications</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Many tools exist that help you configure a printer, use additional printing
filters, add features to your printing capabilities, etc. This chapter lists a
few of them. The list is not exhaustive and not meant to discuss each tool in
great detail.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gtk-LP - A Gtk-powered Printer Configuration Tool</title>
<body>

<p>
With <uri link="http://gtklp.sourceforge.net/index.shtml">Gtk-LP</uri> you can
install, modify and configure your printer from a stand-alone Gtk application.
It uses CUPS and provides all standard CUPS capabilities as well. Definitely
worth checking out if you dislike the CUPS Web interface or want a stand-alone
application for your day-to-day printing routines.
</p>

<p>
To install it, emerge <c>gtklp</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing Gtk-LP">
# <i>emerge gtklp</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<section>
<title>Error: Unable to convert file 0 to printable format</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are having printing troubles and <path>/var/log/cups/error_log</path>
shows this message:
</p>

<pre caption="Error log">
Unable to convert file 0 to printable format
</pre>

<p>
You need to re-emerge <c>ghostscript-gpl</c> with the <c>cups</c> USE flag. You
can either add <c>cups</c> to your USE flags in <path>/etc/portage/make.conf</path>, or
you can enable it only for <c>ghostscript-gpl</c> as shown:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding cups to ghostscript-gpl">
# <i>echo "app-text/ghostscript-gpl cups" &gt;&gt; /etc/portage/package.use</i>
</pre>

<p>
Then emerge <c>ghostscript-gpl</c>. When it has finished compiling, be sure to
restart <c>cupsd</c> afterward:
</p>

<pre caption="Restarting cupsd">
# <i>/etc/init.d/cupsd restart</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
