<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/quick-samba-howto.xml,v 1.44 2013/07/22 16:00:06 swift Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Samba/HOWTO">
<title>Gentoo Samba3/CUPS HOWTO</title>

<author title="Author">
  Andreas "daff" Ntaflos <!--daff at dword dot org-->
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="joshua@sungentoo.homeunix.com">Joshua Preston</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Joshua Saddler</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Setup, install and configure a Samba server under Gentoo that shares files and
printers without the need to install drivers.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>4</version>
<date>2013-07-22</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction to this HOWTO</title>
<section>
<title>Purpose</title>
<body>

<p>
This HOWTO is designed to help you move a network from many different clients
speaking different languages, to many different machines that speak a common
language. The ultimate goal is to help differing architectures and technologies,
come together in a productive, happily coexisting environment.
</p>

<p>
Following the directions outlined in this HOWTO should give you an excellent
step towards a peaceful cohabitation between Windows, and virtually all known
variations of *nix.
</p>

<p>
This HOWTO originally started not as a HOWTO, but as a FAQ. It was intended to
explore the functionality and power of the Gentoo system, portage and the
flexibility of USE flags. Like so many other projects, it was quickly discovered
what was missing in the Gentoo realm: there weren't any Samba HOWTOs catered
for Gentoo users. These users are more demanding than most; they require
performance, flexibility and customization. This does not however imply that
this HOWTO was not intended for other distributions; rather that it was designed
to work with a highly customized version of Samba.
</p>

<p>
This HOWTO will describe how to share files and printers between Windows PCs and
*nix PCs. It will also show you how to mount and manipulate shares.
</p>

<p>
There are a few topics that will be mentioned, but are out of the scope of this
HOWTO. These will be noted as they are presented.
</p>

<p>
This HOWTO is based on a compilation and merge of an excellent HOWTO provided
in the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo forums</uri> by Andreas
"daff" Ntaflos and the collected knowledge of Joshua Preston. The link to this
discussion is provided below for your reference:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=110931">HOWTO
    CUPS+Samba: printing from Windows &amp; Linux</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Before you use this guide</title>
<body>

<p>
There are a several other guides for setting up CUPS and/or Samba, please read
them as well, as they may tell you things left out of this HOWTO (intentional or
otherwise). One such document is the very useful and well written <uri
link="/doc/en/printing-howto.xml">Gentoo Printing Guide</uri>, as configuration
issues and specific printer setup is not discussed here.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Brief Overview</title>
<body>

<p>
After presenting the various USE flags, the following list will outline all of
the topics covered as they are presented:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>On the Samba server:
    <ul>
      <li>Install and configure Samba</li>
      <li>Install and configure CUPS</li>
      <li>Adding the printer to CUPS</li>
      <li>Adding the PS drivers for the Windows clients</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>On the Unix clients:
    <ul>
      <li>Install and configure CUPS</li>
      <li>Configuring a default printer</li>
      <li>Mounting a Windows or Samba share</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>On the Windows Clients:
    <ul>
       <li>Configuring the printer</li>
       <li>Accessing Samba shares</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Requirements</title>
<body>

<p>
We will need the following:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>net-fs/samba</li>
  <li>net-print/cups (built with the <c>ppds</c> USE flag)</li>
  <li>net-print/hplip (if you have an HP printer)</li>
  <li>A kernel of sorts (2.6)</li>
  <li>A printer (PS or non-PS)</li>
  <li>
    A working network (home/office/etc) consisting of more than one machine)
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
The main package we use here is <c>net-fs/samba</c>, however, you will need a
kernel with CIFS support enabled in order to mount a Samba or Windows share from
another computer. CUPS will be emerged if it is not already.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Getting acquainted with Samba</title>
<section>
<title>The USE Flags</title>
<body>

<p>
Before emerging anything, take a look at some of the various USE flags available
to Samba.
</p>

<pre caption="Samba uses the following USE Variables:">
kerberos acl cups ldap pam readline python winbind
</pre>

<p>
Depending on the network topology and the specific requirements of the server,
the USE flags outlined below will define what to include or exclude from the
emerging of Samba.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th><b>USE flag</b></th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th><b>kerberos</b></th>
  <ti>
    Include support for Kerberos. The server will need this if it is intended
    to join an existing domain or Active Directory. See the note below for more
    information.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th><b>acl</b></th>
  <ti>
    Enables Access Control Lists. The ACL support in Samba uses a patched
    ext2/ext3, or SGI's XFS in order to function properly as it extends more
    detailed access to files or directories; much more so than typical *nix
    GID/UID schemas.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th><b>cups</b></th>
  <ti>
    This enables support for the Common Unix Printing System. This provides an
    interface allowing local CUPS printers to be shared to other systems in the
    network.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th><b>ldap</b></th>
  <ti>
    Enables the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP). If Samba is
    expected to use Active Directory, this option must be used. This would be
    used in the event Samba needs to login to or provide login to a
    Domain/Active Directory Server. The kerberos USE flag is needed for proper
    functioning of this option.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th><b>pam</b></th>
  <ti>
    Include support for pluggable authentication modules (PAM). This provides
    the ability to authenticate users on the Samba Server, which is required if
    users have to login to your server. The kerberos USE flag is recommended
    along with this option.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th><b>readline</b></th>
  <ti>
    Link Samba against libreadline. This is highly recommended and should
    probably not be disabled.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th><b>python</b></th>
  <ti>
    Python bindings API. Provides an API that will allow Python to interface
    with Samba.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th><b>winbind</b></th>
  <ti>
    Winbind allows for a unified logon within a Samba environment. It uses a
    Unix implementation of Windows RPC calls, PAM and the name service switch
    (supported by the c library) to enable Windows NT domain users to appear and
    work as Unix users on a Unix system.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
A couple of things worth mentioning about the USE flags and different
Samba functions include:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    ACLs on ext2/3 are implemented through extended attributes (EAs). EA and
    ACL kernel options for ext2 and/or ext3 will need to be enabled (depending
    on which file system is being used - both can be enabled).
  </li>
  <li>
    While Active Directory, ACL, and PDC functions are out of the intended
    scope of this HOWTO, you may find these links as helpful to your cause:
    <ul>
      <li><uri>http://www.bluelightning.org/linux/samba_acl_howto/</uri></li>
      <li><uri>http://www.wlug.org.nz/HowtoSamba3AndActiveDirectory</uri></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Server Software Installation</title>
<section>
<title>Emerging Samba</title>
<body>

<p>
First of all: be sure that all your hostnames resolve correctly. Either have a
working domain name system running on your network or appropriate entries in
your <path>/etc/hosts</path> file. <c>cupsaddsmb</c> often borks if hostnames
don't point to the correct machines.
</p>

<p>
Hopefully now you can make an assessment of what you'll actually need in order
to use Samba with your particular setup. The setup used for this HOWTO is:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>cups</li>
  <li>readline</li>
  <li>pam</li>
</ul>

<p>
To optimize performance, size and the time of the build, the USE flags are
specifically included or excluded.
</p>

<p>
First, add <c>ppds</c> to your USE flags to make sure that when CUPS is built,
it has proper foomatic support:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding ppds">
# <i>echo "net-print/cups ppds" &gt;&gt; /etc/portage/package.use</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now, emerge Samba:
</p>

<pre caption="Emerge Samba">
# <i>echo "net-fs/samba readline cups pam" &gt;&gt; /etc/portage/package.use</i>
# <i>emerge net-fs/samba</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will emerge Samba and CUPS. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Emerging net-print/hplip</title>
<body>

<p>
You only need to emerge this if you use an HP printer.
</p>

<pre caption="Emerge hplip">
# <i>emerge net-print/hplip</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Server Configuration</title>
<section>
<title>Configuring Samba</title>
<body>

<p>
The main Samba configuration file is <path>/etc/samba/smb.conf</path>. It is
divided in sections indicated by [sectionname]. Comments are either
# or ;. A sample <path>smb.conf</path> is included below with comments and
suggestions for modifications. If more details are required, see the man page
for <path>smb.conf</path>, the installed <path>smb.conf.example</path>, the
Samba Web site or any of the numerous Samba books available.
</p>

<pre caption="A Sample /etc/samba/smb.conf">
[global]
<comment># Replace MYWORKGROUPNAME with your workgroup/domain</comment>
workgroup = <comment>MYWORKGROUPNAME</comment>
<comment># Of course this has no REAL purpose other than letting
# everyone knows it's not Windows!
# %v prints the version of Samba we are using.</comment>
server string = Samba Server %v
<comment># We are going to use cups, so we are going to put it in here ;-)</comment>
printcap name = cups
printing = cups
load printers = yes
<comment># We want a log file and we do not want it to get bigger than 50kb.</comment>
log file = /var/log/samba/log.%m
max log size = 50
<comment># We are going to set some options for our interfaces...</comment>
socket options = TCP_NODELAY SO_RCVBUF=8192 SO_SNDBUF=8192
<comment># This is a good idea, what we are doing is binding the
# samba server to our local network.
# For example, if eth0 is our local network device</comment>
interfaces = lo <i>eth0</i>
bind interfaces only = yes
<comment># Now we are going to specify who we allow, we are afterall
# very security conscience, since this configuration does
# not use passwords!</comment>
hosts allow = 127.0.0.1 <i>192.168.1.0/24</i>
hosts deny = 0.0.0.0/0
<comment># Other options for this are USER, DOMAIN, ADS, and SERVER
# The default is user</comment>
security = share
<comment># No passwords, so we're going to use a guest account!</comment>
guest ok = yes

<comment># Now we setup our print drivers information!</comment>
[print$]
comment = Printer Drivers
path = /etc/samba/printer <comment># this path holds the driver structure</comment>
guest ok = yes
browseable = yes
read only = yes
<comment># Modify this to "username,root" if you don't want root to
# be the only printer admin)</comment>
write list = <i>root</i>

<comment># Now we'll setup a printer to share, while the name is arbitrary
# it should be consistent throughout Samba and CUPS!</comment>
[HPDeskJet930C]
comment = HP DeskJet 930C Network Printer
printable = yes
path = /var/spool/samba
public = yes
guest ok = yes
<comment># Modify this to "username,root" if you don't want root to
# be the only printer admin)</comment>
printer admin = <i>root</i>

<comment># Now we setup our printers share. This should be
# browseable, printable, public.</comment>
[printers]
comment = All Printers
browseable = no
printable = yes
writable = no
public = yes
guest ok = yes
path = /var/spool/samba
<comment># Modify this to "username,root" if you don't want root to
# be the only printer admin)</comment>
printer admin = <i>root</i>

<comment># We create a new share that we can read/write to from anywhere
# This is kind of like a public temp share, anyone can do what
# they want here.</comment>
[public]
comment = Public Files
browseable = yes
public = yes
create mode = 0766
guest ok = yes
path = /home/samba/public
</pre>

<warn>
If you like to use Samba's guest account to do anything concerning printing from
Windows clients: don't set <c>guest only = yes</c> in the <c>[global]</c>
section. The guest account seems to cause problems when running
<c>cupsaddsmb</c> sometimes when trying to connect from Windows machines. See
below, too, when we talk about <c>cupsaddsmb</c> and the problems that can
arise. Use a dedicated printer user, like <c>printeruser</c> or <c>printer</c>
or <c>printme</c> or whatever. It doesn't hurt and it will certainly protect you
from a lot of problems.
</warn>

<p>
Now create the directories required for the minimum configuration of Samba to
share the installed printer throughout the network.
</p>

<pre caption="Create the directories">
# <i>mkdir /etc/samba/printer</i>
# <i>mkdir /var/spool/samba</i>
# <i>mkdir /home/samba/public</i>
</pre>

<p>
At least one Samba user is required in order to install the printer drivers and
to allow users to connect to the printer. Users must exist in the system's
<path>/etc/passwd</path> file.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the users">
# <i>smbpasswd -a root</i>

<comment>(If another user is to be a printer admin)</comment>
# <i>smbpasswd -a username</i>
</pre>

<p>
The Samba passwords need not be the same as the system passwords
in <path>/etc/passwd</path>.
</p>

<p>
You will also need to update <path>/etc/nsswitch.conf</path> so that Windows
systems can be found easily using NetBIOS:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/nsswitch.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/nsswitch.conf</i>
<comment>(Edit the hosts: line)</comment>
hosts: files dns <i>wins</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring CUPS</title>
<body>

<p>
This is a little more complicated. CUPS' main config file is
<path>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</path>. It's structure is similar to Apache's
<path>httpd.conf</path> file, so many you may find it familiar. Outlined in the
example are the directives that need to be changed:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/cups/cupsd.conf">
ServerName <i>PrintServer</i>          <comment># your printserver name</comment>
ServerAdmin <i>root@PrintServer</i>    <comment># the person for printer-related hate-mail, e.g. you</comment>

AccessLog /var/log/cups/access_log <comment># probably doesn't need changing</comment>
ErrorLog  /var/log/cups/error_log  <comment># doesn't really need changing either</comment>

LogLevel  debug <comment># only while installing and testing, should later be
                # changed to 'info'</comment>

MaxClients 100 <comment># I've had to set this to 1000000000 or so because some time back,
               # there seemed to be a bug in CUPS' controlling of the web interface,
               # making CUPS think a denial of service attack was in progress when
               # I tried to configure a printer with the web interface. weird.</comment>

BrowseAddress @IF(<i>eth0</i>) <comment># Change this to your internal net interface</comment>

&lt;Location /&gt;
Order Deny,Allow
Deny From All
Allow From <i>192.168.1.*</i>  <comment># the addresses of your internel network
                        # e.g. 192.168.1.* will allow connections from any host on
                        # the 192.168.1.0 network. change to whatever suits you</comment>
&lt;/Location&gt;

&lt;Location /admin&gt;
AuthType Basic
AuthClass System
Allow From <i>192.168.1.*</i>  <comment># same as above, allow any host on the
                        # 192.168.1.0 network to connect and do
                        # administrative tasks after authenticating</comment>
Order Deny,Allow
Deny From All
&lt;/Location&gt;
</pre>

<p>
Edit <path>/etc/cups/mime.convs</path> to uncomment some lines. The changes to
<path>mime.convs</path> and <path>mime.types</path> are needed to make CUPS
print Microsoft Office document files.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/cups/mime.convs">
<comment>(The following line is found near the end of the file. Uncomment it)</comment>
application/octet-stream        application/vnd.cups-raw        0
</pre>

<p>
Edit <path>/etc/cups/mime.types</path> to uncomment some lines.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/cups/mime.types">
<comment>(The following line is found near the end of the file. Uncomment it)</comment>
application/octet-stream
</pre>

<p>
CUPS needs to be started on boot, and started immediately.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting up the CUPS service" >
<comment>(To start CUPS on boot)</comment>
# <i>rc-update add cupsd default</i>
<comment>(To start or restart CUPS now)</comment>
# <i>/etc/init.d/cupsd restart</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing a printer for and with CUPS</title>
<body>

<p>
First, go to <uri link="http://linuxprinting.org">LinuxPrinting.Org</uri> to
find and download the correct PPD file for your printer and CUPS. To do so,
click the link Printer Listings to the left. Select your printers manufacturer
and the model in the pulldown menu, e.g. HP and DeskJet 930C. Click "Show". On
the page coming up click the "recommended driver" link after reading the various
notes and information. Then fetch the PPD file from the next page, again after
reading the notes and introductions there. You may have to select your printers
manufacturer and model again. Reading the <uri
link="http://www.linuxprinting.org/cups-doc.html">CUPS quickstart guide</uri> is
also very helpful when working with CUPS.
</p>

<p>
Now you have a PPD file for your printer to work with CUPS. Place it in
<path>/usr/share/cups/model</path>. The PPD for the HP DeskJet 930C was named
<path>HP-DeskJet_930C-hpijs.ppd</path>. You should now install the printer.
This can be done via the CUPS web interface or via command line. The web
interface is found at <path>http://PrintServer:631</path> once CUPS is running.
</p>

<pre caption="Install the printer via command line">
# <i>lpadmin -p HPDeskJet930C -E -v usb:/dev/ultp0 -m HP-DeskJet_930C-hpijs.ppd</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/cupsd restart</i>
</pre>

<p>
Remember to adjust to what you have. Be sure to have the name (<c>-p</c>
argument) right (the name you set above during the Samba configuration!) and to
put in the correct <c>usb:/dev/usb/blah</c>, <c>parallel:/dev/blah</c> or
whatever device you are using for your printer.
</p>

<p>
You should now be able to access the printer from the web interface and be able
to print a test page.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing the Windows printer drivers</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that the printer should be working it is time to install the drivers for
the Windows clients to work. Samba 2.2 introduced this functionality. Browsing
to the print server in the Network Neighbourhood, right-clicking on the
printershare and selecting "connect" downloads the appropriate drivers
automagically to the connecting client, avoiding the hassle of manually
installing printer drivers locally.
</p>

<p>
There are two sets of printer drivers for this. First, the Adobe PS drivers
which can be obtained from <uri
link="http://www.adobe.com/support/downloads/main.html">Adobe</uri> (PostScript
printer drivers). Second, there are the CUPS PS drivers, to be obtained by
emerging <c>net-print/cups-windows</c>. There doesn't seem to be a difference
between the functionality of the two, but the Adobe PS drivers need to be
extracted on a Windows System since it's a Windows binary. Also the whole
procedure of finding and copying the correct files is a bit more hassle. The
CUPS drivers support some options the Adobe drivers don't.
</p>

<p>
This HOWTO uses the CUPS drivers for Windows. Install them as shown:
</p>

<pre caption="Install the drivers">
# <i>emerge -av cups-windows</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now we'll use the script <c>cupsaddsmb</c> provided by the CUPS distribution.
Be sure to read its manpage (<c>man cupsaddsmb</c>), as it will tell you which
Windows drivers you'll need to copy to the proper CUPS directory. Once you've
copied the drivers, restart CUPS by running <c>/etc/init.d/cupsd restart</c>.
Next, run <c>cupsaddsmb</c> as shown:
</p>

<pre caption="Run cupsaddsmb">
# <i>cupsaddsmb -H PrintServer -U root -h PrintServer -v HPDeskJet930C</i>
<comment>(Instead of HPDeskJet930C you could also specify "-a", which will
"export all known printers".)</comment>
# <i>cupsaddsmb -H PrintServer -U root -h PrintServer -a</i>
</pre>

<warn>
The execution of this command often causes the most trouble. Read through the
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=110931">posts in this
thread</uri> for some troubleshooting tips.
</warn>

<p>
Here are common errors that may happen:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The hostname given as a parameter for <c>-h</c> and <c>-H</c>
    (<c>PrintServer</c>) often does not resolve correctly and doesn't identify
    the print server for CUPS/Samba interaction. If an error like: <b>Warning:
    No PPD file for printer "CUPS_PRINTER_NAME" - skipping!</b> occurs, the
    first thing you should do is substitute <c>PrintServer</c> with
    <c>localhost</c> and try it again.
  </li>
  <li>
    The command fails with an <b>NT_STATUS_UNSUCCESSFUL</b>. This error message
    is quite common, but can be triggered by many problems. It's unfortunately
    not very helpful. One thing to try is to temporarily set <c>security =
    user</c> in your <path>smb.conf</path>. After/if the installation completes
    successfully, you should set it back to share, or whatever it was set to
    before.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
This should install the correct driver directory structure under
<path>/etc/samba/printer</path>. That would be
<path>/etc/samba/printer/W32X86/2/</path>. The files contained should be the 3
driver files and the PPD file, renamed to <path>YourPrinterName.ppd</path> (the
name which you gave the printer when installing it (see above).
</p>

<p>
Pending no errors or other complications, your drivers are now installed.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Finalizing our setup</title>
<body>

<p>
Lastly, setup our directories.
</p>

<pre caption="Final changes needed">
# <i>mkdir /home/samba</i>
# <i>mkdir /home/samba/public</i>
# <i>chmod 755 /home/samba</i>
# <i>chmod 755 /home/samba/public</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Testing our Samba configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
We will want to test our configuration file to ensure that it is formatted
properly and all of our options have at least the correct syntax. To do this we
run <c>testparm</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Running the testparm">
<comment>(By default, testparm checks /etc/samba/smb.conf)</comment>
# <i>/usr/bin/testparm</i>
Load smb config files from /etc/samba/smb.conf
Processing section &quot;[printers]&quot;
Global parameter guest account found in service section!
Processing section &quot;[public]&quot;
Global parameter guest account found in service section!
Loaded services file OK.
Server role: ROLE_STANDALONE
Press enter to see a dump of your service definitions
 ...
 ...
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Starting the Samba service</title>
<body>

<p>
Now configure Samba to start at bootup; then go ahead and start it.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting up the Samba service">
# <i>rc-update add samba default</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/samba start</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Checking our services</title>
<body>

<p>
It would probably be prudent to check our logs at this time also. We will also
want to take a peak at our Samba shares using <c>smbclient</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking the shares with smbclient">
# <i>smbclient -L localhost</i>
Password:
<comment>(You should see a BIG list of services here.)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuration of the Clients</title>
<section>
<title>Printer configuration of *nix based clients</title>
<body>

<p>
Despite the variation or distribution, the only thing needed is CUPS. Do the
equivalent on any other UNIX/Linux/BSD client.
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring a Gentoo system">
# <i>emerge cups</i>
# <i>nano -w /etc/cups/client.conf</i>
ServerName <i>PrintServer</i>      <comment># your printserver name</comment>
</pre>

<p>
That should be it. Nothing else will be needed.
</p>

<p>
If you use only one printer, it will be your default printer. If your print
server manages several printers, your administrator will have defined a default
printer on the server. If you want to define a different default printer for
yourself, use the <c>lpoptions</c> command.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting your default printer">
<comment>(List available printers)</comment>
# <i>lpstat -a</i>
<comment>(Sample output, yours will differ)</comment>
HPDeskJet930C accepting requests since Jan 01 00:00
laser accepting requests since Jan 01 00:00
<comment>(Define HPDeskJet930C as your default printer)</comment>
# <i>lpoptions -d HPDeskJet930C</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Printing in *nix">
<comment>(Specify the printer to be used)</comment>
# <i>lp -d HPDeskJet930C anything.txt</i>
<comment>(Use your default printer)</comment>
# <i>lp foobar.whatever.ps</i>
</pre>

<p>
Just point your web browser to <c>http://printserver:631</c> on the client if
you want to manage your printers and their jobs with a nice web interface.
Replace <c>printserver</c> with the name of the <e>machine</e> that acts as your
print server, not the name you gave to the cups print server if you used
different names.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mounting a Windows or Samba share in GNU/Linux</title>
<body>

<note>
Don't forget to install <c>net-fs/samba</c> on the client(s) that will be
accessing the shares.
</note>

<p>
Now is time to configure our kernel to support CIFS. Since I'm assuming
we've all compiled at least one kernel, we'll need to make sure we have all the
right options selected in our kernel. For simplicity's sake, make it a module
for ease of use. It is the author's opinion that kernel modules are a good thing
and should be used whenever possible.
</p>

<pre caption="Kernel support" >
CONFIG_CIFS=m
</pre>

<p>
Then make the module/install it; insert it with:
</p>

<pre caption="Loading the kernel module">
# <i>modprobe cifs</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once the module is loaded, mounting a Windows or Samba share is possible. Use
<c>mount</c> to accomplish this, as detailed below:
</p>

<pre caption="Mounting a Windows/Samba share">
<comment>(The syntax for mounting a Windows/Samba share is:
  mount -t cifs [-o username=xxx,password=xxx] //server/share /mnt/point
If we are not using passwords or a password is not needed)</comment>

# <i>mount -t cifs //PrintServer/public /mnt/public</i>

<comment>(If a password is needed)</comment>
# <i>mount -t cifs -o username=USERNAME,password=PASSWORD //PrintServer/public /mnt/public</i>
</pre>

<p>
After you mount the share, you would access it as if it were a local drive.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Printer Configuration for Windows NT/2000/XP clients</title>
<body>

<p>
That's just a bit of point-and-click. Browse to <path>\\PrintServer</path> and
right click on the printer (HPDeskJet930C) and click connect. This will download
the drivers to the Windows client and now every application (such as Word or
Acrobat) will offer HPDeskJet930C as an available printer to print to. :-)
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Final Notes</title>
<section>
<title>A Fond Farewell</title>
<body>

<p>
That should be it. You should now have a successful printing enviroment that is
friendly to both Windows and *nix as well as a working share!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Links and Resources</title>
<section>
<title>Links</title>
<body>

<p>
These are some links that may help you in setting up, configuration and
troubleshooting your installation:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="http://www.cups.org/">CUPS Homepage</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.samba.org/">Samba Homepage</uri>, especially the <uri
    link="http://www.samba.org/samba/docs/man/Samba-HOWTO-Collection/CUPS-printing.html">chapter
    on Samba/CUPS configuration</uri>
  </li>
  <li><uri link="http://linuxprinting.org/">LinuxPrinting dot Org</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.linuxprinting.org/kpfeifle/SambaPrintHOWTO/">Kurt
    Pfeifle's Samba Print HOWTO</uri> ( This HOWTO really covers <e>ANYTHING</e>
    and <e>EVERYTHING</e> I've written here, plus a LOT more concerning CUPS and
    Samba, and generally printing support on networks. A really interesting
    read, with lots and lots of details.)
  </li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.freebsddiary.org/cups.php">FreeBSD Diary's CUPS Topic</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<body>

<p>
See <uri
link="http://www.linuxprinting.org/kpfeifle/SambaPrintHOWTO/Samba-HOWTO-Collection-3.0-PrintingChapter-11th-draft.html#37">this
page</uri> from Kurt Pfeifle's "Printing Support in Samba 3.0" manual. Lots of
useful tips there! Be sure to look this one up first, before posting questions
and problems! Maybe the solution you're looking for is right there.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
