<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/udev-guide.xml,v 1.60 2013/04/06 11:40:52 swift Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo udev Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="greg_g@gentoo.org">Gregorio Guidi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This document explains what udev is and how you can use udev to fit your needs.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>16</version>
<date>2013-04-06</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is udev?</title>
<section>
<title>The /dev Directory</title>
<body>

<p>
When Linux-users talk about the hardware on their system in the vicinity of
people who believe Linux is some sort of virus or brand of coffee, the use of
"slash dev slash foo" will return a strange look for sure. But for the fortunate
user (and that includes you) using <path>/dev/sda1</path> is just a fast way of
explaining that we are talking about the primary master SATA, first partition. Or
aren't we?
</p>

<p>
We all know what a device file is. Some even know why device files have special
numbers when we take a closer look at them when we issue <c>ls -l</c> in
<path>/dev</path>. But what we always take for granted is that the primary
SATA disk is referred to as <path>/dev/sda</path>. You might not see it
this way, but this is a flaw by design.
</p>

<p>
Think about hotpluggable devices like USB, IEEE1394, hot-swappable PCI, ... What
is the first device? And for how long? What will the other devices be named when
the first one disappears? How will that affect ongoing transactions? Wouldn't it
be fun that a printing job is suddenly moved from your supernew laserprinter to
your almost-dead matrix printer because your mom decided to pull the plug of the
laserprinter which happened to be the first printer?
</p>

<p>
Enter <e>udev</e>. The goals of the udev project are both interesting and
needed:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Runs in userspace</li>
  <li>Dynamically creates/removes device files</li>
  <li>Provides consistent naming</li>
  <li>Provides a user-space API</li>
</ul>

<p>
Every time a change happens within the device structure, the kernel emits a 
<e>uevent</e> which gets picked up by udev. udev then follows the rules as
declared in the <path>/etc/udev/rules.d</path>, <path>/run/udev/rules.d</path>
and <path>/lib/udev/rules.d</path> directories. Based on the information contained
within the uevent, it finds the rule or rules it needs to trigger and performs 
the required actions. These actions can be creating or deleting device files, 
but can also trigger the loading of particular firmware files into the
kernel memory.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Using udev on Gentoo</title>
<section>
<title>Requirements</title>
<body>

<p>
udev is meant to be used in combination with a 3.x kernel (like
<c>gentoo-sources</c> with the default 13.0 profile). If you're using such a
kernel then you just should have no issues whatsoever with using udev as the 
necessary support is built-in in all stable <c>sys-apps/baselayout</c> 
versions. Normally, udev should already be installed on your system, but if
this is not the case, then it is easy to install:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing udev">
# <i>emerge udev</i>
</pre>

<p>
Kernelwise, be sure to activate the following options:
</p>

<pre caption="Required kernel options">
General Setup ---&gt;
  <comment>(Make sure the following item is *not* enabled)</comment>
  [ ] Enable deprecated sysfs features to support old userspace tools

File Systems ---&gt;
  [*] Inotify support for userspace
  Pseudo filesystems ---&gt;
    [*] Virtual memory file system support (former shm fs)

Device Drivers ---&gt;
  <comment>(Make sure the following item is *not* enabled)</comment>
  &lt; &gt; ATA/ATAPI/MFM/RLL support (DEPRECATED)
  <comment>(This is *absolutely* necessary for /dev to populate)</comment>
  Generic Driver Options ---&gt;
    [*] Maintain a devtmpfs filesystem to mount at /dev (NEW)
</pre>

<p>
If you use <c>sys-kernel/genkernel</c>, you don't need to do anything special.
Genkernel sets up udev by default. You can also try <c>sys-kernel/dracut</c>
which is quite well integrated into Gentoo.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources &amp; Acknowledgements</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Documentation for using <uri 
link="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/systemd/PredictableNetworkInterfaceNames">the
predictable network interface names</uri> introduced in 197, replacing the now
deleted rule_generator's /etc/udev/rules.d/70-persistent-net.rules
</p>

<p>
<uri link="http://github.com/gentoo/eudev">Fork of the systemd git tree without
systemd itself</uri> at github, with aims like longterm stable API, more POSIX
than GNU, aimed much for minimal embedded but works on anything else too.
You decide if it's up to date by looking at the repository's history, since
this documentation might not be.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Known problems</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Stale <c>70-persistent-net.rules</c> (or other network rules) in
<path>/etc/udev/rules.d</path> can prevent the predictable network naming from
being enabled. Both <c>70-persistent-net.rules</c> and
<c>70-persistent-cd.rules</c> are from the now deleted rule_generator
</p>

<p>
Init script called 'udev-postmount' should be removed from runlevels if it's
still there.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
