<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/vpnc-howto.xml,v 1.12 2013/12/10 09:24:14 swift Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Vpnc">
<title>Gentoo vpnc HOWTO</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dhaskew@earthlink.net">David H. Askew</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="fauli@gentoo.org">Christian Faulhammer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="fischer@unix-ag.uni-kl.de">Thomas Fischer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This document details how to connect your workstation to a Cisco VPN
concentrator utilizing vpnc to manage the connection.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>4</version>
<date>2012-04-22</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
If you're reading this, then you likely need to connect to your office network
from home or during travel. Many companies utilize Cisco 3000 VPN concentrators
for their VPN needs, and I am willing to bet that most Linux newbies think that
they are forced to use Windows to connect to them. Well, this document informs
you that connecting to a Cisco VPN is very possible and will hopefully enable
you to setup a working tunnel using your Gentoo workstation or laptop.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What this document is</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>A guide to the basic workings of <c>vpnc</c></li>
  <li>A discussion of DNS and routing issues that relate to VPNs</li>
  <li>Examples of managing VPN sessions</li>
  <li>Useful tips and tricks (hopefully)</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What this document is not</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>An in-depth guide to VPN/encryption technologies</li>
  <li>A feature by feature explanation of <c>vpnc</c></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Assumptions</title>
<body>

<p>
The assumptions made at this point are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>You have Gentoo installed</li>
  <li>You have Internet access</li>
  <li>You want to connect to a Cisco 3000 VPN concentrator</li>
  <li>You know how to configure, build, and install a new kernel</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Kernel Configuration</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
In order for Linux to be able to open a VPN connection <e>Universal TUN/TAP
device driver support</e> must be enabled in the kernel. What is it and why do
you need it? Below is a relatively straight forward explanation from the kernel
configuration dialog:
</p>

<pre caption="CONFIG_TUN">
TUN/TAP provides packet reception and transmission for user space
programs. It can be viewed as a simple Point-to-Point or Ethernet
device, which instead of receiving packets from a physical media,
receives them from user space program and instead of sending packets
via physical media writes them to the user space program.

When a program opens /dev/net/tun, driver creates and registers
corresponding net device tunX or tapX. After a program closed above
devices, driver will automatically delete tunXX or tapXX device and
all routes corresponding to it.
</pre>

<p>
You can verify yourself if your kernel has TUN/TAP support with the following
command:
</p>

<pre caption="Checking the kernel config">
# <i> grep "TUN" /usr/src/linux/.config</i>
CONFIG_INET_TUNNEL=m
# CONFIG_INET6_TUNNEL is not set
# CONFIG_IPV6_TUNNEL is not set
<comment>(TUN/TAP enabled as a module)</comment>
CONFIG_TUN=m
# CONFIG_8139TOO_TUNE_TWISTER is not set
</pre>

<p>
As you can see above, <c>CONFIG_TUN=m</c> is compiled as a module. If it is
disabled in your setup, enable it in your kernel of choice, rebuild, install,
reboot and return to this document before continuing with the next steps.
</p>

<pre caption="Configuration location in the kernel configuration dialog">
Device Drivers  ---&gt;
  Network device support  ---&gt;
    [*] Universal TUN/TAP device driver support
</pre>

<p>
If you built TUN/TAP support directly into the kernel, you should see
information from <c>dmesg</c> output like the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Checking dmesg output">
# <i>dmesg | grep TUN</i>
Universal TUN/TAP device driver 1.5 (C)1999-2002 Maxim Krasnyansky
</pre>

<p>
If you build TUN/TAP support as a module, you first must load the <c>tun</c>
module:
</p>

<pre caption="Load tun module">
# <i>modprobe tun</i>
# <i>lsmod</i>
Module                  Size  Used by
tun                     7296  0
</pre>

<p>
Now that the <c>tun</c> module is loaded, check <c>dmesg</c> output. You should
see something like the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Checking dmesg output">
# <i>dmesg | grep TUN</i>
Universal TUN/TAP device driver 1.5 (C)1999-2002 Maxim Krasnyansky
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Install Needed Software</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Now that you have a working kernel setup, you need to install
<c>net-misc/vpnc</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing vpnc">
# <i>emerge -av net-misc/vpnc</i>
</pre>

<p>
Make sure to check the supported USE flag combinations and see if they apply to
your environment. If you encounter a problem later with the following error, you
will need to enable the hybrid-auth USE flag:
</p>

<pre caption="vpnc complaining about hybrid/cert mode">
vpnc was built without openssl: Can't do hybrid or cert mode.
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Example Setup</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
In order to make the following sections more clear, we need an example setup to
work from. For the purposes of this exercise, we will assume that you have a
home network of several computers. All computers are on the 192.168.0.0 /
255.255.255.0 network. The LAN in question is run by a Gentoo box using an
iptables firewall, DHCP, caching DNS, etc ... and it masquerades the LAN behind
the public IP address it receives from an ISP. You also have a workstation on
the LAN from which you want to be able to VPN into your office with.
</p>

<p>
Our example workstation configuration looks like the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Our workstation configuration">
<comment>(Name server configuration)</comment>
# <i>cat /etc/resolv.conf</i>
nameserver      192.168.0.1

<comment>(Network configuration)</comment>
# <i>cat /etc/hosts</i>
127.0.0.1       desktop localhost
192.168.0.1     router
192.168.2.2     mediacenter

<comment>(Interface configuration)</comment>
# <i>ifconfig -a</i>
eth0      Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:11:2F:8D:08:08
          inet addr:192.168.0.2  Bcast:192.168.0.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
          inet6 addr: fe80::211:2fff:fe8d:808/64 Scope:Link
          UP BROADCAST NOTRAILERS RUNNING MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:3657889 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:2305893 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:1000
          RX bytes:2193722103 (2092.0 Mb)  TX bytes:1415104432 (1349.5 Mb)
          Interrupt:185 Memory:fac00000-0

lo        Link encap:Local Loopback
          inet addr:127.0.0.1  Mask:255.0.0.0
          inet6 addr: ::1/128 Scope:Host
          UP LOOPBACK RUNNING  MTU:16436  Metric:1
          RX packets:35510 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:35510 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:0
          RX bytes:16023838 (15.2 Mb)  TX bytes:16023838 (15.2 Mb)

<comment>(Routing information)</comment>
# <i>netstat -r</i>
Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags   MSS Window  irtt Iface
192.168.0.0     *               255.255.255.0   U         0 0          0 eth0
loopback        desktop         255.0.0.0       UG        0 0          0 lo
default         router          0.0.0.0         UG        0 0          0 eth0
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring vpnc</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Now that you have <c>vpnc</c> installed and we have an example to work from,
let's discuss the basics of setting up <c>vpnc</c>. The configuration file for
<c>vpnc</c> connection settings can be located in a couple places, depending on
how many profiles you want to setup. By default, <c>vpnc</c> looks first for
<path>/etc/vpnc/default.conf</path> for its connection settings. If it doesn't
find that file, then it looks for <path>/etc/vpnc.conf</path>. This setup will
only address a single profile example and will use the configuration file
location <path>/etc/vpnc.conf</path>. Make sure you do <e>not</e> have a
<path>/etc/vpnc/default.conf</path> file.
</p>

<pre caption="Example /etc/vpnc.conf file">
IPSec gateway vpngateway.domain.org
IPSec ID group_id
IPSec secret group_password
Xauth username network_signon
Xauth password network_password
</pre>

<p>
The configuration file example above should be modified to reflect the
appropriate values for your setup. The gateway option
<c>vpngateway.domain.org</c> can be a fully qualified domain name or an IP
address. The ID and secret options should be given to you by a network
administrator. If you cannot obtain this information but you currently have a
working setup on a Windows box which utilizes the official Cisco VPN client,
then all you have to do is export your profile. The user name and password
options are for your normal network sign-on, such as a Windows NT domain
account.
</p>

<p>
If you are forced to export your profile from a Windows machine, then what you
will likely have is a file ending in <path>.pcf</path>. This file will have all
the information you need. Below is an example:
</p>

<pre caption="Example profile.pcf file">
[main]
Description=
Host=VPNGATEWAY.DOMAIN.ORG
AuthType=1
GroupName=group_id
GroupPwd=
enc_GroupPwd=F3256220AA200A1D532556024F4F314B0388D48B0FBF2DB12
EnableISPConnect=0
ISPConnectType=0
ISPConnect=FOOBAR
ISPCommand=
Username=
SaveUserPassword=0
UserPassword=
enc_UserPassword=
NTDomain=
EnableBackup=0
BackupServer=
EnableMSLogon=1
MSLogonType=0
EnableNat=1
TunnelingMode=0
TcpTunnelingPort=10000
CertStore=0
CertName=
CertPath=
CertSubjectName=
CertSerialHash=00000000000000000000000000000000
SendCertChain=0
VerifyCertDN=
DHGroup=2
ForceKeepAlives=0
PeerTimeout=90
EnableLocalLAN=0
EnableSplitDNS=1
ForceNetLogin=0
</pre>

<p>
In the above example, we can see entries for <c>Host</c>, <c>GroupName</c> and
<c>enc_GroupPwd</c>. Your <c>Username</c> and <c>UserPassword</c> may or may
not be exported depending on the setup. To generate a working vpnc
configuration out of it, you can use <c>pcf2vpnc</c>, included with vpnc.
</p>

<note>
You can decrypt the password with the help from the <c>cisco-decrypt</c>
program, shipped with the latest vpnc.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Testing your setup</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that you have a configuration in place, it's time to test your setup. To
start <c>vpnc</c> you do the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Example vpnc usage">
# <i>vpnc</i>
Enter password for username@vpngateway.domain.org:
VPNC started in background (pid: 14788)...
</pre>

<p>
As you can see from the above command output, once you type <c>vpnc</c> (as
root), you are prompted for your password. After entering your password, which
will not be echoed back to you, the <c>vpnc</c> process will automatically
become a background process.
</p>

<note>
If you specified the <c>Xauth password</c> option in your <c>vpnc</c> config
file, then you will not be prompted for your password at <c>vpnc</c> startup.
Additionally, if <c>vpnc</c> needs some extra options not specified in the
configuration file, or if you have forgotten something, don't worry, it will
ask you for it.
</note>

<pre caption="Sample interface configuration changes made by vpnc">
# <i> ifconfig -a</i>
eth1      Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:11:2F:8D:08:08
          inet addr:192.168.0.2  Bcast:192.168.0.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
          inet6 addr: fe80::211:2fff:fe8d:808/64 Scope:Link
          UP BROADCAST NOTRAILERS RUNNING MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:2101119 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:1577559 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:1000
          RX bytes:1757862627 (1676.4 Mb)  TX bytes:732200131 (698.2 Mb)
          Interrupt:177 Memory:faa00000-0

sit0      Link encap:IPv6-in-IPv4
          NOARP  MTU:1480  Metric:1
          RX packets:0 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:0 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:0
          RX bytes:0 (0.0 b)  TX bytes:0 (0.0 b)

tun0      Link encap:UNSPEC  HWaddr 00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00-00
          inet addr:192.168.160.42  P-t-P:192.168.160.42  Mask:255.255.255.255
          UP POINTOPOINT RUNNING NOARP MULTICAST  MTU:1412  Metric:1
          RX packets:1 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:9 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:500
          RX bytes:60 (60.0 b)  TX bytes:616 (616.0 b)
</pre>

<pre caption="Sample routing modifications made by vpnc">
# <i>netstat -r</i>
Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags   MSS Window  irtt Iface
vpn01.domain.or router          255.255.255.255 UGH    1500 0          0 eth1
192.168.0.0     *               255.255.255.0   U         0 0          0 eth1
loopback        desktop         255.0.0.0       UG        0 0          0 lo
default         *               0.0.0.0         U         0 0          0 tun0
</pre>

<p>
As you can see from the above command output(s), <c>vpnc</c> has done the
following:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Created the tun0 network interface, a virtual interface to handle
    the traffic across your VPN tunnel
  </li>
  <li>Obtained the IP address for the tun0 device from your VPN provider</li>
  <li>Set the default route to your VPN gateway</li>
</ul>

<p>
At this point, your workstation is capable of communicating with hosts via the
VPN. Because <c>vpnc</c> sets your default route to your VPN gateway, all
network traffic will travel across the VPN, even if it destined for the Internet
or elsewhere not specifically specified by additional routes. For some, this
basic type of connection may be satisfactory, but for most, additional steps
need to be taken.
</p>

<p>
Additional things you might want to have:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>DNS for the VPN</li>
  <li>
    A routing setup that will only send traffic destined for the VPN down the
    virtual tunnel. This way, you can browse the Internet while connected to
    the VPN, without your personal web/p2p etc. traffic going across the
    tunnel.
  </li>
  <li>
    A script to manage all this, because <c>vpnc</c> just doesn't do enough by
    default.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
When you are ready to end the VPN session, execute <c>vpnc-disconnect</c>. An
example is shown below.
</p>

<note>
Don't disconnect yet, because we have additional things to test. The example
below is just for informational purposes.
</note>

<pre caption="vpnc-disconnect">
# <i>vpnc-disconnect</i>
Terminating vpnc daemon (pid: 26250)
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Set up DNS</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Unfortunately, <c>vpnc</c> doesn't handle the setup and management of DNS for
your newly established tunnel. The user is left to decide how DNS should be
handled. You could just overwrite <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path> when you
connect, but that would utilize your VPN DNS for all DNS queries regardless of
whether or not the traffic is destined for your VPN tunnel. This is a very
functional solution and if you simply need to connect to the tunnel, do your
work, and then disconnect, read no further. But, if you want to be able to
leave your tunnel connected for lengthy periods of time and don't want your
work DNS servers handling requests for your personal traffic, read on.
</p>

<p>
The ideal setup would allow you to separate your DNS queries into two
categories: VPN-related and other. Under this setup, all VPN-related DNS
queries would be answered by DNS servers located at the other end of your VPN
tunnel and all other queries would continue to be answered by local or ISP
supplied DNS servers. This is the setup that will be demonstrated here.
</p>

<note>
We will consider VPN-related DNS queries to be any query belonging to the
example.org domain, such as host1.example.org or server1.example.org.
</note>

<p>
So how do you set things up, so that only requests made to hosts on the
example.org domain get sent to VPN supplied DNS servers? Well, you're going to
need to install a local DNS server, but don't worry, it's much easier than you
think. There are several software packages that can handle the type of setup we
desire, but for the purposes of this demonstration, <c>dnsmasq</c> will be
utilized. Let's emerge it now:
</p>

<note>
This DNS server software will not be available to the network, and will only
answer requests from localhost, <c>127.0.0.1</c>.
</note>

<pre caption="Install dnsmasq">
# <i>emerge dnsmasq</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now you need to add an option to your <c>dnsmasq</c> startup options. Edit the
following option to suit your needs. Substitute .example.org with the
appropriate domain and the IP address with a valid DNS server that belongs to
the VPN tunnel.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/conf.d/dnsmasq">
Config file for /etc/init.d/dnsmasq

# See the dnsmasq(8) man page for possible options to put here.
DNSMASQ_OPTS="-S /.example.org/192.168.125.10"
</pre>

<p>
Next, make sure that the first entry in <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path> is your
local host <c>127.0.0.1</c>, followed by the location of the backup DNS servers
that should handle the DNS traffic in case dnsmasq fails to start, or if it
needs to forward a DNS query it doesn't currently have in its cache. An example
<path>/etc/resolv.conf</path> is shown below.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/resolv.conf">
nameserver 127.0.0.1
nameserver 192.168.0.1
</pre>

<p>
Now that you have setup a rule for your VPN tunnel DNS, you need to start
<c>dnsmasq</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Starting up dnsmasq">
# <i>/etc/init.d/dnsmasq start</i>
# <i>rc-update add dnsmasq default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring the routing table</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The ideal scenario would be if only the traffic destined for VPN tunnel would
travel across the link. At this point, you have a VPN tunnel setup and all
traffic will travel across the tunnel, unless you specify additional routes. In
order to fix this situation you need to know what networks are available to you
on your VPN. The easiest way to find out the needed information is to ask a
network administrator, but sometimes they are reluctant to answer such
questions. If your local network admin won't provide the needed information,
some trial and error experiments will be required.
</p>

<p>
When the VPN tunnel was started, <c>vpnc</c> set the default route to the
tunnel. So you must set your default route back to normal, so that things work
as expected.
</p>

<pre caption="Resetting your default route">
# <i>route add default gw 192.168.0.1</i>
</pre>

<p>
Earlier, when DNS services were being configured for your VPN, you specified a
DNS server to handle your example.org domain. You need to add a route for the
192.168.125.0 subnet so that DNS queries will work.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding a route for dns">
# <i>route add -net 192.168.125.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 dev tun0</i>
</pre>

<p>
At this point, you should add any additional routes for known networks (such as
for the subnet 192.168.160.0, which includes the IP address received by the
TUN/TAP virtual device). If your friendly network administrator gave you the
required info, great. Otherwise, you might need to ping hosts you will be
connecting to frequently, to give yourself an idea about what your routing table
should look like.
</p>

<note>
Due to your setup, when using VPN network services by name, you must specify
the fully qualified domain name, for instance: webserver1.example.org
</note>

<pre caption="Ping example">
# <i>ping intranet1.example.org</i>
PING intranet1.example.org (172.25.230.29) 56(84) bytes of data.


--- intranet1.example.org ping statistics ---
18 packets transmitted, 0 received, 100% packet loss, time 16997ms
</pre>

<p>
As you can see from the above example, the ping probes to
<c>intranet1.example.org</c> were unsuccessful. So we need to add a route for
that subnet.
</p>

<pre caption="another route command example">
# <i>route add -net 172.25.230.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 dev tun0</i>
</pre>

<p>
A few ping and route commands later, you should be well on your way to a well
working routing table.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Manage the connection</title>
<section>
<title>Calling vpnc when needed</title>
<body>

<p>
Next is an example script to manage the VPN connection. You could execute it
(as root) from an xterm to start a connection to your VPN. Then all you have to
do is press return to disconnect the VPN. Obviously you will need to modify
this for your setup, remembering to add all the additional routes that you may
need.
</p>

<pre caption="Example session management script">
#!/bin/bash

source /sbin/functions.sh

ebegin "Connecting to the VPN"
vpnc
eend

ebegin "Modifying the routing table"
route add default gw 192.168.0.1
route add -net 172.25.230.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 dev tun0
route add -net 192.168.160.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 dev tun0
route add -net 192.168.125.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 dev tun0
eend

einfo "Press any key to disconnect ..."

read $disconnect

ebegin "Disconnecting from the VPN"
vpnc-disconnect
eend
ebegin "Reconfiguring the default routing table"
route add default gw 192.168.0.1
eend

einfo "VPN should now be disconnected"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Start vpnc on boot</title>
<body>

<p>
Version 0.4.0-r1 of vpnc contains an init script (<path>/etc/init.d/vpnc</path>)
which can handle multiple configurations. The default script looks for
<path>/etc/vpnc/vpnc.conf</path>, but as many configurations as can be imagined
are possible. Before and after shutdown and start-up custom-made scripts can be
executed that are connected by their name to the corresponding init script
(since version 0.5.1-r1). Their names end in <path>-preup.sh</path>,
<path>-postup.sh</path>, <path>-predown.sh</path> and <path>-postdown.sh</path>,
stored in the <path>/etc/init.d/scripts.d/</path> directory. The general naming
scheme is sketched in the following table.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>init script name</th>
    <th>needed configuration file</th>
    <th>preup script name</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>/etc/init.d/vpnc</ti>
    <ti>/etc/vpnc/vpnc.conf</ti>
    <ti>/etc/vpnc/scripts.d/vpnc-preup.sh</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>/etc/init.d/vpnc.work</ti>
    <ti>/etc/vpnc/work.conf</ti>
    <ti>/etc/vpnc/scripts.d/work-preup.sh</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
Add vpnc to default runlevel with the following commands (in this case for the
standard configuration). Don't forget to add the tun module (if you have built
it that way) to the kernels autoload mechanism at startup.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding vpnc to startup scripts">
# <i>rc-update add vpnc default</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you don't want to save your password in the configuration file, you can tell
the init script to show all output and prompts on standard output by editing
<path>/etc/conf.d/vpnc</path>. Set the variable <c>VPNCOUTPUT</c> to yes or no,
where its default is to not display screen output.
</p>

<note>
The init scripts don't handle DNS separation, but you can use the custom
scripts to achieve that. See <uri link="#tipsscript">Tips and Tricks</uri>.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>
<section>
<title>Graphical remote access</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are looking for a Linux application that supports RDP (Remote Desktop
Protocol) then give <c>grdesktop</c> a try. It's a GUI app written in GTK+ that
fits in well with a Gnome desktop, but doesn't require it. If you don't want
the GUI configuration dialogs that grdesktop provides, then just install
<c>rdesktop</c>. Ultimately, grdesktop is just a frontend for rdesktop.
</p>

<p>
If you are a KDE user, you might want to try <c>kvpnc</c>. It a appears to be a
very mature VPN management GUI.
</p>

<p>
If you need to connect to a Windows machine which doesn't have a DNS entry, and
you know the address of an available WINS server, you can use a tool called
<c>nmblookup</c> to query the WINS server for the host name of the machine you
want to connect to. Unfortunately, you have to install <c>samba</c> to get it,
but if you are going to be working with boxes running Windows you might as well
want to install samba, because it includes several other useful tools.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing samba">
# <i>emerge -av samba</i>
</pre>

<p>
When you have samba and its tools installed, test <c>nmblookup</c> by asking
the WINS server at IP address 192.168.125.11 about a host named wintelbox1.
</p>

<pre caption="nmblookup example">
# <i>nmblookup -U 192.168.125.11 -R 'wintelbox1'</i>
querying wintelbox1 on 192.168.125.11
172.25.230.76 wintelbox1
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="tipsscript">
<title>Custom scripts on boot</title>
<body>

<p>
The custom-made scripts for the <path>init.d</path> file can be used to setup a
user-defined routing for the vpnc connection. The examples below show how to
setup the routing table so that only connections to 123.234.x.x are routed over
the VPN and all other connections use the default gateway. The example uses
work-preup.sh to save the current default gateway before starting vpnc (which
resets the default gateway using the VPN connection). Once vpnc has been
started, <path>work-postup.sh</path> deletes this new default gateway, restores
the old default gateway and sets the route for all connections to 123.234.x.x to
use the vpnc connection.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/vpnc/scripts.d/work-preup.sh">
#!/bin/sh
route -n | grep -E '^0.0.0.0 ' | cut -c 17-32 >/var/tmp/defaultgw
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/vpnc/scripts.d/work-postup.sh">
#!/bin/sh
route del -net 0.0.0.0 netmask 0.0.0.0 dev tun1
route add default gw $(cat /var/tmp/defaultgw)
route add -net 123.234.0.0 netmask 255.255.0.0 dev tun1
</pre>

<p>
The example scripts assume that the vpnc connection uses tun1 as tun device.
You can set the device name in the connection's configuration file.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/vpnc/work.conf">
Interface name tun1
IPSec gateway vpn.mywork.com
Pidfile /var/run/vpnc.work.pid
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Useful Links</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.unix-ag.uni-kl.de/~massar/vpnc/">vpnc homepage</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://home.gna.org/kvpnc/en/index.html">kvpnc homepage</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.nongnu.org/grdesktop/">grdesktop homepage</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Final Notes</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Hopefully by now you have been able to connect to your VPN of choice and are
well on your way to remote office work. Feel free to file a bug at <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri> should you find a mistake
or wish to make an addition or recommendation regarding this document.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
