<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/xen-guide.xml,v 1.12 2012/06/18 22:40:15 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete">
<title>Configuring Gentoo with Xen</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide describes how to start using Xen on your Gentoo system
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>7</version>
<date>2011-12-26</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.xen.org/">Xen</uri> technology allows you to run
multiple operating systems on a single physical system, govern resource
consumption and even migrate domains (which are the virtual environments in
which a guest operating system runs) from one Xen-powered system to another. Xen
requires the host operating system to support Xen (which, in this case, will be
a Linux kernel) but guest operating systems can run unmodified <e>if</e> your
hardware supports Intel Virtualization Technology (VT-x) or AMD Virtualization
Technology (SVM). Otherwise your guest operating systems must also support Xen.
</p>

<p>
This guide will talk you through the configuration steps necessary to get Xen up
and running on Gentoo Linux. We will not discuss Xen itself (the Xen project has
<uri link="http://xen.org/support/documentation.html">decent documentation</uri>
available) nor will we talk about specialized setups that might be very
interesting for Xen setups but are not Xen-related (like exporting Portage
through NFS, booting Linux using PXE, etc.)
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Preparing Domain0</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
<e>Domain0</e> is the primary domain under Xen, hosting the host operating
system which governs all other domains. In this chapter we will prepare an
existing Gentoo installation to become the host operating system in this domain
and build the Xen-powered kernel so that Gentoo is ready to host other Xen
domains.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Rebuilding the Gentoo Installation?</title>
<body>

<p>
A dramatic change that might be necessary is to rebuild the entire Gentoo
installation with a different <c>CFLAGS</c> setting. Guest operating systems
running under Xen might otherwise see major performance degradation. If you,
however, are planning on checking out Xen rather than installing it for
production use and are not terribly fond of rebuilding all programs, you can
skip this step. In this case you will notice performance degradation but you
will still be able to use Xen.
</p>

<impo>
It is advised that, if you change your <c>CFLAGS</c> and build your system with
a gcc lower than version 4, you do not have <c>-Os</c> set as it has been
reported to produce broken code.
</impo>

<pre caption="Editing the CFLAGS and rebuild the Gentoo installation">
~# <i>nano -w /etc/make.conf</i>
<comment>(Add -mno-tls-direct-seg-refs ONLY if you have a 32-bit dom0)</comment>
<comment>(You don't need this flag if you have a 64-bit dom0)</comment>
CFLAGS="-O2 -march=pentium4 -pipe <i>-mno-tls-direct-seg-refs</i>"

~# <i>emerge -e world</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you boot your system using an initial ramdisk (initrd) you need to
rebuild the initrd as well (which is best done by running all steps you would do
when you rebuild your kernel).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing Xen</title>
<body>

<p>
Xen actually contains many components, so you'll need to install a few
packages.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing Xen">
~# <i>emerge xen xen-tools xen-sources</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Building the Kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
Next we'll build the Linux kernel with Xen support. This kernel, whose sources
are available at <path>/usr/src/linux-2.6.x.z-xen</path>, will be our main
running kernel (i.e. the one running domain 0). In the <c>XEN</c> section you'll
find drivers for all kinds of input/output, each driver having a <e>backend</e>
and <e>frontend</e> implementation available. For the domain 0 kernel you need
to select the <e>backend</e> implementation: these are used by the other
domains (who use the <e>frontend</e> drivers) to communicate directly with
the hardware.
</p>

<p>
Of course, don't forget to select <c>Xen-compatible</c> at <c>Processor type and
features</c>. If you're wondering about networking: each interface in a domain
has a point-to-point link to an interface on domain 0 (called
<path>vifX.Y</path> where X is the domain number and Y the Yth interface of that
domain), so you can configure your network the way you want (bridging, NAT,
etc.)
</p>

<pre caption="Enabling Xen Support for i386 Kernels">
Processor type and features  ---&gt;
      Subarchitecture Type (Xen-compatible)
</pre>

<pre caption="Enabling Xen Support for x86_64 Kernels">
Processor type and features  ---&gt;
      Subarchitecture Type (PC-compatible)
  [*] Enable Xen compatible kernel
  [*] Support for hot-pluggable CPUs
</pre>

<pre caption="Domain-0 Kernel Config">
Bus options (PCI etc.)  ---&gt;
  [*] PCI support
  [ ]   Xen PCI Frontend Debugging

Networking  ---&gt;
  Networking options  ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; 802.1d Ethernet Bridging
    <comment>Only required by bridged networking.</comment>

XEN  ---&gt;
  [*] Privileged Guest (domain 0)
  &lt;*&gt; Backend driver support
  &lt;*&gt;   Block-device backend driver
  &lt;*&gt;   Network-device backend driver
  &lt;*&gt;   PCI-device backend driver
           PCI Backend Mode (Virtual PCI) ---&gt;
  [*] Scrub memory before freeing it to Xen
  [*] Disable serial port drivers
      Xen version compatibility (3.0.4 and later)
</pre>

<pre caption="Domain-U Kernel Config">
Bus options (PCI etc.)  ---&gt;
  [ ] PCI support

Device Drivers  ---&gt;
  SCSI device support  ---&gt;
    &lt; &gt; SCSI device support
    <comment>Disabling SCSI support frees up the /dev/sd* device names
    for use as Xen virtual block devices.</comment>

XEN  ---&gt;
  [ ] Privileged Guest (domain 0)
  &lt;*&gt; Block-device frontend driver
  &lt;*&gt; Network-device frontend driver
  [*] Scrub memory before freeing it to Xen
  [*] Disable serial port drivers
      Xen version compatibility (3.0.4 and later)
</pre>

<p>
A nice hint is to have the kernel make process store its intermediate object
files elsewhere so that you can reuse the same kernel tree to build different
configurations:
</p>

<pre caption="Building the Kernel">
~# <i>mkdir -p ~/build/dom0 ~/build/domU</i>
~# <i>make O=~/build/dom0 menuconfig</i>
<comment>(Configure the kernel)</comment>
~# <i>make O=~/build/dom0 &amp;&amp; make O=~/build/dom0 modules_install</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once the kernel is built you'll find the kernel image immediately in the
build directory (not inside <path>arch/</path> or any other directory) called
<path>vmlinuz</path>. Copy it to <path>/boot</path> and then configure your
bootloader to use the Xen hypervisor (one of the components installed
previously) which is stored as <path>/boot/xen.gz</path>. In the bootloader
configuration, add your newly built kernel as the kernel that Xen should
boot. For instance, for GRUB:
</p>

<pre caption="GRUB Configuration for Xen">
title Xen 3.0 / Gentoo Linux 2.6.x.y
root (hd0,0)
kernel /boot/xen.gz
module /boot/kernel-2.6.x.y-xen0 root=/dev/sda3
</pre>

<p>
Now reboot your system into Xen. Once you are booted, you need to load the Xen
daemon:
</p>

<pre caption="Loading the Xen daemon">
~# <i>/etc/init.d/xend start</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now check if you can do whatever you normally do on your system. If this is the
case, you can edit your bootloader configuration to always boot into Xen and add
the Xen deamon to the default runlevel so that it is started automatically
next time you boot.
</p>

<note>
If you wish to start guest domains automatically on boot add <c>xendomains</c>
to the default runlevel as well and create a symlink in
<path>/etc/xen/auto/</path> to the Xen configuration files for the domains
you wish to start.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Creating an Unpriviledged Domain</title>
<section>
<title>Building the Kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
Go to the Xen-powered Linux kernel source and update the configuration. It is
wise to keep as many topics as possible similar to the main kernel except the
<c>XEN</c> settings where drivers should now have their <e>frontend</e>
implementation selected instead of the <e>backend</e>. Then build the kernel
and place the resulting <path>vmlinuz</path> file where you want (we assume this
is <path>/mnt/data/xen/kernel</path>):
</p>

<pre caption="Building the guest kernel">
~# <i>make O=~/build/domU</i>
~# <i>cp ~/build/domU/vmlinuz /mnt/data/xen/kernel/kernel-2.6.x.y-xen</i>
</pre>

<p>
It is also possible to create a single kernel image for both the administrative
domain and the unpriviledged domain. More information about this can be found
in the Xen user manual.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Creating the Domain Disks</title>
<body>

<p>
For best performance, it is best to dedicate a partition (or logical volume) to
a domain rather than a file based filesystem. However, if you are going to use
Xen primarily for tests using a file based filesystem does have its advantages
(especially regarding maintenance).
</p>

<p>
You can create a file based filesystem using <c>dd</c> and <c>mke2fs</c> (or
any other file system creation tool). For instance, to create a 2Gbyte ext3
filesystem:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a file based filesystem">
~# <i>dd if=/dev/zero of=/mnt/data/xen/disks/ext3root.img bs=1M count=2048</i>
~# <i>mke2fs -j /mnt/data/xen/disks/ext3root.img</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring a Domain</title>
<body>

<p>
Next we create a Xen configuration file for a domain. You can store these
configuration files where you want, for instance at
<path>/mnt/data/xen/configs</path>. As an example, we create a configuration
file for a small Gentoo environment which uses the disk image we created
previously:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a domain configuration file">
~# <i>nano -w /mnt/data/xen/configs/gentoo</i>

kernel = "/mnt/data/xen/kernel/kernel-2.6.x.y-xen"
memory = 512
name   = "gentoo"
<comment>(Map the disk image to the virtual /dev/sda1)</comment>
disk   = ['file:/mnt/data/xen/disks/ext3root.img,sda1,w']
root   = "/dev/sda1 ro"
</pre>

<p>
If you are using a block device (such as an lvm volume or partition) for
the disk use 'phy:' instead of 'file:' and leave off /dev. For example:
</p>

<pre caption="Using a block device">
<comment>(LVM Volume)</comment>
disk = [ 'phy:lvm/xen-guest-root,sda1,w' ]

<comment>(Physical Partition)</comment>
disk = [ 'phy:sdb6,sda1,w' ]
</pre>

<p>
You can find example configuration files in <path>/etc/xen</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Launching the New Domain</title>
<body>

<p>
Now we're all set and we can launch the new domain. If the disk image contained
an operating system, we could just create and attach the domain using the
<c>xm</c> command (Xen manager):
</p>

<pre caption="Creating and starting a new domain">
~# <i>xm create /mnt/data/xen/configs/gentoo -c</i>
</pre>

<p>
The domain would be booted inside the terminal in which you executed the
command. However, in our case, the disk image is empty so the domain won't boot
up in anything useful. To fix this, you can loop-mount the image and install
Gentoo as you're used to.
</p>

<p>
If you want to disconnect from the domain, press <path>Ctrl+]</path>. You can
always reconnect to the domains' console using <c>xm console gentoo</c>.
However, there is only one console per domain, so only use it when you can't
access the domain otherwise (for instance, through SSH).
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Networking on Unpriviledged Domains</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Xen supports at least two ways of configuring your (virtual) network:
<e>routed</e> and <e>bridged</e>.
</p>

<p>
When selecting the <e>routed</e> approach, the interface inside your
unpriviledged domain is connected to the virtual interface on your
administrative domain. On your administrative domain (domain 0), the virtual
interface is linked together with <path>eth0</path>. The
interface inside your unpriviledged domain should have an IP address on the same
network as the interface on the administrative domain. Any communication to
that IP address can only occur from the administrative domain, unless you set
up specific routing rules.
</p>

<p>
When selecting the <e>bridged</e> approach, your default network interface on
the administrative domain becomes a bridge which accepts connections to the
virtual domains as well as to the IP address your administrative domain has.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Regular Routed Interfaces</title>
<body>

<p>
Before you set up the interface on your unpriviledged domain, make sure that
Xen's <path>netloop</path> and <path>netbk</path> drivers are loaded. A quick
hint: if you have <path>netloop</path> as a module, load it with
<c>nloopbacks=0</c> so that it doesn't create pointless interfaces to the
loopback device. Then, edit your domain configuration file and add a <c>vif</c>
instruction to it.
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring a virtual interface">
~# <i>nano -w /mnt/data/xen/configs/gentoo</i>

<comment>(Add the vif instruction)</comment>
vif    = [ 'ip=192.168.1.101, vifname=veth1' ]
</pre>

<p>
In the above example, the interface will be created for the unpriviledged domain
(in which it will be called <path>eth0</path>) and Xen will ensure that address
192.168.1.101 will be reachable from the administrative domain through interface
<path>veth1</path>.
</p>

<p>
This doesn't mean that the virtual <path>eth0</path> interface will
automatically have IP 192.168.1.101 assigned to it, but rather that, if you
don't give it that IP, it will not be connected with the administrative domain
and thus cannot be reached.
</p>

<p>
Now edit <path>/etc/xen/xend-config.sxp</path> as follows to select routed
network configuration:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing xend-config.sxp">
~# <i>nano -w /etc/xen/xend-config.sxp</i>

<comment>(Comment out the following lines)</comment>
<i>#</i>(network-script network-bridge)
<i>#</i>(vif-script vif-bridge)

<comment>(Enable the following lines)</comment>
(network-script network-route)
(vif-script vif-route)
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bridged Interfaces</title>
<body>

<p>
Unlike the routed interfaces you now need to load the <path>netloop</path>
driver with <c>nloopbacks=1</c> (or higher) as the additional loopback devices
are used to create the bridge. For the other modules you still need the
<path>netbk</path> module as well as briding functionality (<path>bridge</path>
module if build as such).
</p>

<p>
Now edit your virtual domain and add the <c>vif</c> construct:
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring a virtual interface">
~# <i>nano -w /mnt/data/xen/configs/gentoo</i>

<comment>(Add the vif instruction)</comment>
vif    = [ 'ip=192.168.1.101, vifname=veth0' ]
</pre>

<p>
Next edit <path>/etc/xen/xend-config.sxp</path> as follows to select bridged
network configuration:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing xend-config.sxp">
~# <i>nano -w /etc/xen/xend-config.sxp</i>

<comment>(Enable the following lines)</comment>
(network-script network-bridge)
(vif-script vif-bridge)

<comment>(Comment out the following lines if not done already)</comment>
<i>#</i> (network-script network-route)
<i>#</i> (vif-script vif-route)
</pre>

<p>
By default, the bridge will contain whatever interface is configured to be the
default interface (the device that is listed under the default route through
<c>ip route list</c>). If you want to alter this behavior, edit the
<path>xend-config.sxp</path> as follows:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing xend-config.sxp to change bridge configuration">
~# <i>nano -w /etc/xen/xend-config.sxp</i>

<comment>(Edit the network-script line)</comment>
(network-script <i>'</i>network-bridge <i>netdev=eth0 bridge=xenbr0 vifnum=0'</i>)
</pre>

<p>
Once the configuration is done, restart the <c>xend</c> init script to have Xen
build the bridge:
</p>

<pre caption="Restarting the xend daemon">
~# <i>/etc/init.d/xend restart</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Further Resources</title>
<section>
<title>Xen Documentation</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.xen.org/support/documentation.html">Official Xen
    documentation</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://wiki.xen.org/">Xen Wiki</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Xen Tools</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://virt-manager.org/">app-emulation/virt-manager</uri>
    is a graphical tool for administering virtual machines
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
