<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/xfce-config.xml,v 1.43 2012/06/12 09:47:06 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>The Xfce Configuration Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide provides an extensive introduction to Xfce, a fast, lightweight,
full-featured desktop environment.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>11</version>
<date>2012-06-12</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>The Xfce desktop environment</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.xfce.org">Xfce</uri> is a fast, lightweight desktop
environment for Unix-like operating systems. It is designed for productivity,
and is quite configurable while still adhering to the <uri
link="http://www.freedesktop.org">Freedesktop</uri> specifications.
</p>

<p>
Unlike heavier desktop environments, such as <uri
link="http://www.gnome.org">Gnome</uri> and <uri
link="http://www.kde.org">KDE</uri>, Xfce uses far fewer system resources.
Additionally, it offers greater modularity and fewer dependencies; it takes up
less space on your hard disk and takes less time to install.
</p>

<p>
This guide will not only show you how to install and configure a minimal Xfce
environment, but will also explore options to create a full-featured desktop in
keeping with the Xfce philosophy: light, fast, and modular.
</p>

<p>
The last part of this guide lists a few commands to run after upgrading to Xfce
4.8, so be sure to follow them if you are upgrading from an older version.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Installing Xfce</title>
<section>
<title>The basics</title>
<body>

<p>
First, make sure you've configured Xorg as shown in the <uri
link="/doc/en/xorg-config.xml">X Server Configuration Howto</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Next, double-check your USE flags in <path>/etc/make.conf</path>; you'll
probably at least want <c>USE="-gnome -kde -minimal -qt4 dbus jpeg lock session
startup-notification thunar udev X"</c>.
</p>

<p>
Now that you've set your <c>USE</c> variables in
<path>/etc/make.conf</path>, it's time to install Xfce.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing Xfce">
# <i>emerge -avt xfce4-meta</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next, add your regular user(s) to the <c>cdrom</c>, <c>cdrw</c>,
and <c>usb</c> groups, so that they can mount and use devices such as cameras,
optical drives, and USB sticks.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding users to the hardware groups">
<comment>(Replace username with your actual user)</comment>
# <i>for x in cdrom cdrw usb ; do gpasswd -a username $x ; done</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next, update your environment variables:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating environment variables">
# <i>env-update &amp;&amp; source /etc/profile</i>
</pre>

<p>
You'll also need a graphical terminal so that you can continue working with your
new desktop environment. <c>x11-terms/terminal</c> is a good choice, as it's
made specifically for Xfce. Install Terminal as shown:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing Terminal">
# <i>emerge x11-terms/terminal</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring Xfce</title>
<section>
<title>Starting Xfce</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that Xfce is now installed, we'll configure it to be the default desktop
environment when we issue the <c>startx</c> command. Exit your root shell and
log on as a regular user.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting Xfce as the default desktop environment">
$ <i>echo "exec startxfce4" > ~/.xinitrc</i>
</pre>

<note>
If you have ConsoleKit installed, your <path>~/.xinitrc</path> should instead
contain <c>exec startxfce4 --with-ck-launch</c>. Otherwise, some of your
applications may stop working. You'll also need to add consolekit to the
default runlevel by running the following command as root: <c>rc-update add
consolekit default</c>.
</note>

<p>
Now start your graphical environment by typing <c>startx</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting Xfce">
$ <i>startx</i>
</pre>

<p>
Congratulations, and welcome to your new Xfce desktop environment. Go ahead,
explore it a bit. Then continue reading to learn how you can configure Xfce to
suit your needs.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sessions &amp; startup</title>
<body>

<p>
If you've installed (or plan to install) popular Gnome or KDE applications such
as <c>k3b</c>, <c>nautilus</c>, <c>kmail</c>, <c>evolution</c>, etc. then you
should make sure that Xfce launches the appropriate services for these at
startup. Navigate to Menu --> Settings --> Sessions &amp; Startup. On the
"Advanced" tab, select the appropriate checkbox. This might slightly increase
Xfce startup times, but it decreases load times for KDE and Gnome applications.
</p>

<p>
Xfce has the ability to save your session settings and running programs from the
"General" tab in the Sessions &amp; Startup menu. They can be automatically
saved when you logout, or Xfce can ask you each time. This feature is
particularly useful for undoing configuration mistakes. Accidentally killed a
panel? Just select "No" when prompted to save your current session, and the next
time you start Xfce, your old desktop is restored. Want to automatically launch
your open webbrowser, terminal, and email client the next time you login? Just
save your session before logging out.
</p>

<p>
You've now got a basic working environment installed and configured. But if
you're interested in doing more, then continue reading!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Additional Applications</title>
<section>
<title>Panel plugins</title>
<body>

<p>
In this chapter, we'll discuss some useful plugins and applications for everyday
use within Xfce.
</p>

<p>
There are many plugins for the panel available in Portage; see for yourself with
<c>emerge --search xfce</c>. Though for the most part their names are
self-explanatory, a few deserve extra attention, as they are quite helpful. To
use them, simply <c>emerge</c> them. They'll be added to the list of available
items in the "Add New Items" menu shown when you right-click on the panel.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>xfce4-battery-plugin</c> is perfect for laptop users. It displays battery
    percentage, time remaining, power source (AC or battery), fan status,
    warnings, and can even be configured to execute commands at certain power
    levels. This feature can be used to put the laptop into hibernate mode when
    the battery is almost exhausted.
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>xfce4-verve-plugin</c> is a small command line embedded into the panel.
    It's quicker than opening up another terminal when you want to run a
    command.
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>xfce4-mount-plugin</c> gives you a handy method of mounting devices
    listed in <path>/etc/fstab</path> just by clicking your mouse
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>xfce4-sensors-plugin</c> lets you monitor your hardware sensors, such as
    CPU temperature, fan RPM, hard drive temp, motherboard voltage, and more
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Useful programs</title>
<body>

<p>
We should now <c>emerge</c> some useful applications and utilities:
<c>xfce4-mixer</c>, <c>xfce4-taskmanager</c>, <c>xfwm4-themes</c>, <c>orage</c>,
<c>leafpad</c>, <c>xfce4-power-manager</c>, <c>x11-terms/terminal</c>, and
<c>thunar</c>.
</p>

<p>
<c>xfce4-mixer</c> is a volume control for your sound card. It can also be run
as a panel applet, giving you fast access to playback volume.
<c>xfce4-taskmanager</c> displays a list of all running programs, and the CPU
and memory consumption each one takes up. By right-clicking an item, you can
kill a misbehaving application, pause and restart it, or even alter its runtime
priority, which lets you fine-tune how much of a demand it puts on your system's
resources. 
</p>

<p>
<c>xfwm4-themes</c> adds several window manager themes. You may want to add a
more full-coverage icon theme such as <c>tango-icon-theme</c> just to round out
your desktop.
</p>

<p>
<c>orage</c> is a simple, handy calendar. <c>leafpad</c> is a barebones text
editor that starts up extremely quickly.
</p>

<p>
<c>xfce4-power-manager</c> is an application to monitor and manage power usage.
This is especially important for laptops! The power manager allows you to adjust
screen brightness, choose maximum performance or battery-saving modes, and setup
hibernate, suspend, and shutdown actions when the lid is shut or buttons are
pressed. You can set <uri
link="http://goodies.xfce.org/projects/applications/xfce4-power-manager">xfce4-power-manager</uri>
to warn you when your battery reaches certain levels, or even turn off your
machine. The application comes with a couple of helpful panel plugins to display
battery/charging status, and a brightness control.
</p>

<p>
<c>x11-terms/terminal</c> is an X11 terminal emulator, far more configurable and
useful than the barebones <c>xterm</c>. <c>terminal</c> supports Unicode text,
color schemes, pseudo-transparency and hardware-accelerated transparency via
Xfce's built-in compositor, all out-of-the-box. Just make sure that the default
action on the terminal launcher of your panel runs
<path>/usr/bin/Terminal</path> instead of <path>xterm</path>. Right-click the
launcher and choose "Properties" to change the command.
</p>

<p>
<c>thunar</c> is Xfce's default graphical file manager. It's fast yet quite
powerful, can support several plugins for even more functionality; just install
them with <c>emerge</c>. Let's take a look:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>thunar-archive-plugin</c> lets you create and extract archive files using
    the right-click menu. It provides a handy <uri
    link="http://goodies.xfce.org/projects/thunar-plugins/thunar-archive-plugin">front-end</uri>
    for graphical archiving applications such as <c>xarchiver</c> and
    <c>file-roller</c>.
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>tumbler</c> lets you preview certain types of files from within Thunar,
    such as images and fonts.
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>thunar-volman</c> automatically <uri
    link="http://goodies.xfce.org/projects/thunar-plugins/thunar-volman">manages</uri>
    removable media and drives.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Next, let's see about adding some useful but lightweight desktop applications,
in keeping with Xfce's philosophy.
</p>

<p>
Though <c>leafpad</c> is nice enough as a basic text editor, if you need a
full-featured word processor but don't want the bloat of OpenOffice, try
emerging <c>abiword</c>. <uri link="http://www.abisource.com">AbiWord</uri> is
lighter, faster, and is completely interoperable with industry-standard document
types.
</p>

<p>
Need a nice email client/newsreader that isn't as demanding as
<c>thunderbird</c> or <c>evolution</c>? Try emerging <c>claws-mail</c>.
</p>

<p>
For your internet chat needs, <c>irssi</c> is an excellent, tiny, incredibly
configurable IRC client that runs in your terminal. If you prefer a compact
all-in-one client that handles nearly all chat protocols, you may want to
<c>emerge pidgin</c>.
</p>

<p>
If you need movie and music players, look no further than <c>mplayer</c> and
<uri link="/proj/en/desktop/sound/decibel.xml">decibel-audio-player</uri>. They
can play most every media format available quite nicely.
</p>

<p>
Finally, you'll need a webbrowser. Nearly all graphical webbrowsers require more
resources than most of your other desktop applications. Still, <c>firefox</c>
and <c>midori</c> are always good choices. Alternatively, you may find
<c>opera</c> to be quite fast. However, <c>opera</c> is not available on as many
processor architectures as <c>firefox</c>, and it has more dependencies unless
you override them with a few USE flags.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding a webbrowser">
<comment>(Installing Mozilla Firefox)</comment>
# <i>emerge firefox</i>
<comment>(Installing Midori)</comment>
# <i>emerge midori</i>
<comment>(Installing Opera)</comment>
# <i>echo "www-client/opera gtk -kde" >> /etc/portage/package.use</i>
# <i>emerge opera</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now that we've explored some good suggestions for rounding out your desktop
applications, let's see what else we can do to enhance your Xfce experience.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Graphical login</title>
<body>

<p>
Remember when we added <c>startxfce4</c> to our <path>~/.xinitrc</path>? All you
have to do to get into your desktop is type <c>startx</c> after logging in. This
is fine if you prefer a completely text-based boot and login, but let's use a
display manager that will automatically start Xfce after booting (so that you
can login graphically).
</p>

<p>
First, let's make sure Xfce loads at boot:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding xdm to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add xdm default</i>
</pre>

<p>
We aren't quite finished yet. We have to pick a display manager and set the
appropriate variable. Though there are a few choices available in Portage, for
this guide, we'll stick with <uri link="http://slim.berlios.de">SLiM</uri>, the
Simple Login Manager.
</p>

<p>
<c>slim</c> is speedy and lightweight, with minimal dependencies. Perfect for
Xfce!
</p>

<pre caption="Installing SLiM">
# <i>emerge -avt slim</i>
</pre>

<note>
The <c>branding</c> USE flag will pull in the <c>slim-themes</c> package, which
will give you an assortment of login themes, including a Gentoo Linux theme.
</note>

<p>
Then edit the DISPLAYMANAGER variable in <path>/etc/conf.d/xdm</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/conf.d/xdm">
DISPLAYMANAGER="slim"
</pre>

<p>
SLiM can automatically start your Xfce session if you add
<c>XSESSION="Xfce4"</c> to <path>/etc/env.d/90xsession</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting XSESSION">
# <i>echo XSESSION=\"Xfce4\" > /etc/env.d/90xsession</i>
# <i>env-update &amp;&amp; source /etc/profile</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Beautifying your desktop</title>
<body>

<p>
A little customization of your desktop's appearance can go a long way. Xfce has
all the options you'd expect from a modern desktop environment, font
antialiasing settings, color schemes, dozens of window decorations, themes, and
more. If these aren't enough, it's easy to install third-party themes, icon
sets, mouse cursor themes, and wallpapers.
</p>

<p>
A selection of nice Gentoo wallpapers in a variety of resolutions are hosted on
the <uri link="/main/en/graphics.xml">Gentoo website</uri>.  If you're looking
for icon sets and complete Xfce themes, <uri
link="http://www.xfce-look.org/">Xfce-Look</uri> has a huge collection. The
important thing to remember about any third-party eyecandy you download is that
it will usually first need to be unpacked and then installed to the proper
directory. Icon sets go in <path>/usr/share/icons/</path>, and themes go to
<path>/usr/share/themes/</path>; use these directories when you want all users
to be able to access themes and icon sets. Individual users can install themes
and icon sets to <path>~/.themes/</path> and <path>~/.icons/</path>.
</p>

<p>
If you installed SLiM as your display manager, there are lots of themes in the
<c>slim-themes</c> package available in Portage. Also, be sure to check the SLiM
<uri link="http://slim.berlios.de/themes01.php">themes page</uri> for more
themes. Creating your own SLiM theme is fairly easy; just read the <uri
link="http://slim.berlios.de/themes_howto.php">Themes HowTo</uri>. Gentoo also
ships a <c>slim-themes</c> package that you can <c>emerge</c>.
</p>

<p>
Finally, Xfce has its own built-in compositor to manage window transparency.
This option can be found in Menu --> Settings --> Window Manager. For best
performance, you will need to be running a graphics card with drivers that
support hardware-accelerated rendering. Make sure you emerged <c>xfwm4</c> with
the <c>xcomposite</c> USE flag. Next, you will need to enable compositing in
<path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path> by adding the following section:
</p>

<pre caption="Enabling composite in xorg.conf">
Section "Extensions"
    Option  "Composite"  "Enable"
EndSection
</pre>

<p>
This is the bare minimum configuration required for Xfce and Xorg-X11. However,
setting up hardware-accelerated rendering depends on your individual graphics
card, and is beyond the scope of this guide. Please see the other guides in the
<uri link="/doc/en/index.xml?catid=desktop">Desktop Documentation
Resources</uri> list to learn about configuring hardware-accelerated rendering
for your graphics card.
</p>

<p>
Once you've finished setting up a beautiful Xfce desktop, the next thing to do
is take a picture of it to share with other folks! Just install
<c>xfce4-screenshooter</c> and post your pictures somewhere for all to admire.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Summary</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Congratulations on making it this far! You've installed and configured a speedy
desktop environment with a solid suite of applications for your computing
needs.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Upgrading Xfce</title>
<body>

<p>
If you're upgrading Xfce from a pre-4.8 version to 4.8 or newer, then you will
need to remove your old cached sessions and profiles as they are incompatible
with the 4.8 release (and later releases). For each of your users, run the
following commands to remove your old incompatible cached sessions and profile:
</p>

<pre caption="Deleting old sessions from the cache">
$ <i>rm -r ~/.cache/sessions</i>
$ <i>rm -r ~/.config/xfce*</i>
$ <i>rm -r ~/.config/Thunar</i>
</pre>

<p>
Users will be greeted with a new and shiny interface, but will lose many of
their individual settings. Sadly, no migration of configuration(s) exist that we
know of.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Resources</title>
<body>

<p>
Need additional help on configuring and using Xfce? Need more lightweight
application suggestions? Try checking out:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">The Gentoo forums</uri></li>
  <li>#xfce on irc.freenode.net</li>
  <li>
    The installed help files and other documentation provided by Xfce:
    <path>/usr/share/xfce4/doc/C/index.html</path>. Just point your browser at
    it and start reading. There are even a lot of "hidden" configuration options
    detailed in the help files.
  </li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.xfce.org">Xfce's home page</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
