<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2005.1/hb-install-ppc-medium.xml,v 1.7 2006/02/22 05:46:45 fox2mike Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>5.3</version>
<date>2005-11-29</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Apple NewWorld Machines</th>
  <ti>
    Power/PowerPC microprocessors (G3, G4, G5) such as iMac, eMac, iBook
    PowerBook, Xserver, PowerMac
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Apple OldWorld machines</th>
  <ti>
    Apple Machines with an OpenFirmware revision less than 3, such as the Beige
    G3s, PCI PowerMacs and PCI PowerBooks.  PCI based Apple Clones should also 
    be supported.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Genesi's Pegasos</th>
  <ti>
    Pegasos I/II, Open Desktop Workstation
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>IBM</th>
  <ti>
    RS/6000, iSeries, pSeries
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Memory</th>
  <ti>At least 64 MB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Diskspace</th>
  <ti>1.5 GB (excluding swap space)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Swap space</th>
  <ti>At least 256 MB</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Be sure to read up on the <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-ppc-faq.xml">Gentoo 
PPC FAQ</uri> before you begin.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- Copy/paste of hb-install-x86-medium.xml, with s/x86/ppc/ -->
<!-- START -->
<section>
<title>The Gentoo Universal Installation CD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo Linux can be installed using a <e>stage3</e> tarball file.
Such a tarball is an archive that contains a minimal environment from
which you can successfully install Gentoo Linux onto your system.
</p>

<p>
Installations using a stage1 or stage2 tarball file are not documented in the
Gentoo Handbook - please read the <uri link="/doc/en/faq.xml#stage12">Gentoo
FAQ</uri> on these matters.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo Universal Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
An Installation CD is a bootable medium which contains a self-sustained Gentoo 
environment. It allows you to boot Linux from the CD. During the boot process 
your hardware is detected and the appropriate drivers are loaded. The Gentoo 
Installation CDs are maintained by Gentoo developers.
</p>

<p>
There currently are two Installation CDs available:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The Universal Installation CD contains everything you need to install 
    Gentoo. It provides stage3 files for common architectures, source code 
    for the extra applications you need to choose from and, of course, the 
    installation instructions for your architecture.
  </li>
  <li>
    The Minimal Installation CD contains only a minimal environment that allows 
    you to boot up and configure your network so you can connect to the 
    Internet. It does not contain any additional files and cannot be used 
    during the current installation approach.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Gentoo also provides a Package CD. This is not an Installation CD but an
additional resource that you can exploit during the installation of your Gentoo
system. It contains prebuilt packages (also known as the GRP set) that allow
you to easily and quickly install additional applications (such as
OpenOffice.org, KDE, GNOME, ...) immediately after the Gentoo installation and
right before you update your Portage tree.
</p>

<p>
The use of the Package CD is covered later in this document. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- STOP -->
<section>
<title>Download, Burn and Boot the Gentoo Universal Installation CD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Downloading and Burning the Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
You can download the Universal Installation CD (and, if you want to, the 
Packages CD as well) from one of our <uri 
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri>. The Installation CDs are located 
in the <path>releases/ppc/2005.1/installcd</path> directory;
the Package CDs are located in the 
<path>releases/ppc/2005.1/packagecd</path> directory.
</p>

<p>
Inside those directories you'll find ISO-files. Those are full CD images which
you can write on a CD-R.
</p>

<p>
After downloading the file, you can verify its integrity to see if it is 
corrupted or not:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    You can check its MD5 checksum and compare it with the MD5 checksum we 
    provide (for instance with the <c>md5sum</c> tool under Linux/Unix or 
    <uri link="http://www.etree.org/md5com.html">md5sum</uri> for Windows).
    Verifying MD5 checksums with Mac OS X is described in the <uri
    link="/doc/en/gentoo-ppc-faq.xml#doc_chap1">Gentoo PPC FAQ</uri>.
  </li>
  <li>
    You can verify the cryptographic signature that we provide. You need to
    obtain the public key we use (0x17072058) before you proceed though.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
To fetch our public key using the GnuPG application, run the following command:
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining the public key">
$ <i>gpg --keyserver subkeys.pgp.net --recv-keys 0x17072058</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now verify the signature:
</p>

<pre caption="Verify the cryptographic signature">
$ <i>gpg --verify &lt;signature file&gt; &lt;downloaded iso&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
To burn the downloaded ISO(s), you have to select raw-burning. How you
do this is highly program-dependent. We will discuss <c>cdrecord</c> and
<c>K3B</c> here; more information can be found in our <uri
link="/doc/en/faq.xml#isoburning">Gentoo FAQ</uri>.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    With cdrecord, you simply type <c>cdrecord dev=/dev/hdc &lt;downloaded iso
    file&gt;</c> (replace <path>/dev/hdc</path> with your CD-RW drive's device
    path).
  </li>
  <li>
    With K3B, select <c>Tools</c> &gt; <c>CD</c> &gt; <c>Burn Image</c>. Then
    you can locate your ISO file within the 'Image to Burn' area. Finally click
    <c>Start</c>.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Default: Booting the Installation CD with Yaboot</title>
<body>

<p>
On NewWorld machines place the Installation CD in the CD-ROM and reboot the 
system. When the system-start-bell sounds, simply hold down the 'C' until the
CD loads.
</p>

<p>
After the Installation CD loaded, you will be greeted by a friendly welcome 
message and a <e>boot:</e> prompt at the bottom of the screen.
</p>

<p>
At this prompt you are able to select a kernel for the subarchitecture you use.
We provide <c>G3</c>, <c>G4</c> and <c>G5</c>. All kernels are built with
support for multiple CPUs, but they will boot on single processor machines as
well.
</p>

<p>
You are also able to tweak some kernel options at this prompt. The following
table lists some of the available boot options you can add:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Boot Option</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>video</c></ti>
  <ti>
    This option takes one of the following vendor-specific tags:
    <c>radeonfb</c>, <c>rivafb</c>, <c>atyfb</c>, <c>aty128</c> or
    <c>ofonly</c>. You can follow this tag with the resolution and refreshrate
    you want to use. For instance <c>video=radeonfb:1280x1024@75</c>. If you are
    uncertain what to choose, <c>ofonly</c> will most certainly work.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>nol3</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Disables level 3 cache on some PowerBooks (needed for at least the 17&quot;)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>dofirewire</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Enables support for IEEE1394 (FireWire) devices, like external harddisks.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>dopcmcia</c></ti>
  <ti>
    If you want to use PCMCIA devices during your installation (like PCMCIA
    network cards) you have to enable this option.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
At this prompt, hit enter, and a complete Gentoo Linux environment will be
loaded from the CD. Continue with <uri link="#booted">And When You're
Booted...</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Alternative: Booting the Installation CD on a Pegasos</title>
<body>

<p>
On the Pegasos simply insert the CD and at the SmartFirmware boot-prompt type
<c>boot cd /boot/menu</c>. This will open a small bootmenu where you can choose
between several preconfigured video configs. If you need any special boot
options you can append them to the command-line. For instance <c>boot cd
/boot/pegasos video=radeonfb:1280x1024@75 mem=256M</c>.  The complete list of
kernel appends (in case something goes wrong and you need it) is preconfigured
in the kernel with <c>console=ttyS0,115200 console=tty0 init=/linuxrc
looptype=squashfs loop=/livecd.squashfs udev nodevfs cdroot root=/dev/ram0</c>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Alternative: Booting the Installation CD with BootX</title>
<body>

<p>
If you have an OldWorld Mac the bootable portion of the livecd can't be used.
The most simple solution is to use MacOS to bootstrap into a Linux environment
with a tool called BootX.  Boot floppies are being prepared for Macs without
MacOS, but they are not available at this time.
</p>

<p>
First, download <uri link="http://penguinppc.org/projects/bootx/">BootX</uri>
and unpack the archive.  Copy the the <c>BootX Extension</c> from the unpacked
archive into <c>Extensions Folder</c> and the BootX App Control Panel into
<c>Control Panels</c>, both of which are located in your MacOS System Folder.
Next, create a folder called "Linux Kernels" in your System folder and copy the
<c>G3G4</c> kernel from the CD to this folder.  Finally, copy <c>G3G4.igz</c> 
from the Installation CD <path>boot</path> folder into the MacOS 
<c>System Folder</c>.
</p>

<p>
To prepare BootX, start the BootX App Control Panel.  First select the Options
dialog and check <c>Use Specified RAM Disk</c> and select <c>G3G4.igz</c> from
your System Folder.  Continue back to the initial screen and ensure that the
ramdisk size is at least <c>32000</c>.  Finally, set the kernel arguments as
shown below:
</p>

<pre caption="BootX kernel arguments">
cdroot root=/dev/ram0 init=linuxrc loop=livecd.squashfs looptype=squashfs console=tty0 nodevfs udev
</pre>

<note>
The kernel parameters in the yaboot section above are also applicable here.
</note>

<p>
Check once more to make sure the settings are correct and then save the 
configuration.  This saves typing just in case it doesn't boot or something is
missing.  Press the Linux button at the top of the window to boot into the 
Installation CD and continue with <uri link="#booted">And When 
You're Booted...</uri>
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection id="booted">
<title>And When You're Booted...</title>
<body>

<p>
You will be greeted by a root ("#") prompt on the current console. You can also 
switch to other consoles by pressing Alt-F2, Alt-F3 and Alt-F4. Get 
back to the one you started on by pressing Alt-F1.  Probably you have to hit
Alt-fn-Fx on Apple machines.
</p>

<p>
If you are installing Gentoo on a system with a non-US keyboard, use
<c>loadkeys</c> to load the keymap for your keyboard. To list the available
keymaps, execute <c>ls /usr/share/keymaps/i386</c>.  On NewWorld machines or the
Pegasos do not use the keymaps in <path>ppc</path> or <path>mac</path> as they
are for ADB-based OldWorld machines.
</p>

<pre caption="Listing available keymaps">
<comment>(PPC uses x86 keymaps on most systems. The mac/ppc keymaps provided
 on the Installation CD are ADB keymaps and unusable with the Installation CD 
 kernel)</comment>
# <i>ls /usr/share/keymaps/i386</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now load the keymap of your choice:
</p>

<pre caption="Loading a keymap">
# <i>loadkeys be-latin1</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#hardware">Extra Hardware Configuration</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="hardware">
<title>Extra Hardware Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
When the Installation CD boots, it tries to detect all your hardware devices and
loads the appropriate kernel modules to support your hardware. In the
vast majority of cases, it does a very good job. However, in some cases, it may
not auto-load the kernel modules you need. If the PCI auto-detection missed some
of your system's hardware, you will have to load the appropriate kernel modules
manually. 
</p>

<p>
In the next example we try to load the <c>airport</c> module.  This module
supports only the old Airport cards (b-net).  AirportExtreme is not supported
under Linux:
</p>

<pre caption="Loading kernel modules">
# <i>modprobe airport</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Tweaking Hard Disk Performance</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are an advanced user, you might want to tweak the IDE hard disk
performance using <c>hdparm</c>. With the <c>-tT</c> options you can
test the performance of your disk (execute it several times to get a
more precise impression):
</p>

<pre caption="Testing disk performance">
# <i>hdparm -tT /dev/hda</i>
</pre>

<p>
To tweak, you can use any of the following examples (or experiment
yourself) which use <path>/dev/hda</path> as disk (substitute with your
disk):
</p>

<pre caption="Tweaking hard disk performance">
<comment>Activate DMA:</comment>                                       # <i>hdparm -d 1 /dev/hda</i>
<comment>Activate DMA + Safe Performance-enhancing Options:</comment>  # <i>hdparm -d 1 -A 1 -m 16 -u 1 -a 64 /dev/hda</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="useraccounts">
<title>Optional: User Accounts</title>
<body>

<p>
If you plan on giving other people access to your installation
environment or you want to chat using <c>irssi</c> without root privileges (for
security reasons), you need to create the necessary user accounts and change 
the root password.
</p>

<p>
To change the root password, use the <c>passwd</c> utility:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the root password">
# <i>passwd</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter your new password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter your password)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
To create a user account, we first enter their credentials, followed by
its password. We use <c>useradd</c> and <c>passwd</c> for these tasks.
In the next example, we create a user called &quot;john&quot;.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a user account">
# <i>useradd -m -G users john</i>
# <i>passwd john</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter john's password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter john's password)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
You can change your user id from root to the newly created user by using
<c>su</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing user id">
# <i>su - john</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Viewing Documentation while Installing</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to view the Gentoo Handbook (either from-CD or online) during the
installation, make sure you have created a user account (see <uri
link="#useraccounts">Optional: User Accounts</uri>). Then press <c>Alt-F2</c> to
go to a new terminal and log in.
</p>

<p>
If you want to view the documentation on the CD you can immediately run
<c>links2</c> or even <c>links -g</c> for a graphical framebuffer browser to
read it:
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the on-CD documentation">
# <i>links2 /mnt/cdrom/docs/html/index.html</i>
</pre>

<p>
However, it is preferred that you use the online Gentoo Handbook as it will be
more recent than the one provided on the CD. You can view it using <c>links2</c>
as well, but only after having completed the <e>Configuring your Network</e>
chapter (otherwise you won't be able to go on the Internet to view the
document):
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the Online Documentation">
# <i>links2 http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-ppc.xml</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can go back to your original terminal by pressing <c>Alt-F1</c>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Starting the SSH Daemon</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to allow other users to access your computer during the
Gentoo installation (perhaps because those users are going to help you
install Gentoo, or even do it for you), you need to create a user
account for them and perhaps even provide them with your root password 
(<e>only</e> do that <e>if</e> you <b>fully trust</b> that user).
</p>

<p>
To fire up the SSH daemon, execute the following command:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the SSH daemon">
# <i>/etc/init.d/sshd start</i>
</pre>

<p>
To be able to use sshd, you first need to set up your networking. Continue with
the chapter on <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">Configuring your Network</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
