<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2005.1/hb-install-network.xml,v 1.3 2006/02/10 17:46:57 neysx Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>5.1</version>
<date>2005-08-08</date>

<section>
<title>Do you need Networking?</title>
<subsection>
<title>Who can do without?</title>
<body>

<p>
Generally, you don't need a working network connection to install Gentoo using
the Universal Installation CD. However, there are some circumstances where you
do want to have a working Internet connection:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The stage3 files that are stored in the Universal Installation CD do not 
    match your architecture and you need to download the correct stage3 file
  </li>
  <li>
    You need to install a specific networking application that will allow you to
    connect to the Internet which isn't available on the Universal Installation 
    CD but is supported by the Installation CD (i.e. you can connect to the 
    Internet using the Installation CD but the necessary sources are not 
    available on the Installation CD)
  </li>
  <li>
    You want remote assistance during the installation (using SSH or through
    direct conversations using IRC)
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Do I need Networking?</title>
<body>

<p>
To find out if the stage3 file for your architecture is available, take a look
inside <path>/mnt/cdrom/stages</path> and check if one of the available stages
matches your architecture. If not, you can still opt for a stage3 file of an
architecture compatible with yours.
</p>

<p>
If you on the other hand want to use a stage3 file optimized for your
architecture and the stage3 file of your choice is not available, then you will
need networking to download the appropriate stage3 file.
</p>

<p>
So, if you don't need networking, you can skip the rest of this chapter and 
continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=4">Preparing the Disks</uri>.
Otherwise, continue with the networking configuration sections below.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Automatic Network Detection</title>
<subsection>
<title>Maybe it just works?</title>
<body>

<p>
If your system is plugged into an Ethernet network with a DHCP server, it is 
very likely that your networking configuration has already been set up 
automatically for you. If so, you should be able to take advantage of the many
included network-aware commands on the Installation CD such as <c>ssh</c>, 
<c>scp</c>, <c>ping</c>, <c>irssi</c>, <c>wget</c> and <c>links</c>, among 
others.
</p>

<p>
If networking has been configured for you, the <c>/sbin/ifconfig</c> command
should list some network interfaces besides lo, such as eth0:
</p>

<pre caption="/sbin/ifconfig for a working network configuration">
# <i>/sbin/ifconfig</i>
<comment>(...)</comment>
eth0      Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:50:BA:8F:61:7A
          inet addr:192.168.0.2  Bcast:192.168.0.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
          inet6 addr: fe80::50:ba8f:617a/10 Scope:Link
          UP BROADCAST RUNNING MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:1498792 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:1284980 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:1984 txqueuelen:100
          RX bytes:485691215 (463.1 Mb)  TX bytes:123951388 (118.2 Mb)
          Interrupt:11 Base address:0xe800 
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Configure any Proxies</title>
<body>

<p>
If you access the Internet through a proxy, you might need to set up proxy
information during the installation. It is very easy to define a proxy: you just
need to define a variable which contains the proxy server information.
</p>

<p>
In most cases, you can just define the variables using the server hostname. As
an example, we assume the proxy is called <c>proxy.gentoo.org</c> and the port 
is <c>8080</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Defining proxy servers">
<comment>(If the proxy filters HTTP traffic)</comment>
# <i>export http_proxy="http://proxy.gentoo.org:8080"</i>
<comment>(If the proxy filters FTP traffic)</comment>
# <i>export ftp_proxy="ftp://proxy.gentoo.org:8080"</i>
<comment>(If the proxy filters RSYNC traffic)</comment>
# <i>export RSYNC_PROXY="proxy.gentoo.org:8080"</i>
</pre>

<p>
If your proxy requires a username and password, you should use the following
syntax for the variable:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding username/password to the proxy variable">
http://<i>username</i>:<i>password</i>@proxy.gentoo.org:8080
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Testing the Network</title>
<body>

<p>
You may want to try pinging your ISP's DNS server (found in
<path>/etc/resolv.conf</path>) and a Web site of your choice, just to make sure 
that your packets are reaching the net, DNS name resolution is working 
correctly, etc.
</p>

<pre caption="Further network testing">
# <i>ping -c 3 www.yahoo.com</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you are now able to use your network, you can skip the rest of this
section and continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=4">Preparing the
Disks</uri>. If not, read on.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Automatic Network Configuration</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
If the network doesn't work immediately, some installation media allow you to 
use <c>net-setup</c> (for regular or wireless networks), <c>adsl-setup</c> 
(for ADSL-users) or <c>pptp</c> (for PPTP-users - only available on x86).
</p>

<p>
If your installation medium does not contain any of these tools or your network
doesn't function yet, continue with <uri link="#doc_chap3">Manual Network 
Configuration</uri>.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Regular Ethernet users should continue with <uri
    link="#net-setup">Default: Using net-setup</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    ADSL users should continue with <uri link="#rp-pppoe">Alternative:
    Using RP-PPPoE</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    PPTP users should continue with <uri link="#pptp">Alternative:
    Using PPTP</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="net-setup">
<title>Default: Using net-setup</title>
<body>

<p>
The simplest way to set up networking if it didn't get configured
automatically is to run the <c>net-setup</c> script:
</p>

<pre caption="Running the net-setup script">
# <i>net-setup eth0</i>
</pre>

<p>
<c>net-setup</c> will ask you some questions about your network
environment. When all is done, you should have a working network
connection. Test your network connection as stated before. If the tests
are positive, congratulations! You are now ready to install Gentoo. Skip
the rest of this section and continue with <uri 
link="?part=1&amp;chap=4">Preparing the Disks</uri>.
</p>

<p>
If your network still doesn't work, continue with <uri link="#doc_chap3">Manual
Network Configuration</uri>.
</p>


</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="rp-pppoe">
<title>Alternative: Using RP-PPPoE</title>
<body>

<p>
Assuming you need PPPoE to connect to the internet, the Installation CD (any 
version) has made things easy for you by including <c>rp-pppoe</c>. Use the 
provided <c>adsl-setup</c> script to configure your connection. You will be 
prompted for the ethernet device that is connected to your adsl modem, your
username and password, the IPs of your DNS servers and if you need a basic 
firewall or not.
</p>

<pre caption="Using rp-pppoe">
# <i>adsl-setup</i>
# <i>adsl-start</i>
</pre>

<p>
If something goes wrong, double-check that you correctly typed your username and
password by looking at <path>/etc/ppp/pap-secrets</path> or 
<path>/etc/ppp/chap-secrets</path> and make sure you are using the right 
ethernet device. If your ethernet device doesn't exist, you will have to load
the appropriate network modules. In that case you should continue with 
<uri link="#doc_chap3">Manual Network Configuration</uri> as we explain how to
load the appropriate network modules there.
</p>

<p>
If everything worked, continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=4">Preparing the
Disks</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="pptp">
<title>Alternative: Using PPTP</title>
<body>

<note>
PPTP support is only available for x86
</note>

<p>
If you need PPTP support, you can use <c>pptpclient</c> which is provided by our
Installation CDs. But first you need to make sure that your configuration is 
correct. Edit <path>/etc/ppp/pap-secrets</path> or 
<path>/etc/ppp/chap-secrets</path> so it contains the correct username/password 
combination:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/ppp/chap-secrets">
# <i>nano -w /etc/ppp/chap-secrets</i>
</pre>

<p>
Then adjust <path>/etc/ppp/options.pptp</path> if necessary:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/ppp/options.pptp">
# <i>nano -w /etc/ppp/options.pptp</i>
</pre>

<p>
When all that is done, just run <c>pptp</c> (along with the options you couldn't
set in <path>options.pptp</path>) to connect the server:
</p>

<pre caption="Connection to a dial-in server">
# <i>pptp &lt;server ip&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=4">Preparing the Disks</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Manual Network Configuration</title>
<subsection>
<title>Loading the Appropriate Network Modules</title>
<body>

<p>
When the Installation CD boots, it tries to detect all your hardware devices and
loads the appropriate kernel modules (drivers) to support your hardware. In the
vast majority of cases, it does a very good job. However, in some cases,
it may not auto-load the kernel modules you need.
</p>

<p>
If <c>net-setup</c> or <c>adsl-setup</c> failed, then it is possible that
your network card wasn't found immediately. This means you may have to load
the appropriate kernel modules manually.
</p>

<p>
To find out what kernel modules we provide for networking, use
<c>ls</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Searching for provided modules">
# <i>ls /lib/modules/`uname -r`/kernel/drivers/net</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you find a driver for your network card, use <c>modprobe</c> to load
the kernel module:
</p>

<pre caption="Using modprobe to load a kernel module">
<comment>(As an example, we load the pcnet32 module)</comment>
# <i>modprobe pcnet32</i>
</pre>

<p>
To check if your network card is now detected, use <c>ifconfig</c>. A
detected network card would result in something like this:
</p>

<pre caption="Testing availability of your network card, successful">
# <i>ifconfig eth0</i>
eth0      Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr FE:FD:00:00:00:00  
          BROADCAST NOARP MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:0 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:0 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:0 
          RX bytes:0 (0.0 b)  TX bytes:0 (0.0 b)
</pre>

<p>
If however you receive the following error, the network card is not
detected:
</p>

<pre caption="Testing availability of your network card, failed">
# <i>ifconfig eth0</i>
eth0: error fetching interface information: Device not found
</pre>

<p>
If you have multiple network cards in your system they are named <e>eth0</e>,
<e>eth1</e>, etc. Make sure that the network card you want to use works well and
remember to use the correct naming throughout this document. We will assume that
the network card <e>eth0</e> is used.
</p>

<p>
Assuming that you now have a detected network card, you can 
retry <c>net-setup</c> or <c>adsl-setup</c> again (which should work 
now), but for the hardcore people amongst you we explain how to configure your 
network manually.
</p>

<p>
Select one of the following sections based on your network setup:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#install-dhcp">Using DHCP</uri> for automatic IP retrieval</li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#wireless">Preparing for Wireless Access</uri> if you have a
    wireless card
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#network_term">Understanding Network Terminology</uri> explains
    what you need to know about networking
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#ifconfig_route">Using ifconfig and route</uri> explains how to
    set up your networking manually
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="install-dhcp">
<title>Using DHCP</title>
<body>

<p>
DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) makes it possible to
automatically receive networking information (IP address, netmask,
broadcast address, gateway, nameservers etc.). This only works if you
have a DHCP server in your network (or if your provider provides a DHCP
service). To have a network interface receive this information automatically, 
use <c>dhcpcd</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Using dhcpcd">
# <i>dhcpcd eth0</i>
<comment>Some network admins require that you use the</comment>
<comment>hostname and domainname provided by the DHCP server.</comment>
<comment>In that case, use</comment>
# <i>dhcpcd -HD eth0</i>
</pre>

<p>
If this works (try pinging some internet server, like <uri
link="http://www.google.com">Google</uri>), then you are all set and
ready to continue. Skip the rest of this section and continue with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=4">Preparing the Disks</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="wireless">
<title>Preparing for Wireless Access</title>
<body>

<note>
Support for the <c>iwconfig</c> command is only available on x86, amd64 and ppc
Installation CDs. You can still get the extensions working otherwise 
by following the instructions of the
<uri link="ftp://ftp.linux-wlan.org/pub/linux-wlan-ng/README">linux-wlan-ng
project</uri>.
</note>

<p>
If you are using a wireless (802.11) card, you may need to configure your
wireless settings before going any further. To see the current wireless settings
on your card, you can use <c>iwconfig</c>. Running <c>iwconfig</c> might show
something like:
</p>

<pre caption="Showing the current wireless settings">
# <i>iwconfig eth0</i>
eth0      IEEE 802.11-DS  ESSID:"GentooNode"                                   
          Mode:Managed  Frequency:2.442GHz  Access Point: 00:09:5B:11:CC:F2    
          Bit Rate:11Mb/s   Tx-Power=20 dBm   Sensitivity=0/65535               
          Retry limit:16   RTS thr:off   Fragment thr:off                       
          Power Management:off                                                  
          Link Quality:25/10  Signal level:-51 dBm  Noise level:-102 dBm        
          Rx invalid nwid:5901 Rx invalid crypt:0 Rx invalid frag:0 Tx          
          excessive retries:237 Invalid misc:350282 Missed beacon:84            
</pre>

<note>
Some wireless cards may have a device name of <c>wlan0</c> or <c>ra0</c> instead
of <c>eth0</c>. Run <c>iwconfig</c> without any command-line parameters to
determine the correct device name.
</note>

<p>
For most users, there are only two settings that might be important to change,
the ESSID (aka wireless network name) or the WEP key. If the ESSID and Access
Point address listed are already that of your access point and you are not using
WEP, then your wireless is working. If you need to change your ESSID, or add a
WEP key, you can issue the following commands:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing ESSID and/or adding WEP key">
<comment>(This sets the network name to "GentooNode")</comment>
# <i>iwconfig eth0 essid GentooNode</i>

<comment>(This sets a hex WEP key)</comment>
# <i>iwconfig eth0 key 1234123412341234abcd</i>

<comment>(This sets an ASCII key - prefix it with "s:")</comment>
# <i>iwconfig eth0 key s:some-password</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can then confirm your wireless settings again by using <c>iwconfig</c>. 
Once you have wireless working, you can continue configuring the IP level
networking options as described in the next section (<uri
link="#network_term">Understanding Network Terminology</uri>) or use the
<c>net-setup</c> tool as described previously.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="network_term">
<title>Understanding Network Terminology</title>
<body>

<note>
If you know your IP address, broadcast address, netmask and nameservers,
then you can skip this subsection and continue with <uri
link="#ifconfig_route">Using ifconfig and route</uri>.
</note>

<p>
If all of the above fails, you will have to configure your network manually.
This is not difficult at all. However, you need to be familiar with some
network terminology, as you will need it to be able to
configure your network to your satisfaction. After reading this, you
will know what a <e>gateway</e> is, what a <e>netmask</e> serves for,
how a <e>broadcast</e> address is formed and why you need
<e>nameservers</e>.
</p>

<p>
In a network, hosts are identified by their <e>IP address</e> (Internet
Protocol address). Such an address is a combination of four numbers
between 0 and 255. Well, at least that is how we perceive it. In
reality, such an IP address consists of 32 bits (ones and zeros). Let's
view an example:
</p>

<pre caption="Example of an IP address">
IP Address (numbers):   192.168.0.2
IP Address (bits):      11000000 10101000 00000000 00000010
                        -------- -------- -------- --------
                           192      168       0        2
</pre>

<p>
Such an IP address is unique to a host as far as all accessible networks are
concerned (i.e. every host that you are able to reach must have a unique IP
address). In order to distinguish between hosts inside and outside a
network, the IP address is divided in two parts: the 
<e>network</e> part and the <e>host</e> part. 
</p>

<p>
The separation is written down with the <e>netmask</e>, a collection of
ones followed by a collection of zeros. The part of the IP that can be
mapped on the ones is the network-part, the other one is the host-part.
As usual, the netmask can be written down as an IP-address.
</p>

<pre caption="Example of network/host separation">
IP-address:    192      168      0         2
            11000000 10101000 00000000 00000010
Netmask:    11111111 11111111 11111111 00000000
               255      255     255        0
           +--------------------------+--------+
                    Network              Host
</pre>

<p>
In other words, 192.168.0.14 is still part of our example network, but
192.168.1.2 is not.
</p>

<p>
The <e>broadcast</e> address is an IP-address with the same network-part
as your network, but with only ones as host-part. Every host on your
network listens to this IP address. It is truly meant for broadcasting
packets.
</p>

<pre caption="Broadcast address">
IP-address:    192      168      0         2
            11000000 10101000 00000000 00000010
Broadcast:  11000000 10101000 00000000 11111111
               192      168      0        255
           +--------------------------+--------+
                     Network             Host
</pre>

<p>
To be able to surf on the internet, you must know which host shares the
Internet connection. This host is called the <e>gateway</e>. Since it is
a regular host, it has a regular IP address (for instance 192.168.0.1).
</p>

<p>
We previously stated that every host has its own IP address. To be able
to reach this host by a name (instead of an IP address) you need a
service that translates a name (such as <e>dev.gentoo.org</e>) to an IP
address (such as <e>64.5.62.82</e>). Such a service is called a name
service. To use such a service, you must define the necessary <e>name
servers</e> in <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path>.
</p>

<p>
In some cases, your gateway also serves as nameserver. Otherwise you
will have to enter the nameservers provided by your ISP.
</p>

<p>
To summarise, you will need the following information before continuing:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Network Item</th>
  <th>Example</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Your IP address</ti>
  <ti>192.168.0.2</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Netmask</ti>
  <ti>255.255.255.0</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Broadcast</ti>
  <ti>192.168.0.255</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Gateway</ti>
  <ti>192.168.0.1</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Nameserver(s)</ti>
  <ti>195.130.130.5, 195.130.130.133</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="ifconfig_route">
<title>Using ifconfig and route</title>
<body>

<p>
Setting up your network consists of three steps. First we assign
ourselves an IP address using <c>ifconfig</c>. Then we set up routing to
the gateway using <c>route</c>. Then we finish up by placing the
nameserver IPs in <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path>.
</p>

<p>
To assign an IP address, you will need your IP address, broadcast
address and netmask. Then execute the following command, substituting
<c>${IP_ADDR}</c> with your IP address, <c>${BROADCAST}</c> with your
broadcast address and <c>${NETMASK}</c> with your netmask:
</p>

<pre caption="Using ifconfig">
# <i>ifconfig eth0 ${IP_ADDR} broadcast ${BROADCAST} netmask ${NETMASK} up</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now set up routing using <c>route</c>. Substitute <c>${GATEWAY}</c> with
your gateway IP address:
</p>

<pre caption="Using route">
# <i>route add default gw ${GATEWAY}</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now open <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path> with your favorite editor (in our
example, we use <c>nano</c>):
</p>

<pre caption="Creating /etc/resolv.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/resolv.conf</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now fill in your nameserver(s) using the following as a template. Make
sure you substitute <c>${NAMESERVER1}</c> and <c>${NAMESERVER2}</c> with
the appropriate nameserver addresses:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/resolv.conf template">
nameserver ${NAMESERVER1}
nameserver ${NAMESERVER2}
</pre>

<p>
That's it. Now test your network by pinging some Internet server (like
<uri link="http://www.google.com">Google</uri>). If this works,
congratulations then. You are now ready to install Gentoo. Continue with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=4">Preparing the Disks</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
