<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/2005.1/hb-install-system.xml,v 1.6 2006/02/22 10:17:45 neysx Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>5.4</version>
<date>2006-02-22</date>

<section>
<title>Chrooting</title>
<subsection>
<title>Mounting the /proc and /dev Filesystems</title>
<body>

<p>
Mount the <path>/proc</path> filesystem on <path>/mnt/gentoo/proc</path> to
allow the installation to use the kernel-provided information within the
chrooted environment, and then mount-bind the <path>/dev</path> filesystem.
</p>

<pre caption="Mounting /proc and /dev">
# <i>mount -t proc none /mnt/gentoo/proc</i>
# <i>mount -o bind /dev /mnt/gentoo/dev</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Copy over DNS Information</title>
<body>

<p>
If you configured your network to fetch the appropriate stage file later on from
the Internet, you need to copy over the DNS information stored in
<path>/etc/resolv.conf</path> to <path>/mnt/gentoo/etc/resolv.conf</path>. This
file contains the nameservers your system will use to resolve names to IP
addresses.
</p>

<pre caption="Copy over DNS Information">
# <i>cp -L /etc/resolv.conf /mnt/gentoo/etc/resolv.conf</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Entering the new Environment</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that all partitions are initialized and the base environment
installed, it is time to enter our new installation environment by
<e>chrooting</e> into it. This means that we change from the current
installation environment to your installation system (namely the 
initialized partitions).
</p>

<p>
This chrooting is done in three steps. First we will change the root
from <path>/</path> (on the installation medium) to <path>/mnt/gentoo</path> 
(on your partitions) using <c>chroot</c>. Then we will create a new environment
using <c>env-update</c>, which essentially creates environment variables.
Finally, we load those variables into memory using <c>source</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Chrooting into the new environment">
# <i>chroot /mnt/gentoo /bin/bash</i>
# <i>env-update</i>
>>> Regenerating /etc/ld.so.cache...
# <i>source /etc/profile</i>
# <i>export PS1="(chroot) $PS1"</i>
</pre>

<p>
Congratulations! You are now inside your own Gentoo Linux environment.
Of course it is far from finished, which is why the installation still
has some sections left :-)
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Creating the Portage cache</title>
<body>

<p>
You have already installed the Portage tree, but you should now build the
Portage cache to speed up future emerges. <c>emerge --metadata</c> does this
for you.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the Portage cache">
# <i>emerge --metadata</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section id="configure_USE">
<title>Configuring the USE Variable</title>
<subsection>
<title>What is the USE Variable?</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>USE</c> is one of the most powerful variables Gentoo provides to its users.
Several programs can be compiled with or without optional support for certain
items. For instance, some programs can be compiled with gtk-support, or with
qt-support. Others can be compiled with or without SSL support. Some programs
can even be compiled with framebuffer support (svgalib) instead of X11 support
(X-server).
</p>

<p>
Most distributions compile their packages with support for as much as possible,
increasing the size of the programs and startup time, not to mention an enormous
amount of dependencies. With Gentoo you can define what options a package 
should be compiled with. This is where <c>USE</c> comes into play.
</p>

<p>
In the <c>USE</c> variable you define keywords which are mapped onto
compile-options. For instance, <e>ssl</e> will compile ssl-support in the
programs that support it. <e>-X</e> will remove X-server support (note the minus
sign in front). <e>gnome gtk -kde -qt</e> will compile your programs with gnome
(and gtk) support, and not with kde (and qt) support, making your system fully
tweaked for GNOME.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Modifying the USE Variable</title>
<body>

<warn>
Do not make any modifications to the USE variable yet if you plan to use our
prebuilt packages (GRP set). You can alter the USE variable after having
installed the packages you want. Gremlins are known to attack your system 
if you ignore this warning!
</warn>

<p>
The default <c>USE</c> settings are placed in
<path>/etc/make.profile/make.defaults</path>. What you place in
<path>/etc/make.conf</path> is calculated against these defaults settings. If
you add something to the <c>USE</c> setting, it is added to the default list. If
you remove something from the <c>USE</c> setting (by placing a minus sign in
front of it) it is removed from the default list (if it was in the default list
at all). <e>Never</e> alter anything inside the <path>/etc/make.profile</path>
directory; it gets overwritten when you update Portage!
</p>

<p>
A full description on <c>USE</c> can be found in the second part of the Gentoo
Handbook, <uri link="?part=2&amp;chap=2">USE flags</uri>. A full description on
the available USE flags can be found on your system in
<path>/usr/portage/profiles/use.desc</path>. 
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing available USE flags">
# <i>less /usr/portage/profiles/use.desc</i>
<comment>(You can scroll using your arrow keys, exit by pressing 'q')</comment>
</pre>

<p>
As an example we show a <c>USE</c> setting for a KDE-based system with DVD, ALSA
and CD Recording support:
</p>

<pre caption="Opening /etc/make.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/make.conf</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="USE setting">
USE="-gtk -gnome qt kde dvd alsa cdr"
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
