<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-alpha-bootloader.xml,v 1.26 2014/08/17 16:38:13 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>13</version>
<date>2014-08-17</date>

<section>
<title>Making your Choice</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel is configured and compiled and the necessary system
configuration files are filled in correctly, it is time to install a
program that will fire up your kernel when you start the system. Such a
program is called a <e>bootloader</e>. 
</p>

<p>
Several bootloaders exist for Linux/Alpha. You must choose one of the supported
bootloaders, not all. You have the choice between <uri link="#aboot">aBoot</uri>
and <uri link="#milo">MILO</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="aboot">
<title>Default: Using aboot</title>
<body>

<note>
<c>aboot</c> only supports booting from <b>ext2</b> and <b>ext3</b>
partitions.
</note>

<p>
We first install aboot on our system. Of course we use <c>emerge</c> to
do so:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing aboot">
# <i>emerge aboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
The next step is to make our bootdisk bootable. This will start
<c>aboot</c> when you boot your system. We make our bootdisk bootable by
writing the <c>aboot</c> bootloader to the start of the disk.
</p>

<pre caption="Making your bootdisk bootable">
# <i>swriteboot -f3 /dev/sda /boot/bootlx</i> 
# <i>abootconf /dev/sda 2</i>
</pre>

<note>
If you use a different partitioning scheme than the one we use
throughout this chapter, you have to change the commands accordingly.
Please read the appropriate manual pages (<c>man 8 swriteboot</c> and
<c>man 8 abootconf</c>). Also, if your root filesystem is ran using the JFS
filesystem, make sure it gets mounted read-only at first by adding <c>ro</c> as
a kernel option.
</note>

<p>
Although <c>aboot</c> is now installed, we still need to write a configuration
file for it. Aboot only requires one line for each configuration, so we
can do this:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating /etc/aboot.conf">
# <i>echo '0:2/boot/vmlinux.gz root=/dev/sda2' &gt; /etc/aboot.conf</i>

<comment>
If, while building the Linux kernel, you opted to include an initramfs to boot
from, then you will need to change the configuration by referring to this
initramfs file and telling the initramfs where your real root device is at:
</comment>

# <i>echo '0:2/boot/vmlinux.gz initrd=/boot/<keyval id="genkernel-initrd"/> real_root=/dev/sda2' &gt; /etc/aboot.conf</i>
</pre>


<p>
Additionally, you can make Gentoo boot automatically by setting up some SRM
variables. You can try setting these variables from Linux, but it may be easier
to do so from the SRM console itself.
</p>

<pre caption="Automatically booting Gentoo">
# <i>cd /proc/srm_environment/named_variables</i>
# <i>echo -n 0 &gt; boot_osflags</i>
# <i>echo -n '' &gt; boot_file</i>
# <i>echo -n 'BOOT' &gt; auto_action</i>
# <i>echo -n 'dkc100' &gt; bootdef_dev</i>
<comment>(Substitute dkc100 with whatever your boot device is)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
If you need to get into the SRM console again in the future (to recover 
your Gentoo install, play with some variables, or whatever), just hit 
CTRL+C to abort the automatic loading process.
</p>

<p>
If you're installing using a serial console, don't forget to include 
the serial console boot flag in <path>aboot.conf</path>.  See  
<path>/etc/aboot.conf.example</path> for some further information.
</p>

<p>
Aboot is now configured and ready to use. Continue with <uri
link="#reboot">Rebooting the System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="milo">
<title>Alternative: Using MILO</title>
<body>

<p>
Before continuing, you should decide on how to use MILO. In this
section, we will assume that you want to make a MILO boot floppy. If you
are going to boot from an MS-DOS partition on your hard disk, you should
amend the commands appropriately.
</p>

<p>
To install MILO, we use <c>emerge</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing MILO">
# <i>emerge milo</i>
</pre>

<p>
After MILO has been installed, the MILO images should be in
<path>/opt/milo</path>. The commands below make a bootfloppy for use
with MILO. Remember to use the correct image for your Alpha-system.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing MILO on a floppy">
<comment>(First insert a blank floppy)</comment>
# <i>fdformat /dev/fd0</i>
# <i>mformat a:</i>
# <i>mcopy /opt/milo/milo-2.4-18-gentoo-ruffian a:\milo</i>
# <i>mcopy /opt/milo/linload.exe a:\linload.exe</i>
<comment>(Only if you have a Ruffian:</comment>     
  # <i>mcopy /opt/milo/ldmilo.exe a:\ldmilo.exe</i>
<comment>)</comment>
# <i>echo -ne '\125\252' | dd of=/dev/fd0 bs=1 seek=510 count=2</i>
</pre>

<p>
Your MILO boot floppy is now ready to boot Gentoo Linux. You may need to
set environment variables in your ARCS Firmware to get MILO to start;
this is all explained in the <uri
link="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MILO-HOWTO/">MILO-HOWTO</uri> with some examples 
on common systems, and examples of the commands to use in interactive mode.
</p>

<p>
Not reading the <uri link="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MILO-HOWTO/">MILO-HOWTO</uri> 
is a <e>bad</e> idea.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="reboot">
<title>Rebooting the System</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Exit the chrooted environment and unmount all mounted partitions. Then type in 
that one magical command you have been waiting for: <c>reboot</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Exiting the chroot, unmounting all partitions and rebooting">
# <i>exit</i>
cdimage ~# <i>cd</i>
cdimage ~# <i>umount -l /mnt/gentoo/dev{/shm,/pts,}</i>
cdimage ~# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo{/proc,/boot,/sys,}</i>
cdimage ~# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Of course, don't forget to remove the bootable CD, otherwise the CD will be
booted again instead of your new Gentoo system.
</p>

<p>
Once rebooted in your Gentoo installation, finish up with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=11">Finalizing your Gentoo Installation</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
