<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-arm-medium.xml,v 1.12 2013/12/17 10:38:05 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>11</version>
<date>2013-12-17</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<body>

<p>
Generally if you have an ARMv4 or later, it can run Gentoo.  This is pretty
much a given, so below we'll cover the CPUs that have actually been tested.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>CPU <e>(Big Endian)</e></th>
  <ti>IXP425</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>CPU <e>(Little Endian)</e></th>
  <ti>IXP425, StrongARM-110</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Memory</th>
  <ti>32 MB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Diskspace</th>
  <ti>1.5 GB (excluding swap space)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Swap space</th>
  <ti>At least 256 MB</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Installation Notes</title>
<subsection>
<title>A note about ABIs</title>
<body>

<p>
We support the new ARM EABI as well as the classic ARM ABI, sometimes referred
to as the Legacy or Old ABI (which is required for some old ARM chips like
armv4l). Thumb may not be as well tested, but in theory it should work. Feel
free to help out.
</p>

<p>
Also, another important concept to grasp is the concept of <b>endianness</b>.
Endianness refers to the way that a CPU reads words from main memory. A word can
be read as either <e>big</e> endian (most significant byte first), or
<e>little</e> endian (least significant byte first). Intel x86 machines are
generally Little Endian, whilst Apple and Sparc machines are Big Endian. On ARM,
they can be either. To separate them, we append <c>eb</c> to the architecture
name to denote big endian as little endian tends to be more common in practice.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The Stage3 Tarball</title>
<body>

<p>
A stage3 tarball is an archive containing a minimal Gentoo environment,
suitable to continue the Gentoo installation using the instructions in this
manual. Previously, the Gentoo Handbook described the installation using one of
three stage tarballs. While Gentoo still offers stage1 and stage2 tarballs,
the official installation method uses the stage3 tarball. If you are interested
in performing a Gentoo installation using a stage1 or stage2 tarball, please
read the Gentoo FAQ on <uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/FAQ#How_do_I_Install_Gentoo_Using_a_Stage1_or_Stage2_Tarball.3F">How
do I Install Gentoo Using a Stage1 or Stage2 Tarball?</uri>
</p>

<p>
Stage3 tarballs can be downloaded from <path><keyval
id="release-dir"/>current-stage3/</path> on any of the <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">Official Gentoo Mirrors</uri> and are not provided
on the LiveCD.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Netbooting Overview</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
In this section, we'll cover what you need in order to successfully network
boot a NetWinder. This is just a brief guide, it is not intended to be
thorough, for more information it is recommended that you read the <uri
link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Diskless_nodes">Diskless HOWTO</uri>.
</p>

<p>
What You Need: Depending on the machine, there is a certain amount of hardware
that you'll need in order to successfully netboot and install Linux.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    In General:
    <ul>
      <li>TFTP server</li>
      <li>Patience -- and lots of it</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    NetWinders: you can either do a serial console with a null-modem
    cable, or you can hook up a regular VGA monitor and a PS/2 keyboard.
  </li>
</ul>

<note>
A <uri link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Null_modem">null modem cable</uri>
can be found in most electronics stores.
</note>

<note>
For the terminal, this could be a real VT100/ANSI terminal, or it could be a PC
running terminal emulation software (such as HyperTerminal, Minicom, seyon,
Telex, xc, screen -- whatever your preference). It doesn't matter what platform
this machine runs -- just so long as it has one RS-232 serial port you can use,
and appropriate software.
</note>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Setting up TFTP -- a brief guide</title>
<body>

<p>
Okay, so you've got your bits and pieces together, now to set everything up. As
mentioned earlier -- this is not a complete guide, this is a bare-bones config
that will just get things rolling. You can either use this when starting a
setup from scratch, or use the suggestions to amend your existing setup to
support netbooting.
</p>

<p>
It is worth noting that the servers used need not be running Gentoo Linux, you
could quite reasonably use FreeBSD or any Unix-like platform. However, this
guide will assume you are running Gentoo Linux. You also may run TFTP/NFS on a
separate machine to the DHCP server if desired.
</p>

<warn>
The Gentoo/ARM Team cannot help you with setting up other operating systems as
netboot servers. If you choose a different OS, it is assumed you know what
you're doing.
</warn>

<p>
First step -- setting up the TFTP server. It is recommended that you use
<c>tftp-hpa</c> as it is the only TFTP daemon known to work correctly. Proceed
by installing it as shown below.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing tftp-hpa">
# <i>emerge net-ftp/tftp-hpa</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will create <path>/tftproot</path> for you to store the netboot images.
You may move this elsewhere if you wish. For the purposes of this guide, it is
assumed that you have left it in the default location.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Netbooting your ARM Machine</title>
<subsection>
<title>Downloading a Netboot image</title>
<body>

<p>
Depending on the system you're installing for, there are several possible
images available for download. These are all labelled according to the system
type and CPU they are compiled for. The machine types are as follows:
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Machine</th>
    <th>Files</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>NetWinder</ti>
    <ti><uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~vapier/arm/netboot-netwinder">Netboot</uri></ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
Make sure to place the image into your <path>/tftproot</path> directory.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Start Your Daemons...</title>
<body>
<p>
At this point, you should be ready to start the daemons. Enter the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the TFTP daemons">
# <i>/etc/init.d/in.tftpd start</i>
</pre>

<p>
If nothing went wrong in that last step you should be all set to power on the
ARM machine and proceed with the guide. Note that below we assume the TFTP
server has the IP <c>192.168.0.2</c> so you may have to change this for your
setup.
</p>

<p>
An easy way to verify if the tftp daemon is running is to type the following
command -- if you see something like the output mentioned below -- everything
is fine.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking TFTPd is running">
# <i>netstat -al | grep ^udp</i>
udp        0      0 *:bootpc                *:*
udp        0      0 *:631                   *:*
udp        0      0 *:xdmcp                 *:*
udp        0      0 *:tftp                  *:* <comment>&lt;-- (look for this line)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Netbooting the NetWinder</title>
<body>

<p>
Okay, everything is set, the TFTP server is up and running. Now it is time to
fire up the NetWinder. Once you get into the NeTTrom console, enter the
commands below.
</p>

<pre caption="Netbooting from NeTTrom">
NeTTrom> <i>setenv kernconfig tftp</i>
NeTTrom> <i>setenv kerntftpserver 192.168.0.2</i>
NeTTrom> <i>setenv kerntftpfile netboot-netwinder</i>
NeTTrom> <i>setenv netconfig_eth0 flash</i>
NeTTrom> <i>setenv eth0_ip 192.168.0.15/24</i>
NeTTrom> <i>boot</i>
</pre>

<p>
From this point, the machine should start downloading the image, then, roughly
20 seconds later, start booting Linux. If all is well, you should be dropped at
the Busybox <c>ash</c> shell, where you can move on to <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">Configuring Your Network</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
