<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-ppc-kernel.xml,v 1.71 2013/03/16 18:58:17 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
The Linux kernel is the core of every distribution. This chapter
explains how to configure your kernel.
</abstract>

<version>16</version>
<date>2013-03-16</date>

<section>
<title>Installing the Kernel Sources</title>
<subsection>
<title>Choosing a Kernel</title>
<body>

<p>
The core around which all distributions are built is the Linux kernel. It is the
layer between the user programs and your system hardware. Gentoo provides its
users several possible kernel sources. A full listing with description is
available at the <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-kernel.xml">Gentoo Kernel
Guide</uri>. 
</p>

<p>
For <keyval id="arch"/>-based systems we have <c>gentoo-sources</c>
(kernel source patched for extra features).
</p>

<p>
Choose your kernel source and install it using <c>emerge</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a kernel source">
# <i>emerge gentoo-sources</i>
</pre>

<p>
When you take a look in <path>/usr/src</path> you should see a symlink called
<path>linux</path> pointing to your kernel source. In this case, the installed
kernel source points to <c>gentoo-sources-<keyval id="kernel-version"/></c>.
Your version may be different, so keep this in mind.
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing the kernel source symlink">
# <i>ls -l /usr/src/linux</i>
lrwxrwxrwx    1 root   root    12 Oct 13 11:04 /usr/src/linux -&gt; linux-<keyval id="kernel-version"/>
</pre>

<p>
Now it is time to configure and compile your kernel source. You can use
<c>genkernel</c> for this, which will build a generic kernel as used by the
Installation CD. We explain the "manual" configuration first though, as it is
the best way to optimize your environment.
</p>

<p>
If you want to manually configure your kernel, continue now with <uri
link="#manual">Default: Manual Configuration</uri>. If you want to use
<c>genkernel</c> you should read <uri link="#genkernel">Alternative: Using
genkernel</uri> instead.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="manual">
<title>Default: Manual Configuration</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Manually configuring a kernel is often seen as the most difficult procedure a
Linux user ever has to perform. Nothing is less true -- after configuring a
few kernels you won't even remember that it was difficult ;)
</p>

<p>
However, one thing <e>is</e> true: you must know your system when you start
configuring a kernel manually. Most information can be gathered by emerging 
pciutils (<c>emerge pciutils</c>) which contains <c>lspci</c>. You will now 
be able to  use <c>lspci</c> within the chrooted environment. You may safely 
ignore any <e>pcilib</e> warnings (like pcilib: cannot open 
/sys/bus/pci/devices) that <c>lspci</c> throws out. Alternatively, you can run 
<c>lspci</c> from a <e>non-chrooted</e> environment. The results are the same. 
You can also run <c>lsmod</c> to see what kernel modules the Installation CD 
uses (it might provide you with a nice hint on what to enable).
</p>

<p>
Now, go to your kernel source directory, it's time to configure your kernel.
Start by configuring a kernel that will boot on most 32 Bit PowerPC machines
by first running <c>make pmac32_defconfig</c>. After the default configuration
has been generated, run <c>make menuconfig</c> to start an ncurses-based
configuration menu.
</p>

<pre caption="Invoking menuconfig">
# <i>cd /usr/src/linux</i>
# <i>make pmac32_defconfig</i>
# <i>make menuconfig</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will be greeted with several configuration sections. We'll first list some
options you must activate (otherwise Gentoo will not function, or not function
properly without additional tweaks).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Activating Required Options</title>
<body>

<p>
First go to <c>File Systems</c> and select support for the filesystems you use.
<e>Don't</e> compile them as modules, otherwise your Gentoo system will not be
able to mount your partitions. Also select the <c>/proc file system</c> and
<c>Virtual memory</c>. Make sure that you also enable support for Amiga
partitions if you are using a Pegasos, or Macintosh partitions if you are using
an Apple computer.
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting necessary file systems">
File systems ---&gt;
  Pseudo Filesystems ---&gt;
<comment>(/proc may already be forced on by your configuration, if so, you'll see --- instead)</comment>
    [*] /proc file system support
    [*] Virtual memory file system support (former shm fs)
  Partition Types ---&gt;
    [*] Advanced partition support
    [*]   Amiga partition table support
    [*]   Macintosh partition map support

<comment>(Select one or more of the following options as needed by your system)</comment>
  &lt;*&gt; Reiserfs support
  &lt;*&gt; Ext3 journalling file system support
  &lt;*&gt; Second extended fs support
  &lt;*&gt; XFS filesystem support
</pre>

<p>
Users of NewWorld and OldWorld machines will want HFS support as well. OldWorld
users require it for copying compiled kernels to the MacOS partition. NewWorld
users require it for configuring the special Apple_Bootstrap partition:
</p>

<pre caption="Activating HFS support">
File Systems ---&gt;
  Miscellaneous filesystems ---&gt;
    &lt;M&gt; Apple Macintosh file system support
    &lt;M&gt; Apple Extended HFS file system support
</pre>

<p>
If you are using PPPoE to connect to the Internet or you are using a dial-up
modem, you will need the following options in the kernel:
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting PPPoE necessary drivers">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  Network device support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; PPP (point-to-point protocol) support
    &lt;*&gt;   PPP support for async serial ports
    &lt;*&gt;   PPP support for sync tty ports
</pre>

<p>
The two compression options won't harm but are not always needed.  The <c>PPP
over Ethernet</c> option might only be used by <c>ppp</c> when configured to
perform kernel mode PPPoE.
</p>

<p>
Don't forget to include support in the kernel for your ethernet card! Most
newer Apple computers use the SunGEM ethernet driver. Older iMacs commonly use
the BMAC driver.
</p>

<pre caption="Selecting the network driver">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  Network device support ---&gt;
    Ethernet (10 or 100Mbit) ---&gt;
      [*] Ethernet (10 or 100Mbit)
      &lt;*&gt;   Generic Media Independent Interface device support
      &lt;*&gt;   MACE (Power Mac ethernet) support
      &lt;*&gt;   BMAC (G3 ethernet) support
      &lt;*&gt;   Sun GEM support
</pre>

<p>
If you're booting from FireWire, you'll need to enable these options. If you do
not want to compile in support, you'll need to include these modules and their
dependencies in an initrd.
</p>

<pre caption="Enable support for FireWire devices on boot">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  IEEE 1394 (FireWire) support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; IEEE 1394 (FireWire) support
    &lt;*&gt;   OHCI-1394 support
    &lt;*&gt;   SBP-2 support (Harddisks etc.)
</pre>

<p>
If you're booting from USB, you'll need to enable these options.  If you do not
want to compile in support, you'll need to include these modules and their
dependencies in an initrd.
</p>

<pre caption="Enable support for USB devices on boot">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  USB support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; Support for Host-side USB
    &lt;*&gt;   OHCI HCD support
    &lt;*&gt;   USB Mass Storage support
</pre>

<p>
Do not turn off kernel framebuffer support as it is required for a successful
boot. If you are using an NVIDIA based chipset, you should use the Open
Firmware framebuffer. If you are using an ATI based chipset, you should select
the framebuffer driver based upon your chipset (Mach64, Rage128 or Radeon).
</p>

<pre caption="Choosing a Framebuffer Driver">
Device Drivers ---&gt;
  Graphics support ---&gt;
    &lt;*&gt; Support for frame buffer devices
    [*] Open Firmware frame buffer device support
    &lt;*&gt; ATI Radeon display support
    &lt;*&gt; ATI Rage128 display support
    &lt;*&gt; ATI Mach64 display support
    Console display driver support ---&gt;
      &lt;*&gt; Framebuffer Console support
</pre>

<note>
If you select more than one framebuffer device, it may default to a less than
optimal driver. Either use only one framebuffer device or specify which to use
by passing the driver to use to the kernel on boot by appending a video line
such as: <c>video=radeonfb</c>.
</note>

<p>
When you're done configuring your kernel, continue with <uri
link="#compiling">Compiling and Installing</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="compiling">
<title>Compiling and Installing</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel is configured, it is time to compile and install it. Exit
the configuration menu and run the following commands:
</p>

<pre caption="Compiling the kernel">
# <i>make &amp;&amp; make modules_install</i>
</pre>

<p>
When the kernel has finished compiling, copy the kernel image to
<path>/boot</path> as shown below. If you have a separate boot partition, as
on Pegasos computers, be sure that it is mounted properly. If you are using
BootX to boot, we'll copy the kernel later.
</p>

<p>
Yaboot and BootX expect to use an uncompressed kernel unlike many other
bootloaders. The uncompressed kernel is called vmlinux and it is placed in
<path>/usr/src/linux</path> after the kernel has finished compiling. If you are
using a Pegasos machine, the Pegasos firmware requires a compressed kernel
called zImage which can be found in
<path>/usr/src/linux/arch/powerpc/boot/images</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing the kernel">
# <i>cd /usr/src/linux</i>
<comment>Note, your kernel version might be different</comment>
<comment>(Apple/IBM)</comment>
# <i>cp vmlinux /boot/<keyval id="kernel-name"/></i>
<comment>(Pegasos)</comment>
# <i>cp arch/powerpc/boot/images/zImage /boot/<keyval id="kernel-name"/></i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#kernel_modules">Kernel Modules</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="genkernel">
<title>Alternative: Using genkernel</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel source tree is installed, it's now time to compile your
kernel by using our <c>genkernel</c> script to automatically build a kernel for
you. <c>genkernel</c> works by configuring a kernel nearly identically to the
way our Installation CD kernel is configured. This means that when you use
<c>genkernel</c> to build your kernel, your system will generally detect all
your hardware at boot-time, just like our Installation CD does. Because
genkernel doesn't require any manual kernel configuration, it is an ideal
solution for those users who may not be comfortable compiling their own
kernels.
</p>

<p>
Now, let's see how to use genkernel. First, emerge the genkernel ebuild:
</p>

<pre caption="Emerging genkernel">
# <i>emerge genkernel</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you are using FireWire or USB to boot, you'll need to add modules to the
initrd. Edit <path>/usr/share/genkernel/arch/ppc/modules_load</path> and change
<c>MODULES_FIREWIRE="ieee1394 ohci1394 sbp2"</c> for FireWire support or
<c>MODULES_USB="usbcore ohci-hcd ehci-hcd usb-storage"</c> for USB support.
</p>

<p>
Before compiling your sources, the fstab needs a slight adjustment. The rest of
the fstab will be completed during a later step, so don't worry about the
details now. If you did not create a separate boot partition (NOT bootstrap,
that's different), remove the line referencing <path>/boot</path> from
<path>/etc/fstab</path>. This will need to be done on most Apple computers.
</p>

<pre caption="Removing /boot from /etc/fstab on machines without a boot partition">
# <i>nano -w /etc/fstab</i>
<comment>Remove this line</comment>
/dev/BOOT  /boot    ext2    noauto,noatime    0 2
</pre>

<p>
Now, compile your kernel sources by running <c>genkernel --genzimage all</c>.
For Pegasos, we will need to use a different config and create a zImage instead
of the vmlinux kernel used on Apple machines. Be aware, as <c>genkernel</c>
compiles a kernel that supports almost all hardware, this compilation can take
quite a while to finish!
</p>

<p>
Note that, if your partition where the kernel should be located doesn't use ext2
or ext3 as filesystem you might need to manually configure your kernel using
<c>genkernel --menuconfig all</c> and add support for your
filesystem <e>in</e> the kernel (i.e. <e>not</e> as a module). Users of LVM2
will probably want to add <c>--lvm2</c> as an argument as well.
</p>

<pre caption="Running genkernel">
# <i>genkernel all</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Running genkernel on the Pegasos">
# <i>genkernel --genzimage all</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once <c>genkernel</c> completes, a kernel, full set of modules and
<e>initial ram disk</e> (initramfs) will be created. We will use the kernel
and initrd when configuring a boot loader later in this document. Write
down the names of the kernel and initrd as you will need them when writing
the bootloader configuration file. The initrd will be started immediately after
booting to perform hardware autodetection (just like on the Installation CD)
before your "real" system starts up.  Be sure to also copy down the required
boot arguments, these are required for a successful boot with genkernel.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking the created kernel image name and initrd">
<comment>Note, your kernel version might be different</comment>
# <i>ls /boot/<keyval id="genkernel-name"/> /boot/<keyval id="genkernel-initrd"/></i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#kernel_modules">Kernel Modules</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="kernel_modules">
<title>Kernel Modules</title>

<subsection>
<include href="hb-install-kernelmodules.xml"/>
</subsection>

</section>
</sections>

