<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-ppc64-bootloader.xml,v 1.33 2014/08/17 16:38:13 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
In this chapter we'll describe how to configure a bootloader to our
needs.
</abstract>

<version>13</version>
<date>2014-08-17</date>

<section>
<title>Making your Choice</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel is configured and compiled and the necessary system
configuration files are filled in correctly, it is time to install a
program that will fire up your kernel when you start the system. Such a
program is called a <e>bootloader</e>.
</p>

<p>
On Linux/PPC64 we have yaBoot as a bootloader.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="yaboot">
<title>Using yaBoot</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<impo>
If you are using a 64-bit userland, you must use the <c>yaboot-static</c>
package because yaboot cannot be compiled as a 64-bit application. The 32-bit
userlands should use the regular <c>yaboot</c> package.
</impo>

<p>
There are two ways to configure yaBoot for your system. You can use the new and
improved <c>yabootconfig</c> included with <path>yaboot-1.3.8-r1</path> and
later to automatically set up yaboot. If for some reason you do not want to run
<c>yabootconfig</c> to automatically set up <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> or you
are installing Gentoo on a G5 (on which <c>yabootconfig</c> does not always
work), you can just edit the sample file already installed on your system.
</p>

<impo>
yabootconfig/ybin won't work on IBM. You have to install yaboot another way:
<uri link="#yaboot-ibm">Using yaboot on IBM hardware</uri>
</impo>

<note>
If your root filesystem uses the JFS filesystem, be sure to add <c>ro</c> as a
kernel parameter. JFS must be able to replay its log in read-only mode before it
gets mounted read-write.
</note>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#yabootconfig">Default: Using yabootconfig</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#manual_yaboot">Alternative: Manual yaBoot Configuration</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="yabootconfig">
<title>Default: Using yabootconfig</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>yabootconfig</c> will auto-detect the partitions on your machine and will
set up dual and triple boot combinations with Linux, Mac OS, and Mac OS
X.
</p>

<p>
To use <c>yabootconfig</c>, your drive must have a bootstrap partition, and
<path>/etc/fstab</path> must be configured with your Linux partitions. Both of 
these should have been done already in the steps above. To start, ensure that
you have the latest version of yaboot installed by running <c>emerge --update
yaboot-static</c>. This is necessary as the latest version will be available via
Portage, but it may not have made it into the stage files.
</p>

<pre caption = "Installing yaboot-static">
<comment>(For 64-bit users)</comment>
# <i>emerge --update yaboot-static</i>

<comment>(For 32-bit users)</comment>
# <i>emerge yaboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now run <c>yabootconfig</c>. The program will run and it will confirm the
location of the bootstrap partition. Type <c>Y</c> if it is correct. If not,
double check <path>/etc/fstab</path>. yabootconfig will then scan your system
setup, create <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> and run <c>mkofboot</c> for you.
<c>mkofboot</c> is used to format the bootstrap partition, and install the
yaboot configuration file into it.
</p>

<p>
You might want to verify the contents of <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path>. If you
make changes to <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> (like setting the default/boot
OS), make sure to rerun <c>ybin -v</c> to apply changes to the bootstrap
partition.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting your System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="manual_yaboot">
<title>Alternative: Manual yaBoot Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
First make sure you have the latest <c>yaboot-static</c> installed on your
system:
</p>

<pre caption = "Installing yaboot">
<comment>(For 64-bit users)</comment>
# <i>emerge --update yaboot-static</i>

<comment>(For 32-bit users)</comment>
# <i>emerge yaboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Below you find a completed <path>yaboot.conf</path> file. Alter it at
will.
</p>

<pre caption = "/etc/yaboot.conf">
<comment>## /etc/yaboot.conf
##
## run: "man yaboot.conf" for details. Do not make changes until you have!!
## see also: /usr/share/doc/yaboot/examples for example configurations.
##
## For a dual-boot menu, add one or more of:
## bsd=/dev/sdaX, macos=/dev/sdaY, macosx=/dev/sdaZ

## our bootstrap partition:</comment>

boot=/dev/sda2

<comment>## ofboot is the Open Firmware way to specify the bootstrap partition.
## If this isn't defined, yaboot fails on the G5 and some G4s (unless 
## you pass the necessary arguments to the mkofboot/ybin program).
## hd:X means /dev/sdaX.</comment>

ofboot=hd:2

<comment>## hd: is Open Firmware speak for sda</comment>
device=hd:

delay=5
defaultos=macosx
timeout=30
install=/usr/lib/yaboot/yaboot
magicboot=/usr/lib/yaboot/ofboot

<comment>#################
## This section can be duplicated if you have more than one kernel or set of
## boot options - replace <keyval id="kernel-name"/> with your kernel
#################</comment>
image=/boot/<keyval id="kernel-name"/>
  label=Linux
  root=/dev/sda3
  partition=3
  read-only

macos=hd:13
macosx=hd:12
enablecdboot
enableofboot
</pre>

<p>
Once <path>yaboot.conf</path> is set up the way you want it, you run <c>mkofboot
-v</c> to install the settings in the bootstrap partition.  <e>Don't forget
this!</e> Confirm when <c>mkofboot</c> asks you to create a new filesystem.
</p>

<p>
If all goes well, and you have the same options as the sample above, your next
reboot will give you a simple, five-entry boot menu. If you update your yaboot
config later on, you'll just need to run <c>ybin -v</c> to update the bootstrap
partition - <c>mkofboot</c> is for initial setup only.
</p>

<p>
For more information on yaboot, take a look at the <uri
link="http://penguinppc.org/projects/yaboot">yaboot project</uri>. For now,
continue the installation with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting your System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="yaboot-ibm">
<title>Using yaboot on IBM hardware</title>
<body>

<p>
On IBM hardware you cannot run <c>yabootconfig</c> or <c>ybin</c>. You must
proceed with the following steps:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Install yaboot-static</li>
  <li>
    Run <c>dd if=/usr/lib/yaboot/yaboot.chrp of=/dev/sdXX</c> (fill in XX with
    your disk and partition for the PReP partition; this was in our example
    <path>/dev/sda1</path>)
  </li>
  <li>
    Next construct your own <path>yaboot.conf</path> file and place into
    <path>/etc</path>. (Take a look at the config above, look into the man page
    of yaboot.conf or look at the below <path>yaboot.conf</path> example.)
  </li>
  <li>
    Assuming your boot device in OF is pointing to the harddrive you prep boot
    partition is on then it'll just work, otherwise at IPL time, go into the
    multiboot menu and set the boot device to the one with your prep boot
    partition
  </li>
  <li>That's it!</li>
</ul>

<pre caption="yaboot.conf for IBM hardware">
device=disk:
partition=2
root=/dev/sda2
default=linux
timeout=50

image=/boot/<keyval id="kernel-name"/>
    label=linux
    append="console=ttyS0,9600"
    read-only
</pre>

<p>
For POWER4, POWER5, and blade-based hardware where the PReP disk partition and
the disk partition that contains your kernel are on the same physical disk, you
can use a simplified <path>yaboot.conf</path>. The following should be
sufficient:
</p>

<pre caption="yaboot.conf for PReP hardware">
default = linux
timeout = 100
image=/boot/<keyval id="kernel-name"/>
        label=linux
        read-only
        root = /dev/sda2
        append="root=/dev/sda2"
</pre>

<p>
To verify that yaboot has been copied to the PReP partition:
</p>

<pre caption="Verifying the yaboot install on PReP">
# <i>dd if=/dev/sda1 count=10 | grep ELF</i>
Binary file (standard input) matches
10+0 records in
10+0 records out
</pre>

<p>
A match signifies that yaboot was installed correctly.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="reboot">
<title>Rebooting the System</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Exit the chrooted environment and unmount all mounted partitions. Then type in 
that one magical command you have been waiting for: <c>reboot</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Exiting the chroot, unmounting all partitions and rebooting">
# <i>exit</i>
~# <i>cd</i>
~# <i>umount -l /mnt/gentoo/dev{/shm,/pts,}</i>
~# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo{/proc,/boot,/sys}</i>
~# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Of course, don't forget to remove the bootable CD, otherwise the CD will be
booted again instead of your new Gentoo system.
</p>

<p>
Once rebooted in your Gentoo installation, finish up with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=11">Finalizing your Gentoo Installation</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
