<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-x86+amd64-medium.xml,v 1.29 2013/08/01 19:02:27 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
You can install Gentoo in many ways. This chapter explains how to install
Gentoo using the minimal Installation CD.
</abstract>

<version>17</version>
<date>2013-08-01</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<body test="func:keyval('arch')='x86'">

<table>
<tr>
 <ti/>
 <th>Minimal CD</th>
 <th>LiveCD</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>CPU</th>
  <ti>i486 or later</ti>
  <ti><b>i686</b> or later</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Memory</th>
  <ti>256 MB</ti>
  <ti>512 MB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Diskspace</th>
  <ti colspan="2">2.5 GB (excluding swap space)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Swap space</th>
  <ti colspan="2">At least 256 MB</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
<body test="func:keyval('arch')='AMD64'">

<table>
<tr>
 <ti/>
 <th>Minimal CD</th>
 <th>LiveCD</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>CPU</th>
  <ti colspan="2">
    Any AMD64 CPU or <uri
    link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EMT64#Intel_64">EM64T CPU</uri> (Core 2
    Duo &amp; Quad processors are EM64T)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Memory</th>
  <ti>256 MB</ti>
  <ti>512 MB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Diskspace</th>
  <ti colspan="2">2.5 GB (excluding swap space)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Swap space</th>
  <ti colspan="2">At least 256 MB</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
You should check the <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/">Gentoo
AMD64 Project Page</uri> before proceeding.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- This part can be propagated to the other architectures as well. -->
<!-- START -->
<section>
<title>The Gentoo Installation CDs</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The <e>Gentoo Installation CDs</e> are bootable CDs which contain a
self-sustained Gentoo environment. They allow you to boot Linux from the CD.
During the boot process your hardware is detected and the appropriate drivers
are loaded. They are maintained by Gentoo developers.
</p>

<p>
All Installation CDs allow you to boot, set up networking, initialize your
partitions and start installing Gentoo from the Internet.
</p>

<!--
<impo>
If you wish to install Gentoo without a working Internet connection, or would
like to use one of the provided installers, please use the installation
instructions described in the <uri link="2008.0/">Gentoo 2008.0
Handbooks</uri>.
</impo>
-->
<!--
<p>
The Installation CDs that we currently provide are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The Gentoo <e>Minimal</e> Installation CD, a small, no-nonsense, bootable
    CD which sole purpose is to boot the system, prepare the networking and
    continue with the Gentoo installation.
  </li>
  <li>
    The Gentoo <e>Installer LiveCD</e> contains everything you need to install
    Gentoo. It provides a graphical environment, a graphical as well as console
    based installer which automatically carries out the installation for you,
    and of course, the installation instructions for your architecture.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
To help you decide which Installation CD you need, we have written down the
major advantages and disadvantages of each Installation CD.
</p>
-->
</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo Minimal Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
The Minimal Installation CD is called <c><keyval id="min-cd-name"/></c> and
takes up around <keyval id="min-cd-size"/> MB of diskspace. You can use this
Installation CD to install Gentoo, but <e>only</e> with a working Internet
connection.
</p>
<!--
<table>
<tr>
  <th>Minimal Installation CD</th>
  <th>Pros and Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>Smallest download</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>
    Contains no stage3 tarball, no Portage snapshot, no prebuilt packages and
    is therefore not suitable for networkless installation
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>
-->
</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo Linux LiveDVDs</title>
<body>

<p>
Every 6 months (give or take), a special DVD is crafted by the Gentoo Ten
project which can be used to install Gentoo with too. The instructions further
down this chapter target the Minimal Installation CDs so might be a bit
different. However, the LiveDVD (or any other bootable
Linux environment) supports getting a root prompt by just invoking <c>sudo
su -</c> or <c>sudo -i</c> on a terminal.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<!--
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo Installer LiveCD</title>
<body>

<p>
The Installer LiveCD is called <c><keyval id="live-cd-name"/></c> and takes up
<keyval id="live-cd-size"/> MB. You can use this Installation CD to install
Gentoo, and you can even use it to install Gentoo without a working internet
connection.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Installer LiveCD</th>
  <th>Pros and Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>
    Contains everything you need. You can even install without a network
    connection.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>Huge download</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</subsection>
-->
<subsection>
<title>The Stage3 Tarball</title>
<body>

<p>
A stage3 tarball is an archive containing a minimal Gentoo environment,
suitable to continue the Gentoo installation using the instructions in this
manual. Previously, the Gentoo Handbook described the installation using one of
three stage tarballs. While Gentoo still offers stage1 and stage2 tarballs, the
official installation method uses the stage3 tarball. If you are interested in
performing a Gentoo installation using a stage1 or stage2 tarball, please read
the Gentoo FAQ on <uri link="/doc/en/faq.xml#stage12">How do I Install Gentoo
Using a Stage1 or Stage2 Tarball?</uri>
</p>

<p>
Stage3 tarballs can be downloaded from <path><keyval
id="release-dir"/>current-stage3/</path> on any of the <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">Official Gentoo Mirrors</uri> and are not provided
on the LiveCD.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- STOP -->
<section>
<title>Download, Burn and Boot a Gentoo Installation CD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Downloading and Burning the Installation CDs</title>
<body>

<p>
You have chosen to use a Gentoo Installation CD. We'll first start by
downloading and burning the chosen Installation CD. We previously discussed
the several available Installation CDs, but where can you find them?
</p>

<p>
You can download any of the Installation CDs from one of our <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri>. The Installation CDs are located in
the <path><keyval id="release-dir"/>current-iso/</path> directory.
</p>

<p>
Inside that directory you'll find ISO files. Those are full CD images which you
can write on a CD-R.
</p>

<p>
In case you wonder if your downloaded file is corrupted or not, you can check
its SHA-2 checksum and compare it with the SHA-2 checksum we provide (such as
<path><keyval id="min-cd-name"/>.DIGESTS</path>). You can check the SHA-2
checksum with the <c>sha512sum</c> tool under Linux/Unix or <uri
link="http://www.krylack.com/file-checksum-tool/">File Checksum Tool</uri> for Windows.
</p>

<pre caption="Verifying the SHA-2 checksum">
$ <i>sha512sum -c &lt;downloaded iso.DIGESTS&gt;</i>
</pre>

<note>
If you get the message that no properly formatted SHA checksum was found, take a
look at the DIGESTS file yourself to see what the supported checksums are.
</note>

<p>
Another way to check the validity of the downloaded file is to use GnuPG to
verify the cryptographic signature that we provide (the file ending with
<path>.asc</path>). Download the signature file and obtain the public keys whose
key ids can be found on the <uri link="/proj/en/releng/index.xml">release
engineering project site</uri>.
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining the public key">
<comment>(... Substitute the key ids with those mentioned on the release engineering site ...)</comment>
$ <i>gpg --keyserver subkeys.pgp.net --recv-keys 96D8BF6D 2D182910 17072058</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now verify the signature:
</p>

<pre caption="Verify the files">
$ <i>gpg --verify &lt;downloaded iso.DIGESTS.asc&gt;</i>
$ <i>sha512sum -c &lt;downloaded iso.DIGESTS.asc&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
To burn the downloaded ISO(s), you have to select raw-burning. How you
do this is highly program-dependent. We will discuss <c>cdrecord</c> and
<c>K3B</c> here; more information can be found in our <uri
link="/doc/en/faq.xml#isoburning">Gentoo FAQ</uri>.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    With cdrecord, you simply type <c>cdrecord dev=/dev/hdc &lt;downloaded iso
    file&gt;</c> (replace <path>/dev/hdc</path> with your CD-RW drive's
    device path).
  </li>
  <li>
    With K3B, select <c>Tools</c> &gt; <c>Burn CD Image</c>. Then you can locate
    your ISO file within the 'Image to Burn' area. Finally click <c>Start</c>.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Booting the Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
Once you have burnt your installation CD, it is time to boot it.
Remove all CDs from your CD drives, reboot your system and enter the BIOS.
This is usually done by hitting DEL, F1 or ESC, depending on your BIOS. Inside
the BIOS, change the boot order so that the CD-ROM is tried before the hard
disk. This is often found under "CMOS Setup". If you don't do this, your system
will just reboot from the hard disk, ignoring the CD-ROM.
</p>

<p>
Now place the installation CD in the CD-ROM drive and reboot. You should see a
boot prompt. At this screen, you can hit Enter to begin the boot process with
the default boot options, or boot the Installation CD with custom boot options
by specifying a kernel followed by boot options and then hitting Enter. 
</p>

<p>
When the boot prompt is shown, you get the option of displaying the available
kernels (<c>F1</c>) and boot options (<c>F2</c>). If you make no selection
within 15 seconds (either displaying information or using a kernel) then the
LiveCD will fall back to booting from disk. This allows installations to reboot
and try out their installed environment without the need to remove the CD from
the tray (something well appreciated for remote installations).
</p>

<p>
Now we mentioned specifying a kernel. On our Installation CDs, we provide
several kernels. The default one is <c>gentoo</c>. Other kernels are for
specific hardware needs and the <c>-nofb</c> variants which disable
framebuffer.
</p>

<p>
Below you'll find a short overview on the available kernels:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Kernel</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr test="func:keyval('arch')='x86'">
  <ti>gentoo</ti>
  <ti>Default 2.6 kernel with support for multiple CPUs</ti>
</tr>
<tr test="func:keyval('arch')='AMD64'">
  <ti>gentoo</ti>
  <ti>
    Default kernel with support for K8 CPUS (including NUMA support) and EM64T
    CPUs
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>gentoo-nofb</ti>
  <ti>Same as <c>gentoo</c> but without framebuffer support</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>memtest86</ti>
  <ti>Test your local RAM for errors</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
You can also provide kernel options. They represent optional settings you can
(de)activate at will.
</p>

</body>

<body>
 <include href="hb-install-kernelparams.xml"/>
</body>

<body>

<note>
The CD will check for "no*" options before "do*" options, so that you can
override any option in the exact order you specify.
</note>

<p>
Now boot your CD, select a kernel (if you are not happy with the default
<c>gentoo</c> kernel) and boot options. As an example, we show you how
to boot the <c>gentoo</c> kernel, with <c>dopcmcia</c> as kernel
parameters:
</p>

<pre caption="Booting an Installation CD">
boot: <i>gentoo dopcmcia</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will then be greeted with a boot screen and progress bar. If you are
installing Gentoo on a system with a non-US keyboard, make sure you immediately
press Alt-F1 to switch to verbose mode and follow the prompt. If no selection
is made in 10 seconds the default (US keyboard) will be accepted and the boot
process will continue. Once the boot process completes, you will be
automatically logged in to the "Live" Gentoo Linux as "root", the super user.
You should have a root ("#") prompt on the current console and can also switch
to other consoles by pressing Alt-F2, Alt-F3 and Alt-F4. Get back to the one
you started on by pressing Alt-F1.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#hardware">Extra Hardware Configuration</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<include href="hb-install-bootconfig.xml"/>
</subsection>

</section>
</sections>
