<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-mips-medium.xml,v 1.30 2014/08/17 17:01:48 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
You can install Gentoo in many ways. In this chapter we explain how to install
Gentoo using the MIPS Netboot images.
</abstract>

<version>14</version>
<date>2014-08-17</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>CPU <e>(Big Endian port)</e></th>
  <ti>MIPS3, MIPS4, MIPS5 or MIPS64-class CPU</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>CPU <e>(Little Endian port)</e></th>
  <ti>MIPS4, MIPS5 or MIPS64-class CPU</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Memory</th>
  <ti>128 MB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Diskspace</th>
  <ti>3.0 GB (excluding swap space)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Swap space</th>
  <ti>At least 256 MB</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
You should also check the <uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/MIPS/Hardware_Requirements">MIPS
Hardware Requirements</uri> document available on the Gentoo wiki.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Installation Notes</title>
<subsection>
<title>A note about Processor Architectures</title>
<body>

<p>
On many architectures, the processor has gone through several generations, each
newer generation builds on the foundation of the previous one. MIPS is no
exception. There are several generations of CPU covered under the MIPS
architecture. In order to choose your netboot image stage tarball and
<c>CFLAGS</c> appropriately, you need to be aware of which family your system's
CPU belongs in. These families are referred to as the <b>I</b>nstruction
<b>S</b>et <b>A</b>rchitecture.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>MIPS ISA</th>
    <th>32/64-bit</th>
    <th>CPUs Covered</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>MIPS 1</ti>
    <ti>32-bit</ti>
    <ti>
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R2000">R2000</uri>, 
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R2000">R3000</uri>
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>MIPS 2</ti>
    <ti>32-bit</ti>
    <ti>
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R6000">R6000</uri>
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>MIPS 3</ti>
    <ti>64-bit</ti>
    <ti>
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R4000">R4000</uri>,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R4000">R4400</uri>,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R4000">R4600</uri>,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R4000">R4700</uri>
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>MIPS 4</ti>
    <ti>64-bit</ti>
    <ti>
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R5000">R5000</uri>,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R5000">RM5000</uri>,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/RM7000">RM7000</uri>
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R8000">R8000</uri>,
      R9000,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R10000">R10000</uri>,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R10000">R12000</uri>,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R10000">R14000</uri>,
      <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/R10000">R16000</uri>
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>MIPS 5</ti>
    <ti>64-bit</ti>
    <ti>
      None As Yet
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>MIPS32</ti>
    <ti>32-bit</ti>
    <ti>
      AMD Alchemy series, 4kc, 4km, many others... There are a few revisions in
      the MIPS32 ISA.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>MIPS64</ti>
    <ti>64-bit</ti>
    <ti>
      Broadcom SiByte SB1, 5kc ... etc... There are a few revisions in the
      MIPS64 ISA.
    </ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<note>
The <c>MIPS5</c> ISA level was designed by Silicon Graphics back in 1994, but
never actually got used in a real life CPU. It lives on as part of the
<c>MIPS64</c> ISA.
</note>

<note>
The <c>MIPS32</c> and <c>MIPS64</c> ISAs are a common source of confusion. The
<c>MIPS64</c> ISA level is actually a superset of the <c>MIPS5</c> ISA, so it
includes all instructions from <c>MIPS5</c> and earlier ISAs. <c>MIPS32</c> is
the 32-bit subset of <c>MIPS64</c>, it exists because most applications only
require 32-bit processing.
</note>

<p>
Also, another important concept to grasp is the concept of <b>endianness</b>.
Endianness refers to the way that a CPU reads words from main memory. A word
can be read as either <e>big</e> endian (most significant byte first), or
<e>little</e> endian (least significant byte first). Intel x86 machines are
generally Little endian, whilst Apple and Sparc machines are Big Endian. On
MIPS, they can be either. To separate them apart, we append <c>el</c> to the
architecture name to denote little endian.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Architecture</th>
    <th>32/64-bit</th>
    <th>Endianness</th>
    <th>Machines covered</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>mips</c></ti>
    <ti>32-bit</ti>
    <ti>Big Endian</ti>
    <ti>Silicon Graphics</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>mipsel</c></ti>
    <ti>32-bit</ti>
    <ti>Little Endian</ti>
    <ti>Cobalt Servers</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>mips64</c></ti>
    <ti>64-bit</ti>
    <ti>Big Endian</ti>
    <ti>Silicon Graphics</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>mips64el</c></ti>
    <ti>64-bit</ti>
    <ti>Little Endian</ti>
    <ti>Cobalt Servers</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
For those willing to learn more about ISAs, the following websites may be of
assistance.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/Instruction_Set_Architecture">
      Linux/MIPS Website: MIPS ISA
    </uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/Endianess">
      Linux/MIPS Website: Endianness  
    </uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php/Processors">
      Linux/MIPS Website: Processors
    </uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instruction_set">
      Wikipedia: Instruction Set
    </uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The Stage3 Tarball</title>
<body>

<p>
A stage3 tarball is an archive containing a minimal Gentoo environment,
suitable to continue the Gentoo installation using the instructions in this
manual. Previously, the Gentoo Handbook described the installation using one of
three stage tarballs. While Gentoo still offers stage1 and stage2 tarballs,
the official installation method uses the stage3 tarball. If you are interested
in performing a Gentoo installation using a stage1 or stage2 tarball, please
read the Gentoo FAQ on <uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/FAQ#How_do_I_Install_Gentoo_Using_a_Stage1_or_Stage2_Tarball.3F">How
do I Install Gentoo Using a Stage1 or Stage2 Tarball?</uri>
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Netbooting Overview</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
In this section, we'll cover what you need in order to successfully network
boot a Silicon Graphics workstation or Cobalt Server appliance. This is just a
brief guide, it is not intended to be thorough, for more information, it is
recommended that you read the <uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Diskless_nodes">Diskless
HOWTO</uri>.
</p>

<p>
What You Need: Depending on the machine, there is a certain amount of hardware
that you'll need in order to successfully netboot and install Linux.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    In General:
    <ul>
      <li>DHCP/BOAMD Alchemy series, 4kc, 4km, many others... There are a few revisions in
      the MIPS32 ISA.OTP server (ISC DHCPd recommended)</li>
      <li>Patience -- and lots of it</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    For Silicon Graphics workstations:
    <ul>
      <li>TFTP server (tftp-hpa recommended)</li>
      <li>
        If you want/need to use serial console:
        <ul>
          <li>
            MiniDIN8 --&gt; RS-232 serial cable (only needed for IP22 and IP28
            systems)
         </li>
          <li>Null-modem cable</li>
          <li>VT100 or ANSI compatible terminal capable of 9600 baud</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    For Cobalt Servers (NOT the original Qube):
    <ul>
      <li>NFS server</li>
      <li>Null-modem cable</li>
      <li>VT100 or ANSI compatible terminal capable of 115200 baud</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<note>
SGI machines use a MiniDIN 8 connector for the serial ports. Apparently Apple
modem cables work just fine as serial cables, but with Apple machines being
equipped with USB &amp; internal modems, these are getting harder to find. One
wiring diagram is available from the <uri
link="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/Serial_Cable">Linux/MIPS Wiki</uri>, and
most electronics stores should stock the plugs required.
</note>

<note>
For the terminal, this could be a real VT100/ANSI terminal, or it could be a PC
running terminal emulation software (such as HyperTerminal, Minicom, seyon,
Telex, xc, screen -- whatever your preference). It doesn't matter what platform
this machine runs -- just so long as it has one RS-232 serial port you can use,
and appropriate software.
</note>

<note>
Note that this guide does NOT cover the original Qube. The original Qube server
appliance lacks a serial port in its default configuration, and therefore it is
not possible to install Gentoo onto it without the aid of a screwdriver and a
surrogate machine to do the installation. The following site has a guide for
installing Gentoo on these machines.
<uri link="http://www.metzner.org/projects/qube/">
http://www.metzner.org/projects/qube/</uri>
</note>
</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Setting up TFTP and DHCP -- a brief guide</title>
<body>

<p>
Okay, so you've got your bits and pieces together, now to set everything up. As
mentioned earlier -- this is not a complete guide, this is a bare-bones config
that will just get things rolling. You can either use this when starting a
setup from scratch, or use the suggestions to amend your existing setup to
support netbooting.
</p>

<p>
It is worth noting that the servers used need not be running Gentoo Linux, you
could quite reasonably use FreeBSD or any Unix-like platform. However, this
guide will assume you are running Gentoo Linux. You also may run TFTP/NFS on a
separate machine to the DHCP server if desired.
</p>

<warn>
The Gentoo/MIPS Team cannot help you with setting up other operating systems as
netboot servers. If you choose a different OS, it is assumed you know what
you're doing.
</warn>

<p>
First Step -- configuring DHCP. In order for the ISC DHCP daemon to respond to
BOOTP requests (as required by the SGI &amp; Cobalt BOOTROM) you need to first
enable dynamic BOOTP on the address range in use; then set up an entry for each
client with pointers to the boot image.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing ISCs DHCP">
# <i>emerge dhcp</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once installed you need to create the <path>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</path>. Here's
a bare-bones config to get you started.
</p>

<pre caption="Bare Bones dhcpd.conf">
<comment># Tell dhcpd to disable dynamic DNS.</comment>
<comment># dhcpd will refuse to start without this.</comment>
ddns-update-style none;

<comment># Create a subnet:</comment>
subnet <i>192.168.10.0</i> netmask <i>255.255.255.0</i> {
  <comment># Address pool for our booting clients. Don't forget the 'dynamic-bootp' bit!</comment>
  pool {
    range dynamic-bootp <i>192.168.10.1 192.168.10.254</i>;
  }

  <comment># DNS servers and default gateway -- substitute as appropriate</comment>
  option domain-name-servers <i>203.1.72.96</i>, <i>202.47.56.17</i>;
  option routers <i>192.168.10.1</i>;

  <comment># Tell the DHCP server it's authoritative for this subnet.</comment>
  authoritative;

  <comment># Allow BOOTP to be used on this subnet.</comment>
  allow bootp;
}
</pre>

<p>
With that setup, one can then add any number of clients within the subnet
clause. We will cover what you need to put in later in this guide.
</p>

<p>
Next Step -- Setting up TFTP server. It is recommended that you use
<c>tftp-hpa</c> as it is the only TFTP daemon known to work correctly. Proceed
by installing it as shown below.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing tftp-hpa">
# <i>emerge net-ftp/tftp-hpa</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will create <path>/tftproot</path> for you to store the netboot images.
You may move this elsewhere if you wish. For the purposes of this guide, it is
assumed that you have left it in the default location.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Netbooting on SGI Workstations</title>
<subsection>
<title>Downloading a Netboot image</title>
<body>

<p>
Depending on the system you're installing for, there are several possible
images available for download. These are all labelled according to the system
type and CPU they are compiled for. The machine types are as follows:
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Codename</th>
    <th>Machines</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>IP22</ti>
    <ti>Indy, *Indigo 2, Challenge S</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>IP26</ti>
    <ti>*Indigo 2 Power</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>IP27</ti>
    <ti>Origin 200, Origin 2000</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>IP28</ti>
    <ti>*Indigo 2 Impact</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>IP30</ti>
    <ti>Octane</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>IP32</ti>
    <ti>O2</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<note>
* It is a common mistake to mix up the IRIS Indigo (IP12 w/ R3000 CPU or IP20
w/ R4000 CPU, neither of which run Linux), the Indigo 2 (IP22, which runs Linux
fine), the R8000-based Indigo 2 Power (which doesn't run Linux at all) and the
R10000-based Indigo 2 Impact (IP28, which is highly experimental). Please bear
in mind that these are different machines.
</note>

<p>
Also in the filename, r4k refers to R4000-series processors, r5k for R5000, rm5k
for the RM5200 and r10k for R10000. You will find the images available on the
Gentoo <uri link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>DHCP Configuration for an SGI Client</title>
<body>

<p>
Once you have downloaded the file, place the decompressed image file in your
<path>/tftproot</path> directory. (Use <c>bzip2 -d</c> to decompress) Then edit
your <path>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</path> and add the entry for your SGI client.
</p>

<pre caption="dhcpd.conf snippet for SGI Workstation">
subnet xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx netmask xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx {
  <comment># ... usual stuff here ...</comment>

  <comment># SGI Workstation... change 'sgi' to your SGI machine's hostname.</comment>
  host <i>sgi</i> {
  
    <comment># MAC Address of SGI Machine. Normally this is written on the back</comment>
    <comment># or base of the machine.</comment>
    hardware ethernet <i>08:00:69:08:db:77</i>;

    <comment># TFTP Server to download from (by default, same as DHCP server)</comment>
    next-server <i>192.168.10.1</i>;

    <comment># IP address to give to the SGI machine</comment>
    fixed-address <i>192.168.10.3</i>;

    <comment># Filename for the PROM to download and boot</comment>
    filename "<i>/gentoo-r4k.img</i>";
  }
}
</pre>
</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Kernel Options</title>
<body>
<p>
We're almost done, but there's a couple of little tweaks still to be done. Pull
up a console with root privileges, and enter the following commands.
</p>

<pre caption="Some fixes to SGI machines to have TFTP work properly">
<comment>(Disable "Path Maximum Transfer Unit", otherwise SGI Prom won't find the kernel)</comment>
# <i>echo 1 &gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_no_pmtu_disc</i>

<comment>(Set the port range usable by the SGI PROM)</comment>
# <i>echo "2048 32767" &gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_local_port_range</i>
</pre>

<p>
This should be sufficient to allow the Linux server to play nice with SGI's
PROM.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Start Your Daemons...</title>
<body>
<p>
At this point, you should be ready to start the daemons. Enter the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the DHCP and TFTP daemons">
# <i>/etc/init.d/dhcp start</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/in.tftpd start</i>
</pre>

<p>
If nothing went wrong in that last step you should be all set to power on the
workstation and proceed with the guide. If the DHCP server isn't firing up for
whatever reason, try running 'dhcpd' on the command line and see what it tells
you -- if all is well, it should just fork into the background, otherwise
you'll see 'exiting.' just below its complaint.
</p>

<p>
An easy way to verify if the tftp daemon is running is to type the following
command -- if you see something like the output mentioned below -- everything
is fine.
</p>

<pre caption="Checking TFTPd is running">
# <i>netstat -al | grep ^udp</i>
udp        0      0 *:bootpc                *:*
udp        0      0 *:631                   *:*
udp        0      0 *:xdmcp                 *:*
udp        0      0 *:tftp                  *:* <comment>&lt;-- (look for this line)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Netbooting the SGI machine</title>
<body>

<p>
Okay, everything is set, DHCP is running as is TFTP. Now it is time to fire up
the SGI machine. Power the unit on -- when you see "Running power-on
diagnostics" on the screen, either click "Stop For Maintenance" or press
ESCAPE. You'll be presented with a menu like the following. Enter the commands
as shown below.
</p>

<pre caption="SGI PROM Maintenance Menu">
        Running power-on diagnostics

System Maintenance Menu

1) Start System
2) Install System Software
3) Run Diagnostics
4) Recover System
5) Enter Command Monitor

Option? <i>5</i>
Command Monitor. Type "exit" to return to the menu.
&gt;&gt; <i>bootp(): root=/dev/ram0</i>
</pre>

<p>
From this point, the machine should start downloading the image, then, roughly
20 seconds later, start booting Linux. If all is well, you should be dropped at
the Busybox <c>ash</c> shell as shown below, where you can move on to <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">Configuring Your Network</uri>.
</p>

<pre caption="When things are going right...">
init started:  BusyBox v1.00-pre10 (2004.04.27-02:55+0000) multi-call binary

Gentoo Linux; http://www.gentoo.org/
 Copyright 2001-2004 Gentoo Technologies, Inc.; Distributed under the GPL

 Gentoo/MIPS Netboot for Silicon Graphics Machines
 Build Date: April 26th, 2004

 * To configure networking, do the following:

 * For Static IP:
 * /bin/net-setup &lt;IP Address&gt; &lt;Gateway Address&gt; [telnet]

 * For Dynamic IP:
 * /bin/net-setup dhcp [telnet]

 * If you would like a telnetd daemon loaded as well, pass "telnet"
 * As the final argument to /bin/net-setup.

Please press Enter to activate this console.
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Troubleshooting.</title>
<body>

<p>
If the machine is being stubborn and refusing to download its image, it can be
one of two things, (1) you've made a blunder somewhere, or (2) it needs a
little gentle persuasion. (No, put that sledge hammer down!) Here's a list of
things you can check:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>dhcpd</c> is giving the SGI Machine an IP Address. You should see some
    messages about a BOOTP request in the system logs. <c>tcpdump</c> is also
    useful here.
  </li>
  <li>
    Permissions are set properly in your tftp folder (typically
    <path>/tftproot</path> -- should be world readable)
  </li>
  <li>
    Check system logs to see what the tftp server is reporting (errors perhaps)
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
If you've checked everything on the server, and you're getting timeouts, etc on
the SGI machine, try typing this into the console.
</p>

<pre caption="Coaxing the SGI PROM to work">
&gt;&gt; <i>resetenv</i>
&gt;&gt; <i>unsetenv netaddr</i>
&gt;&gt; <i>unsetenv dlserver</i>
&gt;&gt; <i>init</i>
&gt;&gt; <i>bootp(): root=/dev/ram0</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Alternative Method: Gentoo/MIPS SGI LiveCD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Overview</title>
<body>

<p>
On Silicon Graphics machines, it is possible to boot from a CD in order to
install operating systems. (This is how one installs IRIX for instance)
Recently, images for such bootable CDs to install Gentoo have been made
possible. These CDs are designed to work in the same way.
</p>

<p>
At the moment the Gentoo/MIPS Live CD will only work on the SGI Indy, Indigo 2
and O2 workstations equipped with R4000 and R5000-series CPUs, however other
platforms may be possible in future.
</p>

<p>
You can find the Live CD images for download on your favourite Gentoo Mirror
under the <path>experimental/mips/livecd</path> directory.
</p>

<warn>
These CDs are highly experimental at this time. They may or may not work at this
time. You can report success or failures either on <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org">Bugzilla</uri>, <uri
link="https://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=242518">this forum thread</uri>
or in the <c>#gentoo-mips</c> <uri link="/main/en/irc.xml">IRC channel</uri>. We
would love to hear from you.
</warn>

</body>

</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Burning a Live CD</title>
<body>

<p>
An important thing to note, the SGI PROM does not understand the ISO9660
format, nor does it know anything about the El Torito boot standard. These CD
images are constructed as a SGI disklabel with the boot image in the volume
header like a hard drive. Therefore, care must be taken when burning the CD
image.
</p>

<p>
Below is an example command that assumes 24x burning speed on an IDE burner. If
you have a SCSI burner for instance, you may want to adjust the <c>dev</c>
statement as appropriate. Likewise with the <c>speed</c> option - if you strike
troubles, you might want to try dropping the speed.
</p>

<pre caption="Burning using cdrecord">
# <i>bzip2 -d mips-livecd-prototype-rc2-20041027.img.bz2</i>
# <i>cdrecord -vv -pad speed=24 dev=ATAPI:0,0,0 -tao mips-livecd-prototype-rc2-20041027.img</i>
</pre>

<note>
It may be possible to burn these CDs under Windows, assuming your burning
program just blindly burns the image as is. However, no one has succeeded in
making a working CD this way to date.
</note>

<note>
If you don't know what to put as your <c>dev</c> argument, run <c>cdrecord
-scanbus</c> as root - this will tell you where your burner is located.
</note>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Netbooting on Cobalt Servers</title>
<subsection>
<title>Overview of the netboot procedure</title>
<body>

<p>
Unlike the SGI machines, Cobalt servers use NFS to transfer their kernel for
booting. You boot the machine by holding down the left &amp; right arrow
buttons whilst powering the unit on. The machine will then attempt to obtain an
IP number via BOOTP, mount the <path>/nfsroot</path> directory from the server
via NFS, then try to download and boot the file
<path>vmlinux_raq-2800.gz</path> (depending on the model) which it assumes to
be a standard ELF binary.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Downloading a Netboot image</title>
<body>

<p>
Inside
<uri
link="http://distfiles.gentoo.org/experimental/mips/historical/netboot/cobalt/">
http://distfiles.gentoo.org/experimental/mips/historical/netboot/cobalt/</uri>
you'll find the necessary boot images for getting a Cobalt up and running. The
files you need will have the name
<path>nfsroot-KERNEL-COLO-DATE-cobalt.tar</path> -- select the most recent one
and unpack it to <path>/</path> as shown below:
</p>

<pre caption="Unpacking the nfsroot image">
# <i>tar -C / -xvf nfsroot-2.6.13.4-1.19-20051122-cobalt.tar</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>NFS Server configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
Since this machine uses NFS to download its image, you need to export
<path>/nfsroot</path> on your server. If you have not already done so, you'll
need to install the net-fs/nfs-utils package.
</p>
<pre caption="Installing nfs-utils">
# <i>emerge net-fs/nfs-utils</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once that is done, place the following in your <path>/etc/exports</path> file.
You may set tighter restrictions if you wish.
</p>

<pre caption="Exporting the /nfsroot directory">
/nfsroot      *(ro,sync)
</pre>

<p>
Now, once that is done, you may start the NFS server:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the NFS server">
# <i>/etc/init.d/nfs start</i>
</pre>

<p>
If the NFS server was already running at the time, you can tell it to take
another look at its <c>exports</c> file using <c>exportfs</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Exporting a new filesystem">
# <i>exportfs -av</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>DHCP Configuration for a Cobalt machine</title>
<body>

<p>
Now, the DHCP side of things is relatively straightforward. Add the following
to your <path>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</path> file.
</p>

<pre caption="dhcpd.conf snippet for Cobalt server">
subnet xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx netmask xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx {
  <comment># ... usual stuff here ...</comment>

  <comment># Configuration for a Cobalt Server</comment>
  <comment># Set the hostname here:</comment>
  host <i>qube</i> {
    <comment># Path to the nfsroot directory.</comment>
    <comment># This is mainly for when using the TFTP boot option on CoLo</comment>
    <comment># You shouldn't need to change this.</comment>
    option root-path "/nfsroot";

    <comment># Cobalt server's ethernet MAC address</comment>
    hardware ethernet <i>00:10:e0:00:86:3d</i>;

    <comment># Server to download image from</comment>
    next-server <i>192.168.10.1</i>;

    <comment># IP address of cobalt server</comment>
    fixed-address <i>192.168.10.2</i>;

    <comment># Location of the default.colo file relative to /nfsroot</comment>
    <comment># You shouldn't need to change this.</comment>
    filename "default.colo";
  }
}
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Start Your Daemons...</title>
<body>

<p>
At this point, you should be ready to start the daemons. Enter the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the DHCP and NFS daemons">
# <i>/etc/init.d/dhcp start</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/nfs start</i>
</pre>

<p>
If nothing went wrong in that last step you should be all set to power on the
workstation and proceed with the guide. If the DHCP server isn't firing up for
whatever reason, try running 'dhcpd' on the command line and see what it tells
you -- if all is well, it should just fork into the background, otherwise
you'll see 'exiting.' just below its complaint.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Netbooting the Cobalt machine</title>
<body>

<p>
Okay, everything is set, DHCP is running as is NFS. Now it is time to fire up
the Cobalt machine. Hook up your null modem cable, and set the serial terminal
to use 115200 baud, 8 bits, no parity, 1 stop bit, VT100 emulation. Once that
is done, hold down the left &amp; right arrow buttons whilst powering the unit
on.
</p>

<p>
If all is well, the back panel should display "Net Booting", you should see
some network activity, closely followed by CoLo kicking in. On the rear panel,
scroll down the menu until you see "Network (NFS)" then press ENTER. You should
notice the machine starts booting on the serial console.
</p>

<pre caption="Booting the kernel">
elf: 80080000 &lt;-- 00001000 6586368t + 192624t
elf: entry 80328040
net: interface down
CPU revision is: 000028a0
FPU revision is: 000028a0
Primary instruction cache 32kB, physically tagged, 2-way, linesize 32 bytes.
Primary data cache 32kB 2-way, linesize 32 bytes.
Linux version 2.4.26-mipscvs-20040415 (root@khazad-dum) (gcc version 3.3.3...
Determined physical RAM map:
 memory: 08000000 @ 00000000 (usable)
Initial ramdisk at: 0x80392000 (3366912 bytes)
On node 0 totalpages: 32768
zone(0): 32768 pages.
zone(1): 0 pages.
zone(2): 0 pages.
Kernel command line: console=ttyS0,115200 root=/dev/ram0
Calibrating delay loop... 249.85 BogoMIPS
Memory: 122512k/131072k available (2708k kernel code, 8560k reserved, 3424k dat)
</pre>

<p>
If all is well, you should be dropped at the Busybox <c>ash</c> shell as shown
below, where you can go onto <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">Configuring Your
Network</uri>.
</p>

<pre caption="When things are going right...">
VFS: Mounted root (ext2 filesystem) readonly.
Freeing unused kernel memory: 280k freed
init started:  BusyBox v1.00-pre10 (2004.04.27-02:55+0000) multi-call binary

Gentoo Linux; http://www.gentoo.org/
 Copyright 2001-2004 Gentoo Technologies, Inc.; Distributed under the GPL

 Gentoo/MIPS Netboot for Cobalt Microserver Machines
 Build Date: April 26th, 2004

 * To configure networking, do the following:

 * For Static IP:
 * /bin/net-setup &lt;IP Address&gt; &lt;Gateway Address&gt; [telnet]

 * For Dynamic IP:
 * /bin/net-setup dhcp [telnet]

 * If you would like a telnetd daemon loaded as well, pass "telnet"
 * As the final argument to /bin/net-setup.

Please press Enter to activate this console.
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Troubleshooting.</title>
<body>

<p>
If the machine is being stubborn and refusing to download its image, it can be
one of two things, (1) you've made a blunder somewhere, or (2) it needs a
little gentle persuasion. (No, put that sledge hammer down!) Here's a list of
things you can check:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>dhcpd</c> is giving the Cobalt Machine an IP Address. You should see some
    messages about a BOOTP request in the system logs. <c>tcpdump</c> is also
    useful here.
  </li>
  <li>
    Permissions are set properly in your <path>/nfsroot</path> folder. (should
    be world readable)
  </li>
  <li>
    Make sure the NFS server is running and exporting the <path>/nfsroot</path>
    directory. Check this using <c>exportfs -v</c> on the server.
  </li>
</ul>
</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
