<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-ppc-bootloader.xml,v 1.51 2014/08/17 16:38:13 swift Exp $ -->

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<sections>

<abstract>
Several bootloaders exist. Each one of them has its own way of
configuration. In this chapter we'll describe all possibilities for you
and step you through the process of configuring a bootloader to your
needs.
</abstract>

<version>13</version>
<date>2014-08-17</date>

<section>
<title>Making your Choice</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your kernel is configured and compiled and the necessary system
configuration files are filled in correctly, it is time to install a
program that will fire up your kernel when you start the system. Such a
program is called a <e>bootloader</e>.
</p>

<p>
The bootloader that you use will depend upon the type of PPC machine you have.
</p>

<p>
If you are using a NewWorld Apple or IBM machine, you need to use 
<uri link="#yaboot">yaboot</uri>.  OldWorld Apple machines have two options,
<uri link="#bootx">BootX</uri> (recommended) and <uri link="#quik">quik</uri>.
The Pegasos does not require a bootloader, but you will need to emerge 
<uri link="#bootcreator">bootcreator</uri> to create SmartFirmware boot menus.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="yaboot">
<title>Default: Using yaboot</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<impo>
yaboot can only be used on NewWorld Apple and IBM systems!
</impo>

<p>
In order to find the boot devices, yaboot needs access to the device nodes
created by udev on startup and the sysfs filesystem.  These two filesystems
are found at <path>/dev</path> and <path>sys</path> respectively.  To do this,
you will need to "bind mount" these filesystems from the Installation CD's root
to the <path>/dev</path> and <path>/sys</path> mount points inside the chroot.
If you have already bind mounted these filesystems, there is no need to do it
again.
</p>

<pre caption="Bind-mounting the device and sysfs filesystems">
# <i>exit </i> # this will exit the chroot
# <i>mount --rbind /dev /mnt/gentoo/dev</i>
# <i>mount --rbind /sys /mnt/gentoo/sys</i>
# <i>chroot /mnt/gentoo /bin/bash</i>
# <i>/usr/sbin/env-update &amp;&amp; source /etc/profile </i>
</pre>

<p>
To set up yaboot, you can use <c>yabootconfig</c> to automatically create a
configuration file for you. If you are installing Gentoo on a G5 (where 
<c>yabootconfig</c> does not always work), or you plan to boot from FireWire 
or USB, you will need to manually configure yaboot.
</p>

<note>
You will need to manually edit the <path>yaboot.conf</path> when using
<c>genkernel</c>, even if <c>yabootconfig</c> is used. The kernel image section
of <path>yaboot.conf</path> should be modified as follows (using
<path>vmlinux</path> and <path>initrd</path> as the name of kernel and
<path>initrd</path> image):
</note>

<pre caption="Adding genkernel boot arguments to yaboot.conf">
<comment>###########################################################
## This section can be duplicated if you have more than one
## kernel or set of boot options - replace the image and initrd
## with the exact filename of your kernel and initrd image.
###########################################################</comment>
image=/boot/<keyval id="genkernel-name"/>
  label=Linux
  root=/dev/ram0
  partition=3
  initrd=/boot/<keyval id="genkernel-initrd"/>
  <comment># You can add additional kernel arguments to append such as 
  # rootdelay=10 for a USB/Firewire Boot</comment>
  append="real_root=/dev/sda3"  
  read-only
<comment>##########################################################</comment>
</pre>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#yabootconfig">Default: Using yabootconfig</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#manual_yaboot">Alternative: Manual yaboot Configuration</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="yabootconfig">
<title>Default: Using yabootconfig</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>yabootconfig</c> will auto-detect the partitions on your machine and will
set up dual and triple boot combinations with Linux, Mac OS, and Mac OS X.
</p>

<p>
To use <c>yabootconfig</c>, your drive must have an Apple_Bootstrap partition,
and <path>/etc/fstab</path> must be configured to reflect your Linux 
partitions (note that the Bootstrap partition should <e>not</e> be in your
fstab). These steps should have already been completed before, but check
<path>/etc/fstab</path> before proceeding.  Now, install <c>yaboot</c>.
</p>

<pre caption = "Installing yaboot">
# <i>emerge yaboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now exit the chroot and run <c>yabootconfig --chroot /mnt/gentoo</c>. First, the
program will confirm the location of the bootstrap partition. If you are using
the suggested disk partitioning scheme, your bootstrap partition should be
<path>/dev/sda2</path>. Type <c>Y</c> if the output is correct. If not, double
check your <path>/etc/fstab</path>. <c>yabootconfig</c> will then scan your
system setup, create <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> and run <c>mkofboot</c> for
you.  <c>mkofboot</c> is used to format the Apple_Bootstrap partition, and
install the yaboot configuration file into it. After this enter the chroot
again.
</p>

<pre caption="Re-enter the chroot">
# <i>chroot /mnt/gentoo /bin/bash</i>
# <i>/usr/sbin/env-update &amp;&amp; source /etc/profile</i>
</pre>

<p>
You should verify the contents of <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path>. If you make
changes to <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> (like setting the default/boot OS),
make sure to rerun <c>ybin -v</c> to apply changes to the Apple_Bootstrap
partition.  Whenever you make a change to yaboot.conf, like when testing a new
kernel, always remember to run <c>ybin -v</c> to update the bootstrap
partition.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="manual_yaboot">
<title>Alternative: Manual yaboot Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
First, install <c>yaboot</c> on your system:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing yaboot">
# <i>emerge yaboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
An example <path>yaboot.conf</path> file is given below, but you will need to 
alter it to fit your needs.
</p>

<pre caption = "/etc/yaboot.conf">
<comment>## /etc/yaboot.conf
##
## run: "man yaboot.conf" for details. Do not make changes until you have!!
## see also: /usr/share/doc/yaboot/examples for example configurations.
##
## For a dual-boot menu, add one or more of:
## bsd=/dev/sdaX, macos=/dev/sdaY, macosx=/dev/sdaZ

## The bootstrap partition:</comment>

boot=/dev/sda2

<comment>## ofboot is the Open Firmware way to specify the bootstrap partition.
## If this isn't defined, yaboot fails on the G5 and some G4s (unless 
## you pass the necessary arguments to the mkofboot/ybin program).
## hd:X means /dev/sdaX.
## 
## G5 users should uncomment this line!!

#ofboot=hd:2

## Users booting from firewire should use something like this line:
# ofboot=fw/node/sbp-2/disk@0:

## Users booting from USB should use something like this line:
# ofboot=usb/disk@0:

## hd: is shorthand for the first hard drive Open Firmware sees</comment>
device=hd:

<comment>## Firewire and USB users will need to specify the whole OF device name
## This can be found using ofpath, which is included with yaboot.

# device=fw/node@0001d200e00d0207/sbp-2@c000/disk@0:
</comment>

delay=5
defaultos=macosx
timeout=30
install=/usr/lib/yaboot/yaboot
magicboot=/usr/lib/yaboot/ofboot

<comment>############################################################
## This section can be duplicated if you have more than one
## kernel or set of boot options - replace the image variable
## with the exact filename of your kernel.
###########################################################</comment>
image=/boot/<keyval id="kernel-name"/>
  label=Linux
  root=/dev/sda3
  partition=3
<comment>#  append="rootdelay=10"  # Required for booting USB/Firewire</comment>
  read-only
<comment>##################

## G5 users and some G4 users should set 
##   macos=hd:13/
##   macosx=hd:12
## instead of the example values.</comment>
macos=/dev/sda13
macosx=/dev/sda12
enablecdboot
enableofboot
</pre>

<p>
Once <path>yaboot.conf</path> is configured, run <c>mkofboot -v</c> to format
the Apple_bootstrap partition and install the settings. If you change 
yaboot.conf after the Apple_bootstrap partition has been created, you can
update the settings by running <c>ybin -v</c>
</p>

<pre caption="Setting up the bootstrap partition">
# <i>mkofboot -v</i>
</pre>

<p>
For more information on yaboot, take a look at the <uri
link="http://penguinppc.org/bootloaders/yaboot">yaboot project</uri>. For
now, continue the installation with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the
System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="bootx">
<title>Alternative: BootX</title>
<body>

<impo>
BootX can only be used on OldWorld Apple systems with MacOS 9 or earlier!
</impo>

<p>
Since BootX boots Linux from within MacOS, the kernel will need to be copied
from the Linux Partition to the MacOS partition.  First, mount the MacOS 
partition from outside of the chroot.  Use <c>mac-fdisk -l</c> to find the 
MacOS partition number, sda6 is used as an example here.  Once the partition is
mounted, we'll copy the kernel to the system folder so BootX can find it.
</p>

<pre caption="Copying the kernel to the MacOS partition">
# <i>exit</i>
cdimage ~# <i>mkdir /mnt/mac</i>
cdimage ~# <i>mount /dev/sda6 /mnt/mac -t hfs</i>
cdimage ~# <i>cp /mnt/gentoo/usr/src/linux/vmlinux "/mnt/mac/System Folder/Linux Kernels/<keyval id="kernel-name"/>"</i>
</pre>

<p>
If genkernel is used, both the kernel and initrd will need to be copied to the
MacOS partition.
</p>

<pre caption="Copying the Genkernel kernel and initrd to the MacOS partition">
# <i>exit</i>
cdimage ~# <i>mkdir /mnt/mac</i>
cdimage ~# <i>mount /dev/sda6 /mnt/mac -t hfs</i>
cdimage ~# <i>cp /mnt/gentoo/boot/<keyval id="genkernel-name"/> "/mnt/mac/System Folder/Linux Kernels"</i>
cdimage ~# <i>cp /mnt/gentoo/boot/<keyval id="genkernel-initrd"/> "/mnt/mac/System Folder"</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now that the kernel is copied over, we'll need to reboot to set up BootX.
</p>

<pre caption="Unmounting all partitions and rebooting">
cdimage ~# <i>cd /</i>
cdimage ~# <i>umount -l /mnt/gentoo/dev{/pts,/shm,/proc,/sys,}</i>
cdimage ~# <i>umount -l /mnt/gentoo{/proc,/sys,}</i>
cdimage ~# <i>umount -l /mnt/mac</i>
cdimage ~# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Of course, don't forget to remove the bootable CD, otherwise the CD will be
booted again instead of MacOS.
</p>

<p>
Once the machine has booted into MacOS, open the BootX control panel.  If you're
not using genkernel, select <c>Options</c> and uncheck <c>Use specified RAM
disk</c>.  If you are using genkernel, ensure that the genkernel initrd is 
selected instead of the Installation CD initrd.  If not using genkernel, 
there is now an option to specify the machine's Linux root disk and partition. 
Fill these in with the appropriate values.  Depending upon the kernel 
configuration, additional boot arguments may need to be applied.
</p>

<p>
BootX can be configured to start Linux upon boot. If you do this, you will first
see your machine boot into MacOS then, during startup, BootX will load and start
Linux. See the <uri link="http://penguinppc.org/bootloaders/bootx/">BootX home
page</uri> for more information.
</p>

<impo>
Make sure that you have support for HFS and HFS+ filesystems in your kernel,
otherwise you will not be able to upgrade or change the kernel on your MacOS 
partition.
</impo>

<p>
Now reboot again and boot into Linux, then continue with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=11">Finalizing your Gentoo Installation</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="quik">
<title>Alternative: quik</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>quik</c> allows OldWorld Macs to boot without MacOS. However, it isn't well
supported and has a number of quirks. If you have the option, it is recommended
that you use BootX instead since it is much more reliable and easier to set up
than quik.
</p>

<p>
First, we'll need to install <c>quik</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Emerge quik">
# <i>emerge quik</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next, we'll need to set it up. Edit <path>/etc/quik.conf</path> and set your
image to the kernel that we copied to your boot partition.
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring quik.conf">
# Example of quik.conf
init-message = "Gentoo Linux\n"
<comment># This is the boot partition</comment>
partition = 2
root = /dev/sda4
timeout = 30
default = gentoo
<comment># This is your kernel</comment>
image = /<keyval id="kernel-name"/>
  label = gentoo
</pre>

<p>
Your <path>quik.conf</path> file <e>must</e> be on the same disk as the quik
boot images, however it can be on a different partition on the same disk,
although it is recommended to move it to your boot partition.
</p>

<pre caption="Moving quik.conf to /boot">
# <i>mv /etc/quik.conf /boot/quik.conf</i>
</pre>

<p>
We will now set your boot variables so that quik loads on boot.  To do this,
we'll use a program called <c>nvsetenv</c>.  The variables that you want to
set vary from machine to machine, it's best to find your machine's 
<uri link="http://penguinppc.org/bootloaders/quik/quirks.php">quirks</uri>
before attempting this.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the boot variables">
# <i>nvsetenv auto-boot true</i> <comment># Set to false if you want to boot into OF, not all models can display the OF output</comment>
# <i>nvsetenv output-device video</i> <comment># Check the quirks page, there are many variations here</comment>
# <i>nvsetenv input-device kbd</i>
# <i>nvsetenv boot-device scsi/sd@1:0</i> <comment># For SCSI</comment>
# <i>nvsetenv boot-device ata/ata-disk@0:0</i> <comment># For ATA</comment>
# <i>nvsetenv boot-file /boot/<keyval id="kernel-name"/> root=/dev/sda4</i> <comment>First item is the path to the kernel, the second is the root partition.  You may append any kernel options to the end of this line.</comment>
# <i>nvsetenv boot-command boot</i> <comment># Set this to bye for MacOS and boot for Linux</comment>
</pre>

<note>
It is also possible to change your boot variables from MacOS.  Depending upon
the model, either <uri
link="http://penguinppc.org/bootloaders/quik/BootVars.sit.hqx">bootvars</uri> or
<uri
link="ftp://ftp.apple.com/developer/macosxserver/utilities/SystemDisk2.3.1.smi.bin">
Apple System Disk</uri> should be used.  Please see the quik quirks page above
for more information.
</note>

<p>
Now that we've set up our machine to boot, we'll need to make sure the boot
images are installed correctly.  Run <c>quik -v -C /boot/quik.conf</c>.  It 
should tell you that it has installed the first stage QUIK boot block.
</p>

<note>
If something has gone wrong, you can always reset your PRAM back to the default
values by holding down <c>command + option + p + r</c> before powering on your
machine.  This will clear the values you set with nvsetenv and should allow you
to boot either a MacOS bootdisk or a Linux bootdisk.
</note>

<p>
Now, continue the installation with 
<uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="bootcreator">
<title>Alternative: BootCreator</title>
<body>

<impo>
BootCreator will build a nice SmartFirmware bootmenu written in Forth for the
Pegasos.
</impo>

<p>
First make sure you have <c>bootcreator</c> installed on your system:
</p>

<pre caption = "Installing bootcreator">
# <i>emerge bootcreator</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now copy the file <path>/etc/bootmenu.example</path> into
<path>/etc/bootmenu</path> and edit it to suit your needs:
</p>

<pre caption = "Edit the bootcreator config file">
# <i>cp /etc/bootmenu.example /etc/bootmenu</i>
# <i>nano -w /etc/bootmenu</i>
</pre>

<p>
Below is a complete <path>/etc/bootmenu</path> config file. vmlinux and
initrd should be replaced by your kernel and initrd image names.
</p>

<pre caption = "bootcreator config file">
<comment>#
# Example description file for bootcreator 1.1
#</comment>

[VERSION]
1

[TITLE]
Boot Menu

[SETTINGS]
AbortOnKey = false
Timeout    = 9
Default    = 1

[SECTION]
Local HD -> Morphos      (Normal)
ide:0 boot2.img ramdebug edebugflags="logkprintf"

[SECTION]
Local HD -> Linux (Normal)
ide:0 <keyval id="kernel-name"/> video=radeonfb:1024x768@70 root=/dev/sda3

[SECTION]
Local HD -> Genkernel (Normal)
ide:0 <keyval id="genkernel-name"/> root=/dev/ram0
real_root=/dev/sda3 initrd=<keyval id="genkernel-initrd"/>
</pre>

<p>
Finally the <path>bootmenu</path> must be transferred into Forth and copied to
your boot partition, so that the SmartFirmware can read it.  Therefore you have
to call <c>bootcreator</c>:
</p>

<pre caption = "Install the bootmenu">
# <i>bootcreator /etc/bootmenu /boot/menu</i>
</pre>

<note>
Be sure to have a look into the SmartFirmware's settings when you reboot, that
<path>menu</path> is the file that will be loaded by default.
</note>

<p>
For now, continue the installation with <uri link="#reboot">Rebooting the
System</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="reboot">
<title>Rebooting the System</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Exit the chrooted environment and unmount all mounted partitions. Then type in
that one magical command you have been waiting for: <c>reboot</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Exiting the chroot, unmounting all partitions and rebooting">
# <i>exit</i>
livecd ~# <i>umount -l /mnt/gentoo/dev{/pts,/shm,}</i>
livecd ~# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo{/proc,/sys,}</i>
livecd ~# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once rebooted in your Gentoo installation, finish up with <uri
link="?part=1&amp;chap=11">Finalizing your Gentoo Installation</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
