<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-finalise.xml,v 1.52 2013/01/02 19:16:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
You're almost done. We'll just create one (or more) users for your
system.
</abstract>

<version>11</version>
<date>2013-01-02</date>

<section>
<title>User Administration</title>
<subsection>
<title>Adding a User for Daily Use</title>
<body>

<p>
Working as root on a Unix/Linux system is <e>dangerous</e> and should be avoided
as much as possible. Therefore it is <e>strongly</e> recommended to add a user 
for day-to-day use.
</p>

<p>
The groups the user is member of define what activities the user can perform.
The following table lists a number of important groups you might wish to use:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Group</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>audio</ti>
  <ti>be able to access the audio devices</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>cdrom</ti>
  <ti>be able to directly access optical devices</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>floppy</ti>
  <ti>be able to directly access floppy devices</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>games</ti>
  <ti>be able to play games</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>portage</ti>
  <ti>be able to use <c>emerge --pretend</c> as a normal user</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>usb</ti>
  <ti>be able to access USB devices</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>video</ti>
  <ti>
    be able to access video capturing hardware and doing hardware
    acceleration
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>wheel</ti>
  <ti>be able to use <c>su</c></ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
For instance, to create a user called <c>john</c> who is member of the
<c>wheel</c>, <c>users</c> and <c>audio</c> groups, log in as root first 
(only root can create users) and run <c>useradd</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding a user for day-to-day use">
Login: <i>root</i>
Password: <comment>(Your root password)</comment>

# <i>useradd -m -G users,wheel,audio -s /bin/bash john</i>
# <i>passwd john</i>
Password: <comment>(Enter the password for john)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter the password to verify)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
If a user ever needs to perform some task as root, they can use <c>su -</c>
to temporarily receive root privileges. Another way is to use the <c>sudo</c> 
package which is, if correctly configured, very secure.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Disk Cleanup</title>
<subsection>
<title>Removing tarballs</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that you've finished installing Gentoo and rebooted, if everything has gone
well, you can remove the downloaded stage3 tarball from
your hard disk. Remember that they were downloaded to your <path>/</path>
directory.
</p>

<pre caption="Removing the stage3 tarball">
# <i>rm /stage3-*.tar.bz2*</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
