<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-tools.xml,v 1.55 2013/12/16 21:21:46 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
In this chapter we help you choose and install some important tools.
</abstract>

<version>13</version>
<date>2013-12-16</date>

<section>
<title>System Logger</title>
<body>

<p>
Some tools are missing from the <e>stage3</e> archive because several packages
provide the same functionality. It is now up to you to choose which ones you
want to install.
</p>

<p>
The first tool you need to decide on has to provide logging facilities for your
system. Unix and Linux have an excellent history of logging capabilities -- if
you want you can log everything that happens on your system in logfiles. This
happens through the <e>system logger</e>.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo offers several system loggers to choose from. There are <c>sysklogd</c>,
which is the traditional set of system logging daemons, <c>syslog-ng</c>, an 
advanced system logger, and <c>metalog</c> which is a highly-configurable 
system logger. Others might be available through Portage as well - our number of
available packages increases on a daily basis.
</p>

<p>
If you plan on using <c>sysklogd</c> or <c>syslog-ng</c> you might want to
install <c>logrotate</c> afterwards as those system loggers don't provide any 
rotation mechanism for the log files.
</p>

<p>
To install the system logger of your choice, <c>emerge</c> it and have it added
to the default runlevel using <c>rc-update</c>. The following example installs
<c>syslog-ng</c>. Of course substitute with your system logger:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a system logger">
# <i>emerge syslog-ng</i>
# <i>rc-update add syslog-ng default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Optional: Cron Daemon</title>
<body>

<p>
Next is the cron daemon. Although it is optional and not required for your
system, it is wise to install one. But what is a cron daemon? A cron daemon 
executes scheduled commands. It is very handy if you need to execute some 
command regularly (for instance daily, weekly or monthly).
</p>

<p>
Gentoo offers several possible cron daemons, including <c>bcron</c>, 
<c>dcron</c>, <c>fcron</c> and <c>cronie</c>. Installing one of them
is similar to installing a system logger. However, <c>dcron</c> and
<c>fcron</c> require an extra configuration command, namely <c>crontab
/etc/crontab</c>. If you don't know what to choose, use <c>cronie</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a cron daemon">
# <i>emerge cronie</i>
# <i>rc-update add cronie default</i>
<comment>(Only if you have chosen dcron or fcron)</comment> # <i>crontab /etc/crontab</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Optional: File Indexing</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to index your system's files so you are able to quickly
locate them using the <c>locate</c> tool, you need to install
<c>sys-apps/mlocate</c>. 
</p>

<pre caption="Installing mlocate">
# <i>emerge mlocate</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Optional: Remote Access</title>
<body>

<p>
If you need to access your system remotely after installation, don't forget to
add <c>sshd</c> to the default runlevel:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding sshd to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add sshd default</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you need serial console access (which is possible in case of remote servers),
you might need to uncomment the serial console section in
<path>/etc/inittab</path> if it has not been done already automatically.
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/inittab">
# <i>nano -w /etc/inittab</i>
</pre>

<p>
The following excerpt shows the uncommented section:
</p>

<pre caption="Uncommenting serial consoles in inittab">
<comment># SERIAL CONSOLES</comment>
s0:12345:respawn:/sbin/agetty 9600 ttyS0 vt100
s1:12345:respawn:/sbin/agetty 9600 ttyS1 vt100
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>File System Tools</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Depending on what file systems you are using, you need to install the necessary
file system utilities (for checking the filesystem integrity, creating 
additional file systems etc.). Please note that tools for managing ext2, ext3 or
ext4 filesystems (<c>e2fsprogs</c>) are already installed as a part of the system.
</p>

<p>
The following table lists the tools you need to install if you use a certain
file system:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>File System</th>
  <th>Tool</th>
  <th>Install Command</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>XFS</ti>
  <ti>xfsprogs</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge xfsprogs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ReiserFS</ti>
  <ti>reiserfsprogs</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge reiserfsprogs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>JFS</ti>
  <ti>jfsutils</ti>
  <ti><c>emerge jfsutils</c></ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection test="contains('PPC PPC64', func:keyval('arch'))">
<title>Optional: RAID utilities for IBM hardware</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are using SCSI RAID on a POWER5-based system, you should consider 
installing the <c>iprutils</c> which will allow you to work with the RAID disk 
array, get status on the disks in the arrays, and update microcode among other 
functions.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing iprutils">
# <i>emerge iprutils</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="networking-tools">
<title>Networking Tools</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
If you don't require any additional networking-related tools (such as ppp or a
dhcp client) continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=10">Configuring the
Bootloader</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Installing a DHCP Client</title>
<body>

<p>
If you require Gentoo to automatically obtain an IP address for your network
interface(s), you need to install <c>dhcpcd</c> (or any other DHCP client --
see <uri link="?part=4&amp;chap=3">Modular Networking</uri> for a list of
available DHCP clients). If you don't do this now, you might not be able to
connect to the internet after the installation.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing dhcpcd">
# <i>emerge dhcpcd</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Installing a PPPoE Client</title>
<body>

<p>
If you need <c>ppp</c> to connect to the net, you need to install it.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing ppp">
# <i>emerge ppp</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=10">Configuring the
Bootloader</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
