<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-ppc64-medium.xml,v 1.50 2013/08/15 08:20:26 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
You can install Gentoo in many ways. This chapter explains how to install
Gentoo using the minimal Installation CD.
</abstract>

<version>18</version>
<date>2013-08-15</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>CPU</th>
  <ti>Any PowerPC64 CPU</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Systems</th>
  <ti>
    IBM RS/6000s, Power Macintosh G5, IBM pSeries and IBM iSeries
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Memory</th>
  <ti>64 MB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Diskspace</th>
  <ti>1.5 GB (excluding swap space)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>Swap space</th>
  <ti>At least 256 MB</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
For a full list of supported systems, please go to 
<uri>http://penguinppc.org/about/intro.php#hardware</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<!-- START -->
<section>
<title>The Gentoo Installation CDs</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The <e>Gentoo Installation CDs</e> are bootable CDs which contain a
self-sustained Gentoo environment. They allow you to boot Linux from the CD.
During the boot process your hardware is detected and the appropriate drivers
are loaded. They are maintained by Gentoo developers.
</p>

<p>
All Installation CDs allow you to boot, set up networking, initialize your
partitions and start installing Gentoo from the Internet.
</p>
<!--
<p>
If you wish to install Gentoo without a working Internet connection, please use
the installation instructions described in the <uri
link="2008.0/index.xml">Gentoo 2008.0 Handbooks</uri>.
</p>

<p>
The two Installation CDs that we currently provide are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The Gentoo <e>Minimal</e> Installation CD, a small, no-nonsense, bootable
    CD which sole purpose is to boot the system, prepare the networking and
    continue with the Gentoo installation.
  </li>
  <li>
    The Gentoo <e>Universal</e> Installation CD, a bootable CD with the same
    abilities as the Minimal Installation CD. Additionally, it contains
    several stage3 tarballs (optimized for the individual subarchitectures).
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
To help you decide which Installation CD you need, we have written down the
major advantages and disadvantages of each Installation CD.
</p>
-->
</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo Minimal Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
The Minimal Installation CD is called <c><keyval id="min-cd-name"/></c> and
takes up around <keyval id="min-cd-size"/> MB of diskspace. You can use this
Installation CD to install Gentoo, but <e>only</e> with a working Internet
connection.
</p>
<!--
<table>
<tr>
  <th>Minimal Installation CD</th>
  <th>Pros and Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>Smallest download</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>
    Contains no stage3 tarball, no Portage snapshot, no prebuilt packages and is
    therefore not suitable for networkless installation
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo's Universal Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
The Universal Installation CD is called
<c>install-ppc64-universal-2008.0.iso</c> and uses 460 MB. You can use
this Installation CD to install Gentoo, and you can even use it to install
Gentoo without a working internet connection.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Universal Installation CD</th>
  <th>Pros and Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>
    Contains everything you need. You can even install without a network
    connection.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>Huge download</ti>
</tr>
</table>
-->
</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The Stage3 Tarball</title>
<body>

<p>
A stage3 tarball is an archive containing a minimal Gentoo environment,
suitable to continue the Gentoo installation using the instructions in this
manual. Previously, the Gentoo Handbook described the installation using one of
three stage tarballs. While Gentoo still offers stage1 and stage2 tarballs, the
official installation method uses the stage3 tarball. If you are interested in
performing a Gentoo installation using a stage1 or stage2 tarball, please read
the Gentoo FAQ on <uri link="/doc/en/faq.xml#stage12">How do I Install Gentoo
Using a Stage1 or Stage2 Tarball?</uri>
</p>

<p>
Stage3 tarballs can be downloaded from <path><keyval
id="release-dir"/>current-stage3/</path> on any of the <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">Official Gentoo Mirrors</uri> and are not provided
on the LiveCD.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Choosing a userland</title>
<body>

<p>
On PPC64, the kernel is 64-bit and the <e>userland</e> can be 32-bit or 64-bit.
The userland is basically the applications you are running, such as <c>bash</c>
or <c>firefox</c>. They can be compiled and run in either 64-bit or
32-bit modes. The Gentoo/PPC64 team provides both 32-bit and 64-bit userlands,
so which one should you use?
</p>

<p>
You may have heard that 64-bit applications are better, but in fact, 32-bit
applications take up slightly less memory and often run a little bit faster than
64-bit applications.
</p>

<p>
You really only need 64-bit applications when you need more memory than a 32-bit
userland allows, or if you do a lot of 64-bit number crunching. If you have 4GB
or more of memory or you run scientific applications, you should choose the
64-bit userland. Otherwise, choose the 32-bit userland, as it is recommended by
the Gentoo/PPC64 developers.
</p>

<p>
Additionally, the 32-bit userland has been available in Portage longer than the
64-bit userland has. This means that there are more applications tested in the
32-bit userland that just work "out of the box." Many applications compiled for
the 64-bit userland may be just as stable as the 32-bit version, but they
haven't been tested yet. Though testing isn't difficult to do, it can be
annoying and time consuming if you want to use many untested 64-bit
applications. Also, some programs just won't run in the 64-bit userland until
their code is fixed, such as OpenOffice.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!-- STOP -->
<section>
<title>Download, Burn and Boot a Gentoo Installation CD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Downloading and Burning the Installation CDs</title>
<body>

<p>
You have chosen to use a Gentoo Installation CD. We'll first start by 
downloading and burning the chosen Installation CD. We previously discussed the 
several available Installation CDs, but where can you find them? 
</p>

<p>
You can download any of the Installation CDs from one of our <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri>. The Installation CDs are located in
the <path><keyval id="release-dir"/>current-iso/</path> directory.
</p>

<p>
Inside that directory you'll find ISO files. Those are full CD images
which you can write on a CD-R.
</p>

<p>
In case you wonder if your downloaded file is corrupted or not, you can check
its SHA-2 checksum and compare it with the SHA-2 checksum we provide (such as
<path><keyval id="min-cd-name"/>.DIGESTS</path>). You can check the SHA-2 
checksum with the <c>sha512sum</c> tool under Linux/Unix or <uri
link="http://www.sinf.gr/en/hashcalc.html">Checksums calculator</uri> for Windows.
</p>

<pre caption="Verifying the SHA-2 checksum">
$ <i>sha512sum -c &lt;downloaded iso.DIGESTS&gt;</i>
</pre>

<note>
If you get the message that no properly formatted SHA checksum was found, take a
look at the DIGESTS file yourself to see what the supported checksums are.
</note>

<p>
Another way to check the validity of the downloaded file is to use GnuPG to
verify the cryptographic signature that we provide (the file ending with
<path>.asc</path>). Download the signature file and obtain the public keys whose
key ids can be found on the <uri link="/proj/en/releng/index.xml">release
engineering project site</uri>.
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining the public key">
<comment>(... Substitute the key ids with those mentioned on the release engineering site ...)</comment>
$ <i>gpg --keyserver subkeys.pgp.net --recv-keys 96D8BF6D 2D182910 17072058</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now verify the signature:
</p>

<pre caption="Verify the files">
$ <i>gpg --verify &lt;downloaded iso.DIGESTS.asc&gt;</i>
$ <i>sha512sum -c &lt;downloaded iso.DIGESTS.asc&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
To burn the downloaded ISO(s), you have to select raw-burning. How you
do this is highly program-dependent. We will discuss <c>cdrecord</c> and
<c>K3B</c> here; more information can be found in our <uri
link="/doc/en/faq.xml#isoburning">Gentoo FAQ</uri>.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    With cdrecord, you simply type <c>cdrecord dev=/dev/sr0  &lt;downloaded iso 
    file&gt;</c> (replace <path>/dev/sr0</path> with your CD-RW drive's 
    device path).
  </li>
  <li>
    With K3B, select <c>Tools</c> &gt; <c>Burn CD Image</c>. Then you can locate
    your ISO file within the 'Image to Burn' area. Finally click <c>Start</c>.
  </li>
  <li>
    With Mac OS X Panther, launch <c>Disk Utility</c> from
    <path>Applications/Utilities</path>, select <c>Open</c> from the
    <c>Images</c> menu, select the mounted disk image in the main window and
    select <c>Burn</c> in the <c>Images</c> menu.
  </li>
  <li>
    With Mac OS X Jaguar, launch <c>Disk Copy</c> from
    <path>Applications/Utilities</path>, select <c>Burn Image</c> from the
    <c>File</c> menu, select the ISO and click the <c>Burn</c> button.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Default: Booting the Installation CD on an Apple/IBM</title>
<body>

<p>
Place the Installation CD in the CD-ROM and reboot the system. Hold down the 
'C' key at bootup. You will be greeted by a friendly welcome message and a 
<e>boot:</e> prompt at the bottom of the screen.
</p>

<p>
You are also able to tweak some kernel options at this prompt. The following
table lists the available boot options you can add:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Boot Option</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>video</c></ti>
  <ti>
    This option takes one of the following vendor-specific tags:
    <c>radeonfb</c>, <c>rivafb</c>, <c>atyfb</c>, <c>aty128</c>, <c>nvidiafb</c>
    or <c>ofonly</c>. You can follow this tag with the resolution and
    refreshrate you want to use. For instance
    <c>video=radeonfb:1280x1024@75</c>. If you are uncertain what to choose,
    <c>ofonly</c> will most certainly work.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>nol3</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Disables level 3 cache on some powerbooks (needed for at least the 17")
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>debug</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Enables verbose booting, spawns an initrd shell that can be used to debug
    the Installation CD
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>sleep=X</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Wait X seconds before continuing; this can be needed by some very old SCSI
    CD-ROMs which don't speed up the CD quick enough
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>bootfrom=X</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Boot from a different device
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>dosshd</c></ti>
  <ti>Starts <c>sshd</c>. Useful for unattended installs.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>passwd=foo</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Sets whatever is after the = as the root password. Use with <c>dosshd</c>
    for remote installs.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
At this prompt, hit enter, and a complete Gentoo Linux environment will be
loaded from the CD. Continue with <uri link="#booted">And When You're
Booted...</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>IBM pSeries</title>
<body>

<p>
The CD should autoboot on your pSeries box, but sometimes it does not.  In that
case, you have to set up your cdrom as a bootable device in the multi-boot
menu. If you start your machine with a monitor and a keyboard attached, you can
reach the multi-boot menu pressing the F1 key on startup. But if you start your
machine using the serial console, then you have to press <c>1</c>. Press the
key when you see the beginning of the following line on the serial console:
</p>

<pre caption="Hit the '1' key when this line appears">
memory      keyboard     network      scsi      speaker
</pre>

<p>
The other option is to jump into Open Firmware and do it from there:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    Boot into Open Firmware: same procedure as getting into multi-boot
    (described a few lines above), but use F8 and 8 instead of F1 and 1.
  </li>
  <li>Run the command 0> boot cdrom:1,yaboot</li>
  <li>Stand back and enjoy!</li>
</ol>

<note>
If you get something like the following output, then Open Firmware isn't set up
correctly.  Please use the multi-boot option described above.
</note>

<pre caption="Output if Open Firmware is not set up correctly">
0 > boot cdrom:1,yaboot
 ok
0 >
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="booted">
<title>And When You're Booted...</title>
<body>

<p>
You will be greeted by a root ("#") prompt on the current console. You can also 
switch to other consoles by pressing Alt-fn-F2, Alt-fn-F3 and Alt-fn-F4. Get 
back to the one you started on by pressing Alt-fn-F1.
</p>

<p>
If you are installing Gentoo on a system with a non-US keyboard, use
<c>loadkeys</c> to load the keymap for your keyboard. To list the available
keymaps, execute <c>ls /usr/share/keymaps/i386</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Listing available keymaps">
<comment>(PPC uses x86 keymaps on most systems)</comment>
# <i>ls /usr/share/keymaps/i386</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now load the keymap of your choice:
</p>

<pre caption="Loading a keymap">
# <i>loadkeys be-latin1</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#hardware">Extra Hardware Configuration</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<include href="hb-install-bootconfig.xml"/>
</subsection>

</section>
</sections>
