<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-net-advanced.xml,v 1.24 2014/08/17 16:53:27 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
Here we learn about how the configuration works - you need to know this
before we learn about modular networking.
</abstract>

<version>17</version>
<date>2014-08-17</date>

<section>
<title>Advanced Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>config_eth0</c> variable is the heart of an interface configuration. It's
a high level instruction list for configuring the interface (<c>eth0</c> in this
case). Each command in the instruction list is performed sequentially. The
interface is deemed OK if at least one command works.
</p>

<p>
Here's a list of built-in instructions.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Command</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>null</c></ti>
  <ti>Do nothing</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>noop</c></ti>
  <ti>
    If the interface is up and there is an address then abort configuration
    successfully
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>an IPv4 or IPv6 address</ti>
  <ti>Add the address to the interface</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>
    <c>dhcp</c>, <c>adsl</c> or <c>apipa</c> (or a custom command from a 3rd
    party module)
  </ti>
  <ti>
    Run the module which provides the command. For example <c>dhcp</c> will run
    a module that provides DHCP which can be one of either <c>dhcpcd</c>,
    <c>dhclient</c> or <c>pump</c>.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
If a command fails, you can specify a fallback command. The fallback has to
match the config structure exactly.
</p>

<p>
You can chain these commands together. Here are some real world examples.
</p>

<pre caption="Configuration examples">
<comment># Adding three IPv4 addresses</comment>
config_eth0="192.168.0.2/24
192.168.0.3/24
192.168.0.4/24"

<comment># Adding an IPv4 address and two IPv6 addresses</comment>
config_eth0="192.168.0.2/24
4321:0:1:2:3:4:567:89ab
4321:0:1:2:3:4:567:89ac"

<comment># Keep our kernel assigned address, unless the interface goes
# down so assign another via DHCP. If DHCP fails then add a
# static address determined by APIPA</comment>
config_eth0="noop
dhcp"
fallback_eth0="null
apipa"
</pre>

<note>
When using the <c>ifconfig</c> module and adding more than one address,
interface aliases are created for each extra address. So with the above two
examples you will get interfaces <c>eth0</c>, <c>eth0:1</c> and <c>eth0:2</c>.
You cannot do anything special with these interfaces as the kernel and other
programs will just treat <c>eth0:1</c> and <c>eth0:2</c> as <c>eth0</c>.
</note>

<impo>
The fallback order is important! If we did not specify the <c>null</c> option
then the <c>apipa</c> command would only be run if the <c>noop</c> command
failed.
</impo>

<note>
<uri link="?part=4&amp;chap=3#apipa">APIPA</uri> and <uri
link="?part=4&amp;chap=3#dhcp">DHCP</uri> are discussed later.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Network Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
Init scripts in <path>/etc/init.d</path> can depend on a specific network
interface or just net. All network interfaces in Gentoo's init system provide
what is called <e>net</e>.
</p>

<p>
If, in <path>/etc/rc.conf</path>, <c>rc_depend_strict="YES"</c> is set, then all
network interfaces that provide net must be active before a dependency on "net"
is assumed to be met. In other words, if you have a <path>net.eth0</path> and
<path>net.eth1</path> and an init script depends on "net", then both must be
enabled.
</p>

<p>
On the other hand, if <c>rc_depend_strict="NO"</c> is set, then the "net"
dependency is marked as resolved the moment at least one network interface is
brought up.
</p>

<p>
But what about <path>net.br0</path> depending on <path>net.eth0</path> and
<path>net.eth1</path>? <path>net.eth1</path> may be a wireless or PPP device
that needs configuration before it can be added to the bridge. This cannot be
done in <path>/etc/init.d/net.br0</path> as that's a symbolic link to
<path>net.lo</path>.
</p>

<p>
The answer is defining an <c>rc_need_</c> setting in
<path>/etc/conf.d/net</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="net.br0 dependency in /etc/conf.d/net">
rc_need_br0="net.eth0 net.eth1"
</pre>

<p>
That alone, however, is not sufficient. Gentoo's networking init scripts use a
virtual dependency called <e>net</e> to inform the system when networking is
available. Clearly, in the above case, networking should only be marked as
available when <path>net.br0</path> is up, not when the others are. So we need
to tell that in <path>/etc/conf.d/net</path> as well:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating virtual dependencies and provisions for networking">
rc_net_lo_provide="!net"
rc_net_eth0_provide="!net"
rc_net_eth1_provide="!net"
</pre>

<p>
For a more detailed discussion about dependency, consult the section <uri
link="?part=2&amp;chap=4#doc_chap4">Writing Init Scripts</uri> in the Gentoo
Handbook. More information about <path>/etc/rc.conf</path> is available as
comments within that file.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section id="variable_name">
<title>Variable names and values</title>
<body>

<p>
Variable names are dynamic. They normally follow the structure of
<c>variable_${interface|mac|essid|apmac}</c>. For example, the variable
<c>dhcpcd_eth0</c> holds the value for dhcpcd options for eth0 and
<c>dhcpcd_essid</c> holds the value for dhcpcd options when any interface
connects to the ESSID "essid".
</p>

<p>
However, there is no hard and fast rule that states interface names must be
ethx. In fact, many wireless interfaces have names like wlanx, rax as well as 
ethx. Also, some user defined interfaces such as bridges can be given any name,
such as foo. To make life more interesting, wireless Access Points can have 
names with non alpha-numeric characters in them - this is important because 
you can configure networking parameters per ESSID.
</p>

<p>
The downside of all this is that Gentoo uses bash variables for networking -
and bash cannot use anything outside of English alpha-numerics. To get around
this limitation we change every character that is not an English alpha-numeric
into a <c>_</c> character.
</p>

<p>
Another downside of bash is the content of variables - some characters need to
be escaped. This can be achived by placing the <c>\</c> character in front of
the character that needs to be escaped. The following list of characters needs
to be escaped in this way: <c>"</c>, <c>'</c> and  <c>\</c>.
</p>

<p>
In this example we use wireless ESSID as they can contain the widest scope
of characters. We shall use the ESSID <c>My "\ NET</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="variable name example">
<comment>(This does work, but the domain is invalid)</comment>
dns_domain_My____NET="My \"\\ NET"

<comment>(The above sets the dns domain to My "\ NET when a wireless card
connects to an AP whose ESSID is My "\ NET)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Network Interface Naming</title>
<subsection>
<title>How It Works</title>
<body>

<p>
Network interface names are not chosen arbitrarily: the Linux kernel and the
device manager (most systems have udev as their device manager although others
are available as well) choose the interface name through a fixed set of rules.
</p>

<p>
When an interface card is detected on a system, the Linux kernel gathers the
necessary data about this card. This includes:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    the onboard (on the interface itself) registered name of the network card,
    which is later seen through the <c>ID_NET_NAME_ONBOARD</c> parameter;
  </li>
  <li>
    the slot in which the network card is plugged in, which is later seen
    through the <c>ID_NET_NAME_SLOT</c> parameter; 
  </li>
  <li>
    the path through which the network card device can be accessed, which is
    later seen through the <c>ID_NET_NAME_PATH</c> parameter;
  </li>
  <li>
    the (vendor-provided) MAC address of the card, which is later seen through
    the <c>ID_NET_NAME_MAC</c> parameter;
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
Based on this information, the device manager decides how to name the interface
on the system. By default, it uses the first hit of the first three parameters
above (<c>ID_NET_NAME_ONBOARD</c>, <c>_SLOT</c> or <c>_PATH</c>).
For instance, if <c>ID_NET_NAME_ONBOARD</c> is found and set to <c>eno1</c>, then
the interface will be called eno1.
</p>

<p>
If you know your interface name, you can see the values of the provided
parameters using <c>udevadm</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Reading the network interface card information">
# <i>udevadm test-builtin net_id /sys/class/net/enp3s0 2>/dev/null</i>
ID_NET_NAME_MAC=enxc80aa9429d76
ID_OUI_FROM_DATABASE=Quanta Computer Inc.
ID_NET_NAME_PATH=enp3s0
</pre>

<p>
As the first (and actually only) hit of the top three parameters is the
<c>ID_NET_NAME_PATH</c> one, its value is used as the interface name. If none of
the parameters is found, then the system reverts back to the kernel-provided
naming (eth0, eth1, etc.)
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Using the Old-style Kernel Naming</title>
<body>

<p>
Before this change, network interface cards were named by the Linux kernel
itself, depending on the order that drivers are loaded (amongst other, possibly
more obscure reasons). This behavior can still be enabled by setting the
<c>net.ifnames=0</c> boot option in the boot loader.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Using your Own Names</title>
<body>

<p>
The entire idea behind the change in naming is not to confuse people, but to
make changing the names easier. Suppose you have two interfaces that are
otherwise called eth0 and eth1. One is meant to access the network through a
wire, the other one is for wireless access. With the support for interface
naming, you can have these called lan0 (wired) and wifi0 (wireless - it is best
to avoid using the previously well-known names like eth* and wlan* as those can
still collide with your suggested names).
</p>

<p>
All you need to do is to find out what the parameters are for the cards and then
use this information to set up your own naming rule:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the lan0 name for the current eth0 interface">
# <i>udevadm test-builtin net_id /sys/class/net/eth0 2>/dev/null</i>
ID_NET_NAME_MAC=enxc80aa9429d76
ID_OUI_FROM_DATABASE=Quanta Computer Inc.

# <i>vim /etc/udev/rules.d/70-net-name-use-custom.rules</i>
<comment># First one uses MAC information, and 70- number to be before other net rules</comment>
SUBSYSTEM=="net", ACTION=="add", ATTR{address}=="c8:0a:a9:42:9d:76", NAME="lan0"

# <i>vim /etc/udev/rules.d/76-net-name-use-custom.rules</i>
<comment># Second one uses ID_NET_NAME_PATH information, and 76- number to be between</comment>
<comment># 75-net-*.rules and 80-net-*.rules</comment>
SUBSYSTEM=="net", ACTION=="add", ENV{ID_NET_NAME_PATH}=="enp3s0", NAME="wifi0"
</pre>

<p>
Because the rules are triggered before the default one (rules are triggered in
alphanumerical order, so 70 comes before 80) the names provided in the rule file
will be used instead of the default ones. The number granted to the file should
be between 76 and 79 (the environment variables are defined by a rule start
starts with 75 and the fallback naming is done in a rule numbered 80).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
