<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-net-modules.xml,v 1.32 2014/09/25 08:21:34 jkt Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
Gentoo provides you flexible networking - here you are told about choosing
different DHCP clients, setting up bonding, bridging, VLANs and more.
</abstract>

<version>15</version>
<date>2014-09-25</date>

<section>
<title>Network Modules</title>
<body>

<p>
We now support modular networking scripts, which means we can easily add support
for new interface types and configuration modules while keeping compatibility
with existing ones.
</p>

<p>
Modules load by default if the package they need is installed.  If you specify a
module here that doesn't have its package installed then you get an error
stating which package you need to install. Ideally, you only use the modules
setting when you have two or more packages installed that supply the same
service and you need to prefer one over the other.
</p>

<note>
All settings discussed here are stored in <path>/etc/conf.d/net</path> unless 
otherwise specified.
</note>

<pre caption="Module preference">
<comment># Prefer ifconfig over iproute2</comment>
modules="ifconfig"

<comment># You can also specify other modules for an interface
# In this case we prefer pump over dhcpcd</comment>
modules_eth0="pump"

<comment># You can also specify which modules not to use - for example you may be
# using a supplicant or linux-wlan-ng to control wireless configuration but
# you still want to configure network settings per ESSID associated with.</comment>
modules="!iwconfig"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Interface Handlers</title>
<body>

<p>
We provide two interface handlers presently: <c>ifconfig</c> and
<c>iproute2</c>. You need one of these to do any kind of network configuration.
</p>

<p>
<c>ifconfig</c> is installed by default (the <c>net-tools</c> package is part of
the system profile). <c>iproute2</c> is a more powerful and flexible package,
but it's not included by default.
</p>

<pre caption="To install iproute2">
# <i>emerge sys-apps/iproute2</i>

<comment># To prefer ifconfig over iproute2 if both are installed as openrc prefers
# to use iproute2 then</comment>
modules="ifconfig"
</pre>

<p>
As both <c>ifconfig</c> and <c>iproute2</c> do very similar things we allow
their basic configuration to work with each other. For example both the below
code snippet work regardless of which module you are using.
</p>

<pre caption="ifconfig and iproute2 examples">
config_eth0="192.168.0.2/24"
config_eth0="192.168.0.2 netmask 255.255.255.0"

<comment># We can also specify broadcast</comment>
config_eth0="192.168.0.2/24 brd 192.168.0.255"
config_eth0="192.168.0.2 netmask 255.255.255.0 broadcast 192.168.0.255"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="dhcp">
<title>DHCP</title>
<body>

<p>
DHCP is a means of obtaining network information (IP address, DNS servers,
Gateway, etc) from a DHCP server. This means that if there is a DHCP server
running on the network, you just have to tell each client to use DHCP and it
sets up the network all by itself. Of course, you will have to configure for
other things like wireless, PPP or other things if required before you can use
DHCP.
</p>

<p>
DHCP can be provided by <c>dhclient</c>, <c>dhcpcd</c>, or <c>pump</c>. Each
DHCP module has its pros and cons - here's a quick run down.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>DHCP Module</th>
  <th>Package</th>
  <th>Pros</th>
  <th>Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>dhclient</c></ti>
  <ti><c>net-misc/dhcp</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Made by ISC, the same people who make the BIND DNS software. Very 
    configurable
  </ti>
  <ti>
    Configuration is overly complex, software is quite bloated, cannot get 
    NTP servers from DHCP, does not send hostname by default
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>dhcpcd</c></ti>
  <ti><c>net-misc/dhcpcd</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Long time Gentoo default, no reliance on outside tools, actively developed
    by Gentoo
  </ti>
  <ti>Can be slow at times, does not yet daemonize when lease is infinite</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>pump</c></ti>
  <ti><c>net-misc/pump</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Lightweight, no reliance on outside tools
  </ti>
  <ti>
    No longer maintained upstream, unreliable, especially over modems, cannot
    get NIS servers from DHCP
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>
     
<p>
If you have more than one DHCP client installed, you need to specify which one
to use - otherwise we default to <c>dhcpcd</c> if available.
</p>

<p>
To send specific options to the DHCP module, use <c>module_eth0="..."</c>
<e>(change module to the DHCP module you're using - i.e. <c>dhcpcd_eth0</c>)</e>.
</p>

<p>
We try and make DHCP relatively agnostic - as such we support the following
commands using the <c>dhcp_eth0</c> variable. The default is not to set any of
them:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><c>release</c> - releases the IP address for re-use</li>
  <li><c>nodns</c> - don't overwrite <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path></li>
  <li><c>nontp</c> - don't overwrite <path>/etc/ntp.conf</path></li>
  <li><c>nonis</c> - don't overwrite <path>/etc/yp.conf</path></li>
</ul>

<pre caption="Sample DHCP configuration in /etc/conf.d/net">
<comment># Only needed if you have more than one DHCP module installed</comment>
modules="dhcpcd"

config_eth0="dhcp"
dhcpcd_eth0="-t 10" <comment># Timeout after 10 seconds</comment>
dhcp_eth0="release nodns nontp nonis" <comment># Only get an address</comment>
</pre>

<note>
<c>dhcpcd</c> and <c>pump</c> send the current hostname to the
DHCP server by default so you don't need to specify this anymore.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>ADSL with PPPoE/PPPoA</title>
<body>

<p>
First we need to install the ADSL software.
</p>

<pre caption="Install the ppp package">
# <i>emerge net-dialup/ppp</i>
</pre>

<p>
Second, create the PPP net script and the net script for the ethernet interface
to be used by PPP:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the PPP and ethernet scripts">
# <i>ln -s /etc/init.d/net.lo /etc/init.d/net.ppp0</i>
# <i>ln -s /etc/init.d/net.lo /etc/init.d/net.eth0</i>
</pre>

<p>
Be sure to set <c>rc_depend_strict</c> to "YES" in <path>/etc/rc.conf</path>.
</p>

<p>
Now we need to configure <path>/etc/conf.d/net</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="A basic PPPoE setup">
config_eth0=null <comment>(Specify your ethernet interface)</comment>
config_ppp0="ppp"
link_ppp0="eth0" <comment>(Specify your ethernet interface)</comment>
plugins_ppp0="pppoe"
username_ppp0='user'
password_ppp0='password'
pppd_ppp0="
noauth
defaultroute
usepeerdns
holdoff 3
child-timeout 60
lcp-echo-interval 15
lcp-echo-failure 3
noaccomp noccp nobsdcomp nodeflate nopcomp novj novjccomp"

rc_need_ppp0="net.eth0"
</pre>

<p>
You can also set your password in <path>/etc/ppp/pap-secrets</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Sample /etc/ppp/pap-secrets">
<comment># The * is important</comment>
"username"  *  "password"
</pre>

<p>
If you use PPPoE with a USB modem you'll need to emerge <c>br2684ctl</c>. Please
read <path>/usr/portage/net-dialup/speedtouch-usb/files/README</path> for
information on how to properly configure it.
</p>

<impo>
Please carefully read the section on ADSL and PPP in
<path>/usr/share/doc/netifrc-*/net.example.bz2</path>. It contains many
more detailed explanations of all the settings your particular PPP setup will
likely need.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
<section id="apipa">
<title>APIPA (Automatic Private IP Addressing)</title>
<body>

<p>
APIPA tries to find a free address in the range 169.254.0.0-169.254.255.255 by
arping a random address in that range on the interface. If no reply is found
then we assign that address to the interface.
</p>

<p>
This is only useful for LANs where there is no DHCP server and you don't connect
directly to the internet and all other computers use APIPA.
</p>

<p>
For APIPA support, emerge <c>net-misc/iputils</c> or <c>net-analyzer/arping</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="APIPA configuration in /etc/conf.d/net">
<comment># Try DHCP first - if that fails then fallback to APIPA</comment>
config_eth0="dhcp"
fallback_eth0="apipa"

<comment># Just use APIPA</comment>
config_eth0="apipa"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bonding</title>
<body>

<p>
For link bonding/trunking emerge <c>net-misc/ifenslave</c>.
</p>

<p>
Bonding is used to increase network bandwidth or to improve resiliency in face
of hardware failures. If you have two network cards going to the same network,
you can bond them together so your applications see just one interface but they
really use both network cards.
</p>

<p>
There are many ways to configure bonding. Some of them, such as the 802.3ad LACP
mode, require support and additional configuration of the network switch. For a
reference of the individual options, please refer to your copy of
<path>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/networking/bonding.txt</path>.
</p>

<p>
First, clear the configuration of the participating interfaces:
</p>

<pre caption="Clearing interface configuration in /etc/conf.d/net">
config_eth0="null"
config_eth1="null"
config_eth2="null"
</pre>

<p>
Next, define the bonding between the interfaces:
</p>

<pre caption="Define the bonding">
slaves_bond0="eth0 eth1 eth2"
config_bond0="192.168.100.4/24"
<comment># Pick a correct mode and additional configuration options which suit your needs</comment>
mode_bond0="balance-alb"
</pre>

<p>
Remove the <path>net.eth*</path> services from the runlevels, create a
<path>net.bond0</path> one and add that one to the correct runlevel.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bridging (802.1d support)</title>
<body>

<p>
For bridging support emerge <c>net-misc/bridge-utils</c>.
</p>

<p>
Bridging is used to join networks together. For example, you may have a server
that connects to the internet via an ADSL modem and a wireless access card to
enable other computers to connect to the internet via the ADSL modem. You could
create a bridge to join the two interfaces together.
</p>

<pre caption="Bridge configuration in /etc/conf.d/net">
<comment># Configure the bridge - "man brctl" for more details</comment>
brctl_br0="setfd 0
sethello 2
stp on"

<comment># To add ports to bridge br0</comment>
bridge_br0="eth0 eth1"

<comment># You need to configure the ports to null values so dhcp does not get started</comment>
config_eth0="null"
config_eth1="null"

<comment># Finally give the bridge an address - you could use DHCP as well</comment>
config_br0="192.168.0.1/24"

<comment># Depend on eth0 and eth1 as they may require extra configuration</comment>
rc_need_br0="net.eth0 net.eth1"
</pre>

<impo>
For using some bridge setups, you may need to consult the <uri
link="?part=4&amp;chap=2#variable_name">variable name</uri> documentation.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>MAC Address</title>
<body>

<p>
If you need to, you can change the MAC address of your interfaces through
the network configuration file too.
</p>

<pre caption="MAC Address change example">
<comment># To set the MAC address of the interface</comment>
mac_eth0="00:11:22:33:44:55"

<comment># To randomize the last 3 bytes only</comment>
mac_eth0="random-ending"

<comment># To randomize between the same physical type of connection (e.g. fibre,
# copper, wireless) , all vendors</comment>
mac_eth0="random-samekind"

<comment># To randomize between any physical type of connection (e.g. fibre, copper,
# wireless) , all vendors</comment>
mac_eth0="random-anykind"

<comment># Full randomization - WARNING: some MAC addresses generated by this may
# NOT act as expected</comment>
mac_eth0="random-full"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Tunnelling</title>
<body>

<p>
You don't need to emerge anything for tunnelling as the interface handler can do
it for you.
</p>

<pre caption="Tunnelling configuration in /etc/conf.d/net">
<comment># For GRE tunnels</comment>
iptunnel_vpn0="mode gre remote 207.170.82.1 key 0xffffffff ttl 255"

<comment># For IPIP tunnels</comment>
iptunnel_vpn0="mode ipip remote 207.170.82.2 ttl 255"

<comment># To configure the interface</comment>
config_vpn0="192.168.0.2 peer 192.168.1.1"
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>VLAN (802.1q support)</title>
<body>

<p>
For VLAN support, make sure that <c>sys-apps/iproute2</c> is installed and ensure
that iproute2 is used as configuration module rather than ifconfig.
</p>

<p>
Virtual LAN is a group of network devices that behave as if they were connected
to a single network segment - even though they may not be. VLAN members can only
see members of the same VLAN even though they may share the same physical
network.
</p>

<p>
To configure VLANs, first specify the VLAN numbers in
<path>/etc/conf.d/net</path> like so:
</p>

<pre caption="Specifying VLAN numbers">
vlans_eth0="1 2"
</pre>

<p>
Next, configure the interface for each VLAN:
</p>

<pre caption="Interface configuration for each VLAN">
config_eth0_1="172.16.3.1 netmask 255.255.254.0"
routes_eth0_1="default via 172.16.3.254"

config_eth0_2="172.16.2.1 netmask 255.255.254.0"
routes_eth0_2="default via 172.16.2.254"
</pre>

<p>
VLAN-specific configurations are handled by <c>vconfig</c> like so:
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring the VLANs">
vlan1_name="vlan1"
vlan1_ingress="2:6 3:5"
eth0_vlan1_egress="1:2"
</pre>

<impo>
For using some VLAN setups, you may need to consult the <uri
link="?part=4&amp;chap=2#variable_name">variable name</uri> documentation.
</impo>

</body>
</section>

</sections>
