<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-net-management.xml,v 1.14 2013/12/17 11:48:58 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
For laptop users or people who move their computer around different networks.
</abstract>

<version>11</version>
<date>2013-12-17</date>

<section>
<title>Network Management</title>
<body>

<p>
If you and your computer are always on the move, you may not always have an
ethernet cable or plugged in or an access point available. Also, you may want
networking to automatically work when an ethernet cable is plugged in or an
access point is found.
</p>

<p>
Here you can find some tools that help you manage this.
</p>

<note>
This document only talks about <c>ifplugd</c>, but there are alternatives such
as <c>netplug</c>. <c>netplug</c> is a lightweight alternative to
<c>ifplugd</c>, but it relies on your kernel network drivers working correctly,
and many drivers do not.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>ifplugd</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://0pointer.de/lennart/projects/ifplugd/">ifplugd</uri> is a
daemon that starts and stops interfaces when an ethernet cable is inserted or
removed. It can also manage detecting association to Access Points or when new
ones come in range.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing ifplugd">
# <i>emerge sys-apps/ifplugd</i>
</pre>

<p>
Configuration for ifplugd is fairly straightforward too. The configuration file
is held in <path>/etc/conf.d/net</path>. Run <c>man ifplugd</c> for details on
the available variables. Also, see
<path>/usr/share/doc/netifrc-*/net.example.bz2</path> for more examples.
</p>

<pre caption="Sample ifplug configuration">
<comment>(Replace eth0 with the interface to be monitored)</comment>
ifplugd_eth0="..."

<comment>(To monitor a wireless interface)</comment>
ifplugd_eth0="--api-mode=wlan"
</pre>

<p>
In addition to managing multiple network connections, you may want to add a tool
that makes it easy to work with multiple DNS servers and configurations. This is
very handy when you receive your IP address via DHCP. Simply emerge
<c>openresolv</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing openresolv">
# <i>emerge openresolv</i>
</pre>

<p>
See <c>man resolvconf</c> to learn more about its features.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</sections>
