<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-desktop-plugnplay.xml,v 1.4 2010/08/12 15:27:54 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>Identify your needs</title>
<subsection>
<title>Nothing is automated at first</title>
<body>

<p>
When you first use your system, you'll notice that you need to perform various
steps manually which could be done automatically. Gentoo Linux doesn't put its
development effort in making a system userfriendly in the sense of allowing
everything. Not only can it cause instability on some systems, far from all
users appreciate us touching the configuration of their system and it might
cause security issues on some environments.
</p>

<p>
So, if you want certain tasks automated, you'll need to lend your system a hand
at first. But you can't help your system if you don't know what you want. Next
is a list of automation tasks we'll cover in the next few sections. This list is
far from complete, but should give you a good impression on the possibilities.
Ask around on our IRC channel or mailinglist if you want to automate other
tasks. 
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <e>Removable media</e> covers the automated mounting of removable media like
    floppies, CD/DVDs, USB storage devices, camera's, ... on your system.
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>Network detection</e> explains how to configure your network card
    (wireless or not) to automatically discover networks and run a certain
    configuration based on the network it finds.
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>Data synchronisation</e> describes how to synchronise files and 
    directories on your system with other systems, laptops or PDAs, and also the
    synchronisation of your journal, address books, etc. 
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>Power consumption</e> informs you how you can decrease the power
    consumption of your system (probably a laptop) by automatically putting the
    hard disk to sleep, disable wireless if it isn't needed, adjust the screen
    settings to use less power, etc.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!--
<section>
<title>Removable media</title>
<subsection>
<title>What is ?</title>
<body>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Installing and setting up </title>
<body>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
-->
<section>
<title>Network detection</title>
<subsection>
<title>What you can and can't do</title>
<body>

<p>
If all your networks are nice enough to provide DHCP services, then you just
need to set your interface to ask for an IP address. However, if you need to
provide static IP addresses for a few networks, then you're out of luck: as
networks don't provide an identification service, there is no way for a computer
to know what network it is in.
</p>

<p>
However, when you are using wireless networks, most of them do provide network
identification using the ESSID. The <uri
link="http://hostap.epitest.fi/wpa_supplicant/">wpa_supplicant</uri> tool allows
you to pick wireless settings based on the ESSID. The Gentoo baselayout package
allows for ESSID-specific network settings.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<!--
<section>
<title>Data synchronisation</title>
</section>

<section>
<title>Power consumption</title>
</section>
-->
</sections>
