<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-desktop-graphical.xml,v 1.8 2007/01/09 08:24:09 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>2006-12-27</date>

<section>
<title>The X server</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Many users believe that Linux is a command-line driven operating system. This
isn't true, but the command-line interface is a standard, well-supported input
method for Linux. However, graphical input is well supported and rivals other
operating systems with its usability, flexibility and stability.
</p>

<p>
Like all tools, the graphical environment is also "just a tool" build to do what
it is supposed to do: provide a graphical environment for the end user and
libraries for developers so they can write graphical tools. The base of a
graphical environment are the <e>X11 libraries</e> and <e>X11 server</e>.
</p>

<p>
X11 is a network protocol designed to allow graphical environments to be
exported over the network. As such, any graphical environment built using the
X11 libraries can run on a server while it is displayed on a client. But we're
drifting away now...
</p>

<p>
The X11 server is a service that performs the rendering of graphical
environments. It isn't a graphical environment by itself but offers the base for
graphical environments to be built: it is a framework where other software
packages build upon.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo supports the <c>xorg-x11</c> X11 server.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
Since the X11 server performs the rendering, you need to configure it to use the
hardware you work on. Gentoo has a nice <uri link="/doc/en/xorg-config.xml">X
Server Configuration HOWTO</uri> which you definitely should read.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Desktop Environments</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
With a bare X11 server you won't be able to do much. You need a window manager
which takes care of the graphical layout of the environment and possibly even a
desktop environment which integrates tools and usability guidelines with a
window manager.
</p>

<p>
A desktop environment is a full blown graphical environment offering everything
a desktop might need, all in a coherent package. Backgrounds, file management,
drag and drop, screensavers, menus, theming with icons and sounds, virtual
desktops, ... you name it, all of that is defined in a desktop environment. This
is also why most users are searching for a desktop environment.
</p>

<p>
Users who want a small graphical environment with just the tools they need often
opt for a window manager instead as they don't need all the bells and whistles a
desktop environment offers.
</p>

<p>
The next few paragraphs give a small introduction to various desktop 
environments. The next section discusses a few window managers. The list is not
meant to be exhaustive but rather to provide some guidance to the new Gentoo
user.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>KDE</title>
<body>

<p>
With KDE, users are offered a full-blown environment with a plethora of desktop
utilities. It seems as if the KDE project tries to contain everything a user
might require from a desktop: games, development tools, office suites, imaging
support, multimedia tools, desklets, system utilities, ... and all those build
upon the same libraries so all tools have a consistent look and feel and offer a
well developed drag and drop mechanism.
</p>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.kde.org">KDE project</uri> maintains much
documentation (in various languages) and offers a quick release cycle with new
features and fixes available at every new release.  You'll find that the
integration of the tools is flawless (the address book is linked from the
Personal Information Management tool <c>kontact</c>, E-mail client <c>kmail</c>,
Event Manager <c>kjournal</c> and of course the Address book maintenance tool
<c>kaddressbook</c>) and the configuration interface <c>kcontrol</c> complete
and well documented.
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in using KDE, don't hesitate to read the <uri
link="/doc/en/kde-config.xml">KDE Configuration Guide</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>GNOME</title>
<body>

<p>
The GNOME Foundation offers a consistent desktop environment (GNOME) which is
developed using strict guidelines, offering a maximum on usability (layout and
so on are strictly defined). Many GNOME enthusiasts are proud of their
environment because it is simple to use, yet powerful and fully functional.
</p>

<p>
When you load up GNOME, you will notice that its interface is sober but well
designed: the GNOME menu limits itself to the tools you'll most likely use while
hiding the rest of the tools that probably confuse most of the users anyway.
The window decoration is simple, but gives a nice finished look. Configuration
options are limited at first sight but are very easy to comprehend. Real
configuration gurus know that GNOME has a very extended configuration model, but
it is hidden from the interface because most users wouldn't need it anyway.
</p>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.gnome/org">GNOME project</uri> has multi-lingual
documentation and a good network of related sites where you can find the latest
news about GNOME and GNOME tools. 
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in using GNOME, don't hesitate to read the <uri
link="/doc/en/gnome-config.xml">GNOME Configuration Guide</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Window Managers</title>
<subsection>
<title>Fluxbox</title>
<body>

<p>
The fluxbox window manager began its life as a spin-off of the blackbox window
manager. When you install fluxbox, you'll notice that it is a <e>lot</e> faster
than desktop environments. This of course isn't only true for fluxbox but for
most other window managers: their job is a lot simpler (in size) than those of a
desktop environment.
</p>

<p>
fluxbox offers the user with a simple interface for window managing, yet
supports everything (and more) you require: we aren't talking about window
minimalization and maximalization here (of course fluxbox supports that) but
about tabbed windows, stickyness, virtual desktops, hotkeys, ...
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in using fluxbox, don't hesitate to read the <uri
link="/doc/en/fluxbox-config.xml">Fluxbox Configuration Guide</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>The right tool for the right job</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
After a exaggerating first experience with the graphical Linux environment, many
users ask "What's next?" They don't know what tools exist and just playing
around, clicking on icons, doesn't help you find out what's possible.
</p>

<p>
Working well with Linux means that you know what tools to use. In this section,
we'll give a head start on various tools and projects. These tools aren't
mandatory, but give a nice idea on Linux' possibilities.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Multimedia related</title>
<body>

<p>
When you ask on <c>#gentoo</c> what the best media player for Gentoo Linux is,
you'll get probably two answers: MPlayer and amaroK.
</p>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.mplayerhq.hu">MPlayer</uri> is a well-known movie player 
and includes many features such as DVD playing
(although <uri link="http://www.dtek.chalmers.se/groups/dvd/">Ogle</uri> has a
nicer, intuïtive interface), encoding/decoding of dozens of video formats,
lots of output formats (ever saw a movie using ASCII characters?) and more. Some
might argue that <uri link="http://xinehq.de/">Xine</uri> is an easier
multimedia player - at the end, it is up to you to decide.
</p>

<p>
<uri link="http://amarok.kde.org/">amaroK</uri> on the other hand is a music
player which integrates nicely in KDE and is very featureful: automated lyric
fetching, lots of eye-candy, support for lots of audio formats, ... Another
intuïtive media player is the GNOME-related <uri
link="http://www.gnome.org/projects/rhythmbox/">Rhythmbox</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Office Related</title>
<body>

<p>
With <uri link="http://www.openoffice.org">OpenOffice.org</uri> you have a
full-featured office suite which uses a standard office file format and supports
Microsoft Office documents to a great extend. There is also the <uri
link="http://www.gnome.org/gnome-office/">GNOME Office</uri>, a set of
separately developed applications for word processing, spreadsheet calculations
and database access.
</p>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.abisource.com">AbiWord</uri> is a good choice if you will
only be doing word processing. AbiWord is a full-featured word processor that is
much lighter and faster than OpenOffice, while still retaining complete
interoperability with industry-standard document types. Additionally, AbiWord
integrates particularly well with the GNOME desktop.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
