<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-intro-user_fhs.xml,v 1.1 2006/01/06 20:05:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>Why multi-user?</title>
<subsection>
<title>Separation of privileges</title>
<body>

<p>
One of the advantages of a multi-user operating system like Linux is that the
privileges are separated. Each process runs with specific privileges and can
only execute a limited number of tasks. As long as the process does not run
as the <c>root</c> user (the allmighty administrator privilege) it can only deal
with files and tasks that are assigned to that particular user.
</p>

<p>
This separation of privileges provides a small but working security wall: as
long as all your users use the system with their user account and not with the
<c>root</c> account, the worst that can happen is that the user removed his own
files - the system itself is left untouched.
</p>

<p>
For this reason, you will always hear not to use the <c>root</c> account. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>System accounts</title>
<body>

<p>
To enforce the separation of privileges, specific system accounts are created
for each task. If you run a mail server on your system, that mail server will
have a user account on your system. 
</p>

<p>
These accounts are not usable by regular users: you can not log in on your
system using those accounts. They exist only to allow the specific processes to
run with their own permissions and privileges.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Users and permissions</title>
<subsection>
<title>The user ID</title>
<body>

<p>
To identify a system account, a unique <e>user identification</e> is used: the
UID. This is a number used by the Linux kernel and other applications as 
numbers are easier to deal with than names (strings). However, Linux is 
intelligent enough to immediately translate the UID to a user name and vice 
versa, so in most cases you will only see or use the user name instead of the 
UID.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The process ID</title>
<body>

<p>
When your Linux system is up and running, it will have started various processes
already. Each process is an application (or part of an application) and receives
a unique <e>process identifier</e> (which is also a number): the PID. 
</p>

<p>
PIDs play an important role in the administration of a running Linux system:
you need the PID of a specific process to be able to terminate it (in case it
behaves badly), change priorities or receive specific system usage statistics
regarding a particular application.
</p>

<p>
For regular Linux usage however, the PID is less important: you still need to
understand what a PID is, but you will probably not encounter any use of it
until you administer your system.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Privileges</title>
<body>

<p>
Each process obtains privileges based on the user account it uses. By default, 
a process runs with the privileges of the user that started the
process. For instance, if you start <c>firefox</c> it will run with your
privileges.
</p>

<p>
However, some processes have a specific flag set that tells the Linux kernel not
to run the process as the user that executed it, but as a specific user
instead. This flag is called the <e>set user id</e> (SetUID or SUID) and tells 
the Linux kernel to run this application with the privileges of the 
<e>owner</e> of that application instead of the <e>executor</e>.
</p>

<p>
Most tools that have the SUID bit set are owned by the <c>root</c> user and
therefore start running with the privileges of the <c>root</c> user. Because
this is a security thread (remember, running things as <c>root</c> can be
dangerous) most tools have a feature called <e>privilege separation</e>: when
they are started, they first run the tasks they have to run as <c>root</c> after
which they automatically decrease their own privileges to a less powerful state.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Linux file system hierarchy</title>
<subsection>
<title>Structure of a file system</title>
<body>

<p>
The most pertinent change Linux users will have to be comfortable with is the
file system structure which is quite different from the file system structure
operating systems like Microsoft Windows use.
</p>

<p>
In Linux, the entire file system is structured as one huge tree. You start with
the root of the tree and traverse down until you reach your goal. The next Code
Listing shows you the first depth of a Linux file system:
</p>

<pre caption="Incomplete example of a Linux File System">
/        <comment>(The root)</comment>
+- bin/  <comment>(Executable programs needed to get the system up and running)</comment>
+- boot/ <comment>(Files related to the boot loader and Linux kernel)</comment>
+- dev/  <comment>(Device files)</comment>
+- etc/  <comment>(Configuration files)</comment>
+- home/ <comment>(User home directories)</comment>
+- lib/  <comment>(Libraries needed to get the system up and running)</comment>
+- mnt/  <comment>(Location for mount points)</comment>
+- opt/  <comment>(Contains large package installations not part of a regular install)</comment>
+- proc/ <comment>(Kernel-provided information)</comment>
+- root/ <comment>(Home directory for the root user)</comment>
+- sbin/ <comment>(System administration executables to get the system up and running)</comment>
+- sys/  <comment>(Kernel-provided information)</comment>
+- tmp/  <comment>(Temporary files)</comment>
+- usr/  <comment>(Applications for day-to-day system usage)</comment>
`- var/  <comment>(Variable information like log-files, caches, ...)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
Suppose you want to navigate to the CUPS error logs (CUPS is a printing service
frequently used on Linux systems) which are located inside
<path>/var/log/cups</path> you will find the following tree:
</p>

<pre caption="Expanded tree to /var/log/cups">
<i>/</i>
+- bin/
<comment>(...)</comment>
+- usr/
`- <i>var/</i>
   +- cache/
   +- db/
   +- lock/
   +- <i>log/</i>
   |  +- <i>cups/</i>
   |  |  +- access_log
   |  |  +- error_log
   |  |  `- page_log
   |  +- dmesg
   |  +- emerge.log
   |  +- lastlog
   |  `- messages
   +- run/
   +- spool/
   +- state/
   `- tmp/
</pre>

<p>
Each location has its purpose as defined in the <uri
link="http://www.pathname.com/fhs">Linux File System Hierarchy Standard</uri>.
As said before, Linux builds upon standards and the file system structure is no
exception. Each Linux distribution adheres to this standard (although a few
deviations are known). If you want to learn more about the file system
structure, please read this standard. A short summary can also be found on your
Linux system in the <c>hier</c> manual ("hier" is short for "hierarchy").
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Scattered files</title>
<body>

<p>
One often frowned upon result of this file system structure is that applications
scatter their files around on the system. Indeed, the locations for executable
files, data files, documentation files, configuration files, ... are defined in
the hierarchy standard but result in files being scattered throughout the file
system instead of at a single location.
</p>

<p>
For instance, for a regular application the executable files will be stored in
<path>/usr/bin</path>, data files in 
<path>/usr/share/&lt;application&nbsp;name&gt;/</path>, documentation files in 
<path>/usr/share/man</path> (for the manuals) or in the data file location, 
configuration files in <path>/etc</path>, libraries in <path>/usr/lib</path>, 
etc.
</p>

<p>
It is up to the distribution to keep track of the files that belong to a
particular package. The software management system of a distribution is
therefore a very important tool and is often the application that distinguishes
one distribution from the others. For Gentoo, the software management system is
called Portage.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>System administration versus system usage</title>
<body>

<p>
When you are using your Linux system for daily tasks you should be logged on as
a regular user. This user will only have write-access to his personal <e>home
directory</e>, located in <path>/home</path>, and have read access to most
other places on the system (except where sensitive information is stored). 
</p>

<p>
This user will be able to execute most applications that are stored in the
regular executable locations (<path>/bin</path>, <path>/usr/bin</path> and a few
other places). Whenever the user wants to run an application, the system will
search through those directories for a matching application: it will not 
search through the entire system.
</p>

<p>
The administrative user (<c>root</c>) however has access to every location on
the system. When he wants to execute an application, the system will search
through <e>system administration locations</e> such as <path>/sbin</path> and
<path>/usr/sbin</path> as well. Those locations contain tools that should only
be ran by the <c>root</c> user. The <c>root</c> user can also read and write to
every location on the system (although particular kernel projects exist that
allow for more access control, limiting even the <c>root</c> user's
capabilities).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The role of hardware</title>
<body>

<p>
Within the tree structure there does not seem to be any room for the hardware 
(like disks, CD-ROMs, USB sticks or network mounts). Of course, hardware is 
important - where else would you store your files on if you do not have a hard 
disk? The use of such hardware however happens transparent to the user.
</p>

<p>
Storing files in Linux happens in a layered structure. At the bottom of the
layer, you have the actual storage (most likely the partition or removable
media). On top of the actual storage you have the file system. A file system can
be spanned across several storage devices but most users will have one partition
per file system. The file system is <e>mounted</e> in the Linux file system
structure. Such mount always happens at a certain directory.
</p>

<p>
By default, you will have at least one file system for the root of your file
system. If you only want to use a single file system, you can have your entire
Linux system on a single partition. If you want to use several partitions, you
need to think about what directory (and its subdirectories) you want to store 
on a different file system. 
</p>

<p>
For instance, you might want to have <path>/home</path> stored on a separate
file system which allows you to have all the users their data on a single
partition (or drive). What happens is that you create a file system on that
partition (or drive) and then <e>mount</e> this at <path>/home</path>.
</p>

<p>
If you do not mount it at <path>/home</path>, the <path>/home</path> and all its
contents will be stored on the file system that contains the root of the file
system. If you do mount it at <path>/home</path>, <path>/home</path> and all its
contents will be stored on the other file system.
</p>

<p>
This mounting does have an important implication: if you forget to mount a file
system at a certain location, the Linux file system structure will look as if
that location contains no files. You will be able to add files to that location
of course, but they will then be stored on the root file system instead of on
the file system you forgot to mount.
</p>

<p>
In the next Code Listing we show you an example layered approach. The root file
system is stored on <path>/dev/hda1</path> which represents the first partition
on the first IDE disk in your system. The <path>/home</path> location is stored
on a separate file system (which happens to be the same <e>kind</e> of file
system: an ext3 one). This file system is stored on a <e>meta device</e> (a 
device that actually consists of multiple devices - in this case two 
partitions).
</p>

<pre caption="Example layered approach for the Linux file system">
+--------------------+----------------------------+
|   / (root)         |   /home (home directories) |  <comment>&lt;- location</comment>
+--------------------+----------------------------+
|   ext3 instance    |   ext3 instance            |  <comment>&lt;- file system</comment>
+--------------------+--------------+-------------+
|                    |        /dev/md/0           |
|   /dev/hda1        +--------------+-------------+  <comment>&lt;- devices</comment>
|                    |  /dev/hdb1   |  /dev/hdc1  | 
+--------------------+--------------+-------------+
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
