<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-install-minenv.xml,v 1.1 2006/01/06 20:05:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
The prompt you are now looking at is all-powerful, but a bit daunting at first.
If you know how the Linux command line works, this chapter will give you no
further surprises and you can easily jump to the next chapter, <e>Preparing 
the Network</e>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Basic navigation</title>
<subsection>
<title>Working command-line</title>
<body>

<p>
At the prompt you can enter <e>commands</e> to the Gentoo Linux environment.
Basic commands are just single words, like <c>ls</c> or <c>ps</c>. Most commands
however often require additional words to be added, like <c>cd&nbsp;/var</c> or
<c>man&nbsp;ls</c>. These added characters are called <e>arguments</e>.
</p>

<p>
More often, these arguments represent certain <e>options</e> to the command. For
instance, the <c>ls</c> command (used to list the content of a directory) can
take several options, like <c>-l</c> (for a lengthy description of each found
file), <c>-a</c> (to include hidden files), etc.
</p>

<p>
In the next Code Listing you'll see this terminology explained. The command
shown will list the content of the <path>/var/tmp</path> directory (a temporary
location) showing additional information about each file found, including hidden
files.
</p>

<pre caption="Command, arguments and options">
root ~# <i>ls -la /var/tmp</i>
&lt;--+--&gt;&lt;+&gt; &lt;+&gt; &lt;---+--&gt;
   |    |   |      `- Argument, in this case the target directory to list
   |    |   `- Argument, also two options: lengthy description + hidden files
   |    `- Command (list in this case)
   `- Prompt
</pre>

<p>
After having constructed a command, you can execute it by pressing the return
key. Your shell (the command-line environment you are currently "in" which
interprets commands and helps you navigate through the Linux environment) will
then execute the command and show you the results.
</p>

<p>
The next section will give you a crash course in certain Linux commands that
will help you explore your current minimal Gentoo environment. We won't go in
much detail - there are plenty guides and books available online that will
inform you about the basic Linux tools (<uri
link="http://http://www.chongluo.com/books/rute/">Rute's
Unix Tutorial Exposed</uri> is one of the more famous, freely available books).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Navigating up and down</title>
<body>

<p>
We have already covered how a Linux file system looks like (the hierarchical
structure, remember?). To help you out we'll give you a quick overview on the
most common tools you might need to navigate on your Gentoo Linux system:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Command</th>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>Example</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>ls</c></ti>
  <ti>
    List the content of a given directory, or the current directory if no
    directory is given.
  </ti>
  <ti><c>ls&nbsp;/mnt/cdrom</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>pwd</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Show the current working directory; this is the full pathname of the
    directory you are currently in.
  </ti>
  <ti><c>pwd</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>cd</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Change the current working directory to a different location. If no
    directory is given, go to the user's home directory.
  </ti>
  <ti><c>cd&nbsp;/mnt/gentoo</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>less</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Show the content of a given file on the screen. You can navigate with the
    up and down arrows through the file and quit the application by pressing
    'q'.
  </ti>
  <ti><c>less&nbsp;install.txt</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>rm</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Remove a file from the system (if you have the required privileges). To
    remove a directory with all files in it, use the <c>-r</c> option. Be 
    careful with this command though, it won't warn you when you are about 
    to destroy all your data.
  </ti>
  <ti><c>rm&nbsp;portage.tar</c></ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Concurrent terminals</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo's installation CDs allow you to use a couple of terminals simultaneously.
That means you can work in one, browse the internet in another and chat on a
third. To switch between terminals, type <c>Alt+F#</c> (with <c>F#</c> one of
the function keys). You will notice that your current session is at <c>F1</c>.
</p>

<p>
You can also work in a terminal and then put your working session in the
background using a powerful tool called <c>screen</c>. With <c>screen</c> you
can even let other people work on your terminal while you are watching every
step they perform.
</p>

<pre caption="Working with screen">
<comment>(Starting a screen session:)</comment>
$ <i>screen -S mySession</i>
<comment>(To detach a screen session, type 'Ctrl-A' followed by a 'd')</comment>

<comment>(Reattach to a screen session:)</comment>
$ <i>screen -x mySession</i>

<comment>(To quit a screen session, just type 'exit':)</comment>
$ <i>exit</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Networking utilities</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo offers a few utilities on the installation CDs which you can use to 
surf on the Internet, download files, chat on the IRC network, etc. We will
cover a few of them in this section, but you can't use them until you have
configured your network (and Internet connection) which is described in the next
chapter.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Surfing on the Internet</title>
<body>

<p>
Because no documentation can be perfect and no two environments are alike, you
will often search for additional information and help on the Internet. Websites
such as the main <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/index.xml">Gentoo
documentation repository</uri> or powerful search engines like <uri
link="http://www.google.com">Google</uri> are a welcome resource during your
installation quest.
</p>

<p>
To browse through these sites you need a browser. Because the Gentoo
installation CDs don't contain a graphical environment you need to use either a
different system, a different installation medium or ... a non-graphical
browser. The Gentoo installation CDs offer at least one of the following console
browsers:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>lynx</c>, a general purpose web site browser which operates key-driven
    (for instance 'D' for downloading, 'G' to go to a different site, ...).
  </li>
  <li>
    <c>links2</c>, a featureful browser with support for frames, limited
    JavaScript, svgalib/framebuffer, background downloading, ... which operates
    both menu-driven (press 'Escape' to open the menu) as key-driven.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Both browsers support proxy servers, although the first one uses the standard
way (setting an <c>HTTP_PROXY</c> environment variable) while the second one
requires you to enter the proxy server in the browser.
</p>

<pre caption="Example surfing information with proxy support">
<comment>(For lynx - ignore the export command if no proxy is needed:)</comment>
$ <i>export HTTP_PROXY="http://myproxy.server.tld:8080"</i>
$ <i>lynx http://www.gentoo.org</i>

<comment>(For links2 - ignore the -http-proxy option if no proxy is needed:)</comment>
$ <i>links2 -http-proxy http://myproxy.server.tld:8080 http://www.gentoo.org</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Chatting on an IRC network</title>
<body>

<p>
When you can't find useful information on the Internet, you can always ask your
question on the <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-install">#gentoo-install</uri> or <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo">#gentoo</uri> IRC channels on FreeNode.
Gentoo delivers a terminal-based, yet extremely powerful chat client called
<c>irssi</c>.
</p>

<p>
Its use is quite simple. First, connect to the IRC network. Then, join the
channel(s) you want to participate in. You can use Alt+F# to switch between
channels (or type in <c>/window&nbsp;#</c> if the key combination fails). To
exit the application, type <c>/quit</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Getting online with irssi">
$ <i>irssi -c irc.freenode.net YourNickName</i>
<comment>(Wait until the connection is made)</comment>
[irssi #] <i>/join #gentoo</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Remote shell access</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo installation CD contains an <e>SSH daemon</e>, which is a tool to
allow others to securely connect to your system so they can help you install
Gentoo. This service isn't started by default, but if you want to use it you
should:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>get the Internet connection up and running</li>
  <li>create a user account</li>
  <li>give the root account a password</li>
  <li>start the SSH daemon</li>
</ol>

<p>
If you trust the other person, you can give him your root password, but we
advise you to only give limited access to the other person - they should help
you identify errors and tell you how to resolve them, not fix the errors
themselves. Otherwise you won't learn :)
</p>

<pre caption="Steps to get the SSH service running">
<comment>(First get the Internet connection up and running, then...)</comment>
# <i>useradd -m -G users myuser</i>
# <i>passwd myuser</i>
<comment>(Give the 'myuser' user a password)</comment>
# <i>passwd</i>
<comment>(Give the 'root' user a (different) password)</comment>
# <i>/etc/init.d/sshd start</i>
</pre>

<p>
The passwords you set here are limited to the Gentoo installation CD environment
and only until you reboot. They are not used for your final Gentoo installation!
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
