<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-install-media.xml,v 1.1 2006/01/06 20:05:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>About the Gentoo releases</title>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo versions</title>
<body>

<p>
One of Gentoo's major advantages is that it does not really know
<e>versions</e>. Once installed, you have a Gentoo installation, not a Gentoo
2005.1 or 2004.3 installation. Therefore you will continue to benefit from the
Gentoo development with every system update you perform - there is no need to
run through a specific upgrade procedure every time Gentoo makes a new release.
</p>

<p>
Yes, Gentoo does <e>release</e> often - twice a year to be exact. Such a release
brings you an up to date installation CD with the latest hardware drivers and
features that might improve your installation experience. It can also contain a
set of prebuilt packages, helping you to install Gentoo quickly and efficiently.
</p>

<p>
When you hear someone talk about a specific Gentoo release (<e>Gentoo 2005.1</e>
for instance) they are talking about the installation CDs and set of prebuilt
packages, not about the state Gentoo is at at a certain point in time. Gentoo
evolves on a daily basis, but can't develop, package, test and release new
installation CDs and prebuilt packages every time Gentoo changes...
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo release media</title>
<body>

<p>
By default, Gentoo releases installation CDs: bootable CDs allowing you to
immediately boot in a Gentoo Linux environment containing the necessary tools to
help you install Gentoo on your system. Such CDs shouldn't be read from any
other operating system but immediately booted from.
</p>

<p>
For each architecture (see the note below) you will find two installation CDs: 
a <e>minimal</e> installation CD and a <e>universal</e> one. They both contain
the same hardware support drivers (Linux kernel and additional kernel modules)
and tools; the universal installation CD however also contains the necessary 
files to allow any user to install Gentoo without requiring a working Internet
connection.
</p>

<p>
It is important to understand that:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    the Gentoo installation procedure is a <e>manual</e> procedure, requiring
    lots of input from the administrator
  </li>
  <li>
    there is support for a networkless installation <e>if</e> you use the
    universal installation CD and the stage-3 installation approach (which will
    be discussed later), but that Gentoo should not be considered if you don't
    have a working Internet connection
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
You will also find a <e>packages</e> CD. As the name implies, this CD contains
prebuilt packages you can quickly install to get a working Gentoo installation
without going through much software building. 
</p>

<p>
<e>However</e>, these software packages are only available for those who perform
a networkless installation and are not maintained by the Gentoo project at all:
they are only meant for use during the initial installation of Gentoo. Once
installed, your system is not different from any other Gentoo installation.
</p>

<p>
This part will not talk about the networkless installation. We have decided to
postpone any information regarding prebuilt packages to a later stage because of
the following reasons:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The networkless installation instructions are limiting the user's choices.
    Only a fraction of the software which a user can (and should) install during
    installation is available and the user might not be able to deviate from the
    standard installation routine.
  </li>
  <li>
    The set of prebuilt software is quickly outdated. As Gentoo does not offer a
    continuously maintained repository of prebuilt packages, any user who does a
    networkless installation might be facing an installation with insecure
    software for the time between the (quick) installation and (slower)
    upgrading.
  </li>
  <li>
    The available prebuilt software differs from architecture to architecture,
    from release to release. If one wants to have pseudo-static documentation on
    the Gentoo installation procedure, such variable information should be 
    eliminated.
  </li>
</ul>    

<note>
An architecture is a family of CPUs who support the same instructions. The most
known architecture in the desktop world is <e>x86</e>, referring to the
Intel-compatible systems. Others are <e>sparc</e>, <e>ppc</e>, <e>mips</e>, ...
<e>amd64</e> is also an architecture although it has additional Intel
compatibility. If you are not sure what architecture to pick, don't hesitate to
ask. <br/>
Incidentally, <e>amd64</e> is the most common answer to that question,
followed by <e>x86</e> :)
</note>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo installation approaches</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
You should understand that the Gentoo installation procedure - at least the
officially publicised one - is quite different from most other Linux
distributions: where other distributions try to perform most steps for you,
Gentoo Linux asks you politely (but firmly) to do things yourself.
</p>

<p>
Getting the hardware up and running, configuring the network, partitioning your
disk(s), copying over the initial files, building additional software (including
the kernel), ... all these steps should be performed before you can finally boot
in a minimal Gentoo environment. Not that all these steps can't be automated
(Gentoo even offers tools to automate a few of those steps and you'll find a lot
of unofficial installers that automate most - if not all - steps) but by
documenting these steps in great detail Gentoo almost forces you to learn
various Linux-related procedures.
</p>

<p>
Another advantage of letting the user perform all steps himself is that the user
can now decide himself how he wants to install Gentoo - the options are there,
the user needs to make a choice, over and over again. By clearly identifying the
options and documenting the possible roads Gentoo hopes that the user is not
scared but rather impressed.
</p>

<p>
For instance, Gentoo offers the user with three initial system states where the
user can start from to install Gentoo. These states are called <e>stages</e>:
stage-1, stage-2 and stage-3.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Easy and fast: stage-3</title>
<body>

<p>
The stage-3 system state starts from a minimal Gentoo environment, containing
the core system utils that anyone would need to get Gentoo up and running. This
is the preferred initial state for most users and also the quickest way to
install Gentoo. From this stage onward, the user installs the additional tools
he requires (such as certain networking tools for automated IP information
retrieval, cron jobs for scheduled process execution, system logger for keeping
track of all log events, ...) and builds a Linux kernel to boot from.
</p>

<p>
When you want to install Gentoo without a working Internet connection (the
networkless installation approach) you must use the stage-3 approach since the
universal installation CD only contains source code for the additional tools you
should install - not for the tools already available in the stage file.
</p>

<p>
Although the stage-3 system state is the most full-featured one, many users
often take this as a bloated stage thinking they can't tweak as much as they can
with the other stages. This is wrong, as you can easily rebuild the entire
system with new (compiler and <c>USE</c>) settings - and in many occasions 
faster too!
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Tweaking the system: stage-2</title>
<body>

<p>
The stage-2 system state contains a built and functional toolchain but no system
utilities. This is an intermediate state between a stage-1 and stage-3 and also
the least often used approach to install Gentoo with. Those who do consider
using this stage often alter their profile with respect to base system 
packages and perform major tweaks with the <c>CFLAGS</c>, <c>CXXFLAGS</c>
and <c>USE</c> variables.
</p>

<p>
Although Gentoo offers a stage-2 initial system state, you should consider
performing a stage-2 installation with a stage-3 initial system state. This will
preserve you from possible circular dependency issues that are inherent with the
stage-2 build.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Tweaking the bootstrapping procedure: stage-1</title>
<body>

<p>
The stage-1 system state contains a non-optimized toolchain with no system
utilities. This is the state where Gentoo Release Engineering developers start
from to move to a stage-3 state by rebuilding the toolchain for the specific
architecture (migrating to a stage-2) and using this newly rebuilt toolchain to
install the system core utilities (migrating to a stage-3).
</p>

<p>
This state is only interesting for those attempting to change the bootstrapping
procedure (by changing the <path>bootstrap.sh</path> script) or want to build a
non-default Gentoo environment (for instance using a completely different
toolchain). 
</p>

<p>
Although Gentoo offers a stage-1 initial system state, you should consider
performing a stage-1 installation with a stage-3 initial system state. This will
preserve you from possible circular dependency issues and bootstrapping failures
inherent with the stage-1 procedure (which is quite complex).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Download, burn and boot</title>
<subsection>
<title>Download the media</title>
<body>

<p>
With the information handed to you in the previous sections you should have an
idea what CD(s) you need to download. Gentoo provides the CDs both as an
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/mirrors.xml">FTP/HTTP download</uri> 
or through the <uri link="http://torrents.gentoo.org">BitTorrent</uri>
peer-to-peer network. Pick the latest version available (as that one contains
the most up-to-date hardware support and additional features) although this is
not mandatory: you can easily install a (current) Gentoo from an older
installation CD. 
</p>

<p>
As the directory structure on the FTP/HTTP mirrors suggests, you'll find the 
CDs in the <path>releases/</path> directory.
</p>

<p>
Each CD is fully contained within an ISO file. Such a file contains all the
content of a CD and should be burned on the CD using a specific (but well
supported) procedure. Most CD/DVD burning tools call it <e>Burn ISO</e> or
<e>Raw burning</e>; it differs from the regular burning methods used that it
burns the content of the file on the CD, not the file as-is (i.e. the end result
is not that you just see the single file on the burnt CD).
</p>

<p>
If you want, you can verify the downloaded ISO file using the <path>.md5</path>
file we provide. This file contains an Message Digest 5 checksum of the file, a
known mathematical result of the entire CD that is practically unique to every
file. In other words, you won't find a file anywhere with the same checksum
unless that file is identical. Under Linux, you can use the <c>md5sum</c> tool
to verify the checksum.
</p>

<p>
We also provide a digital signature of the file made with our private Release
Engineering key. This digital signature can be used to validate the origin of
the ISO file: if the digital signature matches the public key of the Release
Engineering team, then the file is authentic. Under Linux, you can use the
<c>gpg</c> tool to verify the checksum.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Booting the CD</title>
<body>

<p>
To get in the initial Gentoo environment, you need to boot from the installation
CD. How to achieve this depends on the architecture you are using. The first
appendix in this book covers the various architecture-specific aspects of a
Linux system, including booting CDs.
</p>

<p>
Once booted, you will see that the installation CD already tried to load the
necessary drivers and hands you over to a <e>root prompt</e>, indicating that
the system is waiting for further input:
</p>

<pre caption="Resulting prompt after a succesful boot">
root ~#
</pre>

<p>
This is the command-line prompt. You are now booted in the initial Gentoo
environment, ready to continue. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
