<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-intro-linux.xml,v 1.1 2006/01/06 20:05:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>Linux: concept and history</title>
<subsection>
<title>What is Linux?</title>
<body>

<p>
Linux is a free operating system, consisting of the Linux kernel, libraries 
and utilities which allow the user to interact with his system.
</p>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.kernel.org/">Linux kernel</uri> is the core of the 
Linux Operating System. It is responsible for all hardware interaction, 
process management, memory management, network protocol support and file 
system support. We probably forgot a few other responsibilities as well, 
but it is obvious that the kernel has many important responsibilities. All these
tasks are handled in the background: as the core of the system, the user has no
direct interaction with the kernel.
</p>

<p>
The core library on a Linux system is the <uri
link="http://www.gnu.org/software/libc/libc.html">GNU C library</uri>, called 
<c>glibc</c>. This library provides an interface between the Linux kernel, 
which operates almost independently, and the user applications. The library 
contains <e>system call</e> definitions and basic features to facilitate
the application development for the Linux Operating System.
</p>

<p>
The core utilities on a Linux Operating System provide you, the user, with a way
to interact with the system. These utilities allow you to create and manipulate
files, navigate around on your system, start and stop processes, etc. There is
no "single" core utility package: the Linux Operating System contains a dozen
different packages and two Linux systems can have different utilities.
</p>

<p>
The most well-known and used utilities however (such as those for navigating on
the system) are generally called the <uri 
link="http://www.gnu.org/software/coreutils/">GNU Core Utilities</uri>. GNU is a
project devoted to the development of a completely free (as in 'free speech')
Unix-like environment. Because GNU plays an important role on most Linux 
systems, many people talk about GNU/Linux. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>So... what is Linux?</title>
<body>

<p>
While the above explanation is quite technical, the Linux Operating System is 
built upon the <uri link="http://www.unix.org/">UNIX</uri> idea, delivering
UNIX-like features and stability. But it is more than just a UNIX clone. It is 
developed by several thousand developers who work on the operating system in 
their free time (although many of them also work on Linux on a paid-for basis).
</p>

<p>
The development of Linux is decentralised: each part of the Linux Operating
System (kernel, libraries, tools, graphical environments, office suites, server
software, ...) is developed by its own project which works independently of 
the other projects. Unlike what many people think, this does <e>not</e> mean 
that the projects do not work well with each other. Each software title that 
interacts with another uses <e>standards</e>. A standard is an established or 
widely recognized technical explanation to accomplish something. The best 
standards are open standards.
</p>

<p>
An <e>open standard</e> is a freely available and sufficiently documented 
technical explanation that allows any developer to write software that operates
as the document dictates or supports the communication described by the
standard. Therefore it can flawlessly interact with other software titles that 
adhere to the document as well. The document and its technical implications 
are free of any juridical limits (like patents, licenses, ...) and the 
document is accepted by a standards organisation (like ISO, ANSI, ...).
</p>

<p>
Examples of such open standards are the various network protocols (like TCP/IP,
HTTP, ...), character encodings (ASCII, UTF-8, ...), etc.
Because the applications use standards, interoperability amongst the various
applications is guaranteed.
</p>

<p>
The Linux Operating System is characterised by freedom and choice. Freedom,
because the software is free (although non-free software exists for Linux as
well). Choice, because you will have the choice between several applications 
for each action you want to perform.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Where can I find Linux?</title>
<body>

<p>
You should not be searching for Linux sensu stricto as you'll only find the 
Linux kernel which you can't use without additional libraries and tools. What 
you need to look for is a distribution. A distribution is a project
that combines the Linux kernel, libraries and tools in a coherent software
package. With a distribution you can install, configure and use a Linux 
system easily.
</p>

<p>
Next to the distribution, you might need to install additional software. If you
can not install it through your distribution (most distributions offer thousands
of software titles out of the box) or you do not know any software title by
name, then you can visit one of the many free software repositories
around. Known repositories are <uri
link="http://www.freshmeat.net">Freshmeat</uri>, <uri
link="http://www.icewalkers.com">Icewalkers</uri>, <uri
link="http://www.sourceforge.net">SourceForge</uri>, etc.
</p>

<p>
Known distributions are <uri link="http://fedora.redhat.com">Fedora</uri>, <uri
link="http://www.mandriva.com">Mandriva</uri>, <uri
link="http://www.novell.com/linux/suse/">SuSE</uri>, <uri
link="http://www.debian.org">Debian</uri>, <uri
link="http://www.ubuntu.org">Ubuntu</uri> and of course <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org">Gentoo</uri>, but many others exist as well.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Linux' history</title>
<body>

<p>
Linus Thorvalds, the creator of the Linux kernel, made a first posting about his
hobby project on August 25th, 1991. People could download his code and use it,
modify it and redistribute it. Linus also made a few ports available to make it
possible for others to run a Linux operating system. Of course, in those days,
the operating system contained only a few applications and hardware support was
very limited.
</p>

<p>
In the next few years, the Linux kernel grew and expanded: support for
networking, SCSI disks, specific file systems, ... was added and bugs were
quickly fixed. Yet installing a Linux Operating System still was difficult as
there were no easy installation methods yet. That changed when the first
distribution got out.
</p>

<p>
Early distributions were hardly maintained so no real good candidate for
continuous usage. In 1993 Slackware was created, and others followed suit
shortly after. Nowadays, several hundred distributions exist. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Free software model</title>
<subsection>
<title>Freedom of speech</title>
<body>

<p>
As mentioned previously, Linux is Free Software. The "Free" here should be read
as "Freedom of Speech", not "Free beer". The <uri link="http://www.fsf.org">Free
Software Foundation</uri> defines the freedom as:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    freedom to run the program for any purpose,
  </li>
  <li>
    freedom to study how the program works, and to adapt it to your needs, 
  </li>
  <li>
    freedom to redistribute copies of the program, and
  </li>
  <li>
    freedom to improve the program, and release your improvements to the public
    so that the entire community benefits
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
The Free Software Foundation has prepared and released a specific license that 
embraces the abovementioned freedom. Their license is called the <uri
link="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/gpl.html">GPL</uri> and is used by
the Linux kernel and various other applications. The Free Software Model builds
upon this freedom. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The role of distributions</title>
<body>

<p>
Distributions play an important role: they bundle the free software in a 
coherent package. A distribution allows you to install a Linux Operating
System easily and maintain the software installed on your system. Thanks to
distributions, you don't need to know how to build packages, what toolchains
are and other packaging-related tasks.
</p>

<p>
One role of a distribution in the free software model is that of the quality
analysis and marketing. Distributions take the source code of many projects and
bundle it together. They test the software and provide feedback to the
developers of the individual projects. When they are happy with the end result,
they present their distribution to the world: it is this end result that the
users will install on their system.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Development model</title>
<body>

<p>
Most free software is developed on a volunteer basis. A free software project
generally has some infrastructure at its disposal:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    a <e>code repository</e>: a location where several people can work on the
    source code simultaneously. When you hear about CVS or SVN then the topic of
    the discussion is most likely code repositories or the tools to manage them.
    A versioning tool allows developers to deal with collaborative source code 
    development. Such tools keep track of all changes made to the project.
  </li>
  <li>
    a web site, displaying news and information about the project. The web site
    will probably include download and installation instructions, documentation,
    etc.
  </li>
  <li>
    a mailinglist where developers and users discuss the future of the project,
    changes and change requests, bugs, etc.
  </li>
  <li>
    a <e>bug tracking system</e> where users can submit bug reports and
    enhancement requests. Such bug tracking systems allow the developers to
    keep track of bugs easily. 
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Most free software projects are ran by volunteers. These people put their
knowledge of programming, documentation writing, infrastructure, ... in the
project. The motivation that drives these developers makes free software
evolve quite fast: why else would someone work on a project in his free time if
he wasn't motivated?
</p>

<p>
Because a project is mostly ran by volunteers, there is no limit to the amount
of developers that can work on the project. The Gentoo distribution has more
than 350 developers, the Linux kernel has several hundred developers. Many
updates to a project are made by contributors as well: people who have found and
fixed an issue but are not part of the development base of the project.
</p>

<p>
The entire development process is open to the public (everyone can see
how the project evolves), so there is a lot of feedback from the users. Users
participate in discussions on the mailinglists or through IRC (lots of projects 
have a chat channel). In many cases, active users are asked to join the
development team because they provide valuable feedback.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Is Linux your thing?</title>
<subsection>
<title>Expectations</title>
<body>

<p>
So what can you expect from Linux? 
</p>

<p>
Linux is a very stable platform that can be used in every area you can be
interested in: desktop, workstation, server, programming, embedded, ...
Stability is a core concern with Linux. The Linux kernel for instance is a 
separate entity in the Operating System and not integrated in the shell or
hidden from the user. Any instability of an application will cause the
application to fail but not the kernel, so the system remains functional.
</p>

<p>
Because of the development model used, Linux is a fast moving operating system.
With Linux you can expect frequent updates with lots of new features. You will
notice that as you update your system, the system will remain recent and
completely up-to-date with the latest developments. Some distributions 
(Gentoo included) don't even require you to upgrade your system: once 
installed, you will always have the latest release. Such an approach is quite
unique and you can't find this in operating systems like Microsoft Windows.
</p>

<p>
Programmers will find that Linux offers them the best development platform they
can imagine. An Operating System where you can learn a lot from the inner
workings of the system, where you can find a plethora of (free) development
tools for languages such as C#, C++, Java, C, PHP, ... where communities help
each other in the development of peer projects. 
</p>

<p>
Home users will find Linux to be extremely interesting, with lots of documents
available to help you find your way through this new and exciting system. Yes,
documentation is a powerful asset: you have sites devoted to the ongoing 
development of good, professional and clear documents about various 
Linux-related subjects. Documents are not only available in English but
in various languages and this international approach is also taken within the 
Linux software products themselves: most applications are available in several 
languages. You can have your entire system available in your native language!
</p>

<p>
Lots of developers are security-aware. Therefore you will find that most
applications are written with a high sense of secure defaults. E-mail clients 
are not that likely to be easily trapped by viruses; the system only allows you
to alter files you have created, leaving system-wide files intact; free updates
lessen the chance that an exploitable bug remains on your system; firewalls and
other security-related software is freely available and easy to install. Do not
read this as if Linux is secure by default, but it does stress security more
than some other operating systems.
</p>

<p>
A Linux Operating System is quite cheap. Many distributions are freely available
(free as in free beer), others are available for a small price compared to what
they have to offer. To understand how the Free Software Model is sustainable we
will discuss this in <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">Freedom, Support and
Finances</uri>. You are also not forced to stay with a single vendor since most
applications use standards which improve interoperability.
</p>

<p>
You will find that Linux is extremely flexibel. You can use Linux as a desktop,
as a workstation, as a TV receiver/recorder, ... You can save disk space by
installing just the applications you need without any additional stuff, you can
install an entire desktop suite or just the tools you need. You can optimize
your installation for your system, or use a generic installation to speed up the
installation of hundreds of desktops you administer. You can choose amongst
various applications that offer the same functionality but use different ways 
to achieve their goals. You can do whatever you want, the way you want.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Linux is not...</title>
<subsection>
<title>... a Microsoft Windows look-a-like</title>
<body>

<p>
Do not expect Linux to behave like Windows, to run Windows programs, to be
compatible with everything Windows offers. Linux is a completely different
Operating System with its own way of dealing with things. It is completely
different by design, by development model, by community, ... and will most
likely stay different.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>... secure by default</title>
<body>

<p>
Security is a major concern with Linux, but "Secure by Default" is something
completely different. You should not expect that your Linux environment will
always be untouchable; security lays in the hands of whoever controls the
system.
</p>

<p>
Keeping your system up to date is a prerequisite: if you do not update your
system regularly, you will eventually have applications on your system that have
known exploitable bugs in them. Having a clear policy is important as well: do
not trust everyone on the Internet, do not use empty or easy-to-guess passwords,
do not use applications from untrusted sources, etc. Know what you do on your
system: badly configured services can be the weakest link in someone's security.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>... an alternative</title>
<body>

<p>
The word "alternative" is often used for a less powerful but "sufficient"
solution. Linux is <e>more</e> powerful and different. It is not an alternative
for any other operating system, but a different operating system.
</p>

<p>
Forget what you know about the operating system you currently use. Linux is
different and you <e>will</e> need to learn it. It will take a while but it is
definitely worth it.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
