<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-intro-choice.xml,v 1.1 2006/01/06 20:05:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>Distributions</title>
<subsection>
<title>Differences</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that you know a bit about Linux and Free Software, you need to make a choice
about the distribution you want to use. As you already know, a distribution
makes it easy for a user to install and maintain software. But a distribution
does a lot more than this. In the next few sections we describe various topics
which are filled in differently by distributions.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Architectures</title>
<body>

<p>
For a system to become functional, the source code of an application must be
translated to machine instructions. These instructions differ from CPU to CPU. A
set of machine instructions for a certain brand of CPUs (and its clones) is
called the <e>architecture</e>. The best known architecture is the <c>x86</c>
architecture, but several others exist, such as alpha, sparc, ppc, ...
</p>

<p>
Not all distributions support all possible architectures. Some distributions
even limit their support to a single architecture, others take pride in the fact
that they support quite a lot architectures.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo supports quite a few architectures: alpha, amd64, hppa, ia64, mips, ppc,
ppc64, sparc, x86 and even has unofficial support for arm, m68k, s390, sh, ...
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Package building</title>
<body>

<p>
There are many ways a software title can be packaged. Some distributions do not
prebuilt the software (so that the system still needs to compile the source code
prior to installing it to the system), but most do. Prebuilt software can be
packaged in an RPM file (RedHat Package Manager), a DEB file (Debian Package),
... Each of those package formats has its advantages and disadvantages.
</p>

<p>
By default Gentoo lets the system built the software. The format Gentoo uses is
called an <e>ebuild</e> which contains instructions for Portage, the Gentoo
software manager, to built the software for the user.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Provided software</title>
<body>

<p>
Some distributions only provide a few software titles because they aim on a very
particular niche (like embedded Linux, a Linux terminal server, ...) while
others provide a plethora on software titles. This is quite different from other
Operating Systems where you need to acquire additional software, or at least
have to locate, download and install it separately. With Linux, this process is
often embedded in the distribution which makes it a lot easier for the user.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo provides more than 9500 packages.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Preconfiguration</title>
<body>

<p>
When you install software, the distribution can try to preconfigure the
software for you. Some distributions go quite far so that the user hardly needs
to know how to configure anything - for the common user, everything works out of
the box. Other distributions do not try to configure most packages and leave it
to the user. After all, the user knows best what he needs and what not.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo mainly stays with the configuration as provided by the software project
and informs its users how to configure the software through excellent
step-by-step documentation.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>System maintenance</title>
<body>

<p>
A Linux system is not only a collection of installed software, the software
needs to work well (configuration) and should be manageable. System maintenance
is a job where you make sure that the system works as it should. You can
maintain your entire system through a single software package (like
<c>webmin</c>) or through a collection of software titles.
</p>

<p>
While some distributions try to provide an all-in-one maintenance solution, most
distributions opt for a decentralised maintenance with specific tools for
specific jobs. 
</p>

<p>
Gentoo does not offer any configuration tools - the user should configure his
system through the standard Linux tools.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Branding</title>
<body>

<p>
When a system is <e>branded</e> it is beautified: logo's are added, backgrounds
changed, behaviour altered, ... so that the system feels as if it was developed
and released by a single entity instead of several ones. Not all distributions
like branding because it removes the default look and feel that the individual
software projects have given to their software. They leave it as-is out of
respect for the software projects.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo does not brand applications by default.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Installation</title>
<body>

<p>
Whereas several distributions have a similar or even identical way of installing
software, almost no distribution has the same installation method. Some
distributions provide an installation where you hardly need to provide any
information, others require you to perform every single step yourself. And all
the other distributions are situated somewhere between those extremes.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo lets you perform every single installation step yourself, making a great
learning school for Linux internals. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Policies</title>
<body>

<p>
Albeit this is less visible in most distributions, some have a policy they
adhere to. For instance, some distributions might have a policy that they don't
allow non-free software in their distribution. Therefore such distributions will
always be free to use with no restrictions whatsoever (apart from those governed
by the free software license(s) they use).
</p>

<p>
Gentoo has a policy, written down in their <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/contract.xml">Social Contract</uri>. It is
less strict than the one mentioned in the previous paragraph, informing the user
that Gentoo will never depend on non-free software. In other words, you will
always have the ability to use a completely free Operating System with no
crippled features whatsoever. Gentoo <e>does</e> offer non-free software through
Portage - at least, it offers the instructions on how to integrate it
succesfully on your system. It will never allow you to install software against
the spirit of the license which it is released under.
</p>


</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Software choices</title>
<subsection>
<title>Why it doesn't matter</title>
<body>

<p>
When you are starting with Linux (and Gentoo Linux) you will undoubtedly find it
difficult to know what software to install. How is the best e-mail client
called? Can you run Windows applications on Linux? How is the support for the
many Word documents you might have? How can you edit pictures?
</p>

<p>
There are many, many tools available for Gentoo Linux. They offer a plethora of
possibilities and functions. It is not mandatory for you to know what software
you will use now: when you install Gentoo Linux, you first install a minimal,
bare-boned system. When you have this, you can start finding out what software
you would like to use.
</p>

<p>
Since all software is freely available, the best way to know what software to
use is to try and test them out until you find one that suits you the best. Of
course, it is often wise to build upon the knowledge of others: ask around what
the best software would be for your needs. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
