<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-install-configure.xml,v 1.2 2007/06/10 23:23:10 jkt Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2007-06-11</date>

<section>
<title>File system information</title>
<subsection>
<title>The fstab file</title>
<body>

<p>
<path>fstab</path> stands for <e>file system table</e>; when you would take a
look at a fully configured <path>/etc/fstab</path> file you can easily see why:
</p>

<pre caption="Example fstab file">
/dev/sda8               /             ext3    defaults,noatime          0 0
/dev/sda5               none          swap    sw                        0 0
/dev/sda6               /boot         ext2    noauto,noatime            0 0
/dev/sda7               /home         ext3    defaults,noatime,noexec   0 0
/dev/cdroms/cdrom0      /media/cdrom  auto    defaults,user,noauto      0 0

none                    /proc         proc    defaults                  0 0
none                    /dev/shm      tmpfs   defaults                  0 0
</pre>

<p>
Each line declares what storage location (first field) is mounted at a certain
location (second field) using a file system (third field) and mounted with
one or more options (fourth field). The last two numbers are not that actively
used anymore so you can safely set them to <path>0 0</path>.
</p>

<p>
It is vital that your <path>/etc/fstab</path> file is a reflection of your
environment. By default, Gentoo offers an almost empty <path>/etc/fstab</path>
file with illegal storage locations (such as <path>/dev/BOOT</path> and
<path>/dev/ROOT</path>). Any user should change the file, otherwise the system
might not boot.
</p>

<p>
The <path>fstab</path> file is used during the system boot procedure to find out
what file systems should be mounted, but also during regular system operation.
For instance, when you insert a CD in your CD-ROM player, Linux ought to know
where it should mount the CD so that you (and perhaps other users) can reach it.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Mount options</title>
<body>

<p>
The mount options which you can place in the fourth field in
<path>/etc/fstab</path> are well documented in the <c>mount</c> manual page:
</p>

<pre caption="Reading the mount manual page">
# <i>man mount</i>
</pre>

<p>
Each set of mount options is documented in a section pertaining to the file
system used (for instance, ext2, reiserfs, ...). Some of them are available to
all file systems, such as <c>defaults</c>, <c>auto</c> or <c>noauto</c>
(automatically mount file system or not).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Special file systems</title>
<body>

<p>
Some lines in the <path>/etc/fstab</path> file have a <e>none</e> as the storage
location. Such file systems are <e>pseudo file systems</e> and do not require
any storage on the disk.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The <e>proc</e> file system represents kernel information (like
    statistics, hardware settings, process information, memory data, ...) as
    regular files on the file system. You can read from those files to obtain
    the information you need, but these files are never actually written to
    disk. Every time you read them, the information is recalculated.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <e>tmpfs</e> file system is storage located entirely in memory. Although
    it is extremely fast, it is also volatile meaning that it loses its content
    when you reboot the system. The <e>tmpfs</e> file system is often used for
    temporary file storage (hence the name), but in the previously given
    <path>/etc/fstab</path> example it serves as a storage point for certain 
    applications who want to share memory without using the shared memory
    functionality offered by the c library.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <e>sysfs</e> file system (not shown in the example as Gentoo mounts
    <path>/sys</path> automatically when it is present) is the successor of the
    proc file system. It servers the same purpose, but is restructured so it
    scales well in larger environments.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Edit /etc/fstab</title>
<body>

<p>
Don't forget to edit <path>/etc/fstab</path> to suit your environment. You can
use <c>nano</c> to open the file:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/fstab">
# <i>nano -w /etc/fstab</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>System logging</title>
<subsection>
<title>Purpose of logging</title>
<body>

<p>
The system logger is an important <e>daemon</e> on the system. A daemon is a
tool that runs in the background; you can't work with it interactively.
</p>

<p>
The job of the system logger is to obtain information from various processes
(and in certain configurations even from remote processes) like logon events,
web server requests, security events, kernel messages, ... and write them down
in separate files: log files.
</p>

<p>
Such log files can then be used to resolve issues on the machine (hardware
errors are usually quite verbose), generate usage statistics (for instance for
web servers), backtrack logon events (for security purposes), etc.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Installing a system logger</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo provides various system loggers, each of them with their own pros and
cons: <c>metalog</c>, <c>newsyslog</c>, <c>socklog</c>, <c>sysklogd</c> and
<c>syslog-ng</c>. Which one you choose is up to you, but it is quite important
that you pick one: if you do not install a system logger, all events will be
displayed on your terminal, cluttering up your screen instead of nicely
archiving the events in files.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a system logger">
# <i>emerge &lt;systemlogger&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next you'll need to add the system logger of your choice to the default run
level:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding the system logger to the default runlevel">
<comment>(First find out how the init script is called)</comment>
# <i>ls /etc/init.d</i>

<comment>(Then, add it to the default runlevel)</comment>
# <i>rc-update add &lt;initscript&gt; default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>System information</title>
<subsection>
<title>Root password</title>
<body>

<p>
With the <c>passwd</c> tool you can set or change any user account password. At
first, you need to set the <e>root</e> user his password. Run <c>passwd</c> and
enter the new password. The tool will ask you to confirm the password by
reentering it after which the password is updated.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the root user password">
# <i>passwd</i>
</pre>

<p>
You might want to verify that your keyboard settings are correct before you
enter the root password. If the keyboard settings deviate a bit from what you
expect them to be, your root password might actually differ from the one you
thought you have entered. As the <c>passwd</c> tool does not echo the characters
on screen, you can not verify the password by just looking at it.
</p>

<p>
On most Gentoo installations, the password itself will be stored in a hashed
format in <path>/etc/shadow</path> which is only readable by the root user.
Hashed means that the password itself is not shown, but a mathematical result
based on the password. A hash gives a theoretically unique value based on
certain input (here: the password) but from which you can not revert (i.e. you
can not use the hash to obtain the password).
</p>

<p>
The <path>/etc/passwd</path> file, which contains user account information, is
readable by any user. Note though that this file does not always contain your
user account information - larger networks will probably store this information
on a central server (for instance an LDAP server). Where to look for the account
information is stored in <path>/etc/nsswitch.conf</path> at the <c>passwd</c>
field.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>User account</title>
<body>

<p>
Next, it is <e>heavily</e> recommended to create a user account for daily tasks.
The root user is all-powerful; any mistyped command can severely damage your
system. Running your applications as the root user also exposes you to security
breaches - although not many Linux viruses exist, the damage that a virus can do
depends on the privileges it obtains, and it obtains the privileges from the
tool whose flaw it has exploited.
</p>

<p>
To create a user, use <c>useradd</c> and pass on the <c>-m</c> option so that
the user's home directory (<path>/home/username</path> for the <e>username</e>
user) is created. Also add the groups to which you want to make the user part
of:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a user">
# <i>useradd -m -g users -G wheel,audio,cdrom,games,users john</i>
</pre>

<p>
Most groups are self-explanatory, but the <e>wheel</e> group
might need a small introduction.
</p>

<p>
The <e>wheel</e> group contains all users who can run <c>su</c> to switch from
one user to another (including the root user). Only put trusted users in this
group. A better alternative to the <e>wheel</e> access (since it still requires
the user to know the passwords of the accounts it wants to switch to) is to use
<c>sudo</c> of which an excellent <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/sudo-guide.xml">guide</uri> exists on the
Gentoo web site.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Networking information</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
To configure your wired network, Gentoo uses the <path>/etc/conf.d/net</path>
file. Its syntax might seem a bit strange at first - you'll find 
well-documented examples at <path>/etc/conf.d/net.example</path> - but allows
you to configure your entire network easily.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Automatic IP retrieval</title>
<body>

<p>
If your network interface(s) should retrieve their configuration automatically
(using DHCP) you don't need to do anything in this file - you can leave it
empty. You will find that Gentoo gives a cosmetical warning that it assumes DHCP
since you haven't provided anything. If you don't want any warning, explicitly
enable DHCP for each interface:
</p>

<pre caption="Specifying DHCP for eth0">
config_eth0=( "dhcp" )
</pre>

<p>
Don't forget to install a DHCP client. Available ones are <c>dhcpcd</c>,
<c>dhclient</c> (in the <c>dhcp</c> package), <c>udhcpc</c> (in the <c>udhcp</c>
package) and <c>pump</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing a DHCP client">
# <i>emerge dhcpcd</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you want to pass additional options to the DHCP client (we refer you to the
man page of each DHCP client for more information about the available options)
use the <c>&lt;client&gt;_&lt;interface&gt;</c> directive. For instance, to set
the time out to 10 seconds (the default for most clients is 1 minute) for the
<c>dhcpcd</c> client:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting the DHCP time out">
dhcpcd_eth0="-t 10"
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Static IP address</title>
<body>

<p>
If your interface should be configured with a static IP address, you need to
provide the following information:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>the IP address, </li>
  <li>
    the gateway (where the network packets for different networks should hop
    to first) address, and
  </li>
  <li>
    the domain name server(s) (which translate hostnames to IP addresses)
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
For instance, suppose that your IP address is 192.168.0.2 and you're part of a
network where all IP addresses start with 192.168.0, then you specify:
</p>

<pre caption="eth0 configuration for a static IP address in /etc/conf.d/net">
config_eth0=( "192.168.0.2/24" )
</pre>

<p>
The <c>/24</c> tells the configuration that the first three numbers (each number
uses 8 bits, so 24 bits in total) define the network and the last number the
host. If all of your IP addresses start with 192.168, then the configuration
would read <c>192.168.0.2/16</c>.
</p>

<p>
Next, we need to define where all network packets should go to if they aren't
meant for the internal network: the <e>gateway</e>. For instance, if 192.168.0.1
would be the gateway:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding routing information">
route_eth0=( "default via 192.168.0.1" )
</pre>

<p>
The last setting defines where the domain name service servers are. These DNS
addresses translate hostnames (such as <c>www.google.com</c>) to an IP address
(such as <c>66.249.93.104</c>). Save <path>/etc/conf.d/net</path> first and then
open <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Example /etc/resolv.conf">
<comment># Substitute the IP addresses with your DNS server addresses
# Contact your network administrator or ISP if you don't know what to enter.</comment>
nameserver 195.130.130.133
nameserver 195.130.131.10
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The hosts file</title>
<body>

<p>
The <path>/etc/hosts</path> file is a small table the system uses to make
immediate translations between hostnames and IP addresses. This file should
at least contain one line:
</p>

<pre caption="Important line in /etc/hosts">
127.0.0.1       localhost
</pre>

<p>
All other lines should be set under that line using the following syntax:
</p>

<pre caption="Syntax for /etc/hosts">
&lt;ip address&gt; &lt;fully qualified hostname&gt; &lt;aliases&gt;
</pre>

<p>
For instance, if you want to assing the host name <c>gentoobox</c> to your eth0
interface address (for instance, 192.168.0.2):
</p>

<pre caption="Example /etc/hosts line">
192.168.0.2     gentoobox
</pre>

<p>
If you use a domainname for your network (like <c>boxes</c>, but it can also be
a real reserved domain name like <c>company.com</c>), you should set it like so:
</p>

<pre caption="Example /etc/hosts line for named network">
192.168.0.2     gentoobox.boxes     gentoobox
</pre>

<p>
Next to the host names assigned to your interfaces, you can also add in the IP
address and hostname information for the other hosts on your system if they
aren't known to the DNS servers you've specified (in
<path>/etc/resolv.conf</path>, perhaps automatically with DHCP).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Automatically starting the network at boot</title>
<body>

<p>
With the configuration in place, your next step would be to assure that the
configuration is loaded when you boot your system. Go to
<path>/etc/init.d</path> and make symbolic link from the <path>net.lo</path>
init script to the interfaces you need. For instance, if you have one interface
(called <c>eth0</c>):
</p>

<pre caption="Automatically starting the eth0 interface at boot">
# <i>cd /etc/init.d</i>
# <i>ln -s net.lo net.eth0</i>
# <i>rc-update add net.eth0 default</i>
</pre>

<p>
These commands might need some explanation:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The <c>ln</c> command makes a named link to a file (in this case,
    <path>net.lo</path>) called <path>net.eth0</path>. This file shouldn't exist
    before you run this command. There are two types of links one can make:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <e>symbolic</e> links merely point to a file or directory. If you remove
        the destination (like <path>net.lo</path>) then the file is really gone
        - the symbolic link will point to a non-existing file. You can create a
        symbolic link using the <c>-s</c> option to the <c>ln</c> command.
      </li>
      <li>
        <e>hard</e> links don't just point to a file, they are actually a second
        name for the same file. If you remove the destination file, the hard
        link still contains the content of that file. More technically, if you
        create a file, you actually reserve some space on a device and create a
        hard link to it. <c>ln</c> just makes a second hard link to it.
      </li>
    </ul>
    The advantage to using hard links should be obvious - if you remove one, the
    content still remains accessible through the other link. However, hard links
    have one disadvantage to symbolic links: they can not point to files on a
    different file system. Symbolic links can.
  </li>
  <li>
    The <c>rc-update</c> command configures the boot sequence Gentoo Linux goes
    through when starting the system. By using the <c>add</c> option, you tell
    the system that the given script (in this case, <path>net.eth0</path>)
    should be added to the <c>default</c> runlevel.
    <ul>
      <li>
        A <e>runlevel</e> is a name for a certain set of scripts that need
        to be started in order for the system to function. By default, Gentoo
        calls its default runlevel ... default. Others are <c>nonetwork</c>
        (which doesn't start network related scripts), <c>boot</c> (important
        scripts that <e>must</e> be started) and <c>single</c> (where only those
        scripts are started that are needed for an administrator to be able to
        fix a broken system).
      </li>
      <li>
        The script <path>net.eth0</path> is an <e>init script</e>. Such scripts
        are written using a specific syntax and reside in
        <path>/etc/init.d</path>.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Various configuration settings</title>
<subsection>
<title>The /etc/rc.conf file</title>
<body>

<p>
The <path>/etc/rc.conf</path> file contains system-wide settings for the entire
system. You will find lots of variables already defined in the file, accompanied
with lots of documentation.
</p>

<p>
The first variable you'll see is the <c>UNICODE</c> variable. Unicode (also
known as UTF-8) is the new standard for character encoding. Character encoding
tells the system what sequence of bits resembles what character. Well-known
encodings are ASCII, ISO-8859-1, etc. The UTF-8 or Unicode encoding is important
because it is able to provide encodings for every possible language (including
special characters like €, but also chinese characters, etc.).
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in using Unicode on your system, please read the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/utf-8.xml">UTF-8 Guide</uri> on the Gentoo 
web site.
</p>

<p>
Another variable of importance is the <c>DISPLAYMANAGER</c>. A display manager
is a tool which shows a graphical logon screen after having booted your system.
Most display managers even allow you to automatically log on as a specific user.
If you want to use a display manager, you need to install one, add the
<c>xdm</c> init script to the default runlevel and make sure that this variable
points to the display manager of your choice.
</p>

<p>
Together with the <c>DISPLAYMANAGER</c> variable you'll find the <c>XSESSION</c>
one. This tells the display manager what graphical environment it should load by
default if the user didn't specify one explicitly. Well-known graphical
environments are KDE, GNOME, XFCE, fluxbox, ... For specific instructions on how
this variable influences the graphical logon process please read the comments in
the <path>rc.conf</path> file.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Select keyboard language</title>
<body>

<p>
If you aren't using a US Qwerty keyboard, you'll need to edit the
<path>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</path> file to tell the Gentoo system what keyboard
layout it should use. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
