<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-intro-support.xml,v 1.1 2006/01/06 20:05:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>Priceless</title>
<subsection>
<title>Userbase</title>
<body>

<p>
Free Software has a very active user community, filled with people who are eager
to help you install, configure and maintain free software. <e>Help your
neighbour</e> has never been as succesful as with Free Software.
</p>

<p>
Take the <uri link="irc://irc.freenode.net/#gentoo">#gentoo</uri> support
channel as an example. It has over 800 users who help any Gentoo user or
interested party with whatever question he or she might have. Or the <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri> which has over 2'000 posts
per day.
</p>

<p>
You can and will find support for the Free Software you want, support given by
users of that software, who believe the software is the best in its field and
have good experiences with the software. Of course, there is a trade: this
support is on a volunteer basis, so don't expect someone to answer your question
immediately - if you are not friendly, you will undoubtedly be ignored or even
removed from the support channels.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Developer base</title>
<body>

<p>
When you have feature requests, or you have found a bug in the software, the
developers are always happy to hear from you. Most projects even have public
bugtracking systems where you can submit bugreports to or ask for software
enhancements.
</p>

<p>
As a user, you deal with the developers personally and not with some obscure
phone number with a robotic voice on the other end, or an automated reply server
who thanks you for your submission only to never hear from it again. These
developers are devoted in bringing you the best software available and hope that
you can help them improve it. 
</p>

<p>
Those developers live all over the world, in all possible timezones, so when you
mail a developer or talk with him directly (for instance over IRC), do not
expect him to be available all the time. Not only can he be very sleepy because
it is 03.00 on his side, he can also be unavailable due to real-life issues, 
phone calls, etc. Remember, most developers work on the software in their free 
time.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Timeless</title>
<subsection>
<title>Archives</title>
<body>

<p>
Free Software is timeless. Most projects keep older releases around and some
projects even archive free software for various reasons (such as allowing people
to find out how old a certain feature is). 
</p>

<p>
You will also find archives of the mailinglists used by the project, sometimes
even daily IRC logs. Support channels like the bugtracking system or the forums
keep all posts and information around in case you would ever need it.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Stalled software</title>
<body>

<p>
When a software project "dies" (for instance because the developer(s) are too
busy with real-life or just dropped interest in the project), it does not
disappear. Such projects are only <e>stalled</e> and ready to be picked up by
someone who wants to devote some of his time to the project. Nothing of the
project gets lost: the software itself remains, documentation remains, ...
</p>

<p>
This is one of the major advantages of Free Software: unlike propriatary
software which might get dropped by the company, the software does <e>not</e>
disappear. If you require long time support for any type of software, you can
only trust Free Software - you can never know when the propriatary software is
discontinued. In the worst case with Free Software, you will need to
take on development of the software on your own or hire someone to do it for
you.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Immortal</title>
<subsection>
<title>Freedom</title>
<body>

<p>
Because the software is free, you can not kill it. The software can not be taken
over by another company. When the project is turned over to an organisation that
you do not like, you can just take the software and <e>fork</e> it (a term
used to denote that two or more projects develop software based on the same
code, but do this independently with their own goals and development accents).
</p>

<p>
The author of the software can not revoke the rights he has given to you first:
once the software is free, it remains free. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Paid support</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are not satisfied with the support you receive, you can obtain paid
support (contracts with a certain support level attached to it) if you want.
In many cases, this paid support isn't given by the project itself but by a
third party that is well known to the software code base and maintenance.
</p>

<p>
On certain occasions, you can obtain paid support from the software project
itself as well. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
