<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-intro-next.xml,v 1.1 2006/01/06 20:05:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>Handbook syntax</title>
<subsection>
<title>Used symbols and colors</title>
<body>

<p>
Okay, we are now at the end of this first part. As you might have seen, the
previous sections suddenly started using some Linux-specific commands. I will
quickly explain how this handbook uses those Code&nbsp;Listings and other
syntax.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Code listings</title>
<body>

<p>
A Code&nbsp;Listing can be a command that needs to be executed. When this is the
case, the command is prepended with a symbol that refers to the <e>prompt</e>.
</p>

<p>
A prompt is a short string given by the system to the user, telling that the
user can give a command. By default, the prompt for a regular user would look
like so on a system with hostname "localhost" and username "john":
</p>

<pre caption="Example prompt">
john@localhost ~ $
</pre>

<p>
When you are the root user, the prompt will look like so:
</p>

<pre caption="Example prompt for the root user">
root@localhost ~ #
</pre>

<p>
As you can see, it differs not only by the user name, but also the ending
character: regular users have a prompt that ends at <c>$</c>, but the root user
has an ending character of <c>#</c>. For this reason, we will use this single
character throughout the rest of the document to refer to the prompt. When the
character is a <c>$</c> you can (should) execute the command as a regular user.
When the character is a <c>#</c> you can (should) execute the command as the
root user.
</p>

<p>
For instance, the <c>ls</c> command (which lists the content of the current
working directory) can very well be ran as a regular user, but to install a
package (like <c>bzip2</c>) you need to be root:
</p>

<pre caption="Example Code Listing usage for commands">
$ <i>ls</i>
# <i>emerge bzip2</i>
</pre>

<p>
As you can see, the command itself is highlighted. When there is output from the
command to the screen that you do not need to type, it will be in plain text.
When we add some comments, you will notice that it has a different layout. For
instance, to change your password:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the current user his password">
$ <i>passwd</i>
Old password: <comment>(Enter your old password)</comment>
New password: <comment>(Enter the new password)</comment>
Re-enter new password: <comment>(Re-enter the new password to verify)</comment>
Password changed.
</pre>

<p>
We will also use Code&nbsp;Listings to show the contents of a file.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Warnings</title>
<body>

<p>
When the information in this handbook is incorrect due to a bug or a temporary
issue, I use a warning to inform you about this temporary setback. I prefer to
do it this way than to fix the content itself because I feel that documentation
should not be used to fix bugs (or provide workarounds).
</p>

<p>
An example warning would look like so:
</p>

<warn>
Due to a <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=100456">bug</uri> in
the Evolution ebuild you can not install version 2.2.3-r2 for the time being.
Please use 2.2.3-r1 until a fix has been found.
</warn>

<p>
A more permanent warning will look like so:
</p>

<p>
<brite>Warning!</brite> Do <e>not</e> set the <c>USE</c> variable on the command
line as a variable. This will temporarily assume that those USE flags are given,
but the next time your system is updated this information is forgotten.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Important</title>
<body>

<p>
When we want to stress out something important, we will normally put this in the
paragraphs using <e>emphasised text</e> or <b>bold text</b>. However, when it is
quite urgent and would require a larger rewrite, we will temporarily use an
importancy-box like so:
</p>

<impo>
Make sure <path>/etc/hostname</path> is removed afterwards. Otherwise the error
will remain since the <c>baselayout</c> package first checks this file prior to
<path>/etc/conf.d/hostname</path>.
</impo>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Notes</title>
<body>

<p>
At the end of a chapter we might add a few notes, either as a certain type of
footnote or a reference to another resource. If the amount of notes aren't too
large, we will use a note box like so:
</p>

<note>
The <uri link="http://www.tldp.org">Linux Documentation Project</uri> has a 
few guides on networking as well. Definitely worth a read.
</note>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>What can you expect</title>
<subsection>
<title>Installing Gentoo</title>
<body>

<p>
In the next part, we will give you lots and lots of Linux technical information
to allow you to install Gentoo Linux on your system. Unlike with the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook">Gentoo Handbook</uri> we will try
to be <e>more verbose</e> (yes, that's possible :) but less step-by-step.
</p>

<p>
Why? Because you should be able to install Gentoo the way you like it without
the need to take a look at the step by step decriptions. Not that the Gentoo
Handbook is written badly (hey, I wrote the most of it :p) but just...
differently :)
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
