<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/complete/hb-install-next.xml,v 1.1 2006/01/06 20:05:07 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>0.0</version>
<date>2005-06-19</date>

<section>
<title>Rebooting the system</title>
<subsection>
<title>Exiting the chrooted environment</title>
<body>

<p>
The base Gentoo installation is almost finished. Right now, you'll need to exit
from the chrooted environment, unmount all mounted file systems from the system
and reboot. Then we'll find out if the boot procedure settings are correct: if
you can log on to your system, great. If not, well, no worries - you don't need
to redo everything all over again :)
</p>

<p>
To exit the chrooted environment, type <c>exit</c>. When you get back at the
installation CD environment, find out what file systems are mounted at the
<path>/mnt/gentoo</path> location and unmount them one by one. You can't unmount
a file system that still has mounted file systems in it, meaning that you can't
unmount <path>/mnt/gentoo</path> before <path>/mnt/gentoo/proc</path> and others
are unmounted.
</p>

<pre caption="Exiting the chrooted environment and unmounting the file systems">
# <i>exit</i>
# <i>mount | grep '/mnt/gentoo'</i>
/dev/sda3 on /mnt/gentoo type ext3 (rw,noatime)
proc on /mnt/gentoo/proc type proc (rw)
/dev/sda1 on /mnt/gentoo/boot type ext2 (rw,noatime)
# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo/boot /mnt/gentoo/proc /mnt/gentoo</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next, reboot the system and hope for the best...
</p>

<pre caption="Rebooting the system">
# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<p>
Don't forget to remove the installation media from the system, otherwise you'll
boot right into the installation environment again.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Boot failed?</title>
<body>

<p>
If the reboot failed, you need to dig through the error messages you receive to
find out what went wrong. You'll find that the <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri> represent a wonderful
Knowledge Base with solutions to many problems. 
</p>

<p>
To help you get back, we'll explain how to return to the installation
environment so that you can fix whatever fault is causing the error.
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    Reinsert the installation medium and reboot your system so that you are back
    inside the installation environment, just like you were in the beginning of
    the Gentoo installation.
  </li>
  <li>
    Load up any drivers you need and configure your network just like you did
    with the Gentoo installation.
  </li>
  <li>
    Instead of taking a stab at the storage configuration, immediately mount all
    your file systems at <path>/mnt/gentoo</path>. Don't forget to mount the
    <c>proc</c> file system as well. You never know when you'll need it and it
    is often forgotten.
  </li>
  <li>
    Chroot into the Gentoo installation (<c>chroot /mnt/gentoo</c>), run
    <c>env-update</c> and <c>source /etc/profile</c> so that your session
    environment is configured correctly.
  </li>
  <li>
    Now fix whatever needs to be fixed.
  </li>
  <li>
    Exit the chrooted environment, unmount the partitions and reboot to retry.
  </li>
</ol>
</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Finishing off the base installation</title>
<subsection>
<title>USE flag changes and rebuilding</title>
<body>

<p>
If you didn't alter your USE flags during the installation, this is a good time
to do it. Log onto your system as root (using the password you supplied
previously) and edit the <c>USE</c> variable inside <path>/etc/make.conf</path>
using your favorite editor (<c>nano</c> is available by default) and reread the
information we gave you about USE flags earlier in this book in the chapter on
<e>Building the System</e>.
</p>

<p>
Once you've updated your USE flags, we'll tell Portage that it needs to rebuild
the tools that are affected by your USE flag change. To verify what Portage
wants to do, we'll first ask it to show it to us without actually performing the
rebuild. The <c>emerge</c> command has an option called <c>--pretend</c> (or
<c>-p</c> in short) that does exactly that. When we add the <c>--verbose</c> (or
<c>-v</c> in short) option we'll also ask it to display <e>why</e> it wants to
rebuild the packages. And of course, we need to ask Portage to do all that just
for the packages that are affected by the USE flag change (<c>--newuse</c>, or
<c>-N</c> in short):
</p>

<pre caption="Rebuilding packages affected by USE flag change">
<comment>(In this example, we've changed the nls USE flag:)</comment>
# <i>emerge --pretend --verbose --newuse world</i>

These are the packages that I would merge, in order:

Calculating world dependencies ...done!
[ebuild   R   ] sys-apps/man-pages-2.11  <i>-nls*</i> 0 kB 
[ebuild   R   ] sys-apps/grep-2.5.1-r8  -build <i>-nls*</i> +pcre -static 0 kB 
[ebuild   R   ] media-sound/alsa-utils-1.0.10_rc3  <i>-nls*</i> 0 kB 
<comment>(...)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
If you are okay with whatever Portage proposes, drop the <c>--pretend</c> so
that the packages can be rebuilt.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Orphaned packages</title>
<body>

<p>
Some packages are installed on your system as dependencies of a tool if certain
USE flags are set. When you unset the affecting USE flag, Portage will
<e>not</e> unmerge the dependency even though the original package is rebuilt.
Such dependencies which aren't needed by any package on the system anymore but
are stil present are called <e>orphaned packages</e>.
</p>

<p>
You can ask Portage to find such orphaned packages and remove them from the
system. The method is called <e>depclean</e> (which stands for dependency
cleaning):
</p>

<pre caption="Running depclean on the system">
# <i>emerge --pretend --depclean</i>
</pre>

<p>
Take a look at the packages Portage wants to remove. If you want to scroll
through the list, try pressing <c>Ctrl-PgUp</c> or filter the list through the
<c>less</c> utility:
</p>

<pre caption="Using 'less' for the depclean output">
# <i>emerge --pretend --depclean | less</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you're satisfied with the list, drop the <c>--pretend</c> and let Portage
sort the packages out.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Updating the system</title>
<body>

<p>
Finally, update your system so it uses the latest versions of all packages.
First, let Portage obtain a more recent snapshot of the Portage tree:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating the Portage tree">
# <i>emerge --sync</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next, ask Portage to update the packages that have a more recent version
available. We'll use the <c>--update</c> argument for <c>emerge</c> to inform
Portage that we want to update them, but also the <c>--deep</c> argument so that
not only those packages you have installed (using
<c>emerge&nbsp;&lt;packagename&gt;</c>) and their immediate dependencies are
updated, but also the dependencies of the dependencies. You'll also notice we
use the <c>--newuse</c> argument again. That is because Gentoo might add a USE
flag to the default USE set, either because of a profile update, or because you
installed a package that "provides" a USE flag.
</p>

<pre caption="Updating the packages on the system">
# <i>emerge --update --deep --newuse world</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Installing additional software</title>
<subsection>
<title>Some recommendations...</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your base system is available, you'll still left in the dark as you
don't have many tools at your disposal. No graphical environment for the desktop
users, no services for the servers, so development tools (apart from the
toolchain) for the developers.
</p>

<p>
Your next stop should be to investigate the Portage tree for software you want
to have. You can just browse through <path>/usr/portage</path> and use
<c>emerge</c> for every tool you want, but better would be to follow one or
more <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/index.xml">guides</uri> from our
web site that help you install <e>and</e> configure the tool.
</p>

<p>
For instance, Gentoo has a nice <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xorg-config.xml">Xorg Configuration
Guide</uri> for those who want to set up their Gentoo installation as a
graphical environment desktop or workstation. The <c>xorg-x11</c> tool is the
service that provides windowing features and other graphical possibilities to
the various desktop environments.
</p>

<p>
Possible desktop environments are KDE, GNOME or fluxbox who also have
configuration guides at the Gentoo web site (<uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/kde-config.xml">KDE Configuration
Guide</uri>, <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gnome-config.xml">GNOME
Configuration Guide</uri> and <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/fluxbox-config.xml">Fluxbox Configuration
Guide</uri>).
</p>

<p>
For those interested more in services should take a look at the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/security">Gentoo Security Guide</uri> which
helps you harden your system configuration.
</p>

<p>
Other interesting resources are the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo
Forums</uri>, <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/irc.xml">Gentoo IRC
channels</uri> and <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml">mailinglists</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
